sixty one eight lection No.9
announcements
the midterm is graded
and regrade requests are due on Monday
you make those in grade scope
you are welcome to post questions on piazza
but we're not going to fix
any problems unless you make a
grade scope regrade request
as a class
I think you did very well on this challenging midterm
nice work
I am delighted to see how much you've learned
now many of you didn't solve all the problems
and that's fine
the point is to learn this stuff
and if you haven't mastered it all yet
you still have plenty of opportunity to do so
on midterm two and the final exam
so keep up the hard work
focus on the parts that haven't clicked yet
and hang in there
I'm also delighted to say
that we've been checking our
various forms of collaboration detection
and so far have detected
a very very low rate of collaboration among students
as far as I can tell
the vast majority of you decided to just take the exam
instead of asking somebody else for help
and that is the right decision so I'm glad you made it
I take no pleasure in catching people who cheated
instead I hope to set up
our exam so that the obvious and default thing to do
is just take the exam according to the rules
so that's why we have the
rather elaborate amount of teating detection
and the video proctoring and all of that
just to make sure that students know
taking the exam without collaborating with others
is not going to put you into disadvantage
because that's what everybody else is doing too
and also the course is uncurved
so who cares about other people's scores
but the best thing to do for your own score
is just take the exam
which as far as I can tell
is what you did
if you're wondering whether you can
delete your midterm one
recordings from your google drive
please keep them there
until at least the end of Monday
while we finish our checks
homework two will be posted today stu next Thursday
there's no exam prep section this week
since you just took an exam
and said we'll hold an ask us anything session
with both your instructors to morrow two ten pm
this will not be recorded
if you want to hear our answers to anything
then you have to come
and the only other thing going on is the
completely optional hog strategy contest
the submission form has been posted in
in previous announcement videos
I said you should try to make sure that your code
runs in reasonable time
but that's no longer a requirement
there's no time limit on your final strategy
as long as it finishes submitting
before the contest ends
then it's fine
and if you submit early
you can see where you stand
relative to everybody else who submitted
on the hong strategy contest
leader board
so as I'm making this video
there's a submission called blockchain
that has won against all 45 opponents
followed by the golden ratio
followed by somebody who tried to break our web app
and failed
I am definitely not going to click on that link
whatever it is
and you can see that
other folks have come up with strategy
is very effective
like always roll -1
and some strategies are so far not as effective
that's fine
always roll late
still one eight times
and who is the worst of all oh apparently it's stanford
well they should really work on that shouldn't they
so I encourage you to participate
this is completely optional but can be kind of fun
and entries are due next
Monday
today's lecture video is a little bit different
in the past most notably because it's not just me
professor fried made some videos
and I think they're great
the first one which will come next
it's kind of a review of last lecture
but he presents it in a different way
and I think it's always good to kind of
go over the fundamentals of occursion
more than ones
so take a look at that video
and then the rest of the videos of the lecture will be
new content
and today's content is very important
but typically require some practice to master
so that's why we'll have a lab next week and a homework
to give you some practice
so here we go talking about recursion
welcome back at this point in the course
we
believe it or not
covered
the core computational machinery that you need to know
to be a python programmer
there's lots to learn
there's a lot of data structures and algorithms
but in terms of functions variables looping constructs
while in four
conditional statements
if
lf l statements that
forms the core of
the programming language
that you need to know to be a general purpose
python programmer
and again lots more to learn
refining honing those skills writing good
efficient well documented smart code
will come with experience
but that's the corven
now we're going to
just before we get into some more
the data structures and algorithms
and we're just called object oriented programming
I want to just take a little breath
and talk about something called recursion
and recursion in my opinion
is this very beautiful computational construct
and it's particularly beautiful because it
deviates from everything we have seen up until now
in the way you think about the nature of computation
so again everything we've been thinking about
and everything we've been doing up in tamaw has
been functions variables
looping it and conditionals
and recursion
brings in this very nice and
elegant and beautiful way of thinking
about the nature of computation
and we're gonna spend a little time talking about that
because I think it's an important construct
to understand as a general purpose
computer scientist and programmer
and dave scientist
I
let me start by reminding you of the definition of the
factorial operator
so of course
the factoral operator is denoted with an exclamation
mark and it has the following definition
it is defined as you can see here
only on
positive integers that are greater than
or equal to zero
and so the definition of factorial says that if
n is zero
you're trying to of course compute un factorial
that end factorial is equal to one
so zero factorial is one
and for all integers greater than zero
n factorial is defined to be n
times n minus one times n minus two
down to one that is the product
of all of the positive integers
from n down into one
and of course we've seen this before
we see the pops up in
in
set theory and in probability
and encounting all the time
standard mathematical operator
so before we dig
into the recursion
that I wanted to be the topic of the
set of lectures
let's just by way of practice
write
some python code to compute those
and if you want to you can pause the video
now this is a good little exercise
but if not let's just go ahead and do it together
I'm going to write a function
called factorial that takes his input and n
now let me just say before I dig into the code here
really
I should have some code in here that saysmake sure
and as an integer make sure it's greater than zero
I don't typically do that in these little examples
because it just creates a lot of code
but generally speaking
when you have functions like this
that have constraints on the input
you should put chuckson balances in your code
to make sure
that what is being passed in from the outside world
conforms to your expectation
but again just for cleanliness I won't do this here
this code is going to compute victoria
we'll go through the step by step in a second
and you can see at the very end it returns
and again remember what return does
it sends it back
to the calling function
and this distinction
between return and for example print is important
it has never been more important than when
we are about to
start talking about recursion in a few minutes
until then
let's go ahead and look at this code and make sure we
understand it
so fact of course
you can see here
is going to be the variable that I send back
I apologize they should both be color coded the same
I initialize that to be one
that's going to hold on to the
running product
I is equal to one is a counter
that is going to
as you can see in my loop here
while I is less than equal to one
is going to go from one to two to three to four
up until n
I'm of course going to computer running product
all right here is my increment
I'll come back to this line in the second
notice
by the way I just want to introduce the short hand
what do I want to do
on each iteration of the wild loop
is I want to increment
I by one I takes on the value one
and then two and then three and then four and so on
this is a little shorthand
because this is such a common
expression we say I
plus equals one which simply means I equals I plus one
so on each iteration I'm incrementing I by one
and what do I want to do
I want to keep a running product
so fact starts out as one
I multiply it by one that's of course one
next time through I have a two
multiply that product by two
next time through multiply by three
next time through multiply by four
and you can see I'm keeping a running product
fact is equal to the previous value of fact
times the current value of I
I get through that whole body of the wild loop
including end of course because end factorial is
end times and minus one all the way down to
one and then I return fat
one little point by the way
notice that in the previous
definition of factorialized
special case zero
alright I said zero factorial is one
and then anything greater than zero is this
I don't seem to have a special case here for zero
so let's make sure this works
okay so let's run through the code
and is zero fact is it one
I is one while I is less than equal to
while one is less than equal to zero
does that a value to true no
so what happens I pop out here and where do I return
one
that's zero factorial nice little
I could have put a special case
I could have said it's an equal zero
return one otherwise
but it just comes out because of the way
factorial is defined in this iterative scheme here
perfectly find iterative scheme
let's go through and just make sure we see how
fact and I are incrementing
because that's going to lead us to where we want to go
when we start talking about recursion
let's say I want to call factorial with five
so I want to compute
five times four times three times two times
one
good
first iteration through
first time through fact is one I as once
I'm gonna
do two columns here showing these values as I iterate
that boolean expression of course evaluates the true
so I go into it
into the bottle of the wild and what do I do
I say fact equals fact times I
so what is fact going to be
one and what is I going to be
two because I incremented by one right there
come back up two is still less than equal to five
dive back into the body of the wild blue please
now fact is going to be the current value of fact
times the current value of I
one times two
good so fact is two
increment I by one
go back up blue expression is true
multiply those two I get six increment
let's do it again
product of six and four twenty four increment
okay now we got to start being a little careful
because we're getting near the end
so I is five I come back up
is five less than or equal to five
sure is come back in
multiply those two values of course to get 120
now increment I by one
I come back up
six lescenter equal to five
no come back to the
get out of the body of the while loop return fact
and I'm done I've got 120
good
and you can see here that what we've done is
on each iteration
we've computed exactly what we promised
this line is computing a running product
so by the time I get to the fifth iteration
I've multiplied five times four times three
times two times one
and when I was this iteration
I multiplied four times three times two times one
and so on and so forth
now there's something interesting looking
at this iterative process
because what you notice here is that
when I computed five factorial
along the way
I also computed four factorial
and along the way I computed three factorial
two factorial and one factorial
and that sort
of makes sense if you think about
the nature of the product
so what is end factorial
end times end minus one times end minus two
down to one well what's end minus one factorial
and minus one times end minus two down to one
and so to get end factorial
I sort of have to get up to end minus one
and to get the end minus one
I have to get up to and minus two
and so I can sort of
think about this definition slightly differently
I can define end factorial or five factorial
let's say to instantiate it
as five times four factorial
and what is four factorial what
it's four times three factorial
that sort of makes sense right
because it's four times the product of 3 2 1
or what's the product of 3 2 1 it's three factorial
that's sort of interesting
so let me let me redefine
this definition of factorial
so our initial definition of factorial was
if end of zero and factorial is one good
easy
if that is greater than zero
then it's the running product of integers between n
and one
so let me take what we
that insight that we just had from that iterative code
and redefine factorial
here it is recursively
I'm gonna define
I'm gonna tell you what I mean by recursively
in a second so typically speaking
recursive definitions have two components to it
a base case and a recursive case
and sometimes you can have more than one base case
by the way so the base case stays the same
the simplest thing you can do is say give me
a zero factorial and I just tell you one
there's nothing to compute it's literally by definition
for all other integers greater than zero
instead of defining infectoral lb
n times n minus one time z and minus two
oddly down to one
I'm going to define n factoral v n times
and minus one factorial
which lets start off by agreeing is absolutely 100%
correct why
because
minus one factorial is and minus one times a minus two
through the previous definition
but imagine I didn't give you the previous definition
imagine you didn't know what factorial was
and you came to me and said
hey press a breed
what is end factorial and I said oh it's really easy
if you ask me for zero factorial the answer is one
if for all other values of
end factorial is equal to end times
and minus one factorial
you might say well
okay but what's end minus one factorial
and I'm a go that's easy
that's end minus one times and minus two factorial
and you get the sense that I'm sort of
screwing around with you a little bit
because I'm sort of defining
a function in terms of itself
and that is exactly what recursion means
but I am not in fact messing with you
in fact this definition works so let's see why
let's say you ask me what is three factorial
and I say it's three times two factorial
and so you made a little bit of progress
you know it's three times something
but you don't know what that's something is
and so you ask me what's two factorial
and I tell you what's two times
one factorial
we made a little bit more progress
what's one factorial oh that's easy
it's one time zero factorial
what's zero factorial
aha
the base case
zero factorial is one
and now what do you know
you know that three factories
three times two times one times one the base case
and so it seems like this is sort of a weird definition
because I'm defining
a function in terms of itself
but eventually if I follow down that road
because
notice this problem is getting simpler and simpler
by decrementing by one
I will eventually get to
the base case
and I will have built up
an expression along the way
when you asked me for three factorial
I said it's three times two factorial
and then
you went and figured out what two factorial was
and then you came back and said
odds three times that quantity
and then you do the same thing for two and for one
and eventually for zero
and that is the nature of a recursive definition
and of course
we can now implement that in python
in very beautiful way
so let's go ahead and do now a recursive
versus an iterative
so I will refer to wild and four loop implementations
as iterative solutions
because you're iterating
and what we're about to do are called recursive
and you'll see in a minute why there's
a difference between these two
and what that difference is
please define please
I write a function
a recursive function
factorial that takes a parameter end
again I won't check if the parameters are greater than
we go to zero
base case is easy
if n is equal to zero return one
and notice here
I'm going to now make the base case explicit
okay so this is easy and absolutely correct
not a very useful function
because for all of the various event
there's nothing to do
now what do I want to do if n is greater than zero
well if end is greater than zero
I want to compute end times and minus one factorial
well how do I compute end minus one factorial
I've got a function to do it
so what happens if I just say
return end times factorial of n minus one
there's the recursion
that function definition and that function call
are the same thing
you are calling yourself recursively
now also notice this return
I said earlier when we did the editor of solution
this is really really really important
and you're gonna see in a minute why it's important
but notice I'm not printing I'm not assigning
in fact there's no variables here
there's no fact there's no fact equals
I'm just building an expression
and we're gonna see that in a minute
put this into python and it will work
it will return for you
five factorial 10 factorial whatever you want
and it seems sort of like we're cheating
it doesn't seem like it should work
but let's now in fact see why it works
and the magic here
is that while it seems like we are
all we're doing
is calling this function over and over again
notice that we are building up an expression here
so I've peeled off
I've simplified the problem a little bit
I've said three factorial is three times something
what's that something
well go ahead and figure it out
and when you're done
come back and put it into this expression for me
and I'll tell you what the final answer is
so
this little thing right here this is it
and this returning of a value
that's where
the nature of the computation is happening
and now you can see why recursion is so different
there's no variables there's no assignment operator
you're building this expression up
and now let's make sure we can go
and see that
and let's do that by calling three factorial
so here's my function definition
if an eco zero return one otherwise return end times
a recursive call to myself
with and minus one as a parameter
I call three factorial
and now you've just got to follow the code
it's like all
everything we've done to now just write out the code
what happens okay
three comes in
it's not equal to zero
so I come into the statement and I return
to the user three times factorial two
but I can't quite return it to the user yet
because that is not a value that I can
compute multiplication on
so I have to go call factorial of two
so it's sort of like if I'd said return three Times
Square root of 27
I'd have to go compute square root of 27
it's not a recursive call
come back
can do the arithmetic and then send it back to the user
it's the same thing here
the only difference is I'm calling myself
and I just have to remember
that when I eventually get an answer here
I'm going to have to multiply by three
and that will eventually get sent back to the
calling function
all right so forget about three times for now
we'll keep a memory of that yeah it's called a staff
let's compute two factorial
that's what we need in order to finish this expression
all right
two comes into here it's not zero so we return what
two times one factorial
okay so
we sort of got somewhere
we sort of didn't yeah
so three factorial
needs to know the answer to two factorial
two factorial there's two times something
but I don't know what that's something is yet
so I've got a
okay I gotta go and figure that out
and then I'll eventually compute this
let's go figure out one factorial
one factorial comes in
that's not true so return one times zero factorial
there it is right there
all right now we're getting closer
right because what's going to happen
when I call zero factorial
zero comes into here and a zero return one
I have a value here
so this is going to go off and call something
and it's going to return an actual value
no more recursion we hit the face case
no more recursive case
alright now let's see what happens
let's forget about the three
forget about the two for a minute
let's just look at one in below
yeah so one factorial is one times zero factorial
zero factorial is a function called
happens to be recursive but honestly I don't care
it returns one
and so now that one and here it is
it's a return statement
why does that matter
because that's a function call
and that means I'm going to send a value
into that function
and it has to send me something back
that I can use it in
expression it's exactly like calling square root
you can't print the square root that does me no good
I'm trying to use it in an expression
you have to return it to me
return it to me so that I can use it in expression
all right
one gets popped back into this call for your factorial
and now
I can do the arithmetic I can do the multiplication
so I'm going to multiply one times one
and now I have an answer to one factorial
because that evaluated to an actual value
and it's being returned
back because of that return statement right there
so now the one gets replaced in there
and now I have two times one
is the answer to two factorial
a two get returned to that
the two gets returned to the factorial of two
and now I have an expression that I can evaluate
so eventually it took a little while
eventually what happened
is that that two factorial called one factoria
which called zero factoria
which hit the base case
and then I started popping up those expressions
and now I have an expression
and I return of course six
so the nature of recursion is that we build up
expressions using a recursive definition of a function
and these return statements which
essentially hold the memory of that expression
as it is being built
so you can see here it's a really
really different way of thinking
about the nature of computation
it's not right or wrong better or worse
sometimes it's a little bit better
sometimes it's a little bit more elegant
sometimes it's a little worse
sometimes it's less efficient
because you have to
hold on to the memory of all of these things
but it's a really powerful concept
and I think it's an important way to
think about the nature of computation
so we're going to spend a little bit of
time looking at some more recursive examples
and make sure that we
understand this paradigm of computation
and we'll pick it up in a few minutes when we come back
understanding the order of recursive calls is important
and
understanding the behavior
of recursive functions
and the thing to remember is that
when you make a function call
you have to wait
for it to return before you can do anything else
so if one function calls another function
and then does something after that
that function call has to return
before whatever else happens next
let me illustrate what I mean with the cascade function
the cascade function
takes in a positive integer n
if n is less than 10 it just prints out
ant
otherwise
at first prince end
then makes a recursive call to cascade
on a smaller number
that's everything except for the last digit of an
or and divided by 10
with the remainder thrown away
and finally after that recursive call to cascade
it prints end again
let's take a look at the behavior of this function
so if I cascade just the No.5 that's the base case
then I print out the No.5
but if I cascade 1 2 3 4 5
then I see this beautiful design
4 1 2 3 4 5 is printed
and then we see a cascade of smaller versions of that
and by the way
the original number is printed again at the very end
now the first and the last
lines all come from this print statement
and in fact most of the lines that you see here
come from either this print statement or this
print statement
only the base case which is for the No.1
comes from this print statement
what this is supposed to illustrate is that
all the cascading that happens recursively
happens before the final print
and that's why you get this nice nested structure
let's take a look at the environment diagram
so that we can see exactly what's happening
so we defined cascade and then call it on 1 2 3
the original call
checks for the base case
doesn't find it and so prints out 1 2 3
in the python tutor
you can see that the program output generated so far
is just the number one
two three we still have to generate all the rest
and how do we generate everything smaller than 1 2 3
while that involves a recursive call to cascade
in this case where we've thrown away the last digit
and were left with just one two
so the
important thing is that this call te cascade will
complete
before we ever go back
and finish
the original one
so what do I mean by complete
well it's gonna print 12 make a recursive call
on an equals one
which is the base case which gets printed out
so now we've cascaded all the way down
how is it that we cascade all the way back up
well our 3rd call the cascade returns
what does it return none
why
because there's no return statement at all
and if when executing the body of a function
you reach the end of the body
without ever seeing a return statement
you always return none
okay now we have to ask ourselves
where do we return to
when we were in the middle of this call to cascade
which involved this line
finally we figured out that that had a value of none
and then we go on and finish printing
n is 12 right there
and when we print that we actually see that 12 appear
and we have a return value of none from this call
which means that we can
finally return to our original call to cascade
and finish up
so we've evaluated this
and in the course of evaluating that
we generated all this output
and finally we're gonna print in at the very end
and now we're done
okay so
a critical moment in the environment diagram was when
we had returned from the second call to cascade
but we hadn't yet finished the first call
so the first call had printed in
it had cascaded all the way down to get twelve
one and twelve
but it hadn't printed in yet
and that's the very last step of cascade
so each cascade frame
comes from a different call to cascade
and until the return value appears
that call has not yet completed
and so any work that happens after that call
hasn't happened yet
any statement can appear before or after
a recursive call
there's the one before and there's the one after
it was
the third call to cascade that printed out the No.1
it was the second call to cascade that printed out
both of those twelves
one before and one before after printing the No.1
and finally this first call printed the 1 2 3
and is about to print 1 2 3 at the very end
now that's not the only way to define cass gate
an even shorter version would say well
in the base case
or in the recursive case I always print in first
so why not just put that at the very top
and then there's actually nothing left to do
in the base case
so I could just change
the zif statement to be all about the recursive case
which is when n is greater than 10
I will cascade and then print again
so now if I cascade 1 2 3 4 5
it still works
and I have a slightly shorter function definition
by the way this works even if I add more numbers
and it only becomes more beautiful
but which version of cascade is better
so we have one
that breaks out the base
case and the recursive case
and tells you what to do in each
we have this other one that finds what's similar
between the two and tries not to repeat itself
the two implementations are equally clear
then
I think it's usually better to prefer the shorter one
just because it takes other people less time to read it
in this case the longer implementation is more clear
at least to me
because it clearly breaks out
what's the base case and what's the recursive case
in that order
and that's the way I'm used to reading
recursive functions
so when learning to write recursive functions
I recommend doing that as well
but you don't have to
but both of these are recursive functions even if
only the one on the left has a typical structure
if you're trying to choose between one and the other
remember that when you write programs
they should be written for somebody else to read
and only incidentally for a computer to execute them
so think about which one you'd like to read
if you were reading somebody else's program
and make your choice there
let's let you try one
now we want to write a function
that computes an inverse cascade
what's that
well if we pass in the number one two three four
we want it to print out the following lines
1 1 2 1 2 3 1 2 3 4
and then get smaller on the way down
now if you want
you can try to implement this from scratch
I'm going to give you some structure right now
so that you can implement it in a particular way
using higher order functions
1st here's the implementation we'll use
we'll call grow
to print the one the one two and the 1 2 3
we'll call print
in in order to print the longest line of all
then we'll call shrink
now what are growing shrink
while they're both
going to be
related to the following higher order function
which takes in two functions f and g
and a number n
and if n meaning if n is not zero
zero is the only false value of a number
so if fn is not zero
then we'll call f and then we'll call g
in that order
so here's the challenge to you
define grow and shrink
which are both functions of a single argument
for call n that evolve calling fng
on some arguments
so your goal now is to figure out
what arguments we could pass in
in order to
complete the implementation of inverse kestgate
pause the video and think about it
I'll show you the answer in 321
one way to implement inverse cascade
is with a grow function
that first grows and then prints
so why does grow grow and then print well
because we want to do the small stuff first
and then the big stuff
and we're calling it first on end
and then passing in
and divided by 10
passing in and divided by 10 there etc
and so by growing first and then printing
we get from smallest to largest
shrink
prints first and then shrinks some more
so that when we pass in the large number
we first print it out
and then we print out the rest of the smaller ones
in decreasing order
tree recursion
happens when one function
makes more than one recursive call
so tree recursion
creates tree shaped processes that arise whenever
executing the body of a recursive
function makes more than
one call
to that function
and there's one example that almost every
class that includes
tree recursion
covers at some point
the fibonacci numbers
there's our friend fibonacci
he indexes his numbers starting at zero
so the zeroth number is zero
the first fibonacci number is one
the second is one as well
the third is two
and then one and two make three
and two and three make five
and three and five make eight
and five and eight make 13
so each is the sum of the previous two
except for the base cases zero and one
which are just defined as zero and one
now growth is flow
at the early stages of the fibonacci sequence
but as you can see
the numbers start to grow
a little bit faster when you get around to n is eight
but what happens if we get all the way out to n is 35
well it turns out that the fibonaji sequence
grows quite quickly
all the way up to 9,227,465
is fibonacci No.35
so let's look at a tree recursive way
of computing fibbanatchi numbers
we'll define fib to take in n
if n is zero return zero
if n is one will return one
those are two base cases
what's the recursive case
well
each fibonacci number is the sum of the previous two
which we can write as fib and minus two
plus fib and minus one
this is a tree recursive function because to
compute fib I have to call fib and fib again
so there's more than one call to fib in the body of fib
the computational process of
computing a fibonacci number
in this way evolves into a tree structure
so computing fib five
involves computing both fib three and fib four
fib three involves computing fib one in fib two
fib two involves computing fib zero in fib one
and these are all base cases
where the value of the function is returned
directly without any recursive calls
okay what about computing fib four
we're not done with that yet
that involves computing fib two and fib three
each of those has a very small
structured process to compute that
and this whole diagram is tree structured
if you flip it upside down
then you can see there's a root and then hump branches
and those branches have their own smaller branches etc
so computing fib 5
actually traverses this tree structured computation
in the following way
in order to compute fib fively compute fib three first
that's n minus two
in order to compute fib three we compute fib one
that gives us the No.1
so I put a blue dot here to say that this is the first
return value that we ever reach
when we're computing fib five
we then find a return value for fib zero and fib one
and finally this call to fib two can return
now we have the values one
and one that we can sum together to get two
and this call to fib three returns
so within fib five
we now have computed fib and minus two or fib three
but we still have to compute fib four
or fib and minus one
in order to sum those two values together
and finally reach the answer that we want
and that is another tree structured process
where we return from this and this
and then we can
finally use those return
values in order to compute fib two
in order to compute fib three
we have to compute fib one
and fib zero and fib one to get fib two
and then using those we get fib three
and now finally
with fib two and fib three computed
we can get fib four
and ultimately fib five
okay so I've told you a story about
how this recursive process
makes its computations
let's see if we can illustrate that using a program
so first thing I'll do is all define fib
just like I told you
the recursive case returns fib
and minus two
plus fib and minus one
and if we now compute fibonacci numbers
the base cases are what we expect
the next one is one the next one is two
the fifth one is five
what about No.8 that's 21
what about 10 that's 55
what about 20 that's 6000 already
the thirtieth one is 832,000 and the thirty fifth one
is still computing
what's really working hard
I thought computers were fast
what's going on
well in a moment
we'll try to illustrate the computation
to try to understand why it takes so long to compute
9,227,465
now let me just stop and say there are
faster ways of computing fibonacci numbers
so it's not that we have to wait that long
but this particular implementation
with this particular
tree structured process for computation
does take a little while
okay what is it doing
well let me show you a function that I've given you as
part of your project
and
perhaps you want to use it on future projects as well
it's called trace
it's imported from the ucb module which I provided
with your project
trace is called a decorator
you place it with an ad sign
just before the function that you want to define
and it changes the behavior
of the function to print out
when it gets called and when it returns
so that we can see
exactly what's happening in what order
as we execute the body of the function
so now if I call fib zero
what trace does
is it prince out when fib zero gets called
and then when it returns it shows the return value
so fib zero and fib one
since they reach the base case immediately
have very simple traces
but fib two
involves calling fib zero and calling fib one
which returns zero and one respectively
those two are added together
and then fib two returns one
and this one at the end is the one that was always
there
that's the return value of fib two
if we call fib three we see even more structure
or fib three involves calling fib one in fib two
and calling fib two involves some
internal computation as well
okay so now we can call fib five
and see
a tree structured process unfold before our eyes
so calling fip 5
involves calling both fip iii in fib four
each of which has some internal work
so fip iii returns two
fib four returns three down here
and by the way calling fib four is quite a bit of work
so now we can see why calling fib 10
is just a much bigger process than calling fib five
because within it
or calling fib nine which went all the way up to here
and fibate which goes all the way up to the top
and within fibate
there's fib six and fib four and fib two
and all of those have recursive structures within them
as well
and if we call fib 15
all of the sudden we have really long lines
that are extending off the end of the page
and we can see that this trace just goes on forever
and so when we computed fib 35
while there was just a tremendous amount of work to do
in order to compute all of these
intermediate values
in order to sum up what we wanted to sum up
now
let's be clear
this is not an
efficient way to compute fibonacci numbers
in particular
because there's a great amount of repetition
within this tree recursive computation
fib is called on the same arguments multiple times
and the same values are computed each time
so in particular
for fib five we can see that the fib three
computation is repeated twice
and wouldn't it be nice if we could just do that once
remember the value that came out
and not try to recompute it
and in fact
we can speed up this computation dramatically
by doing exactly that
and we'll do it in a few weeks
so don't think that
tree recursive processes have to be slow
they certainly don't
but just for the moment this one is pretty slow
welcome back
at this point we've seen
a number of examples of recursion
and I think it's fair to say
that it's not immediately obvious
why we should care about recursion because
the iterative solutions looked at least as
simple for most of the examples as
the recursive solutions
but in addition to just being
this is a powerful way to think about solving problems
and computationally
it is going to as you're going to see in a minute
turn out that
there are some really interesting examples where
recursion just solves problems
so beautifully and so elegantly
in a way that would be very difficult iteratively
and to show you just one example of that
we are going to talk about the game
towers of henoi
and if you're not familiar with the game
it's a very simple game
there are three sticks
and there are
discs of varying size that form a pyramid or a tower
and your job is to move the discs from one peg
to another peg
and there's a couple of simple rules
you can only lift one disc at a time
and you can never put
a larger disc on top of a smaller disc
so that's simple rule
and if I'm going to show you a couple of examples
you can go read about the towers of annoy
but before we get into how to solve this
go ahead and watch this video
it's a video of me
playing a version of towers of annoy with four disks
and you'll get a sense of the rules and what I'm doing
and then we'll come back
and talk about how we solve this recursefully
one two peg two
well there's no hard work here
you just simply pick up the disc and you drop it down
and the reason you can do that is
you can pick up one disc
and as long as you're not putting that
on top of something that's bigger
you're done so the case with one disc is trivial
okay
I think I've probably stated the obvious at this point
let's do the case with two discs
your job is to move these two from peg one to peg two
well okay pretty obvious
to do this the small one
obviously can't go here because then the big one
wouldn't be able to go there
so we've got to move from one to three
and at this point that we're sort of done
we've cleared the air for one to move
two is free so we simply move one
disk from peg one to peg two
and then we move three back to two
and then the pyramid or the tower
has moved from one to two
so two is pretty easy to
good
let's do three
okay now at this point where do we know
we know how to move two discs from one peg to another
I moved it from one to two
right
and we know that we move the small one over to here
we move No.2 over here and we do this over here
and by the way it doesn't matter which peg
so if I wanted to move one two to either two or three
it's the same thing
if I wanted to move these two to the third peg
I would move one to here
two to here and then one pops over
right so it doesn't really matter what
the final peg is
well okay so if I want to move all three
well I already know how to move two
so without going through the steps
let's just go ahead and move
both of those over to here
okay using the same
technique that we just used on the previous slides
and at this point I'm free to move three over to two
and again
I've got to move two disks from one peg to another
but I know how to do that
we've already done that
we've already shown that you move the small one
to the spare peg
we move the next one to where it wants to go
and then you move it back
and so I can just do that on mass
okay and now you can start to
start to see where I'm going with this
you can think about solving a towers of Hanoi
with three discs as sort of solving two versions
with two discs and then just sliding that 3rd disc over
and of course we're going to be able to scale that up
okay
so let's do this now with a little bit of pseudo code
and then we'll actually write out the code
so let me just formalize what I just set
so I'm going to write a function
henoi and it takes three parameters
how many discs
what is the start peg and what is the final peg
so this says please
take three discs from peg one and move them to peg two
and or 3 1 2
now to do that what do I need to do
well I know that I need to get one and two off of
this number three's
back here so I need to move one and two over to
peg three okay
well what does that mean
well it means I want to solve henoi with two discs
starting at peg one and moving to
not peg two of course
but to peg three
so to solve this problem
what I'd like to do is to solve this problem first
take two discs from peg one to peg three
how do I do that it's precursive
don't worry about it right now we'll come back to it
and at this point what am I free to do
I'm free to move that disk from one to two
so let's go ahead and define another function called
move which is not
which is simply to actually perform an operation
so this henoi as you're going to see in a little bit
has to do is going to be the recursion
but the move is
you're actually moving a disc at this point
so now I can move
a disc three from one to two
obviously that's from one to two that comes up here
now what do I have to do
well I've got to take these two discs
and move them from three
back to two how do I do that
well just let's solve another hernoi problem
what the start and the stop
peg r doesn't really matter to me
so now I'm going to solve
please move two disks from peg three to peg two
how do I do that
it's recursive
don't worry about it
we'll get paid that back to then a little bit
okay
good
so let's now start to write out this code in python
so I'm sorry I changed the name of the function
it's now going to be called solve henoi
it takes three parameters
n which is the total number of disks
start peg and peg
so for example on the last example it was 3 1 2
three discs from peg one to peg two
okay we're going to do this recursively obviously
and so we have to think about the base case
and then we have to think about the recursive case
although we've sort of seen the recursive case albin
we also seen the base case
the base case is that if you only have one disc
if you have one disc it's a trivial problem
just move it you have to move it from
so if n is equal to one
just go ahead and move that disc from here to here
okay so if n is one then move a disk
numbered
one and sorry
from the start peg to the end peg
and what does it move to mean to move a disc
well I'm not going to go out and do all the graphics
so for move I'm simply going to print out
what is being done
what is the move
and then you can follow those instructions
so I'm going to print move disk
I'm going to print out the disk number from this peg
to this peg okay so I take these three numbers here
and I just print out an instruction
that you can then see
this gets done
this backslash
by the way
is just because I've got a line continuity here
a line brake
all right so that's the easy part
move this disc from here to here okay good
let's do the recursive part now
so if n is not one I have to do what
well I've got to get the top disks off my back
and I've got to move them to the spare pig peg
and then I've got to take
that one big distance on the bottom
move it physically move it onto the end peg
and then take those remaining end minus one
and then move them back
sounds a lot like recursion
because solving towers of hinoi with 3 2 1
it's all the same
it's the same rules
and since that bottom one is the big one
I can put anything on top of that
so there's no rules against moving anything there
so first thing first
we've got to figure out what the spare peg is
so if I want to move from
say one to two what's the spare peg three
if I want to move from one to three
what's the spare peg two
so for any start and stop and peg
I've got to be able to know what the spare peg is
now I could write it conditional
I could say if
start is one and end is two then spares three
it start is one and end is three then spares two when
so on and so forth
or I can use this clever little equation here that says
for any given startand end peg the spear peg is 6
the difference between those
first of all
first of all let's convince ourselves that that's right
and then let's ask why it's right
so if start is one and end is two
that's six minus one minus two which is three
good if start is three and end is one that's four
six minus four is two
and you can convince yourself for any start and unpag
this will be true
why is this true by the way
three plus two plus one of course is six
and so if I take the values associated with
two of the pegs
the one remaining must be 6
whatever these values are that's a clever little trick
to figure out the spare peg from these two
all right so now
and badly why do I need to know the spare peg
well when I move
if I want to move all three from say one to three
I have to move
two of the discs from one to the spare pegs
I'm going to have to be able to figure what
that is for any pair of
starting night
good now let's go back to our recursive code
so here's my simple move disc that's an instruction
here's my base recursion case
and now I'm ready to go
so first things first figure out what the spare peg is
it's 6 start minus end
why do I want to know that
well because to solve towers of henoi
with three discs from start to end
I'm going to solve a simpler problem
there's my recursion
solve henoi is solve henoi with n minus one discs
so that's the top of the thing leaving the bottom one
from the start
obviously that's where they started to not the end
but to the spare
so please solve for me take off
take these end minus one diss off my back
and put them onto the spare
how does that happen recursively
we'll walk through that in a minute
once that's solved trust that it's been solved
what do I do
well now I've got this one diss sitting on the start
and where do I want to move it
to the end and I know the end is free
because these end minus one are on the spare disc
so I'm now going to move
the
enth disc from start to end
good so I solve this I solve this
and now what do I want to do
I've got n minus one on the spare
and I want to move it to where
the end peg good
so solve that problem
solve an oy and minus one from the spare to the end
done this is the power in the beauty of recursion
it seems like I'm cheating
I'm cheating how am
I defining
the solution of this problem with complex rules
by simply saying solve a simpler version of yourself
that's the power of recursion
now let's convince ourselves that this actually works
alright so here's my little code up here
remember move disc is just a print statement
and for purposes of space
I won't print that out here
so an equals one base case you can just move the disc
if n is greater than one
figure out what the spare disc is
solve two towers of hinoi with n minus one
and then move the disc in between
all right
so let's walk through this and see how it works
in oy 3 1 2 I have three disks on peg one
please move them from 1 2 2
good how do I do that go into the code
does the base case hold of course not
so what is the spare peg
in this case the spare peg is three
six minus one
minus two so my job is to solve
sorry I've abbreviated henoi here
and I think I did that for space
so henoi here should be the solve henoi
I just did this because we're gonna run
out of space here
so move three from one to two I need to do three things
I need to move henoi
two discs from one to three that's the spare
so
two disks from here to here
move the third disks from one to two
and then move two disks from what was the spare
back to the original
and notice that I've written
all three of these out here
because that's these three lines of code
and all I've done is fill in
the values for n and minus one
start stop and end
now
what happens at this point
I've made a call to this function
that is a recursive call to this function
I'm going to expand that out in a second
but we can't forget that we have to come back
we're going to make this recursive call
which is going to lead to some more things
but when it's done
we have to come back
and do this and then do this
so that nature of the recursive call is
there is a promise to come back here
when this is done being executed
but if this leads to another call
which leads to another call
you keep going down
and then when you're done
you come back and do this it's sort of like
the examples we've done with recursion before
we build up this expression
so here we're not building up an expression
but we're building up a series of
moves that we promise to get back to
okay so let's go ahead and start expanding this out
this is a recursive call so let's go ahead and make it
now start all over again
right the
start is one the end is three so the spare is two
your job is to solve a simpler problem
one from one to the spare
so that means move this disc from here to here
and then at that 0.2 is free to move to the end peg
so two moves here and then I move one from two to three
so these three steps are going to accomplish
the following
I move one from one to two that's the current spare
I move two over to the end and then I solve henoi one
and I'm not expanding this out
because that's eventually going to hit the base case
and so I just move it
so at this point
I have now completed
this initial recursive call which required
another recursive call
a move and another recursive call
but at this point
this function is now done
will evaluate and it is done
and now I'm free to move on to the next
remembered command from the first call
which is to move three from 1 2 2
good and now I've sort of got to do it all over again
I've got to take these two discs but now from three
and move them to there
well how do I do that
another set of recursive calls
move the first disc from three to one
move the second disc to the final disc and then move
back to there so I'll just go ahead and do that
so one moves from three to one
I'm now free to move that disc
so I'm going to move it over
and then I do one more recursive call
which of course hits the base case
and then I am home
good
so you can see in some ways here I hope
the power of this recursion
that by thinking about
solving this very complex problem with
lots of different moves
and we'll talk in a second
about how many moves there are
because we've been doing simple number cases
and I thought about it is
sort of recursively in terms of well what
if I can solve a simpler problem
how does that help me solve the bigger problem
so this is a very nice example
I think I would argue that
the best iter of solutions won't be nearly so elegant
and easy to implement
because this is literally the code that you need
to do this to solve this problem and that's pretty nice
now I just mentioned the number of moves
and I just
wanted to talk about this very briefly because it's
a little bit of a
hint of something that we will be talking about
in two o six b
and it's really important
when you are thinking about algorithms
whether they are recursive or iterative
or whatever they are
which is how expensive is this algorithm
so how much time is it going to take me to run
so let's just think about
that little elder than we just did
and there's ways of really
formalizing this analysis that I'm going to do
but I'm going to do this sort of back of the envelope
until we get to 206 b
if I have one disc how many moves do I have to make
just one I just move a disc from one peg to another
if I have two disks how many moves do I have to make
well I've got to take
one of the discs and put it onto the spare peg
that's one I've got to then move the base
over to the final two and then I move
the one that's on the spare back
that's three moves I've had to make
not too bad well what about three discs
well for three discs I've got to take two discs
and move them on to a spare pag
slide one over and then do it again
well how much does it cost me to move two discs
well three
so if I've got to move two discs that cost me three
I move one disc over that's four
and then I've got to do another three that's seven
so notice for here I sort of did it recursively
I didn't have to reanalyze
move a disk move a disk move a disk
I know that two of those disks are going to move over
and I know how much it cost me to move
two of the disks
okay well what about with four discs
well I've got to solve
two versions of towers of hernoi with three disks
move three on to despair
slide one over move three back on to the resting spot
so that's going to be seven plus seven plus one fifteen
what are you noticing here
every time I add a disc
how many more steps do I have to do
double
I'm doubling right and plus one so three
double is six plus one
seven double is fourteen plus one thirty
thirty plus one
sixty four sixty two plus one and so on and so forth
that's a little scary right
because every time I increment by one here
I'm doubling my workload
well
why why is it doubling
well think about the recursion
the recursion says in order to solve
a problem with n disks I've got to solve n minus one
twice move and minus one to the spare
slide one over that's the plus one move and minus one
and so this is a very expensive computation
so that by the time you get to 64 discs
you have a very
very expensive computation
that you are probably not going to want to do
and even with just 12 discs you've gone from
only from one to 12
you've only added 12 but you've gone very rapidly
this is called exponential growth
and this is very very bad
for certain things
it's really good if something's expensive
if you're trying to protect your password
like breaking encryption
should be exponential growth
but if you're trying to actually solve a problem
exponential growth is a real problem obviously
so I just love this towers have annoyed for two reasons
one is
it shows really the power and the beauty of recursion
and it also gave me
an excuse to show you what exponential growth is
which is something we'll be talking about
down the line
much much more and much much more formally
all right that's it for recursion
a couple of things
I want to say at the end of all of this
don't get too confused
when I ask you to solve a problem
I will tell you if it's iterated recursion
and I don't expect you right now
to know which is sort of the best
I just want you to be able to
solve these problems thinking
about them a little bit differently
but don't feel like just because recursion's weird
you have to solve all the problems with that
or you should avoid them
like any design problem
you have to think about what is the best most elegant
most efficient solution
and sometimes that will be recursive in nature
and sometimes it won't
and that's okay good
all right
so at this point we're not ready to transition to
object oriented programming
so the next three full lectures
are going to be classes and objects
and at this point
we really do have
all of the scaffolding we need to be
python programmers
we have functions
we have variables we have looping constructs
we have conditionals we have return variables
we have parameters
we have recursion of course
and now we're going to start thinking about data
not just computation
but how do we store information
and make good
use of that data to solve
interesting problems in efficient and elegant ways
and so when we pick it up
we're gonna start sort of a new chapter
if you will of this class which are classes
and objects and then for the last two weeks
we'll talk about something a little bit different
as well all right I'll see you in a little bit
now we'll look at a very important example
called counting partitions
and this example is important because
it's a tree recursive process
that's actually quite hard to write without
tree recursion
so one of the reasons we learn
about recursion in this course
is to solve problems like this one
like counting the partitions of an integer
what is that
well the number of partitions of a positive integer n
using parts up to size m
is the number of different ways in which n
can be expressed as the sum
of parts up to m
in increasing order
let me show you an example
say we want to count the partitions of n equals six
using parts opticize m equals four
here are all of those partitions
and this is an exhaustive list of everything
that counts as a partition of six
using parts up to size four
so each line is a sum of different parts
where the parts are an increasing order
so we have 2+4
but we don't have 4+2
because that's a decreasing order
okay now notice that each part is always
up to four but never bigger
so we don't include 1+5
that doesn't count as a partition of six
using parts up to size four
but we do include two plus four
and one plus one plus four
as different ways of partitioning up the No.6
the idea here is we're counting the number of different
ways that we can break six into groups
now we can illustrate these different partitions
by showing what we're grouping
so we have two here and four here
or we have one and one and four here
and all of the other options
can be illustrated on a line as well
and the purpose of the count
partition's function is just to tell us
how many different
partitions there are
not necessarily to tell us what they are
so in this case there are 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
different options
so count partition six comma four
should return the No.9
okay
let's understand how we would compute this value nine
and we need a strategy that will compute partitions
for any n and nem that we pass it
so let me tell you this strategy first
and it will work on the implementation afterwards
we're going to look for a recursive decomposition
of the problem
meaning that we need to
express this problem in terms of simpler
instances of the same kind of problem
and we're going to do that by exploring
two different possibilities
one is that
will include at least one group of four or one four
in the sum of parts that we use in the partition
and the other option
which is everything that doesn't include a four
says that we're never going to include a
four in the partition
we're only going to use parts up to size three or less
now
splitting these two possibilities actually splits
the set of all things that we want to count
into two disjoint subsets
the ones that include a group of four
and the ones that don't
another observation is that everything
that includes a group of four
really just has to partition
what's left over after we subtract for
so in both of these cases
we're actually just partitioning the No.2
we can get it by just a No.2 or by 1+1
using groups up to size four still
and what about the bottom half
well the bottom half is all the ways of partitioning
six
but using parts up to size only three
so we're really solving two
simpler instances of the same problem
meaning we'll make
two recursive calls to count partitions
when we're trying to compute count partition six four
using at least one four
means that we then have to count the partitions of two
again using parts up to size four
so there's the simpler instance
of the problem that we solve
above this line
assuming that we use at least one four
the other simpler
instance is that we count
the partitions of the whole No.6
using parts that are one smaller
than the one we had before
so we're assuming we're not going to use any fours
so we'll use parts up to size three
and we need to count up all of those
so if we count up these two and we count up these seven
we'll get the nine and total that we want
in order to solve the problem
and that's the recursive decomposition that we
used in order to count the partitions of a
positive integer et
so tree recursion can be thought of as a technique
for exploring different choices
or different possibilities
these are the two possibilities we explore in this case
and what do we do with the result
will we sum the results together
because we actually want
all the different alternatives
and these two possibilities split that set
evenly right here
now when we make one of these recursive calls
that's going to involve further decomposition
in the same way
the count partitions of six using parts opticized three
will divide that set of seven up into two groups
those that use a three and those that don't
and here we have the count partitions of the three
that remain
here we have the count partitions of all six
using parts up to size only two
and each of those has recursive decompositions as well
sometimes here and sometimes here
and in this way
we explore all the different possibilities
and can compute
the final result that we want
hooray
so we're finally ready to write some coat
once we have a recursive plan in place
we just need to add an implementation
that executes that plan
so we define count partitions of a number in
using parts up to size m
and let's start with the recursive case
because that's what we've been talking about
we count the partitions of n minus m
using parts of to size m
which is all the cases in which we use at least
one part of size m
we also count the partitions of n
using parts that are smaller than m or m minus one
and then we summed together
the cases in which we used in m
and the cases in which we didn't
and that should give us all the different cases that
were interested in
and the total ways of partitioning in
so for the case of six comma four is our inputs
this with them is count partitions two comma four
and without them is count partition six comma three
now we just need base cases
if we're partitioning zero
well let's just say there's one way to do that
which is to add nothing together
if we're partitioning
non positive number
we've done something wrong along the way
there's no way to do that
and so we return zero
because we're not allowed to use negative parts
and if the maximum part size m gets to be zero or less
well there's no way to build anything
out of parts of size zero
so we return zero there as well
and that's our
complete implementation of count partitions
let's watch it work
so I'm going to define count partitions
I'll count partitions of a slightly simpler instance
then we talked about before
we're going to count partitions of five using
parts up to size three
and here all the different alternatives that we want
to sum up
1 1 1 1 1 or 1 1 1 2 or 1 2 2 or 1 1 3 or two three
so the original called account partitions with anna
five and Ms Three
involves two recursive calls
one of which
is partitioning the No.2 using parts up to size Three
which if we do some computation eventually returns
the No.2
so if we try to use an m
like if we try to use a part of size
three in order to petition two
that's impossible
so that's why we get a zero there
if we try to partition the No.2
with things smaller than three
then we find there are two different ways
1+1 and just the No.2 alone
so those are the two different alternatives
and we've computed
what we get when we count the partitions of two
now what happens when we count the partitions of five
using parts of size two or smaller
well those are
these three alternatives that we have left over
so if we run through the computation
we see many recursive calls
and after some amount of work
we compute that using m which is the number of two
we find two different ways of summing up the No.5
so here are the two different options
that involve using the No.2
with part size two or less
and the only thing we haven't accounted for
is the sum of all ones
so without m should include the sum of all ones
we run some computation
try some different alternatives
and right here
we found that without using m so using only five
so computing five with only parts one
there's a way to do that and we return that one way
so we return it here
we some two and one together
we find out that without them we get three
we some two and three together
and we get the
actual value we want which is all five ways
of counting partitions
of five using parts up to size three