61a lecture 15 q and a
uh so the question was what does it mean
to reference a list
and in the last video there were a bunch
of examples
of different expressions that evaluate
to the same list
and each way of evaluating you can think
of as a reference so this notice of a
reference is
i can refer to hani as hani or
professor of cs61a or
coolest guy i know and these are all
like different ways of referring to the
same thing
and so different references and the same
story holds for
any object in python but it's really
important for lists because
lists change and so if you have multiple
references to the same list and that
list changes
then the value that you'll see
when you evaluate any of those
expressions that refer to that list is
going to change as well
so we see this in simple examples and
moderately complicated examples
and really complicated examples so maybe
we'll start with a moderately
complicated one and then we'll decide
whether we should go simpler or more
complicated
so if you have a list one with another
list in it
two three and then you have
b equals a and c equals a
one and
then you append four
to c this will actually change b
and let's see why so if we print b we
won't get
one two three but instead one two three
four
in this case a and b are both references
to the same list
it's this list this box which happens to
have as its contents 1
and another list 2 3. 3
c is a reference or a name
for the element at index 1
of a which is also the same as the
element at index 1
of b because a and b are just two
different names for the same thing
and that means if i append to c i've
really changed a
and b as well even though
i'm my expression says c that append for
anything that contains this value
of c is going to be affected as well so
when we print b
we'll see one two three four as opposed
to the original
one two three that we typed in because
we mutated or changed part of it
so let me just inject something here so
the the the most
important line here is the b equals a
line
right so that before we were doing this
if i had said for example a equals five
and b
equals six if i changed a b doesn't
change
yeah so that that's sort of what's a
little confusing here but with
lists and with objects when you assign
one
var one list one variable to another
variable each of which are now list
there's only one copy of the data yeah
that's the important part but when i say
a equals five
b equals a there's sort of two fives out
there in space
and this is what's nice about these
environment diagrams so right after you
and you can see it here in the
environment diagram
b is not pointing to its own list it's
pointing there's only there's only one
list in memory now
both a and b are pointing to it and now
i can modify this is sort of what's
sort of terrifying and interesting about
it is
either if a modifies it modifies b if b
modifies it modifies a they're just
there
it's there's only one list in memory and
that's the thing to keep in mind when
you do what's on line two is you're not
making a copy of the list
great question so the question is about
this example
from lecture that involved printing out
t
and seeing some dots
let's see if we can find them oh there
they are
what is that well let me give you kind
of a simpler example that doesn't
involve
slice assignment just so make sure
everyone can follow along so i'm just
going to comment those out
and make a new t which is
a list containing one and then i'll
append
t to it like what should this look like
this should be a list that has one
and then within it it has a list that
has one and within it it has a list that
has
and this could go on for you know a
little while
what's interesting is that
there is some logic built into python
about how values are displayed
so for example the fact that a list
appears with just one space after the
comma
is part of how python works
now that part about how python works is
actually just a function
that says whenever it's time to display
a
list you should display it in this
particular way
and that function has the following
behavior
if at any time you want to display
the entire list that you're in the
process of displaying
then don't display it but instead
display this dot dot dot to say you know
this would kind of go on forever because
t
contains itself but we don't want to
fill your screen with ones
and so we'll stop there so
uh yeah i i guess we'll study this in
more depth later in the course but one
of the interesting things is that
there's a relationship between
this object which is weirdly
self-referential
and the way it is displayed and
the relationship is some function that's
built into python but we could write it
ourselves if we wanted to
that takes in t and starts displaying it
since t is a list it has an open bracket
since the first element is one it writes
one
since there's another element it writes
the comma and the space
and then since the next element is t
again
it has this special case where it says
okay time to draw
a list but not display its contents
because that would take forever
so maybe we'll then go back to this
particularly
bizarre thing you could do in python
which is slice
assignment so slice assignment basically
says
take a piece of the list there's the
slice from one to three
and replace it with the contents of
another list
so i could replace it with five six
seven
and then the two and the three would go
away and the five six seven would be
there and i would get one five six seven
if instead you replace it with something
that has a t in it then you get that
dot dot dot but i i mean this could have
been five six seven and then t
and then the dot dot would appear at the
end
by the way notice too that i mean i mean
john
said it exactly right that there's a
distinction between how the data is
being stored
and how the data is being printed so
in the print it looks like the list goes
on forever
but in storage it doesn't because that
last element is just a pointer back so
it's not like
we blew out memory having to store this
huge list it's not
until you go to print this thing that
you have to be like oh what's that last
element oh it's the first list oh what's
the last time of that and now you have
sort of a problem
but from a storage capacity from a
representation capacity
no problem at all i just have a
self-referential and it's it you can
somebody asked in the
question can you think of this as sort
of recursion you can you can think of
sort of like
you're defining a list in terms of
yourself
yeah exactly the list is recursive in
the sense that it contains itself
also the function that prints out a list
is recursive in the sense that what it
does is it prints some brackets
and then it displays all of the elements
and so to display the whole thing you
display each of the elements that sounds
like recursion to me
and it happens to have this bass case
which says if it's ever time to display
the whole thing again
just uh return this special dot
dot thing instead of continuing
all right great that's good somebody's
asking the chat what kind of situation
would this kind of self reference be
applied
that's a good question yeah so
um if you wanted to represent a website
where each the website is like a list of
the things it links to
sometimes websites link to themselves
and
so if you want to simulate the idea of
clicking on that link nine times
which kind of just cycles back to itself
over and over again well you could do
that using a python
list so there are things in the world
that refer to themselves that's why you
would use this
i don't see like another good reason why
you'd use this though maybe there is but
i think that's the main one
yeah and there's another question is the
dot dot dot because of a
quote unquote infinite loop that calls t
or because it calls itself yeah it is
essentially an infinite loop
um you can think about it like that
exactly so i would say
the function that displays the list
yeah would loop infinitely if it weren't
for the fact that we had this special
case
and that would be bad so the object
itself is finite like
it refers to itself but it's really just
a list with one two three
four five elements but displaying it
could take forever if you're not careful
so there's that really it's a really
interesting distinction i can have
something that is finite
but that takes an infinite amount of
time to display because it's
self-referential
that's fine right it's like chasing your
tail
yeah and it's like uh well okay so this
shows up in mathematics sometimes i
guess we're
going too far straight but you could
define a sequence of numbers like
it starts with 1 zero and then one
and then each element is the sum of the
previous two is the fibonacci sequence
that description was finite yet the
sequence is infinite if i wanted to
write it out that's kind of what's going
on here
nice very nice
good question so the question is what's
the relationship between
a selector function and data abstraction
versus a dot expression that refers to
an attribute of an object
in uh object-oriented programming which
is kind of what we're building up to
and the answer is there's no difference
so in a typical program you wouldn't
have both
you kind of pick how you're going to do
things the selector function
was there to show you that through data
abstraction you could bundle stuff
together and break it apart
using a constructor and selector
functions and this
functionality doesn't actually require
you to define your own functions it's
built into python and we're seeing that
for the first time
with the objects video today is that
lots of different values are in fact
abstractions
that have their own components and those
components and the object system are
called attributes
you access them through dot notation and
so like in a typical python program
you don't write a lot of constructors
and selectors instead
you write a bunch of uh dot expressions
that access particular attributes
and that's fine uh you know python could
have been built another way
and you know it is built with a
constructor for lists where like you can
build a list out of something like a
tuple um
so that looks basically like the
constructors that we had in data
abstraction
but instead of having just a bunch of
functions to access the elements
of this value the way python is built
internally is that you access the
components
not through selector functions but
through dot expressions that get
particular characteristics
like uh i i i guess there's this like
for list there's this special syntax
where you use
square brackets but for a lot of
different things i guess i should have
talked about dates
with dates you use uh dot expressions to
access the parts
so same concept two different ways of
doing it
you could roll your own which is to
define functions so select your
functions and constructor functions
or you can use the built-in
functionality within python in order to
use
attributes and access them through dot
expression and
you're basically doing the same thing
with slightly different code
yeah it's important to understand that
that square bracket notation
is a selector it's just a syntactically
different selector
right so all of these it's sort of like
um using the plus sign as opposed to the
add function
same thing it's just a different syntax
that just a little bit more convenient
because we use it so often
so a great question the question is
about how slice assignment works
which is the weirdest thing in python
maybe we shouldn't even teach it in this
course but i did so now we'll learn
about it
it's called slice assignment because we
have a slice
and an assignment statement and this has
its own behavior
it's not like you can think about this
as
you're like first computing the slice
and then you're assigning to it
instead this whole thing is kind of its
own construction
and so it has its unique behavior that
you have to learn and it's different
from how all
other assignment works the way that this
works
is that this must be something you can
slice
like a list and something you can change
well like a list
this must have elements so if for
example i put five here
i would run into an error it would say
can only assign an
iterable that's the problem is that five
is here
and that's not allowed in slice
assignment
it must be the case that you have
something that's got elements in it like
a list or a tuple or a string or
whatever
now what it does so we kind of have
gotten the domain right we know that
this needs to be something that we can
slice and we need to decide
how we're slicing it and we
need some elements to insert
now we have to talk about the behavior
and the behavior is that s
gets modified the way it gets modified
is that whatever slice here
is removed from s and then at the
position that that slice was removed
all of the elements of this are
inserted into s so
s actually doesn't have any elements
from
zero to zero because this is a zero
length slice it does have a position
it's like right here before the one
but it doesn't include the one or the
two or the three because it only goes
from zero to zero
so if for example i had
just taken a slice from zero to zero i
would get an empty list
because there aren't any elements from
the slice from zero to zero but that's
not what we're doing we're assigning to
this slice
and we're assigning some new elements
which means we're going to insert into s
all of the elements in t which is 4 and
5 and 6 and we're going to put them in a
particular position
which happens to be at the beginning so
we get 4 5 and 6
at the beginning if instead i had
sliced from 1 to one that's still a zero
length slice but it's in a different
place
so the four five six would have shown up
starting at position one which is where
this empty slice would have been it
would have been like
right in there and so that's where we
put the four
five six if we hadn't had a non-empty
slice
the slice from position one to position
two covers
the two this would remove the two and
replace
it with the four five six so we get one
four
five six three i think the reason this
exists
is that python tries to do this quite
efficiently so if you like went through
and removed all these elements
and then you started inserting
afterwards then sometimes that would be
a little bit slower
than kind of doing it all at once which
is to remove the slice and slap
in some replacement values instead but
it does mean it's like one more piece of
syntax that
you might want to know and since we
taught in the course i guess you need to
know it although this is definitely not
the most important thing
you're supposed to learn from this
lecture it just happens to be one more
way that you can change the contents of
a list
good question so why isn't it that t
becomes an
element of s and the reason is that's
just how slice assignment works
is that it takes a container full of
elements
and it doesn't put that whole container
in s instead of puts the elements of
that container
in s now it doesn't necessarily
copy those over if for example
t had lists in it
so t has a list in it
then the things i'm gonna do is i'm
going to remove the two
because that's the slice from one to two
you can see the indices here
and i'm gonna replace it with the number
four this list
and the number six so what we'd end up
with
is one for this list
the number six and the number three
which was in there before
a question of the chat was why can you
explain why you cannot
insert an integer into a list again in
general you can
insert integers into lists if you're
using
something other than slice assignment so
if i were just using
element assignment then i could put the
number five in there let's pick another
number the number eight in there no
problem
and it would just change element number
one of s
to eight that's okay the reason that
uh we ran into a problem is that we were
using slice
assignment which is this weird thing
that takes multiple elements from
s and replaces them with the elements
from eight oh except eight doesn't have
any elements that's why we ran into a
problem here
is that slice assignment only works if
what's to the right hand side
evaluates to something that has elements
in it like a list
so i could have put 910 in here
or i could have put t both of those are
lists
and then what it does is it replaces
what was in there before
in this slice from one to three with
these new elements 910
but it actually doesn't uh put a list
containing nine and ten in there it puts
the elements themselves
and steve's asking why did you use s 0
colon 0 instead of s
0 colon 1. the difference is the s of 0
colon 0 is not replacing
any elements it's inserting at position
0.
the s zero colon one is going to replace
what's in the zeroth position with
whatever's on the right hand side so he
could have done that
so it's a question of insertion versus
replacement
yeah so the second version lost the one
and michael's asking is s sub zero the
same as
s zero colon zero yes and no
um so if you say s sub zero
is equal to something then you
are not using that slice assignment
operator
so it's different then you're allowed to
have whatever you want on the right hand
side
yeah so distinguish between
list assignment with a simple index and
the slicing assignment as
john said earlier on is a thing in and
of itself it is distinct from other
types of assignments
yeah let's just try to get these two
things next to each other because they
do have different pictures
and the differences in the pictures is
important but it's hard to keep a track
of it all at the same time
so slice assignment took all the
elements in t and stuck them in s
so now s which used to have three
elements has six elements
y6 well it had three and we put three
more in it
this which is not slice assignment but
instead element assignment
just replaced whatever was in
position zero of s with a reference to
t and so we lost the one
remember in this one we didn't lose the
one and here we lost the one because we
replaced the one with a reference to t
there's no fours and five fours and
sixes in here anymore
there's only t and this used to be three
elements long it's still three elements
long element assignment never changes
the length of the list it just changes
what's in it
slice assignment is different it changes
the length of the list
it replaces an existing slice with some
new elements
audrey's asking when we do the list
slicing does the iterable that we are
setting the list sliced to need to be
the same length longer or can it be
shorter than the existing list slice
it can be anything you want so so the
iterable
i'm sorry and the slice can be zero
you're inserting
it could be of length one two three or
anything you want and what you're going
to do
is think about it this way so on the
left hand side with the slicing you say
grab those elements
throw them out and then take whatever's
on the right hand side and
shove them into the position so they can
be longer
shorter it doesn't matter and something
that does show up once in a while
is that you'll have some long list and
you realize oh i don't want some of
those elements
so you might slice them out which would
mean
uh finding the slice you want from
element two to element five let's say so
that's the three
the five and the six and we could assign
that to the empty list meaning
take those elements out and replace them
with nothing
and then they're gone so that's the
that's the most common use that i use
for the slice assignment operator is to
just annihilate things from a list
that's actually not that uncommon to do
something like that
the next question was what's the
difference between a tuple and a list
and what does it mean for one to be
mutable and want to be immutable
and there's kind of an underlying
question of what's the point of all this
the unspoken question is why do i care
man i don't know how to answer that
okay so if i call tuple on s which is a
list
you know it's a list because it has
square brackets this says give me a
tuple with the same elements
as s so now we've got two different
objects
one's a list one's a tuple they got the
same thing in it
but they have slightly different
behavior and the right way to think
about a tuple is it's like a list except
for it
doesn't allow you to do a bunch of
things that you would otherwise like to
do
slice assignment on a tuple not allowed
so you don't have to know how it works
because you can't do it anyway
element assignment not allowed appending
not allowed extending not allowed you
can't change
the content like the length
or which elements are in a tuple
so there's nothing i can write that
would take this tuple
and change this 3 to a 9 or change it to
a reference to this list or something
like that
it cannot be changed i could
do a lot of things anyway like i could
reassign t
to something else so i could say u
equals t and t equals nine
and for this reason it's not the name
t that can never be changed it's the
tuple itself that can never be changed
the important consequence of this is
that if i say u equals t
and then i write some expression
involving t
it will not affect you unlike a list
right look at the distinction here if
those were lists they would have
modified the list
exactly but since this is a tuple can't
be modified
no matter what i do to t that's allowed
which
a lot of things aren't allowed you can't
depend you can't slice a sign
you can't element a sign or whatever but
you can do some other stuff you can take
slices or whatever
won't affect t so if i slice this
from element 3 to element 6 that is
allowed
and i could call that v but that hasn't
changed u
u is still one two three four
sorry one three one two three five six
seven uh i don't know what happened to
four along the way but
oh well um so
uh that's the difference is that you
know a list you can do a lot of
different things with you can slice it
you can get elements
but you can also change it topple you
can't do some of those things but you
can do others you can still slice it you
can still
figure out its length you can still
build a new one but you can't change it
in any way
that's what makes it immutable whereas a
list is called
mutable meaning mutation applies meaning
you can change it
but now i guess we should say something
about why
yeah and i guess there's there's really
two reasons one is a little bit about
efficiency
sometimes a program will just run faster
if it's using a bunch of tuples instead
of a bunch of lists
because they can take a little bit less
space in the memory of the computer
but the more common reason is that
people are designing their programs so
that they don't have to think about
mutation back when you could just
describe
every function by its domain range and
behavior
life was easier i'm not saying it was
easy there were plenty of like tricky
recursion problems and stuff like that
but at least you knew that if you called
a function the only thing you really
have to worry about is what does it
return
not what does it change and if you use
tuples everywhere
since they can't be changed you kind of
don't have to think about what does it
change you just have to think about what
it returns
whereas if you're using lists everywhere
if you're not careful
the consequence of calling a function
will be not only that it changes
something
or that it returns something but also
that it changes something
and that's like twice as many things to
keep track of when you're writing a big
program
and trying to understand how all the
parts work so that's like the main
reason to have some immutable version of
a sequence
is just to like make sure you write
programs in such a way
that nothing can change anything else
except by passing in arguments and
returning them
it's it's called side effects the thing
that's scary when you call a function is
there some side effect
that it that goes beyond just what was
passed and what was returned it modified
a list
and i how did i how do i know that that
how do i control that
and so the tuples are nice or tuples
which one do you call it john i want to
call it the other one
uh i've been calling it tuples all the
time so you got to use tuple for a while
all right i'll use that we'll switch in
a couple minutes
all right good so the tools are nice
because it's essentially like you're
locking your data
right it's giving you data security yeah
um a follow-up in the chat was what
happens
if my couple has a list in it so
this temple is immutable in the sense
that it will always be length three
and it will always have this particular
list in it
so the the the aspect of this that's
immutable is that
it will always have three elements and
they always will be the number one
this list and the number seven that
those facts cannot be changed however
this list might change and the fact that
it is part of a tuple
will not control what's allowed it's
still a list you can still do whatever
you want to it
so if i give it a name i say t is s1
and then i start mucking around with it
i append
five all right you know we've been well
okay i wasn't i was about to do slice
assignment but i think we've done that
to death today okay then uh
now in a sense the contents of this
tuple has changed the tuple itself has
not changed
it's still one this list and seven but
if you were to print it out you'd see
something different than you did before
because you'd see one three four five
seven instead of one three four
seven so being immutable
doesn't mean that nothing about you can
ever be altered
it just means that this this particular
part of the environment diagram
never will change yeah good question so
when is a value protected from mutation
there is not a mechanism in python
to take a mutable value and protect it
from mutation somehow
if a value can be changed then anything
that can access
that value can change it that's just a
fact about how python's designed
this is not true of other programming
languages there are programming
languages
that keep track of for each
function that can reference a value is
it allowed to change it or is it not
allowed to change it
c plus plus is a good example of this
and that is like another element that
you could add to a programming language
to give yourself kind of more control
over whether something can be mutated or
not but that's not something that python
allows
instead it's part of the value to say
this value is something that can be
changed
or this value is something that cannot
be changed and so lists can be changed
temples cannot so what about
writing python how do you make sure that
you don't accidentally change something
well if you have a list there are
actually only so many ways that you can
change it
you can use element assignment
or slice assignment that will change it
you can use one of the mutation methods
like append or extend that will change
it
um if you don't use
any of those then you're not going to
change it
so for example if you just slice it
that doesn't change it why not because
we don't have an equals here
if we don't have an equals we just have
like t equals this this doesn't change s
let's just build some new list with some
of the elements of s
so as long as you're not doing element
assignment or slice assignment
or appending or extending or removing or
popping or all these other
melt methods that perform mutation then
s
will not change and so that's the
mechanism that you have to verify that
you're not going to muck with something
that you don't want to muck with
is that you don't use any of these
now to kind of be extra careful a lot of
times what people will do
is they just won't use s at all
because they want to make sure they
don't change s so they're not going to
use s
they could instead make a copy
of s this is really building a new list
with all the elements of s and then they
write all their code about t
the nice thing about this is that if you
accidentally change t you haven't
changed s so that's like
a sort of uh heuristic mechanism for
trying to
guard against accidental mutation is
that you could
try to avoid using this list at all but
instead use some other list
um but that isn't like not really any
kind of guarantee that it's impossible
to mutate us
uh it's just a way of avoiding it
the next question was if you have two
lists s and t
and you append s to t and then change s
to that effect
t and if so how
i think the answer is that it would if t
is 4
5 6 and then you append s to t now t
is 4 5 6 followed by the list 1 2
3 but this is a list that can be changed
and whenever it's changed
then all of the ways of referring to it
are changed as well including looking at
t's element at index three and so if you
print out t
at this point you'll get four five six
followed by the list one two three four
because you changed this list that's in
it
okay so the question is do you ever have
a function
f of x that takes some
optional second argument that is
something
mutable and
is this ever like a good idea
my take is the answer is no this is
never a good idea
but i have seen people use it before
they could for example
try to write a function that returns
the sum of everything f has ever been
called on
so we're gonna i guess we don't need to
print
we're gonna call f on 2 then we're going
to
call our f on 1 then we're going to call
f on 3
then we're going to call f on 5 then
we're going to call f on 7.
this first call is going to return 1.
the second call is going to return
four the third call is going to return
four plus five
is nine this last call is going to turn
16.
you know don't do this but i've seen it
done so i guess
you might as well know that someone else
might do it
what's going on here is that
we're using the default argument's value
as some kind of persistent storage
that's part of this function that's kind
of keeping track of everything that
this has ever been called on the reason
this is extra weird
is that you could call f on
you know some new thing and then it
wouldn't behave the way
that you wanted it to behave at all like
uh
instead of summing one three five seven
and nine
it would sum nine and one is ten which
just like is inconsistent with
everything that's happened before
so nasty nasty feature of python by the
way i think it's ridiculous that it
works this way
yeah so this is this is something to
avoid by knowing it exists
as opposed to something to exploit or
use by knowing it exists
is that the default argument value is
part of the function which means there's
kind of only one of them
and so if you wanted to mess with it you
could but don't
uh one quick question we'll get to the
last hand raise the question is is the
default value in a function defined in
the global frame
i don't know if it's actually defined in
the global frame but it effectively is
that's what it's doing
it is true that this expression here
is evaluated in the global framework
shouldn't you use x just do something
else
because this is evaluated
when the function is created not when
it's called
uh okay so like none of this would work
anymore but we could like
return y of x or something like that
and uh could we refer to something
globally
i think the answer is yes see if i'm
right
yeah so when you create the function
before you ever call it we never called
it
it not only creates the function but it
creates the default argument value which
means evaluating this expression
if this expression is two square
brackets that makes an empty list
if this expression is some lambda then
it creates a function
yeah yeah i don't like it don't do that
so the question is what is the
difference between a class and an object
the class is so here's how i think about
it think about
a blueprint for a house is the class
and the house is the thing you build
from the blueprint
okay so i can have a class date
um that is the sort of the definition of
the data i'm storing and the
functionality of it
and then i can instantiate i can create
as many of those objects as i want so
they're essentially realizations
of the thing that you've created so the
class is just
it's sort of like a definition nothing
exists and then when you create an
object
well now i can sort of do things with it
so there's a
class of type list and then i can define
lists i can define one list two lists
50 lists whatever i want yeah
yeah and that analogy is nice because
you can live in a house but you can't
live in a blueprint right like if you
just have the class
you can't really do anything with it
until you
construct one of the things that it
describes build the house
and then you can go live and you can go
live in it right and it's sort of like a
function definition right you define a
function
but doesn't do anything it's just a
definition it just hangs out in the
global frame somewhere
but then when you call it ah now we're
actually doing something
and uh you're not supposed to know this
all i mean it's fine that you know it
but
we will cover this fact of the
relationship between classes and objects
next week so
it's for those of you that are a little
hazy on what's going on
um that's because we haven't not yet in
this class defined our own class or
really looked at what's inside of one
but we will yeah so what's to come is
we've been using the built-in
classes and of things like lists and
dates but
i don't think it'll surprise you that we
can now start building our own classes
and our own data representations and our
own functionality
i saw one more question in the chat
let's see if we can get it is a range a
couple
it's kind of like a tuple but it's not a
tuple it's range
[Laughter]
for the same reason that
like you can make a really long range
that goes from one to
whatever that huge number is but you
kind of can't take
make a really huge tuple that goes all
the way
to this number so tuples have an
explicit representation like all these
values are sitting around in memory
somewhere
whereas this is a implicit
representation of a range of numbers
which may be very long
but you really just have to remember the
beginning and the end in order to talk
about the whole thing
so in that sense ranges and tuples are
different
now they have similar characteristics
which is that they're both
immutable sequences so like uh
tuple could have anything in it it could
have lists it could have strings a range
can only have numbers in it but
it's true of both of them that you can't
do slice assignments you can't
extend or append or anything like that