61a lecture 32 q a
all right while we wait for the first
call john let's answer an important
question
is it sql or sql it's such a good
[Laughter]
question
yeah i don't know when people started
calling it sequel but that's what i call
it in like
in my life uh such a nice thing to say
yeah i like it i think most people say
sql now although it didn't used to
always be like that
right it's not so clear that you'll
someone will think you're strange if you
call it sql yeah that's the main
question i was asking will you look like
a noob if you uh if you say squish
dave i think the answer is no it's fine
right
the next question was whether it's
common to represent trees using sql
as opposed to data that's not
hierarchically structured
i don't i don't know if that tree
structure is common i think that's just
probably an artifact of the example that
john used john
yeah i think that's right so um
the the way in which a table is
structured is it's just a bunch of rows
a bunch of entities but what's
interesting is that you can represent
all kinds of more interesting structures
from that just by you know for example
describing the parent relationship in a
tree
or the connected relationship in you
know some kind of network
so i i guess the point of that example
was to show that
what you're trying to describe doesn't
always look tabular
and yet you can use a table to describe
it or maybe several tables
and that's kind of the the art that you
get
about building databases that comes with
experience
yeah good question so uh you've found
one of the topics that we've removed
from this semester but uh i'll
i'll talk about it anyway for a minute
which is about dynamic scope which is
different from lexical scope which is
what you're used to
so lexical scope basically says that um
the all of the variables within a
function
can be identified just by looking at the
code
so this is true in python if you have an
inner function
like the adder function within make
adder
you can see all the names within the
adder function
in the code they might be part of the
adder function they might be part of the
make getter function the enclosing scope
but they're all kind of there that's
what's called lexical scope
it's the most common way in which
programming languages work
in other offerings of this course we
talk about an alternative called dynamic
scope
which is hardly ever used it's kind of
interesting um
intellectually and there are a few cases
where it gets used but mostly it doesn't
exist in modern programming languages so
for that reason it's fine to just not
know about it but if you want to know
about it the
the story is basically that you um
when you call a function that functions
environment
inherits all of the names that already
existed
from wherever it was called and
that means that when you look at the
body of the function it might have names
in it that you just
you can't see anywhere in the code
because they're actually
defined where that function is called
maybe in a different file or something
like that
and dynamic scope allows you to kind of
set up your environment and then make a
function call
which is pretty different from lexical
scope where you have to pass in
everything that's relevant
but for that reason it can simplify some
things where instead of like passing in
seven different arguments
you just kind of have them already and
uh you don't have to pass any of them in
uh so that's kind of the story with
dynamic scope is that uh it's just the
same as lexical scope except for the
parent of a frame is always
the frame from which that function was
called as opposed to where that function
was defined
so the question is when you evaluate
some block some scheme expression or set
of scheme expressions
how many times does the eval function
get called in the scheme interpreter
especially when you have special forms
involved
and with special forms every special
form has its own rules
about what parts get evaluated when so
the most important special form is if
because it skips evaluating part of it
but some parts do get evaluated so if
you wonder
like if plus x
1 2 equals
3 then
what should we do compute that
uh well how about we print
five otherwise we print six
you actually have to call eval a lot of
times in order to evaluate this
you have to call eval on the entire
expression
that's what happens first actually and
then it's up to the rules of the special
form to decide what to evaluate next
so the next thing you evaluate always in
an if
is that first predicate expression
because you have to decide which of
these two you're going to evaluate and
you don't know in the beginning
so this is just something that's a rule
of if is that you always evaluate the
first expression and then you pick
and you evaluate either the first or the
second now
evaluating this actually is quite a bit
of work you have to
evaluate this symbol to figure out what
you're calling
you have to evaluate this whole
expression
this is a combination which means you
have to evaluate this symbol to figure
out what you're
calling and evaluate this number to
figure out what you're calling it on
and this number so we've actually called
eval
once twice 3 4 six seven eight times
already now we figure out that three
really does
equal three and it's time to
then evaluate either this or this well
we'll evaluate the first one
so we call eval on print56
print 5 6 is a call expression which
means we recursively
call eval on the operator to figure out
that we're printing
and the operand to figure out that we're
printing the number five
and then i think that's all the evals
that we're going to call
so one two three four five six seven
eight nine ten eleven
calls to eval in total is what you'd get
if you traced through the interpreter
while it was evaluating this program
and saw how many times eval got called
great so let's do one more example
where we've defined a user-defined
procedure like
cube x which what does that do
that multiplies x by x by x
and then we'll cube uh 1 plus 2
let's say when you evaluate
this notice i'm always evaluating like a
whole expression first that's what
happens is you pass the whole expression
into eval and say eval what the heck do
i do with this
when you evaluate a whole expression
that starts with define
it doesn't end up evaluating anything
else
right because that's the whole story
with a procedure definition
is that you don't evaluate the body
until later when you call it
so that's just one call to eval
the next called eval would be on this
whole thing where
you have to figure out what you're
calling by evaluating that symbol
calling it on now what you're calling it
on is not the expression plus one two
it's a number but to get to that number
you have to evaluate the plus in order
to figure out that you're adding
the one and the two and now you've
figured out that you're cubing three
so we've called eval a bunch of times
but we still haven't cubed anything
to cube something means to bind
x to three and then evaluate
this expression so that will be the next
step in terms of like calls to evaluate
it will be to evaluate this expression
here
hopefully that lines up can't really
tell but probably close enough
what i'm evaluating is this thing up
here to evaluate that i have to figure
out
what i'm calling and what i'm calling it
on
so the total number of calls to eval was
one here one two three four five six
in order to get ready to call cube and
then another uh
one two three four five in order to call
cube
so we have 12 in total
and maybe i solved the homework question
for you but that's fine
but it's kind of amazing like how much
recursion there is in an evaluator but
that's because
like every little piece of the big
expression needs to be evaluated in
order to get the result
um so aaron asks can you go over apply
for these expressions as well
yeah so i guess the question is how many
times does apply get called
apply gets called whether you're
applying a user-defined procedure or a
primitive procedure
every time a call expression gets
evaluated
assuming there's no error along the way
so finding all the applies is a little
bit easier
uh i think there's i guess
what symbol should i use how about that
uh
we applied once to do that we applied
again to do that
we applied again to do that we applied
and down here we didn't apply at all
when we were defining cube
but we did apply the cube procedure and
the plus procedure so
you know there's four applies to do this
one and there's two applies to do that
one
uh it does not involve apply when you
reach a special form
special forms are all handled by
something other than apply apply is kind
of the default case when you know it's
not a special form it's just a regular
procedure call
then you're going to be calling apply in
order to apply the procedure to its
arguments
and there's the times in the function
john
minus one for me we do need to apply
that
but following up on this the one tricky
part with apply is that if i were to
call cube
twice then i would end up applying this
twice so if for example
you know this is going to screw up all
my indentation but if we had like cube
cube
or whatever um
then not only do you have to apply the q
procedure twice
but since you're calling cube twice you
have to apply the times
twice so sandra's asking in the chat
would the apply cube not take into
account the times is the question
it is a different call to apply when you
apply
cube which is like a procedure that will
do something but
you know the interpreter doesn't know
what it is yet
versus the second call to apply which is
when you're actually evaluating the body
of cube
and it's time to apply the times so
these are two different
uh applies and uh
you know you're gonna have to apply the
plus and then apply the cube to apply
the times then apply the cube to apply
the times and you'll
end up getting five applies in order to
do this this code
okay and somebody's asking the second
print the second print doesn't get
applied that's correct because oh yeah
so so you can't just look at the code
you got to think about what gets
evaluated but every time you evaluate a
call expression then you apply
okay we've finally drawn something that
i think is coherent
okay the next question asked us to
re-explain the last slide in the lecture
which was about string manipulation okay
so i showed you this slide
with some descriptions of how to combine
and manipulate strings in sql which is
possible
you can concatenate strings together you
can get sub strings
you can find things within strings
and there might be more stuff you can do
with strings but i guess
just using those three pieces you can do
an awful lot
strings can really represent anything
they can represent text
they could also represent code they
could represent
um like any kind of data could kind of
be written out in some kind of string
form if you come up with a clever enough
representation
and so for that reason you can kind of
store anything in a sql table
but the kind of more clever you are
about what you store inside of a string
the harder it's going to be to use that
database later
so that was the idea behind these
traffic lights is that if you
treat strings as a way of representing
text you'll almost never run into
trouble
because that's kind of what they were
designed for originally
if you then
involve a lot of manipulating that text
like you come up with an expression that
that that doctors the text in
interesting ways
well sometimes that's a good idea
because that's exactly what you need
but usually it's better to have like
some other program doing this
manipulation
something that gives you a little bit
better control
over string manipulation like python's a
good string manipulation language
and what i don't recommend is that you
try to use strings to represent
some other data structure like a list
or an image or you know a snippet of
code
or something like that and then be
manipulating that as if it were a list
or an image or a snippet of code
this can be done sometimes if you're
clever
so here's an example of trying to use a
string to represent a whole list
and here we've like
come up with a way of finding the
second element in the list but when you
do this
you're usually making your database
harder to use
and your sql code more complicated than
it needs to be
it would instead be better to come up
with some other way of representing the
list
for example have each element in the
list be its own row
as opposed to trying to squeeze it all
into a string
where it's much harder to access the
pieces
one of the nice things about things like
sql lite also
audrey is that you can incorporate them
into other languages so for example
there are python hooks into
sql lite there are javascript hooks into
it where you can
query the database get the data out and
then do the manipulation there you don't
have to do everything in sql so these
things
interact in really nice ways i tend to
think of i don't like doing
database manipulations the way john is
shown here i prefer to have that be the
storing of the data
i'll extract the data using python
javascript whatever it is
and then do whatever i want to to draw
the inference
yeah like another reasonable thing is
maybe this should be a yellow light and
this should be a red light and this
should just be on fire or something like
that
it's a perfectly reasonable point of
view to say like look uh
let the let the data manipulation happen
elsewhere there are reasons
why you want sql to do some work
sometimes that is the most efficient way
because kind of the the processing can
happen where the data is in some cases
but
for most applications i think it's
better to have the application logic be
outside of the database
and keep the database queries pretty
simple
and on friday in this optional lecture
which i would recommend
we'll talk about how to get python to
interface with sql lite so you can kind
of have both of them happening at the