61a lecture 35 q a
except that today i forgot to record the
q a so i'm going to do my best
to remember some of the questions that
people asked
and answer them here it turns out that
this was a pretty short q a anyway so
hopefully you didn't miss much
we didn't go over any exam problems or
anything like that
we just talked about recent lecture
content
so here we go the first question was was
the tail call
how does that relate to a tail context
well a tail call is a call
expression if you have just like a
number literal like 12
then that's never a tail call you have
to call a procedure
and what's the tale context is is it
always the last thing
and what does it mean by the last thing
that gets evaluated
well it's more specific than just being
the last thing that gets evaluated
it's really that it's the thing that you
evaluate in order to get the return
value
of the whole procedure that you're
currently calling
so you know if this were python and we
actually had return statements
then basically you'd know you're in a
tail context
if you had the return keyword right
there and that expression was a call
expression
where the result of that call expression
was going to be what you were returning
from the current function that you're in
and after that we talked a little bit
about map so let's look at this map
example
here it is uh map checks to see
if s is null um the predicate position
the first position
in an if is never a tail context because
you're always going to have to evaluate
either this or this
afterwards so the only things that could
be
tail context are here and here and they
are as long as this whole thing is in a
tail context which it is because it's
the only thing
in the whole procedure so null s is not
entailed context but it's not calling
map anyway so it kind of doesn't matter
this is this whole cons expression
is in a tail context but the map within
it is not
now this is an interesting case because
after you
evaluate the call to map you've like
done a bunch of work
you actually don't need the current
environment for this original call to
map
in order to do any more evaluation
you've already evaluated cons you've
already evaluated the result of calling
procedure
you've already evaluated map really the
only thing left to do is apply
the cons procedure to the results the
arguments that you get from these two
so you don't really need the environment
but you do need to remember
that you were about to cons and that you
have this procedure that you're
consuming with so you have some like
information
associated with this call to map that is
more than just the information you get
from returning from this call to map
there's like more work to do still after
you call map from within map
and therefore it is not a tail call so
the rest of the slide looks like this
it says this whole thing is a tail
context and so is this but this part is
not although we came up with a way of
rewriting map
such that all of the recursive calls
were in tail contexts
and it turns out that's possible but
only with some amount of reversing
and by the way there's another way to do
this which is to perform mutation in
order to build up the result
but we haven't talked about mutation in
scheme it's part of the language but
just not part of this course
and so um you know you can work out how
to make map
tail recursive in that way too the
second question was about the
code.cs61a.org sql interpreter
how do you get it to display tables that
you defined
so for example if you're working on the
homework and you want to
see what this table looks like if you
paste it in here
then you don't see the table well create
table doesn't really
output anything it just assigns the name
parents to some new table
you would have to select star from
parents in order to see the whole table
okay another question was about when you
would ever join three tables together
where you join a table with some other
table and then back with itself
and it turns out that when you join
a table with itself and another table
versus joining a table with another
table and back to itself that's the same
thing the order in which you join tables
doesn't matter
i mean it matters a little bit in that
if you select star from the result
you'll see
values in the table order that you join
them in but
you're not going to get different rows
at the end of the day you're not going
to get different contents
regardless of what order you join things
in so
we went back and looked at this example
from lecture this is from lecture 32
that was the second sql lecture
and here was a case where it made sense
to
join a table with itself and some other
table and i think this is the standard
way in which you see a three-way join
where some table is there twice and then
some other table is there once
is that you're trying to relate two
different attributes
for two different entities in some table
like the dogs table
in this case we're trying to relate
their fur together make sure their fur
is equal
but you're also trying to express some
other relation that requires a join
so the other relation here is that you
want
um not just to find two dogs with the
same fur
but two dogs with the same fur and the
names of those dogs are related to each
other one is the grandparent of the
other
but you can't just look at a name from
dogs and another name from dogs
and know that their grandparent
grandchild
you have to join in information from
another table in order to get that
so some other table tells you what all
the grandparent pairs are
and there you end up with a three-way
joint in order to go from
dog's name to grandpup's name to
granddog's name
to dog's name and now you know that the
name of this dog and this name of this
dog are referring to two dogs
that have this granddaughter grandpup
relationship
now in a three-way joint it's not always
the case that you want their
characteristics to be the same here we
have they have the same fur but you
could also say like
you know what are all the fur pairs you
know the fur of one dog and the fur the
other dog
where one's a granddog and one's a grand
pup you'd still need a three-way joint
for that
even if you didn't have the fur in the
wear condition but instead showed up in
select somewhere
so in the q a we were talking about you
know how would you write an expression
of
what kind of shoes one professor has and
what kind of shoes another professor
have but you only care about pairs of
professors that are teaching the same
course
you might get the same kind of
relationship just like the dog's table
tells you about the fur of the dogs
there might be a professor's table that
tells you about what kind of shoes they
wear
and then instead of a grandparents table
telling you who's granddaughter grandpup
you could have some table that tells you
oh here's pairs of professors that are
teaching the same course
and you'd end up with a three-way joint
too the next question was about the
order of operations within
a sql statement
particularly does the where happen first
or does the having clause happen first
and the answer surprisingly is it
depends what's in those clauses i think
so here is a cities table
that's hard to read here's a city's
table from lecture
where you have a latitude longitude and
name of the city
so there are all the rows you might
think you know if you write something
like
i want the name from cities
where latitude is greater than 38
in order to get the cold cities that
what happens is that
you know first you get all the rows and
then you filter them
and then you get their names there's
some order here
like from comes first and then where and
then select it turns out this is not the
case
if i wrote something like select name
and i want to know
if they're cold or not so i create a
column for that
and i select that from cities and then i
write a where clause
i'm fine to refer to the cold in the
result
so it turns out that you might compute
these values
before you filter by them
and that's just how sql works is that
the sql
query engine figures out which parts
need to be evaluated first
in order to evaluate later parts later
that's kind of one of the interesting
characteristics
of database management systems so you
know we don't write our own
query engine in this course because
they're pretty complicated when you take
a database course you can learn about
how to do that
but then there's this kind of question
of does where select input rows
or output rows and the answer is it kind
of depends on
what you put in there okay so those are
actually all the questions that i
remember from q
a today connie also made a very nice
comment about how he hopes that you all
have a nice relaxing thanksgiving break
and get recharged in order to finish out
the semester
which i think is a great thing i'm sorry
you couldn't hear him say it because i
failed to record it
but um we both really hope that you get
some rest this week after you finish the
scheme project
maybe find some pumpkin pie and enjoy
the rest
and we will pick this up again next week
because there's no lecture on wednesday