61 a lecture No.35
announcements
the scheme project is due on Tuesday
you can get an early submission
bonus point for completing it
by Monday
if you want the early submission bonus point
and the extra credit for
solving the letter lambda problem
do it all by Monday
homework nine is do the Thursday after thanksgiving
it's posted already
but you could ignore it until next week
that would be fine
lab 13
which would normally be do
this Tuesday is optional
everybody will get credit for that lab
whether you touch it or you don't
but I recommend that you do the lab
because it's good preparation
for the final exam
we normally have five lab orientations
but we've reduced that down to two
since this is optional
I suspect that attendance will be a little bit lower
we will of course
post the lab orientation recordings if
that time is inconvenient
so that you can take a look at those
this Wednesday through Friday
there will be nothing associated with the class
no lecture no discussion no tutorials no office hours
and the only other thing going on
is the completely optional
scheme recursive art contest
which has entries
do the Monday after thanksgiving
you will find an assignment for the scheme contest
that describes the rules
and how to submit
one more thing to look out for
the week after thanksgiving
is that we've added some
longer 45min tutorials for that week
where they will focus on review
discussion and lab
that week are focused on review anyway
but we're going to try out some longer tutorials
if you think that format would fit better
so if you scroll around on tutorials
that'll see a sixty one eight
at oreg which is linked here
you'll find some of those
so I hope you have a great thanksgiving
today's lecture is optional
you should really watch it
that's one of my favorite topics in the course
called tail calls
which is scheme's answer to the wild loop
how come there's no wild statement in scheme
well you could use recursion
but isn't recursion slow and take up a lot of memory
well not necessarily
here's a topic
about
programming languages and how they're interpreted
that deals with exactly that problem
throughout the lecture
you might hear reference to extra credit
because in a typical semester
re engineering your interpreter
so that it performs tale call optimization
is an extra credit problem
and the
let talamda problem is typically a required problem
but now we've made it extra credit
and remove the tail call problem
it's still there
optionally you can work on it if you want
in fact it's kind of fun to
work out how you would add
that to the interpreter that you have
it requires you to
understand the whole structure of the program
you've written in
project four
or if you don't want to do that
you could just listen to this lecture
and then you'll know all about
what people mean when they say
tale recursion or tale calls
and if one of the lecture videos says something
about extra credit
and you're wondering whether you could get
extra credit for doing that this semester
the answer is no
but I did not re record all the videos
because the content is the same
alright let's dive in
the entire lecture today
is about how to solve the extra credit problem
on project four
but it also brings up a very important concept
in programming languages called tail recursion
so functional programming is this idea
that you can organize entire programs
according to pure functions
which our modular can be combined interesting ways
and also have other advantages
so functional programming
is a very broad term
but often refers to the following properties
that all functions are pure functions
they don't have side effects
there's no reassignment
no mutable data types
when you create something it's there to stick
and the name
value bindings that you create are permanent as well
when you have these things
then you gain certain advantages
1st
the value of an expression is independent of the order
in which sub expressions are evaluated
now
we could just pick a particular order
and that's what we do in python
but would it be nice
if we could choose any order we want
depending on the circumstances
in particular
we could evaluate sub expressions in parallel
if we had multiple different processing units
or we could even wait
and see if we really
need the value of an sub expression
before getting around to evaluating it
these things are productive referential transparency
this idea that the value of an expression
doesn't change
when you substitute one of its sub expressions
with the value of that sub expression
which allows you to do things like memorization
without ever worrying
that you're changing the behavior of your program
so these are all good things
and so functional programming has a lot of excitement
around it especially in this era when
computers are having more and more processing units
wouldn't it be nice to just paralyze work automatically
but one might wonder
if there are no four and wild statements
because we're not allowed to rebind a name
to a new value
can we really make basic iterated procedures efficient
or we just stuck using recursion and recursion is slow
and so
there's no way these languages could ever be fast
well it turns out there's an answer to this question
you can make a functional programming language
just as efficient
as one that's not
by using this idea
of tail recursion that we're gonna talk about today
so let's look at an example
recursion versus iteration
in python and python recursive calls always create new
active frames
let's see what that means
well let's ever riding a function factorial nk
that computes k times n factoria
here's a recursive definition
if n is zero
we just return k because zero factorial is one
otherwise we return a recursive call
where end is decremented and also multiplied in
to the constant
so then we've accumulated
all of the different terms of the factorial
by the time we reach and is zero
and here's an integrity of definition
factorial nk while n is greater than zero rebind and nk
to end minus one and k times in and then return k
so the same
logic is being applied in both of these cases
but there is a difference
the difference in time is only up to a constant factor
this is a linear time recursion
but linear time recursions take linear amounts of space
the iterative version also takes linear time
you have to go through the
body of this wild statement many times
ones for each end
and then it gets deck permitted each time
but we only have a constant amount of space
because we have a constant number
of names that we have to remember
and nk and factorial regardless of how big and is
so how do we bridge this gap
between the space that's required
for a factorial in the recursive sense
versus the intrigible one
that's the whole idea of what we're talking about today
if you read the specification of the language ski
it says
implementations of schema required to be properly tale
recursive
this allows the execution of an iterative computation
in constant space
even if the iterative computation is described
by a syntactically recursive procedure
so remember we have our iterative version in python
which takes linear time but constant space
the idea is that if you write the same logic
as the scheme procedure
so this says the way you compute and time
k times on factorial
is you check and see if an is zero
then you return k otherwise you make a recursive call
and that should use resources like this
but how do we do that
well the answer is that we eliminate the middleman
we eliminate frames that we don't need anymore
when we make recursive calls
let me show you which frames those are
so we're back in python
we're looking at the recursive definition of factorial
and as we step through it
we see that each call to factorial creates a new frame
and here we have end bound to four
here end bound to three end bound to two
soon we'll have end bound to one and end bound to zero
which is the final state
now what's going to be returned
well this one's going to return to 40
we see that but notice that each one of these other
calls is also
just going to return the result of the last one
forty
forty two forty two forty two forty and we're done
now there was no need to keep around this end in this k
in order to figure out that we were just
kind of returned whatever we got back
from the next call
so all these extra frames in the middle
they were needed briefly in order to figure out
how to make the recursive call
but they weren't needed any more
after the recursive call was made
we kept them around anyway
because that's how python works
but a properly tale recursive language will not do that
the fundamental idea here to make
these recursive procedures efficient
is that some calls
are tail calls and some aren't
it's a distinction that figures out whether
when one procedure is calling another procedure
is there more work to do
when that called procedure is finished or not
if there isn't anything else to do
besides
just return the value of the expression you call
well then that's a tale call
so tail calls have kind of a long definition
so let's go through it
a procedure call that has not yet returned as active
meaning
we're still going to return something from it someday
some procedure calls are tail calls
a scheme interpreter
should support an unbounded number
that means as many as we want
an unbounded number of tail calls
using only a constant amount of space
and it's going to do that
by skipping over all those extra frames that you saw
in the environment diagram
this shows up in python
okay so what's a tail call
a tail call is a call expression
in a tail context
what's a tail context
well there's several
one is the last
body sub expression in a lambda expression
so it turns out that the lambda expression
can have multiple different
body expressions
the last one is the one that determines the return
value
and so that expression is in a tail context
meaning it's a description of the last thing
that this procedure is going to do
before it returns
now in addition
you can also have a tail call as sub expression
two or three in a tail context if expression
so remember
if expression has three sub expressions that predicate
the consequent
and the alternative
those consequent and alternatives are tail contexts
if it's the case that the whole if
expression is in a tail context
so let's look at this factorial definition
the last body sub expression
in the definition of factorial
is this whole thing
which is an if expression
so this if expression is in a tail context
which means that its sub expressions two and three
are also in a tail context
that's this k here
and then this call to factorial here
so that's a tail context as well
and this is a call expression in a tail context
and so it's a tail call
so that's the kind of thing
that should only require a constant amount of space
no matter
how many times we call it over and over again
the idea is once you compute factorial
of n minus one and k times in
you've
already done all the work you need to do for factorial
mk all you have to do is return it
so it doesn't really matter what n and kr anymore
once you've done all this work
now there are other tail contexts
so all non predicate sub expressions in a tail context
con which you'll read about in your project
the last sub expression in a tail context and or or
and the last sub expression in a tail context begin
these aren't terribly important except that
if you're actually sitting down and writing
a scheme program
you need to know what the tale context are
so you know
what's going to be the space efficiency or space usage
of your program
so people spend a lot of time making
sure that they put all of their
recursive talls and tail contexts when possible
so that their whole program doesn't use too much space
but for today we're just gonna focus on these first two
cases last body sub expression in alamda expression or
sub expressions two and three in a tail context
if expression
so we've seen both of these examples right here
let's do another example
computing the length of a list
a call expression is not a tail call
if more computation is required
in the calling procedure
so if after I finish
my recursive call
I still need to combine that value with something else
then I don't have a tail call
but it's the case that linear recursive procedures can
often be rewritten
to use tail calls
so here is a
linear recursive procedure for computing the length
of a list s
and it says
it fesses nullet zero
otherwise
it's one more than the length of the rest of s
now this is a tale context
because it's the last expression in length
since it's a tale context and it's an if expression
both zero and
the alternative here are both in tale context
so this is good
this is a call expression in a tail context
so this addition is a tail call
however this is not
so this is a call expression within a call expression
and that's exactly when you know you're not
in a tail context
after we've compute the length of the rest of s
we still have more work to do to add one to it
now we don't know what work there might be to do left
and so
for instance maybe there would be a reference to s
and so we might need the environment
for this function call
around because there's more work to do
so in this case
an implementation of length here would require
linear space to keep around all the frames for length
in each recursive call
but let's see if we can rewrite length so that it is
tail recursive
here's a common way to do so
we define another procedure
length itter which takes in
the same list that we're computing the length of
and also the length that we've computed so far and
if s is null
then we've computed the entire length and we return in
otherwise
we return the value of recursive call on the rest of s
with one more than the length of what we've seen so far
so in the beginning we haven't seen any length
so we start with zero
each time we make a recursive call we add one
until we get to the end
and then we've computed the length
now this is a very different program
in terms of its behavior
this is in a tail context
because it's the last expression
in a lambda expression or define
why do I keep calling it a lambda expression
well a define
of a procedure is implicitly a lambda expression
remember this is the same as saying
define length tail lambda s
blah blah blah
okay
so that's in a tail context
this is in a tail context because this is a separate
procedure definition
and this is the last thing in the procedure definition
which means this is an a tale context
because when you have an if
expression in a tale context
then its alternative is also a tale context
and that's a call expression in a tail context
meaning it's a tail call
meaning this whole thing is only going to run
in constant space
now the actual list itself takes a blender space
but the additional
space that's used in order to compute the length
doesn't have a whole bunch of frames in it
and only has one
so I hear this recursive call as a tale call
or as this recursive call was not
so how do I convince you that this really matters
well we're going to have to run a demonstration
so it should be that the return value of the tale call
is the return value of the current procedure call
meaning we can skip
keeping around all the frames that we don't need
because the return values for the last frame
can return straight up to the original call
pale calls shouldn't increase the environment size
and we can see that
by calling this factorial function on a big input
okay so
here's scheme that pie
which is part of your project
and way down below where you implement the extra credit
it says uncommon
the following line
to apply a tail call optimization
so right now it's commented out as you can see
which means we're using just a regular schema val
which is not optimized for tail calls
because we haven't implemented that part yet
that's the extra credit
okay so let's
define a function that returns
factorial times k
define factorial of n and k
if
n is zero we just return k
otherwise we'll return factorial
of n minus one
and
k times it
okay so what sort of state are we in
we have a tail recursive function
we analyze that already
this is a tail context so this is a tail context
we have an interpreter
that is not optimized for tail calls
so it's just going to create a frame
every time we make a recursive call
and that frame will stick around until
we return from the call
and that will use a linear amount of space
which means that if we run scheme dot pi
and load in this factorial
we can compute the factorial of 10
we can compute the factorial of 100
what if we compute the factorial of 1000
we reach an error
it says maximum recurs and depth exceeded
while calling our python object
so what happened it got all the way up it seems
to computing the factorial of 673
and then it just gave up
because it had made too many recursive calls
and so was using up too much memory
so python said sorry you've reached your limit
we're done
which is unfortunate
because we should be able to compute
as much of this as we want
using our constant amount of space
so I have an implementation of the extra credit
which just says use a different eval function
one that
doesn't create an extra frame when it doesn't need to
so let's run this again
let's load our factorial function
if I compute the factorial of 10 it works fine
100 works fine
1000 works fine as well
and if I compute the factorial of 10,000
well sure it takes a while
I'm not making anything really faster
but I am saving the extra space
so we computed this huge No.10,000 factorial
now eventually this program will run out of space
not because we create extra frames but because
representing this
number will just become too big
because it has so many digits
but that's gonna take a long while
so very efficiently we've computed factorial of 10,000
using tail over cursion
to make sure
that we don't use any space that we don't need to use
let's look at some examples
of tail recursion
so here's your task
figure out which of the four procedures defined below
are tail recursive
for a recursive function to be tail recursive
what I mean is that
all of the recursive calls are tail calls
and therefore
the procedure will be executed in constant space
so which of the following procedures run
in constant space
take a look yourself
and then I'll go through the answers
let's first look at length
length defined here
is not tail recursive
the final expression
in the procedure definition
is a tail context
but the sub expressions of it aren't
so in particular
this if expression is not in a tail context
and that idea that the
consequent and alternative sub expressions of an if
are in tail context
only works if the whole if is in a tail context
so this is not either
which means that
evaluating length here is going to require linear
space in the length of s
let's look at contains next
contains is
tail recursive because the recursive call
to contains is in a tail context
this is a tail context because it's the last expression
in a procedure definition
and this is a tale context because
it's one of the second or 3rd
sub expressions in an if expression
that's in a tale context
and therefore this is in a tale context too
and that's the recursive call
so contains will take in something that's linear size
because s is a list
but
the amount of additional space required
for contains to be called is constant
how about has repeat
well
has repeat as exactly the same structure as contains
so has repeated as a function
that figures out whether s has any repeated elements
and it does so by calling contains
so the entire
if expression which is the body of this procedure
is in a tail context
which means this is in a tail context
which means this is two
so the whole thing runs in constant space
and by the way
when it calls contains that's not a tail context
but since contains already just runs in constant space
because it itself is tail recursive
we don't have to worry about
that taking up a bunch of route
finally we have a procedure
to compute the end fibonacci number
so let's see how this actually works
fit bitter takes the current fibonacci number
which is fibonacci number k
and if we're all the way up to the nth one
which is the one we're looking for
then we return current
otherwise we call phil bitter
on the current plus the k minus one phibonoggy number
and we increment k when we do that
so starting out
we check and see
if we're just looking for the first one
well then we return zero otherwives we call fib ditter
starting with the second fibonacci number which is one
so this is a tail context
so far so good
this whole thing is a tail context
and so that is
so this recursive call is fine
but the problem is that this sub expression of a call
expression is not a tail context
so this is not a tail call
and it is a recursive function call to fip
so this whole thing
is not going to run in constant space
because it makes a recursive call
even though we have two mutually recursive functions
and fib iter for them to run in constant space
both would have to make
tail calls to each other
and in this case
we have something that's not a tail call
there's more work to be done
as soon as we figure out
the k minus one fibonacci number
we still have to combine it with current
in order to finish
and then we have to call fi bitter on that
next we'll look at two higher order functions
map and reduce
so let's look at reduced first
reduces a
procedure that takes another procedure
some list s which we're going to add right over
and then a starting value
and what it does is
it combines a starting value with the first element of
s combines that result with the second element etc
using the procedure to combine them
so if we reduce
what is the multiplication up procedure
the list 3 4 5
starting with two
then we'll get two times three times four
times five is 120
and if we reduce
using a procedure
that takes two things and khansas them together
why first the next
with a starting value of the list containing two
will then cons on three
then we'll cons on four to that
then we'll cons on five to that
consing a number where the list
gives you a longer list with the number in front
so the entire result will be 5 4 3 2
okay let's look at the definition
if s is null then we just use this starting value
otherwise we reduce with the procedure
the rest of s
though we need to create a new starting value
which is
the procedure that was passed in
called on the starting value we had before
and the first element of s
so in this way we create a new starting value
which already includes
not only what we started with before
but also the first element of s
so in this case we'll start with two
but in the next recursive call to reduce
we'll have two times three to six
and in the next one after that
we'll have multiplied in four to get 24
and eventually 120
so let's take a look
this whole thing is a tail context
which means this is a tail context
but this is not
so does the whole thing run in constant time
well it really just depends on what the procedure does
so the recursive call to reduce is a tail call
but the other call
in particular the procedure call is not
and this is a higher order function
so we don't know what procedure will be passed in
so the total space of reduce will depend on
whether the procedure requires constant space or not
hopefully it just requires constant space
in which case the entire reduce will require only
constant space
okay now let's talk about
how to map with only a constant number of frame
map is a function that applies a procedure
to every element in a list and constructs a list
containing all of the results
so
let's come up with the most natural version to define
map
and then we'll come up with a tail recursive version
so a natural way to define
map is to say we take in a procedure
in a list test
if s is now we return the empty list
otherwise
we're going to create a new list with a first element
is whatever we get by applying the procedure
to the car of s to the first element of s
and then the rest of this result
will be what you get
when you map the procedure over the rest of the list
so for example if I map a function
that takes each element and subtracts it from five
to the list one two
under this definition which is not tail recursive
we start out with the list one two
we bind it to s in the first call to map
the second call to map takes the rest of s
and the third call takes the rest of that
now the final result
of returning from the third call is just nill
but the second call
returns a list that starts with three
and the third call starts a list that starts with four
so four is five minus one and three is 2-1
and that's what we're computing here
so this is not tail recursive because
we have a tail context for all of if
but within cons
which isn't a tail context
we have a sub expression
that's not in a tail context that calls map
so here is a tale recursive definition of map
not what you would expect
define map by computing the reverse of the map
meaning exactly what we want but in the reverse order
this first checks if s is null
if so we return the result which is the
map list in reverse that we've already constructed m
if it's not null that we have more work to do
so we call map reverse on the rest of s
so that's everything else we're going to work on
and what we're going to do is we're going to
cons on the next element of the resulting
mapped list so we cons
on the result of calling the procedure on the car of s
and
what's the rest of that
well that's the m we've constructed so far
so we're gonna start out with a nill
we're gonna add the four on first
and then we're gonna add the three on
thus giving us our list in reverse order
so finally we need to call reverse on map reverse s no
now as this a tale context well
this whole thing is in a tale context
so the call to reverse is
this call is not
but notice it's not a recursive call to map
it's a call to map reverse which is
a tail recursive procedure that runs in constant space
now what about reverse
well
we need to make sure that that's tail recursive too
so here's a definition of reversing a list
we define
reverse iter which takes s and the reverse list so far
and what we're going to do is cons
on a reversed version of s to r
so if s is null then we just have r otherwise
we call reverse hitter on the rest of s
conzagon the first element of s onto r
so think about it for a minute
you'll see that this will reverse the list
if I just start out with nil as my reverse list
and s as the thing I'm reversing
so this is one of the more complex examples
of making a procedure tail recursive
there were two steps
we had to figure out
how to make sure
that we could build up something
that maps over the elements of s
such that we collect all the results
and then
we realized that I would build it in the reverse order
because as you are building up the recursive list
from the back to the front
you're processing the input from the front to the bet
and so then we have the defined refers
in order to give us exactly the result that we want
our final thought today is
what is it that we're creating
when we create an interpreter
well we're creating a general computing machine
so here's an analogy
think of programs as defining little machines
by laying out the procedure
by which we evaluate some input to give some output
so the program specifies
the logic of some computational device
so if we create a device that computes factorials
well that might look like this
or it says
if the input is one
then we just have one
otherwise we have to multiply the input
by 1 the factorial of the input
and factorial here
of course is just another copy
of this computational device
so five comes in 1120 comes out five factorial
well interpreters are like general computing machines
so the interpreter takes in his input
any piece of code that tells it to simulate
any particular machine that we want
so the scheme interpreter
might take in five as the input
but also the source
code that tells us how to compute the factorial
and it uses both of these things together
in order to create any sort of computation
that we wish
for instance computing 120
so our scheme interpreter that we've built
or we are in the process of building
as your project
is a universal machine
it can perform any computation we wish
depending on how it's parameterized
by the input source code that's given to it
so think of it as a bridge
between the data
objects that are manipulated
by our programming language
and the programming language itself
it's the thing that puts them together
internally though
remember that it's just a set of evaluation rules
an interpreter is nothing more than a program