61 a lecture No.26
announcements
very little to announce
because you made it through midterm two
congratulations
I know it's been a lot of work recently but you made it
and I think we'll have a little bit of
space in the course now
today's lecture is optional
I hope it's interesting
and we've made some other
lectures in the last
part of the course optional as well
just to make sure that you have
enough time to learn the really important stuff
this Friday there won't be any instructor office hours
but we will have an instructor ask us anything session
starting at 2 10
I change the link
so here's the new link
this will not be recorded
so if you want to ask us stuff and hear our answers
you have to come
there will not be an exam prep section
Friday because you just took the exam
in addition to watching today's lecture
I recommend going back and watching lecture 25
if you missed it
that was from this Monday
it's cool
today's lecture is very cool as well
professor fried is going to talk about
some very important
issues at the intersection
of computer science and society
around algorithmic bias
data bias the ethical use of artificial intelligence
and the ethical use of data
so I encourage you to watch this before
coming to ask us anything session
because something
in here might inspire you to ask us some questions
and I hope to see you tomorrow
when we have this session
and you can ask us anything you want
we are all living through phenomenal digital revolution
advances in technology and data acquisition
and artificial intelligence
have impacted just about every corner of our live
not just here in the u s
but around the globe to some 7 billion people
and many of these things are wonderful
there are really many tremendous things
about democratization
of access to information and technology
and bring the world closer
and communication
on betas with every innovation there are dark sides
and as a young
budding computer scientist we shouldn't ignore those
we should pay attention to the ethical issues
and the potential harm
that can come
from technologies that we ourselves are developing
and that's what this lecture is about today
by way of a case study
so I'm going to be talking a little bit
about ethical issues around artificial intelligence
and data and the work I'm going to be describing
is that of julia dressa
julia was a student with me at dartmouth college
she graduated in 2007
and the work I'm going to be describing was
her senior thesis work
and this work all started
around this issue of the use of ai
to make recommendations
now you have all
almost certainly been subjected to a recommendation
that looks something like this
if you liked x then you may like y
Netflix amazon spotify
recommendations that look
at the patterns of movies you watch
products you buy music that you listen to
look at what other people have done with those
same patterns and make recommendations
sometimes it works sometimes it doesn't
either way it's fine
I mean there's just recommendations for watching movies
now you may have also been subjected
to
a recommendation engine that looks something like this
if you are like x then we may accept you
companies in some cases universities
are using automatic algorithms
to review your applications and make determinations
as to whether you should be interviewed
or granted a job
your the stakes are of course
getting a little bit higher now
because we are talking about your potential employment
and educational prospects
maybe you have not already because you're all young
but many of us have been subjected to
predictions that look like this
if you are like acts then we may give you alone
banks financial institutions routinely look
at your credit history
your history in financial transactions
compares that to other people
looks to see what the default rates are
and make recommendations
do you get a mortgage do you get a small business loan
stakes are giving a little bit higher now
this is now your financial well being as well
and more and more over the last few years
people have been subjected
to the following type of prediction
if you are like axe
then we may put you in jail
courts now around the country are routinely using
predictive algorithms to determine whether you are at
risk of committing a crime
whether you are being released on probation
whether you be unconsidered for bail
and now the stakes are getting very high
which is now it is your very liberty that is a stake
for these prediction algorithms
and it is these types of algorithms in particular
that we're going to talk about today
now in 2006 pro publica wrote a really impactful piece
and if you have not seen this
I'm going to encourage you
to search for this piece called machine bias
they're softer
used across the country to predict future criminals
and it is biased against blacks
it was a phenomenal body of reporting
that pointed to some very troubling patterns
in a softer that was being used in the courts of law
to make predictions
about whether somebody is at
risk of committing a crime in the future
and whether that person should be granted bail or not
so let me talk a little bit
about what this article found
and I'm going to tell you a little bit of that
about what julia and I
worked on for the following year to try to really
understand
what's happening with this type of machine bias
so a pro publica found is that one particular software
produced what's called the recidivism risk score
this essential takes his input
some information about you
how many times you've been committed a crime before
how many times you've been arrested
how much time you served in jail
your employment history
your age your gender
and the long list of things that you might
have information
about somebody
and it produced a score
and that score was
what is your risk of committing a crime
in the next two years
and then that could be used
and in fact was being used by the courts
to make a judge minus to whether you were at risk for
recivivating and whether they should grant you bell
and what pro publica found
is that the mistakes that this
algorithm made it
it's okay
we understand that these things are not perfect
but the nature of the mistakes were very problematic
so I'm going to talk about two types of mistakes
the first one is a false positive
which says I'm going to predict that you recidivate
but you in fact don't
so I'm going to classify you as high risk
but in fact you are not high risk at all
and what they found is that if you were black
then you were 44.9% of the times you were predicted
to recidivate when you didn't
but if you were right that was only about half of that
23 and a half percent
that is a huge difference
across the races
so that is black people were being
falsely accused of being high risk
one in fact they were not
at a rate twice that of white people
now that's not the only type of mistakes
that the algorithm makes
it also can make a false negative
which is that you are predicted not to recidivate
but in fact you do
so I say you know what this person's not high risk
but it turns out they go out and they commit a crime
so let's look at the error rate for these
false negatives
for across races
if you were black
that error only happened 28% of the time
but if you were white it happened 47.7% of the time
exactly the opposite
so in the previous false positive
blacks were at about a factor of two disadvantage
of saying they were high risk when they weren't
and not only that
but in this mistake's white are being advantaged
by saying that they are not high risk
when they are
so obviously this is deeply troubling
this is not obviously fair
and we need to understand this
if we're going to use these types of ai algorithms
we need to understand
where is this coming from and what can we do about it
so shortly after this article appear
julia came to me and said
we have to do something about this
we are technologists we are mathematicians
we are computer scientists
we have to fix this
we have to build a better prediction algorithm
and I agreed with her
and we set out over the next year and a half or so
to try to do that
and as we were doing that a question came up
we were sitting in my office one day
and
one of us asked the question as well
you know we keep trying to come up with
algorithms that are better
than humans but
do we actually know
what how good humans are at this task
I mean just baseline
I mean if you're trying to build an algorithm that
deals with
potential bias in the criminal justice system
shouldn't we ask how well humans are
and of course the answers yes
and so we were not looked at the lord turin
in fact we
couldn't find anybody
who would assess what the baseline is
so what are these algorithms being compared against
how do you know whether an algorithm is improving
the state of the art
if you don't know how well humans are performing
and so that's what we set out to do
at the very beginning
is just to ask a really simple question
is the ai these algorithms any better than you
in me
and potential people who are making these decisions
and then we want to understand
what is the nature of that racial bias that we saw
and then can we fix it
so we're going to start by answering this
and then we're going to get to those other questions
all right I'm going to stop right here
and we'll pick it up in a little bit
and start getting at this question right here
I'll see you in a few minutes
where we left off was that we saw that commercial
softer that is being used in the courts
seems to have a racial problem
that is that these algorithms are more likely
if you are black
to say that you are at high risk
then if you are white
and they are more likely to say that you are
if you are white
that you are low risk when you are not
so there's this dual ace symmetry
it disproportionately affects black people
by saying they're high risk
and it disproportionately affects white people
by saying that they are low risk
when in fact they are not
and as I mentioned julian
I wanted to start off by just
asking a very basic question
which is if you're going to use these algorithms
surely we should understand
where are we the human
and making this judgment
and then we can start getting at
are these algorithms better
how do you deal with the racial bias
and the long list of questions we should think about
when developing and deploying technology
so let's start by answering this question
so here's what we did
we want to enter a crowd sourcing website
this is amazon's mechanical turk
you pay people a couple of bucks
and they answer a bunch of questions for you
and you can collect
thousands and thousands of these data
within a matter of days
and get a sense of how do people make these judgments
now obviously these are not judges lawyers
social workers people in the criminal justice system
these are just random people on the internet
answering questions
so surely this will be a lower bar for performance
but we wanted to start there
and then we'll see where we are
now we need some data
so we have got the people who are going to ask
but now we need data
so fortunately broward county Florida has
made public
thousands of records anonymized of course of people
what their demographics are
their race their gender their age
their employment history
their criminal history
and then they track them for two years
so at point of arrest we could ask
based on the historical data where is this
what is the prediction
and then we can follow that person for two years
now obviously let me just state the obvious
we don't know whether they committed a crime or not
all we can know about is whether they were
arrested and charged for a crime
so that's what we mean by recidivism here
okay so we got data thousands of people
we have a number of data
and let me show you what that data looks like
so this is a
snapshot of what we asked our mechanical turk users to
do we didn't give them all
the data associated
with the people in that broward county database
because it was just too much
but here's what the information we gave them
so we said that we gave them the gender
the defendant is male
age 43
they have been charged with disorderly intoxication
and then down below here
because some of these charges are not entirely
obviously we would define what that charge is
so now you know
their gender and their age
and what the current charge is
the crime is classified as a misdemeanor
that's the fourth piece of data
so a misdemeanor found in the etc
and they have been convicted of two prior crimes
and they have zero juvenile felony
charges and zero juvenile misdemeanor
so we tell you how many charges as an adult ii
and how many felony and misdemeanors as a juvenile
obviously the felonies are the more serious charges
as opposed to the misdemeanors
and then we ask the person reading this short paragraph
do you think that this person will commit another crime
within two years
and the answer yes no
and we show them their current accuracy up here
and to motivate them to do the task well
we say that if you get above a 65 % accuracy
and you'll see why I pick that number in a minute
then we will give you a bonus
so we try to motivate them to
you know actually do the task
all right
so 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 pieces of information and that is it
and I'm going to ask you to determine
to predict whether this person commits a crime
so let's do a few
and see how you do
oh by the way notice that race doesn't come in here
we'll come back to them a little bit
but we don't say what the race of the person is
that's intentional of course
the defendant is a female age 29
they have been charged with
aggravated assault with a deadly weapon
here's the charge right here if you want to read it
this crime is classified as a felony
they have zero prior crimes
they have zero juvenile felony charges and
zero juvenile misdemeanors
do you think this person will commit a crime within
two years yes or no
what do you think
you've got to make the call
do I let this person not un bail or not
okay so in fact this person did not commit
a crime in the neck or
was not charged with a crime
in the following two years
let's just do a few
more to give you an intuition for this
this defended in his female age 52
they've been charged with theft
this crime is a misdemeanor
they've been convicted of six prior crimes
they have zero juvenile
felony and two juvenile misdemeanors
do you think they'll commit a crime
in the next two years
yes or no what do you think
this person in fact
did go on to commit a crime in the next two years
all right one more
male age 22
they have been charged with possession of cannabis
20g or less this was obviously before
widespread legalization of marijuana
this crime is classified as a misdemeanor
they have two prior crimes
zero felony juvenile zero
juvenile misdemeanors
what do you think yes or no
and this is also no
and that's it
so our users just read one after another these
they saw about 60 to 70 of these
I don't remember the exact amount
and how'd they do
so we got hundreds and hundreds of responses
the overall
accuracy of the computer algorithm was 65.4%
so 65 so figure about race
forget about false positive
false negative and all that
just overall accuracy
diagrams had 65%
that's by the way why we put that as the target
for users to get a bonus
we wanted to see if we can reach the same
accuracy as the computer algorithm
our human respondents on average were at 64 %
basically the same
so reading just that short paragraph
was seven pieces of information
they were performing as well on average
as the computerized software
that was being used in the court of law
to help judges make these decisions
now is the obvious oh
interestingly
if we do a little bit of averaging
to see if there's wisdom in the crowd as it's called
so instead of just relying on one person
telling us what the answer is
we had a majority rules
you can get a little bit of bump you go from 64 to 67 %
but they're really statistically almost no different
than the computerized algorithms and the ai algorithm
so it looks like
the humans and the algorithms are doing
about the same
and so now let's get at the nature of the mistakes
write this racial issue
so the humans
had a false positive
and let me remind you what a false positive is
is they predicted that they would recitivate
but they don't
so this is that you're essentially
falsely accusing somebody of being high risk
when they are not
so our subjects on average said that a black person
recitivate when they wouldn't
at 37% they made a mistake
and white to 27%
there's a racial bias here
this is weird
why is it weird
they don't know the race of the person
it's not in the data directly we don't provide it
we give you the age and the gender
so that's a little weird
and about a little bit better than the software
but not much better
right so black people are being predicted at high risk
incorrectly at a higher rate than white people
let's look at the other mistake false negative
I predict that you won't recitivate
but you do I say you're a good guy
go out in prosper but you go out and commit a crime
we make that mistakes
humans make that mistake
with blacks only 29 % of the time
but with white's 40% of the time
so again you have this racial discrepancy
and it's weird
it's weird because there's no race in the data
how are you biased
against black people when I don't tell you
what their race is
that's strange
and by the way
I should tell you that when that propublica
piece came out
the software said this is impossible because we don't
provide race into the predictive algorithm
they don't either
all right we're gonna have to get to the bottom of that
and we will
all right but what we thought is okay
so something weird is going on
let's just go ahead and rerun
the experiment and tell them the race of the people
maybe somehow by telling them the race we thought
oh that's gonna make them racially bias
but maybe if we tell them
it'll balance itself out
so we added one more piece of information
everything's the same
the gender the age
the current charge prior crimes all that
and then we just told you whether the person was
white or black
and then how did they do
all right let's go see what happens there
all right crowd accuracy
without race we just saw they were at 67%
with race they're at 66 and a half percent
they're basically the same
so it makes no difference
for the overall accuracy whether you know the person's
race or not it's irrelevant
let's look at the mistakes
false positive
predict that you recidivate when you don't
I say that you're going to be high risk but you are not
without race black
we make a mistake with blacks at 37 % white to 27 %
there's the racial a symmetry
if I tell you the race it's basically the same
40 26 % a little bit of a bump here
but not statistically different
so whether you know the race or not
you are biased against black people
in terms of the false positive
false negatives
I predict that you will not recitivate when you do
without race 29 to 40 %
30 to 42 % it's exactly the same thing
so whether you know the race or not
we seem to have a racial bias problem
and that's weird
how is that possible
okay so a couple of things we need to get to
how is it that
making predictions about recidivism is not race blind
when you don't know the race
obviously we have a problem
the software the humans
there's a racial ace symmetry here
and we need to get to the bottom of that
I would argue more fundamentally
how is it that in ai algorithm
that is being
sold to our court here in the United States
and is being
used by the court to predict whether you should get
bail or not
is as accurate
as a random person on the internet
being paid a couple bucks to answer
survey question from
seven pieces of data
how is that possible
all right we need to get to the bottom of
both of those questions
and that's what we're gonna do in the next segment
so I'll see you in a few minutes
okay where do we leave off
so here's what we know
we know that commercial software
being used to predict recidivism
is not particularly accurate
65% accurate and seems to have a racial bias issue
No.1 No.2 is that when we pulled people on the internet
on mechanical turk to do a similar task
they had the same accuracy as the commercial ai
software and they seemed to have the same racial bias
despite the fact
that they don't have information about race
so whether they knew race or not they had that same
bias in terms of the errors they were being making
so that leads us to two questions
how is it that both the softer and the humans
and not knowing race
are not race blind
that's weird and we should understand that
and perhaps more importantly is it
how is it that ai being used in the court
is as accurate
and as bias is random people on the internet
these aren't even judges lawyers
social workers
and people in the criminal justice system
these are people being paid a few bucks
on the internet
and we need to get to the bottom of both of these
and that's what we're going to do in this segment now
all right so here's a
if you will
a toy picture of how an ai algorithm might work
so you take you have a little box here that
I'm going to show you what that looks like
computation a little bit
that's your ai that's your decision making
and you feeded some information
in our case the information we fed to our human
reviewers were sex age
the crime they were
accused of the crime degree misdemeanor felony
prior crimes
juvenile felony priors and juvenile misdemeanor priors
these are the seven pieces of information
we feed that information into
well for humans into the brain
and then we make a risk assessment
and now we're going to feed that information
into an ai algorithm
the classifier if you will
that then has to make a prediction
okay so let's
think a little bit about what that box might look like
because if we're going to understand
the race blind problem and the accuracy problem
we've got to start to get at what is happening
in these ai algorithms
okay so let's unpack that box a little bit
alright now to keep things simple
let's imagine I only have two pieces of information
and you're going to see in a minute why I do that
because it makes visualizing
this box a little bit easier
so imagine all you have at your access
and I could have picked any two
these are this is
it's random it's how old somebody is
and their total number of juvenile felony
that's all the information you have
and your eye algorithm
now has to make a risk assessment
okay so one way to think about this ai algorithm
is to think about these two pieces of data
as in terms of the euclidean plane
the age of somebody from zero to whatever
and the number of juvenile felony
convictions just upon the vertical axis
so we're going to train this algorithm
so what does that mean
we get a bunch of data
where we like the broward county data that we use
in our studies
and every point here is an individual
so this point corresponds to somebody that was this age
and had very few juvenile felonies
this data point
corresponds to somebody who was younger and had
more juvenile felonies
and so on and so far
so every point in this two dimensional space here
corresponds to somebody that
was arrested we have the historical data
we followed them for two years
and they did recidivate somewhere in that
two year period
good training data
now we have another body of training data
of people who didn't recidivate
and again
every data point here I've just color coded digitally
because these are people who did not recidivate
right so they were
arrested followed them for two years
clean record after that
and that's their data
now that's training data
so what is the goal of an ai algorithm is now
given that you've seen these patterns
can you make predictions of people you've not seen
in the same way when I started this lecture I said you
may predict products you may like
we may predict that you may like
we may predict whether you can give you alone how
you look at historical data
you look at the patterns that emerge and you learn
what is the likelihood of
somebody not recitivating or somebody recitivating
okay and there's lots of different ways of doing this
ai machine learning
I'm going to talk about one very very simple technique
and here's the basic idea
it's called a linear classifier
which in this two dimensional space
again arbitrary access age and juvenile felonies
you draw a line
this is why it's called a linear classifier
because there's a linear separation
between these clouds of data
the red data points and the
yellow data points
now obviously in a seven dimensional space
I can still do this
but my separator is not a line it's a hyperplane
so in three d it would be a plane
and four d and beyond it's a hyperplane
that's why I'm doing it in 2d
because I can draw this as a line
so the ai's goal
is to learn this line
that separates one class from another
people who did recidivate
from people who didn't recidivate
so let's just talk about how that's going to look like
so let's say this is the classifier I learned this line
now I get a new person
that little blue dot right there
and there on the left
side of the line which I've shaded red
they are predicted to recidivate
right that's the nature of recidivism
by the way you can see the errors
see that yellow dot right there
and the yellow dot right there
that's a mistake
that's predicting somebody didn't
would recitivate when they didn't
and these red dots down here are the mistake
the classifiers are not perfect
but the majority of the yellow dots are there
and the majority of the red dots up here
and once I learned that separating surface
I can put any data point into the space
right there and then I make a prediction
which side of the line are you on
so if you're on the left side
predict that you will recidivate
and if you are on the bottom line
like that blue point right there
then I say you are not going to recidivate
I have a classifier
okay again not perfect
but the majority of the yellow dots are there
and the majority of the red dots are there
so how do you learn that line
lots of different ways to do it
I'm going to just describe
just to give you some intuition on how this works
one classifier called a linear discriminate analysis
it's also referred to as a fisher
linear discriminate as well
so an lda is the classifier I'm going to describe
just very briefly
all right here's our training data
this is so called supervised learning
I have training data and I know the labels
I know that's a red
I know that's a yellow dot
and now my job is to learn a separating line
higher dimensions it's a hyperplane
that will separate it
and how do I do that I need some objective function
so here's the objective function
I'm going to change this line
from this separating surface to a projection
so now what I'm going to do is I'm going to find a line
such that when I project
all the data onto that one dimensional subspace
I'm going to accomplish two things
the first thing is I'm going to minimize
the within class variants
so classes red did recidivate
or yellow did not recidivate
and what I want is
I want to find a line that as I rotate through this
space all of the red dots are bundled up really
really tightly
and all of the
yellow dots are bundled up really tightly
that's the within class red yellow variance
so I want to minimize those variances so that
all everybody's
tightly bungled up together
and at the same time I want to maximize
the across class variants
that is I want
these red dots to be really tightly coupled
and to be very far away
from the yellow dots
that are themselves very tightly coupled
why why am I doing this
well if I can
drive these dots apart from each other
and keep them coupled well
then I can separate them
I can draw a line down the middle and say
red dots yellow dots one class the other class
so this is the objective function for lda
different types of machine learning albums have
different objective functions
not necessarily good or bad
that this is probably the simplest one
you will learn this in your machine learning class
almost certainly in the first week
it's really like the standard technique you'll always
start with and then you go from there
okay turns out by the way
when
you specify the problem is minimizing within class
and maximizing a cross class variants
you can solve it using a
generalized egg invector problem
and I only mention that because you should
take a linear algebra class
just because your computer scientist
do not shy away from the mathematics
in order to do almost anything really interesting
in the space of ai machine learning
pattern recognition image processing
computer vision computer graphics robotics
natural language processing
the long list of really cool things out there
you need to know a lot of math
so linear algebra
probability multiverary calculus are really
really good things to spend some time on
so this lva reduces to a generalized egg invector prom
it can be solved with one line of python or matte lab
code really nice really simple very efficient
now once I have that classifier
I've learned this projection
I'm going to project all the data onto it
and now I have a classifier
but I need to make a decision
where's my boundary
right so where do I
so if everything projects onto this line right here
where do I
draw the separation that I'm going to predict
all these are red and all these are white
and are yellow rather
and I have a choice
I can draw the line anywhere I want
so let's say I drew the line here
this will lead to a
low false positive and a low tube positive
what do I mean by that
so a false positive says that I take a yellow dot
and I predict you as recidivating
right I falsely accuse somebody being high risk
but if I draw the line way up here
very few yellow dots are going to be on
this side of the boundary
there's just that one right there
so I minimize the false positive
but also notice that a lot of red dots are down here
so I've also minimized the true positive
as when somebody's high risk
very few of them are being classified as high risk
so I can trade off the errors that I'm comfortable with
now I can move the line
so if I move it down a little bit I've got a
higher true positive rate
you can see more the red dots are on the side
but I've got another yellow dot
got caught and as I slide down what's going to happen
well eventually
I'm going to get to this point where I have a really
high true positive rate
most of the red dots are now being predicted
as high risk but
I have a really high false positive rate
look at all the yellow dots that have now gotten
caught in the web
so I get to draw that line
in the way that I want to balance these
which mistakes do I want to minimize
what is the accuracy that I want
and I get to make that decision
okay
all right so that is
in some ways the simplest possible ai
that you can have for making this type of prediction
lda linear discriminant analysis
so now
what I'm going to describe to you in the last segment
of this talk
is what happens when you have these seven things here
and then what can we learn
in terms of the commercial software
it's bias and why
human performance is bias when they don't have race
and why are they as good as a commercial software
so once we're going to build a classifier
based on some information over here
and then we're going to see if we can get insights
into those questions
in this last segment
so we'll be back in a few minutes to finish up
to summarize where are we
commercial software is not very
accurate and has a race problem
humans are the same
we have a problem that we don't really understand
why is it that a commercial software
and humans are
not race blind
when they don't know the race of the defendant
and how is it that commercial software and
paying people a couple of bucks on the internet
are giving us the same overall accuracy
so where I left off in the previous segment was
we really need to start to understand these algorithms
if we're going to get answers to those questions
we got to start by asking
what are these algorithms to do
I can't probe the brain
I'm not a neuroscientist
and so but I can probe these algorithms
and in the last segment
I describe to you a very very simple basic
classifier for taking information
and making a prediction about risk
and so here's what we did
we took all seven pieces of information
and we built a classifier
and we asked how well does it do
and then what we said is well
do we really need all seven of those
what if I only had six
what if I didn't know the sex for example
or I didn't know the age
or I didn't know the prior crimes
and then we thought well okay what if we only need five
what if you only need four pieces of data
what if you only need three two and one
so we looked at
all
possible subsets of these seven pieces of information
from the full set to all subsets of size 6 5 4 3 2 1
so class firewood one would only
take the age and try to make a prediction
only take the sex and try to make a prediction
and then we asked
what's the best you can do
where is the best of all of those classifiers
in terms of overall accuracy
and then the hope is
by looking at that classifier
and what information is latching onto
we can get answers to our questions
that have been plaguing us from the beginning of this
talk and so here's what we found
it turns out that if you feed only
two pieces of information
how old somebody is
and their total number of prior crimes
don't care about juvenile
felony misdemeanor
sex don't care about any of that
if I only have two pieces of information
the classifier that we built
the linear discriminant analysis
the simplest possible classifier you can build
was as accurate as the commercial software
so this accuracy is the average accuracy
of a commercial piece of software
being sold to the courts
to make predictions
about defendants in the court of law
this is something
that julia and I hacked up in an afternoon
right so that's interesting for a couple of reasons
we're going to get to that in a little bit
here's the most interesting part of it
so what I'm going to show you here are the
two pieces of information
that we are using in our class fire
total number of prior crimes
age so again
this is that two dimensional
space that I was talking about earlier on
how old is somebody from young to old
how many prior crimes do they have
from very few to a lot
and what this color
coating is here is our prediction of risk
yellow
up here in the top corner is considered high risk
and blue in the bottom right hand corner
is considered low risk
and this is the color coding of our classifier
so once we have a classifier based on two things
it's supervised learning
we train it we can feed in
any possible combination of age and prior crime
and it'll make a prediction
and then I just make that
turn that prediction into a color code
and I can visualize
what the prediction space looks like
and so what is it doing well let's see
what it's saying is that if you are young
and have a lot of prior crimes you're at high risk
sure that sort of makes sense I guess
and it's saying if you're old and have very few
prior crimes you are
no risk and of course if you're old
and have a lot of prior crimes you're still at risk
but less so than if you are young
okay so that's what the classifier is doing
and what's nice about our linear classifier is
it's interpretable
we can reason about it
because we know the data coming in
we were able to show that this was the best classifier
that came out of it
and we can look at this space and see
or at least into it
what is the classifier doing that's very nice
very positive
so how does this help get it our questions
it's not race blind when it doesn't know race
this classifier doesn't know race
and how is it that it's as good as
painting somebody a couple of bucks on the internet
so let's go to this one first
so the problem of course is that
prior crimes is a proxy for race
we know that in this country for decades now
if you are a person of color
you are significantly more likely to be arrested
charged and convicted of a crime
with balancing for all other aspects
that is a largely undisputed fact
in the criminal justice system
so when we were saying
that the algorithms and the humans don't know
about race that was strictly true but not entirely true
because yes
I didn't tell you
this person's black or this person's white
but I told you something that is a proxy for race
because people of color again are more likely to be
charged convicted
charge arrested charging convicted
and therefore looking at the number of prior crimes is
a peak into their race
again it's a proxy
so this
just the understanding that total number of crimes was
in addition to age was the single
most important predictor
gives us some insight into this race problem
for both the algorithms
and probably for the humans as well
I mean there's really no other explanation
if you don't know the race of the person
and we know that humans were probably
doing something very similar to this as well
now let's get to this question
how is it that ai and a random internet user are
basically the same accuracy
well the answer is that it's a really simple classifier
so think back to when you were looking at those feud
and that's why I showed you those examples
what were you doing right
I mean if you saw somebody who was 45
and had zero prior convictions
do you really think
they're gonna go out and commit a crime in the future
does that seem reasonable to you
or do you think now
they did something stupid and they got caught
as opposed to a young kid who's 20 something and has 13
prior convictions
that person
clearly something is going on in their life
and so basically the reason why
these algorithms
and the random internet users
the name is that we're doing something very simple
we into it we believe we infer
that basically what people are doing is saying
the same thing
are classifier saying if you're young
with a lot of prior convictions
you're high risk
if you're old with very few
prior convictions you're low risk
that explains two things in one
why internet users in this
ai are basically the same accuracy
and also where the
lack of race blindness comes in
because this access prior crimes is a proxy for race
all right you can say well who cares
who cares that the ai in the random internet user are
exactly the same
I mean at least
at least they're not worse
and so why not use the ai
and take the human eye of the loop
well I would argue however
there's a little bit of a problem with that
and that is because of the sense of authoritarian voice
so what do I mean by that
imagine the following scenario imagine you're a judge
and you haven't defended before you
and they're being asked to be released on bell
and the court tells you hey
we have this sophisticated ai system build on big data
in the latest advances and deep learning
and it's commercial product
we paid for this thing
which obviously associates value with it
and it's said that this person is high risk
you would think the judge would at least give
some credence to that
yeah like that would sound authoritative
now imagining a different scenario
same defendant same question bail or nobel and
the lawyer says
while
somebody on the internet tweeted that this person is
high risk
do you think the judge would
care at all what a random person on the internet said
of course not
that's not authoritative
what somebody on RedDit or Twitter or Facebook said
I don't care and yet
the accuracies are exactly the same
and the mistakes are the same
and so when you wrap things around
these ai boxes they seem authoritative
and if they're authoritative
you give more credibility to that
even if it doesn't deserve it
so I would argue it still matters
even though that these accuracies are the same
now here's a really interesting question is
I remember I told you we built this really dumb
simple classifier right
so can we do better
now we're going to get back to the original question
that julia and I set out to do
so all of this was in some ways
just you know what is going on here
why are these things racially buys
what is the baseline
once we figured out the baseline were like
well why is there
bias in the first place when they don't know race
and I think that we've probably unraveled that
we've gotten to the bottom of that
it's an incredibly simple classifier
and we have
a proxy for race in terms of the total number of prior
so I think we have a good
understanding of now of the space
and now the question is
can you get rid of bias
and can you make the accuracies better
okay so let me just talk very briefly
about some of the work we've done on that
so the first thing we asked is
well what happens if we go from a linear classifier
the simplest possible classifier
you can build to a
non linear classifier
and without going into the details of it
a non linear classifier basically allows you to build
not just a line through this space but a curvy
a curve that allows you to carve out exceptions
right so here you can see for example
I'm carving around here so I have
more of the yellow points down below
and more of the red points above
so these are called nonlinear classifiers
support bacter machines neural networks deep learning
all of those fall
into that category of nonlinear classifier
and just one nonlinear classifier that we build
was really really disappointing
again this is the overall
accuracy of the commercial software 65%
our human 64%
the linear classifier
the lda that we've already talked about was 66%
and the non linear was 65%
they're all exactly the same
we just seem to be stuck at around 65 %
okay I posit I cannot prove but I posit
I think that this is a fundamentally hard problem
and I am unconvinced
that you can actually do better than this
because think about what you're asking
the algorithm to do
you're asking it to predict the future
from a relatively small amount of data
and the future two years in advance
of a fairly complex set of socioeconomic personal
and just what is
random dumb luck going to happen in somebody's life
and I don't think that's a stretch of imagination
to say that this is really hard
so here's a question for you
should we even be doing this
should we actually be trying to predict
whether
somebody's going to commit a crime in the future
and then incarcerate them if we think that they are
if the actor is 65%
what if the accuracy 75% what if it's 85%
what if it's you
what if it's somebody you love
do you want this algorithm being applied to somebody
with this kind of error rate
what's an acceptable error rate
are these things really better than humans
how do you deal with the bias
nobody has good answers to these things
so here's a question
now I come back to the title right
just because you can do something
doesn't mean you should
and as you enter into
what is undoubtedly an incredibly exciting
time for us in terms of
computation and ai and data
and the impact that we can have on the world
we have to start thinking about
what are the negative aspects of what we are doing
should we be trying to make these decisions
and if we do the answer may be yes
but then are they accurate
are they fair
do they disproportionately affect women
people of color lgbtq community
people who are not born in this country
people who aren't native speakers
whatever it is
we have to think about the consequences of that
we have spent the last 20
years with the mantra of move fast and break things
and while lots of good things have come from that
some really bad things have come from this
bias and algorithms for hiring
bias and algorims and healthcare
bias for algorithms in financial sectors
bias for algorims in the criminal justice system
bias in facial recognition
we've got to tread lightly here
and what that means is you can't come at this
after the fact
you can't develop deploy and then debug on the fly
this isn't a word processing software
if you have a bug somebody loses a document
this is the real world where you make a mistake
in somebody sitting in jail
or somebody doesn't get a home loan
or somebody doesn't get a small business loan
or somebody doesn't get a job or go to the university
we are impacting real people's lives
with our algorithms and our data
and if we don't understand these things
we have the potential to do way more harm
than we do good
and so the free for all of the last two decades
in my opinion
should be over
and I want to emphasize that I am not anti technology
I'm not saying don't do things
I'm not saying don't innovate
but I'm saying think
think carefully about
the consequences of what you are doing
and make sure that there is transparency
there is fairness and there is accuracy
and how these technologies are being used
and more generally
making sure that you
understand how your technologies can be
misused as well
because
almost all technologies have benefits and drawbacks
and we have to start
thinking about those things up front
and simply try to mitigate the harm
while harnessing the phenomenal power
of technology and ai and data
all right I'm done
I hope you enjoyed this
and I hope you learned something from it
and we'll see you soon