61a lecture number 21 q a
hey john while we wait for the first
question let me ask you something so
i've always taught linked lists i think
they're really
great um dude in in at google did you
see people really using them or was it
just
you know we just use a list that's sort
of easier
i think that there are many more
applications where you use a list
than a linked list yeah yeah that was my
sense because it's
there's clearly a benefit but it's not
clear that it's outweighed by
the you know the hassle of having to
implement everything
yeah and i think um when there's a lot
of mutation that's when it can matter
because you can kind of stick something
in the middle of a linked list
yeah um and uh
so you know definitely if we didn't have
them then like
something at google wouldn't work like
it's supposed to work you know it's a
necessary component but
it doesn't show up all that often yeah
it doesn't doesn't remind me if i'm
wrong python does this cool thing when
you allocate memory for a list
where it actually gives you more memory
than you need so that as you're
expanding it
it's not having to sort of move things
around in memory did i get that right
yeah i think that's right they round up
to the next power two or something like
that right it's always powers
so actually it's a little bit better
than constantly having to move things
around when you're inserting in the list
but even when you insert like you don't
have to allocate new memory but you do
have to copy everything over to make
room so still linked lists are kind of
nice
oh that's yeah that's true by the way
back in the day when we programmed in
c you had to you had to every time you
wanted to create a data structure you
had to you had to actually go in and
allocate the memory for it and then you
allocate the memory for it
so that memory management is
was brutal yeah that's how i started in
my first computer science class and
uh also when you did it wrong it didn't
really tell you where
you were and it was it was deterministic
because sometimes you would run in the
code would be fine and then sometimes
you run the questions
i recently had to implement uh an
algorithm and speak that it had to run
really really fast in those four
dimensional matrices
and it took me like a week just to get
the memory management right
just don't write memory management yeah
no
my initial reaction having to deal with
memory management was like why does ever
anyone take computer science courses is
awful so
you know i think learning computer
science is still frustrating but in
different
ways now we sound like old guys but back
in my day i had to allocate memory
exactly all right guys whenever you're
ready
sorry by the way did anybody else notice
that a list is just a a tree with one
branch
i suppose we could have just done we
could have implemented using trees yeah
john
you could have made a linked list just a
tree where you're only allowed to have
one branch yeah okay uh there was a
problem on homework four that was yield
all the
permutations of some list s
so for example if you called
permutations on
uh one two three well then you just get
back a
generator but if you then listed out all
the contents then you'd get
one two three and one three two
and uh okay so those are the ones that
start with one but then there's
something to start with two like two one
three
and let me shuffle around my
zoom a little bit uh two three one
okay so those are the ones that start
with two oh there's actually some that
start with three
you got three one two and
three two one
i think that's how i didn't do four
elements i know
[Laughter]
so i know a lot of people did this
question already but let's just talk
through it really quickly i think um
there's uh a couple different ways you
can do this and i don't think there's
one that's better than the other
um but one of them is that you
pick which element you want first in
your permutation
so that you could either have one first
or two first
three first and then you have the rest
of the elements
filling out your permutation but you
don't know what order they come in they
might come in two three or
three two well actually that turns out
to be the two different
permutations of the numbers two three
and likewise once you've committed to
two being your first
number you've got two different options
for everything else and these are the
two different permutations
of one three or if you say threes first
then these are the two different
permutations
of one two so you can see that coming up
with all the permutations of one two
three involves coming up with the
permutations of two three
and the permutations of one three and
the permutations of one two so there's
gonna be a recursive structure here
and now that we have like a recursive
story then we just put it into code so
um if you want all the different
permutations then you have to consider
all the different elements that you
could start with
so the starting element let's say is s i
now we need the rest of the elements
these are all the elements except for
the one that we chose so if we chose two
we need to get
one and three there's a number of ways
to do this
one way is to say i want sj
for every j in
here if uh
j isn't i
that's one way to do it another way to
do it with slicing might be i want to go
up to i but don't include it
and i also want everything after i so i
plus 1 on
either way would be fine but basically
however you do it
what rest is going to be is
uh if we got 2 here
this is going to be the list of 1 3. so
everything else that we need to permute
and then if we want to generate these
two permutations then we have to
permute the rest of them so try one
three and also try three one
so if we get the permutations of the
rest of the list now our
rest permutation is first gonna be bound
to one three and then it will be bound
to three one
but that's not what we're supposed to
yield so if we yielded rest permutation
we would be yielding something too short
we'd be yielding something like
1 3 or 3 1. but really what we want to
yield
is 2 1 3 or
2 3 1 so we have to decide how to do
that i think the easiest way is to use
list addition
where you put that to the starting value
in at the beginning of the list
by the way notice that when the problem
statement was defined
there was the recursive definition i
could hear it right
take the one off and then find the other
the permutations of the other ones and
that's one of the tricks of recursion
is as you're thinking about the problem
there's always
like slight simplification of the
problem and also it's in the definition
right take one and then add it to all
the other permutations of the remaining
elements
well there it is and then when you do
all that work you got to think about a
base case so it's a good base case well
and you could do it with list length 1
or list length 0. i think list length 0
is probably the
most basic of the base cases so if you
say
if len s equals 0 then
what's all the permutations of that oh
we're yielding
there's really only one permutation of
an empty list which is just uh
you know the empty list let's see what
happens
oh seems like it worked any questions
about this
great question so why is it the case
that within this four
where we're picking the first element we
have another four where we're picking
the permutation of the rest of the
elements
and i think that nested loop is just
inherent to this problem so there isn't
really a way to get around it i mean you
could use a
list comprehension instead and try to do
this all in one line
uh if you really wanted to but
it's not like you've gotten rid of the
for loop you've just sort of
changed its syntax right so uh
it's still in there it's just kind of
hidden away a little bit
yeah and so what are the two loops by
the way so there's one loop
that we agree we have to peel off the
first element in the list
and then the second loop has to permute
everything that's
left so i think john's right that this
is inherent in this um
problem definition yeah the way we're
getting to all six of these
is we're looping over groups
and then within each group we're looping
over the two different permutations in
the group
yeah so great question is there another
way to do this where you
have the same elements but you group
them in a different way
where you're taking the first element
and inserting it
so the story there is you start with
uh a split of the first element and
everything else your outer loop is that
you permute
everything else so it's either going to
be 2 3 or
3 2. the inner loop is where do you put
the 1
i could put the 1 at the beginning i
could put the 1
in the middle i could put the 1 at the
end
but notice the order of 2 and 3 is the
same in all of these cases
and then i could consider the other
permutation which is that 3 comes before
two
and i could decide to put one at the
beginning
or one in the middle
or one at the end and this is a
perfectly good way of doing this problem
as well
so if we wanted this kind of answer
slightly different order
how would we go about it well base case
looks fine the way it is
but here we're saying
the split is the first element
and the rest of the elements
we're considering rest
permutations
as the outer loop so rest permutation
might be something like 2
3 this might be something like
1 and this is 2 3
just annotating it with examples okay
now what do you do
is you have to consider all the
different places where you could
put uh first
and so here we have another for i in
range
len s you could put it in the zeroth
position or the first position or the
second position
so the code hasn't changed very much
this i think we've handled already
but we have to think about what to yield
and one of the questions was if i just
insert so if i write for example
rest.insert
first in position i then something goes
wrong
so let's talk about how insert works
let's say rest is two three
and first is one and i
is first zero right
then if i write rest.insert
first r
oh what have i done
oh i got it in the wrong order i think
let's try again
rest oh yeah first i equals zero
you're supposed to be inserting into a
particular position a particular value
okay so that's what we want ah sorry
this is great this is something we could
yield so we yield that
and then we change i to one
that was what going through the for
statement again would do
and then what if we evaluated this again
trouble we have a problem the problem is
that insert is a mutation operation and
so the insertions are accumulating in
the
rest and so it's getting longer and
longer this is not what we wanted we
wanted 2 1 3 but now we have something
else
so just writing this isn't going to work
you could write result is
a new list that has all the elements of
rest in it
and then you could insert into that
result and yield that result
and you'd get away from this problem of
inserting into the same list twice
because you'd be making a new list each
time that always kind of started out
at 2 3 and then you're inserting into a
different place
so i suspect that this will work oh
apparently not
uh did something wrong
that much is clear oh sorry this is
supposed to be that rest permutation
yes yeah
okay now it works uh
sorry about that yeah so you have to
consider all the permutations of rest
and insert into all of those and then we
have a different grouping we have uh
all the places where two comes before
three and then all plays where three
comes before two
so those are the two different rest
permutations and then we're considering
all the different places of pudding
uh first
so when you're modifying that list in a
recursive call you just be very careful
right so the way the reason why this
worked is we peeled off and we created a
new list and notice also the list
operator there
uh two lines up from where the cursor is
it's not
result equals permutation that would
have been the same object so we create a
new list
we mutate it and then when we go back in
the lip it
literally creates a new distance time
yeah
yeah and another reasonable way would be
to try to avoid
mutation operations like insert entirely
and here you would yield rest
permutation
up to position i and then put in
first and then get the rest of the rest
permutation
uh that would probably work too
apparently
okay uh two quick questions somebody's
asking would this work
for strings okay um
would this work with strings i guess it
probably would
uh i don't remember if you can call me
if we want
the permutations of abc we're not going
to get strings back right this
always yields lists but we will get
the list of all
lists that are permutations of abc
and the reason that this works is that
what have we actually done with
s well we've checked its length that's
something you can do
with a string and
we've gotten elements of it or slices of
it
that's something you can do with the
string so
uh yeah i guess um s could be a string
it could be kind of any sequence
anything that you could take the length
of and get
elements of or get slices of wood work
here
but it won't give you strings back it'll
give you back lists
but we could have changed this to to
yield the empty list and do everything a
string concatenation instead of list
concatenation that would have worked
also oh that's a quick change here and
then down below also john
uh in first gotta get rid of that
yeah now maybe we're in business
yeah so i think for the most part things
that operate on strings and this work
but there's a few operations and i think
audrey's confirmed that you can't insert
into a string there's a few things
the operators don't work you just have
to sort of push everything together in a
slightly different way
yeah that's right strings you can't
mutate a string they're immutable
objects so you'd have to do it this way
so if you have okay so the question is
can you create a
circular um linked list
and if so is that ever a good idea or
not um
so here's the link from uh
lecture and if we create link one link
two link three um
that's something i can look at i can
print that print
life is good but if i change it so that
s dot rest equals s
then s dot rest is just s
star first is still something the number
one we've lost track of the numbers two
and three
um because now s dot rest on first is
still one and as the rest i rest at
first is still one
i can't print it why
well there was a print method uh
that we came up with which was basically
like
you know uh start with the angle bracket
and then get the first thing
and then get the rest
and keep doing this until you hit a rest
that's empty but the rest of this is
never empty because it's always just
s again so this is running forever
we've created an infinitely long linked
list
there are cases in which you might want
exactly that
you might want to represent some
repeating decimal of like you know what
happens when you divide one by seven
well actually this should go on forever
and we could represent that
as a circular linked list and then we
could ask you know what's the 50th digit
of one divided by seven
and we could just call rest fifty times
and find it so there are cases in which
you might want to do exactly this
this is a feature of linked lists that
doesn't really exist for lists
lists have to have a length but these
things don't really have to have a
length if you make them
cyclical though i would guess like 99 of
the time you want them to actually end
it's pretty rare that you want something
to
go on forever so this there's a name for
this era to your question too
is that these are called circular lists
um
and one of the benefits is as you're
traversing a list
you know there's something nice that
when you get to the last element you can
get back to the first element so this
idea that there's no real
end to the list but it causes problems
but we could have fixed that problem
with a different print function
we could have had some notion of
wrapping around and one way to do that
is what's called a sentinel and you put
a special
node at the front of the list that
indicates
that it's not a data field it's a
sentinel so you put something in the
data field that
that specifies this is not data it's
it's showing you that at the beginning
of the list and then when you start
going through and you wrap back up to
the sentinel you know you've
wrapped around so then the print
statement could have said okay keep
printing
until i loop back and then sp have some
notation to say
this will keep going like dot dot dot
yeah
so they're not fundamentally bad but you
do have to put um precautions in place
and circular linked lists are actually a
common data type
and that's a great point that if we had
just a slightly smarter version of stir
then we could print this out just fine
and just like put a data
sure great question so the question is
about discussion 5
question number 1.3 which was called
square tree
when you write an implementation of this
then it's unclear how python actually
executes that
code this was using the tree data
abstraction but since in this lecture we
talked about the
tree class maybe we'll use that one
instead and it'll have almost the same
code so
uh
now we have our tree class what would it
mean to square a tree
well uh i think that
you want to square the label
of the tree so one way to write that
is t
dot label squared or t dot labeled items
t dot label
either way is fine but the goal of
square tree is not to
return the square of the label is to
return a whole tree
so we need to return a whole tree where
this thing is the label
and what are the branches well the
branches are the result
of calling a square tree on each branch
so how did i get that far
well i know i want to square all the
other labels
each label appears as the root of
some node within the tree so
if i've said square the top of the tree
and then i
apply that operation everywhere else in
the tree
then i'm going to end up squaring every
label in the tree
so i could write squared tree b
for b in t dot branches
and then if i have a particular tree
here's a short one
oh i shouldn't use one because you can't
tell whether one got squared can you
and i square that
then i have squared everything i've
squared the 4 to get 16 i squared the 2
to get 4 i squared the 3 to get 9.
let's do a medium tree
and we'll talk about how it actually
gets executed so if we have 4 there
three two we have a uh
branch of this tree like uh five
and then we have a tree three
so this is almost the same as the one we
had before except for it has one extra
little leaf here
when we square this tree even the five
gets
squared the easiest way to think about
it is through abstraction
and say okay so the result of square
tree
on this medium tree is that i get a new
or i've squared the root and i've
applied square tree to all the branches
so there's what's happened when you
square tree this
and here's what's happened when you
square tree that
and you kind of just don't think about
the process
but it is the case that
uh python is going through and
traversing the whole tree and squaring
things bit by bit
so maybe it's worth just printing out
what it's doing next
as it goes and we can see what happens
so here's our medium tree
and here's what happens when you square
medium tree oh that's not
exactly what i wanted let's print the
wrapper
is that first just trying to square that
but we make a recursive call on the
first branch which makes a recursive
call
on the first branch that's that's the
that gets us 325.
and that's the call that gets us three
nine
four twenty five but notice that
that's just using a piece of what has
already been computed
and then once you've computed this piece
and this piece already then you can
build the whole thing
the next question was about spring 2019
midterm two
question one what would python display
all right so items is an empty list
n is two um
air pods is a clast that's got its own
two i think we really do need to
annotate a little bit
to show what's going on i'm just gonna
try drawing freehand and it's probably
gonna look terrible but
who cares so we got items
we got n and we've got the airpods class
and the airpods class
has
cost a okay
okay at zero
and then it's got um three different
methods an f method an
init method and a wrapper method and
then two
airpods is like airpods doesn't have any
class attributes
and then we've got some functions and um
so we can see what happens
so let's see what happens if we kind of
just trace through this uh
two airpods dot cost this is a class
we're looking up a class attribute the
way you look up a class attribute is
that you look in the class it has no
class attributes called cost so you look
in its base class
so this would give you the number 200.
what happens when you create an instance
of an
airpods well in that case you create a
new air pods and you call in it
and so we're going to have to do that uh
i think it's handy just to like keep
track of all the
instance attributes in a box so let's
say that's our
uh lost air pods and let's track what
happens
so i'm going to interrupt just for a
second because raya asked a question in
the comments
um she's saying i thought it was a
hundred because discount was called
before
uh oh it's true i wasn't paying any
attention so
i think we lost the discount i kind of
skimmed over this part but it actually
is important so discount
takes whatever class you pass into it
and divides its cost by two
so then uh i agree with you that this
would be 100.
yeah so what happened there is that we
changed this cost
oh apparently you cannot change things
in
maybe you can
and so this is hundred uh
okay and that's all that happened all
right so we created an airpods
what does airpods do it um changes the
class attribute k
to increment uh so this is now one
it calls some function that's part of
the class so that's
f on self and what does that do
that prints out self so this self that's
getting printed out is this new
instance of the airpods class
when you print something out then it's
going to look for the stir method
if that doesn't exist it will call the
repper method instead
so printing this out is going to display
whatever this returns so we have to read
this
this says airpods k is less than 2
which is true and lonely
which is a true value because uh
you know strings that aren't empty are
true
so um this is actually going to evaluate
to lonely
and when you well this is definitely not
an exam that i wrote
uh and then when you or that with pair
then you have to know this rule about
what happens when you
uh evaluate an or expression which is
that the first true value of the true
ends up being the value very mean
so basically what the way to unpack this
is to have it say
if error positive.k is less than two
return lonely
else return pair right what that's doing
so um calling this method will give
you back the string lonely what printing
does is it displays the contents of that
string
so it doesn't display the quotes
then there's one more thing that happens
which is that items which happens to be
global
is extended with a list containing only
self
what extend does is it takes all the
elements of this list and adds it to
items
there's only one element of this list so
now items
which we didn't bother to draw but
should have if we were trying to
actually do this correctly so no i guess
we need it
uh oh i can draw squares
items now has something in it and the
thing that it has in it
is this
beautifully laid out okay
uh what happens when you make it two
airpods well when you make it two
airpods you don't
you call the init method for two airpods
um so we're gonna create a new
uh dang it
i wanted a box we're gonna create a new
instance
this times it's a two airpods instance
we're gonna
execute all this which says it gets an
instance attribute called k
and then we call airpods.init
on this and we're going to do it twice
so the first time we
call this we're passing in the two
airpods instance as self
air pods dot k plus equals one okay so
we've
changed this again
to two um
we call this function which just prints
it out which
calls this wrapper method again k is no
longer less than two
so uh i think that this is going to
display pair this time
okay and then we extend
um the items list yet again
so now there's two elements in the items
list
but actually we're calling airpods in it
twice so we have to play this whole game
again
uh where we increment airpods.k
this is now three
if zoom will let me edit it
print out pair again
and we add this to
items so there's where we are
okay and these things have names by the
way in the global frame
there's one called lost uh
which is this first one
and there's one called man i
really made a mess will be lost
which is this one and now we're
apparently gonna
look at what happens with these
so stir lost what happens when you call
stir on lost
well you check for a stir method there
isn't one
so we'll use the wrapper method instead
we have to reevaluate this whole
expression
now errorpos.k is not less than two so
we get the string
pair let's see what else we got here
item.k
for item and items we have three things
in items so we're going to end up with a
list with three things in it
and we have to figure out what dot k is
for each of them
for this element
um it has no instance attribute called k
so we look in its class and we find that
k is 3.
for this element it does have an
instance attribute k
so that's 2 and this element is actually
the same thing so it has the same k
home stretch you lost will be lost which
takes in lost and will be lost
and uh keeps them in the same order
and returns the result of calling print
u
on each one so we have to print out
we've already talked about what happens
when you print i believe it displays
pair and so that will be the pair that
comes from printing the first one
that will be the pair that comes from
printing the second one but then we have
to return the result of whatever
print returned and print returned none
both times
so uh we get a list with none and none
in it take the person who wrote this
question out back and smack them around
a little bit john
okay okay so this is spring
2015 midterm two uh
question four b
takes a string and a dictionary that
contains words as values and their
secret
codes as keys it returns a list of all
possible ways in which
s can be decoded by splitting it into
secret codes
and separating the corresponding words
by spaces
so if you have something like alan
turing
then there's lots of different ways this
could be decoded
because alan could be spooky
and turing could be ghosts or
al could be drink
and could be your and ring
could be ovaltine so that's how you got
these two and apparently there's another
one spooky scary skeletons
maybe this exam was on halloween okay so
um
this has a for statement in it
and one of the questions was how come
what happens if you have a recursive
call
in the for statement um and
you know as long as you treat your
recursive call as a functional
abstraction then maybe it's just not so
bad that it happens to be in a for
statement
as long as you know like oh i have a way
of taking
the rest of the string and deco
decrypting that um
then i guess what we'll do is we'll go
through all the prefixes of the string
that match something in codes and then
we'll
have the rest of the string that is
after the part that we match so if we
match the allen
then we have the rest as touring and
we're going to have to decrypt that
so alan will tell us that there's drink
but a recursive call to touring will uh
oh sorry ah alan gave us spooky but a
recursive call to touring will give us
either ghosts or scary skeletons and
we'll just have to figure out which it
is
by letting recursion do the trick
okay let's take a look at the code
empty string has no way of decrypting it
ms is going to be what we eventually
return so these are the messages
uh if it's the case
i think that all
of s is in my codes dictionary
annotate again
if s and d
then
what should we do we should
decrypt it yes
okay now we're going to split up s into
two parts
there's going to be a part where
we try to decrypt the beginning and then
there's like
the rest which we're going to handle
with a recursive call
and we can see that k is being used as
an index into s so we need some way of
saying
uh 4k in a bunch of numbers
i think there has to be at least one
letter
and i think that
there's got to be at least one letter in
the first and there's got to be at least
one letter in the suffix
i'm not sure yet but that's a reasonable
hypothesis so we'll check it later
so maybe it's something like that so
this breaks up the first and the suffix
so they have at least one letter each
by splitting on k now what do we do
if it's the case that the first is
actually something that we know how to
decrypt
if first in d
then i think what we want to do is go
through and decrypt
the rest what's this thing called
decrypt i hope
i'm not gonna well okay i'm i'm not
gonna scroll because then my annotations
will move
uh so this is going to iterate over a
bunch of different options
like um scary ghosts or whatever it is
and now we're going to build up a full
decryption of the whole thing
this is not so different from
permutations here what we're doing is
building a longer list
that's got d first
in it as well as whatever's
in the rest that line i wrote is
actually wrong
i was supposed to build a string not a
list and append that
so i shouldn't have put d first in a
list instead i should have left it bare
and i should have added a space in
between
d first and the rest
so to figure out whether this range is
right i guess we'd have to think about
particular cases so what happens
if uh
yeah i think this is right if if we had
had
empty suffixes and we made a recursive
call on an empty suffix then we'd have
nothing to iterate over because of the
way this is defined
so we need to have the suffix contain
something and to hit this particular
base case
this isn't really it's kind of like a
base case if it's the case that s is all
the way in d
then we actually get to see the
decryption of that
we made it through another question do
you have any questions about this
question
somebody is asking could a problem like
this be on the next midterm
sure i don't think it'll get any
spookier than this but
this is the kind of thing we'd like you
to be able to do
yeah this is a more sane problem i would
say
somebody's asking what dia first does
again
this gets the decryption so this goes
from alan to
spooky or whatever it was
so yeah if you notice there are no
allens or turings in the results there's
only drinks and ovaltines and spookies
and ghosts
so it has to be that when we build these
things they have to be built out of the
result of looking up strings in the
dictionary as well that's a dictionary
look up in case it wasn't clear
oh yeah that's the whole thing at the
very beginning
d is this codes thing that has all the
all the decryptions all right oh tan is
asking why only to the length of s minus
one
and the reason is that underneath you
have to you have to break the list up
into at least two parts
first and suffix so if there's not two
parts there's nothing to break down and
so you don't have to do any more work
right so we're trying to make sure