lecture 18 q a
so the question was if you have an
account class like this
is deposit a
class attribute and technically it is
but that's because it's a
very special kind of class attribute it
is
what's called a method so um
it would be rare for someone to call
this a class attribute even though that
is technically true
what it really is is a method which
means that
uh the only way that it usually gets
used
is by having an instance of an account
and then depositing into that some
particular amount at which point itself
gets filled in automatically
and the other part of the question was
what are the instance attributes
in this example there are two
they are holder and balance you know
something's an instance attribute if
it's assigned
to an instance and self
always refers to an instance of count
in uh inside of the body of a class
that's about an account
sure so the question is what's a bound
method
and how is it used well if i have an
account
it's mine uh normally i would deposit
into it like this
this expression here actually build
something
we could give it a name if we want
this thing is called a bound method and
what's a method about it well it's a
function defined within a class
and what's bound about it is that the
self
arguments already filled in so
this is not just depositing in general
f is depositing into a
that john's account which is called
a in this example is already bound to
self
meaning what we're left with in this
bound method is a function that only
takes one argument
so that's what a bound method is it's a
method a method is some function that's
defined within a class
that has already had itself filled it
right so the saunders question the chat
um they are
different um it's just as john was just
saying
in the bound method you've already
filled in one of the parameters
what is the object you're sending in
it's still doing the same
thing of course it just sort of you've
delayed the evaluation a little bit
right you've taken like one step in the
evaluation by finding yourself
yeah and i guess a follow-up question
might be what's a method that's not
bound
you can actually access that it's a
little more rare but there are reasons
why you might want to do it
if we access the deposit method directly
from the account class notice the
difference we had an instance here
here we don't have any particular
account that we're talking about we're
just talking about accounts in general
what does it mean to deposit well this
is a method
that takes self and amount so if i
wanted to call this thing
i would need to pass in both the account
that i want
to deposit into and the amount and then
the depositing would happen
i find that really offensive john
i don't like this is something i don't
like about python by the way is that
you know the syntax it lets you do the
same thing
many many different ways and i find that
a little confusing
yeah it is confusing i mean i think that
functions are very fundamental in python
and classes
yes they are but it's if you look under
the hood like it's actually just built
out of things that we already know
so this thing that's like a method is
actually really just a function
except for uh if you have an account
instance then something special happens
with that function meaning self gets
filled in
so uh things are unfamiliar in that kind
of everything's new with object oriented
programming
and yet it is built on the stuff that
we've already
yeah the question is like what can self
ever refer to
and self by itself sorry
self itself is always a name for
an object which is an instance of
this account class
so what that means is that every time
you use self
within one of these methods
you're referring to a particular account
which one
well you don't know that's going to come
later is that somebody's going to build
an account
and going to start depositing into it
and self will be the name that you use
to refer to whatever that thing is that
somebody built
later so it's a placeholder just like
you'd always have
within parentheses of a function like
stuff that hasn't been determined yet
but this one is special because it's
going to be
an account an object which is an
instance of the account class
because you know that's true you know
certain things about it like
it was passed as the argument to init
therefore it has a holder and a balance
the next question was can self only be
used
to refer to particular attributes or
could it be used to refer to methods as
well
sure so if we start writing more methods
function
i can within the class call one of my
own method functions
yeah so at the other side within the
class
so we certainly know outside you can
call a method function of a class
once you have an object self is just the
object it's just a special name for an
object so within the class
sure i can call member functions all day
long using self dot and then whatever
the function is and
pass some parameters yeah even within it
you're kind of free to do whatever you
want so this
this is like a really nice bank i'm not
sure such a bank
exists but john is a really nice bank
you could deposit into it
right away yeah just go ahead and so say
when you open your account you want to
deposit
well john's a little stingy four bucks
um
all right and that will do it okay
so uh yeah go ahead 400 better
great question so is every time we're
referring to self.something
and assigning to it is that a form of
mutation
yes what we're changing is
self is the account object so
this account is something that's mutable
and instead of like having elements like
a list or something like that
it has attributes ways that it can
change
are that it can get brand new attributes
that's what happened here we gave it a
holder attribute that it didn't have
before
or you could update attributes that
already exist
this already had a balance and now the
balance is changing but
in either case we are mutating which
does mean
that if we have two names for the same
account
and i deposit into a
i have in fact deposited into b as well
because b and a are just names for the
same thing and it's the thing that's
changing it's not the variables that are
changing
okay good question i think you're asking
about an example where
an instance has an attribute with some
particular name like interest
and the class also has an attribute with
that particular name interest
and therefore if you have an instance
and you try to look up the attribute
value for interest
you get the instance attribute instead
of the class attribute
because that's where python looks first
so when does this happen there's two
ways to set a class attribute
i could just write it in here
that will be fine or i could add it
if i have access to the account class i
could give it a class attribute
like that and uh both of them do the
same thing
okay so now that the account class
has an interest that means every
instance of this
class will also have an interest and so
if i make one of these
it has an interest but this is actually
not an instance attribute it's a class
attribute there's no real way to tell
that
based on how we used it here it's just
part of python that it looks in the
instance attributes first and if it
doesn't find interest then it looks in
the class
and it happens to have found this one in
but if we gave this thing an interest
attribute
i might be too high now
it has changed but the account's
interest rate has not changed
because this was instance attribute
assignment which changed an instance
attribute
and we didn't change the account if i
made a new account at this point
its interest rate would be whatever the
classes was
because b doesn't have its own instance
attribute
um and yeah let me pause there and then
i'll answer your final question
okay i think your final question was is
there some way
to get a to behave like all the other
accounts
like right now a has a different
interest rate than
all the other accounts
could we make it go back and like use
the class
instead of the instance well there's a
way to get the values to be the same
which would be to write that the
instance attribute is
the same value as the class attribute
then they would look the same for now
but if the class changed again
for some reason then a would be out of
sync oh sorry i typed this wrong
oh my gosh now i got to go back to one
do it because of that one typo
okay so if account's at point three
now a is at point three but if we
change the account to 0.4
then a's interest is still 0.3 there's
still a lot of sync
can you somehow say like i i don't want
a to have its own
special instance level interest rate i
want it to just be like all the other
accounts
there is a way uh i don't typically
teach it in this class because it's used
so
rarely that it's like you could not
worry about it but there is a way which
is
that there is like a special keyword
called dell
that would get rid of the instance
attribute at which point
a still has an interest it just happens
to be the classes interest so that's
kind of the answer to your question but
this is not something you need to know
because i just have never seen it used
in the world
and so it's possible but but i don't
it's hard for me to imagine a case where
you would want it
the next question was about the
relationship to java which has
private and public keywords that don't
seem to exist in python
is there some equivalent in python
okay so let me just interject here for
those who haven't not done
java michonne obviously knows a little
bit of java so a lot of languages have
this notion of classes and objects
c plus plus c sharp java et cetera not
all languages do by the way
uh and within java for example there is
a notion of a public method and a
private method a public method can be
called
by anybody and the private methods can
only be called from member functions
within the class
um i john i actually haven't i don't
know if this is changing python 3. is
there a notion of public and private in
classes in python 3 um
it is there is but it's much lighter
weight
so in a language like java it's really
like strictly
enforced in python instead
there's a naming convention it's a weird
one
we don't really talk about it in this
course but you'll see it in like
industrial code
which is that if you want a method that
you don't want anyone else to call but
it just like is there to help
like uh check that balance
is not negative or something like that
uh assert that self.balance is greater
than equal to zero
you might want this somewhere but
you don't want other people to call it
the convention is to put one underscore
in front of it
and that basically says like oh this
could change people shouldn't rely on
this
um but it's possible to call it anyway
it's just like uh try not to use it
right but it's not enforced right john i
could still call that function that's a
you can still call that function it like
it doesn't show up when you generate the
docs
and stuff like that so there is like a
little bit of
uh soft enforcement there is a
stronger enforcement which is that if
you put two underscores
then this is genuinely hard to call
because
uh some crazy thing happens with naming
that i won't describe
but um that is a feature that i think is
quite rarely used because it's
like hard to understand so the
convention is basically like
if there's stuff that you that is just
like for internal implementation reasons
then you put a little underscore there
and that lets everybody know
this is not something that's part of the
class it's just part of the
implementation that is the very
definition of a hack
it is definitely a hacker now you might
wonder like is python deeply broken well
this idea of private and public came
from a time
when you wanted to write code that's
kind of protected from other bad
programmers
and um there are settings in which this
is a good idea
like if you're building a library that
thousands of people
might use and they might you know use it
wrong and if using it wrong like delete
somebody's bank account
then it really is important to make sure
that it's impossible for them to do it
wrong
and uh this protection system that
exists in java is for that kind of
industrial setting most of the cases
where python is used
um it's more collaborative rather than
defensive
like you know you write your class and
you tell people how they use it but they
can hack on it and mess around with it
if they want to
and as long as all the programmers are
friends and they're willing to
understand how it works
like that can can be perfectly
productive too so it's a different
approach to building libraries and
building code that interacts with other
people's
question so is there some way to make a
user-defined class
immutable um
there this is basically not part of
python as far as i know
there might be some way but i don't
really know what it is
and it doesn't really happen what does
happen sometimes and we'll learn about
this in the next lecture
is that you can specialize some kind of
immutable class that already exists so
you can make like a special kind of
tuple that
behaves slightly differently than a
regular tuple but fundamentally since
tuples are immutable then this
specialization would be too
but other than that i think the answer
is no
um that's that was that i'm not positive
but i don't know of a way of doing it
and by the way it's that's not a bad
feature you could certainly imagine
wanting to create that type of
protection i just i just
don't know or don't think it exists and
there are
i would say there's certainly lots of um
open source projects where classes are
defined that are meant to be used
immutably meaning like the design of
this thing is that you create it and you
don't change it
it's just that the python language
doesn't force you not to change it
so it's really kind of up to you as the
user to read the docs and say
oh this says and we're not supposed to
change it and then it will work
correctly so let's not
change it so raymond is
asking a question about what we call
selector functions and i think we've
actually talked about this in the class
and so you you saw that john in the in
the python window was directly accessing
the balance
uh variable which you're allowed to do
um
i think john can disagree with me if he
wants to that's considered bad form
um that really you should use functions
to access
and set the data fields and not access
to them directly
so it's really all about the abstraction
what's nice about having a function that
says give me the balances i don't need
to know the
the variable name and if i change
something in the underlying data
implementation which you've heard us
talk about before
all the functions are going to do what
the functions do and i don't have to
change my code
so i like when i build classes to have
what i call selector functions which
return to balance return the name
and i like to have functions that set
them and that's the only way i access
the data
now python doesn't force that you can
you can do whatever you want but i think
that's
i like that as sort of a clean
implementation so that if i then go back
up and change the underlying data
representation
i've only got to change a couple of
functions and john's writing them
exactly here these selector and
uh functions yeah so i mean there's
trade-offs and everything
so uh a getter and setter
or a selector and i'm not quite sure
what
how they call it i don't know what the
other one is but often they're called
functions um might look like this
and you know something you might
typically see in a python program is
that this
will indicate that it's not supposed to
be accessed directly with
like an underscore or something like
that um
and the nice thing about this level of
indirection
is that yeah if instead of having a
balance you decide
one day you really want like uh to
represent this
as something else you can do that
and the interface that people access
this with
hasn't changed which is nice um
so i but you've added you know a little
bit of code
and you still have the case that like uh
this part can't be changed or everyone
has to change their code
and so um you've pushed it upstream a
little bit
yeah i think you just gotta think i
don't think there's like a perfect
general rule sometimes this kind of
indirection is quite helpful because
you're not sure
about what your final attributes are
going to be
sometimes it's just kind of extra work
because you're pretty sure you're going
to have a balance
forever and you want people to be able
to mess with it and so
like why have them mess with it with
these functions instead of just using it
directly
it's just a trade-off right you know how
much do you want to future proof your
code to make sure you can change it
later this is one technique to do it
and in some settings it's a good idea
i think that there was like a big push
in the education community
to tell everybody to do this everywhere
all the time
because of this disposition i described
earlier that you need to be very
defensive
of the users of your programming
language or users of your library later
on you want to like
make sure that they don't use it in the
wrong way and so you want to kind of
protect your data and make sure that
it's impossible for them to change it
and that disposition is effective in
certain like
industrial settings and in other ones
it's not like if you have a more
collaborative group of people all
working together then it can be really
nice
to be able to kind of dip in below the
abstraction and mess with something
because the original programmer
didn't anticipate exactly how you want
to use it and you want to do some
feature
that manipulates the balance in a way
that they didn't think about and so
you you want that like access to stuff
that they didn't
really think that you were going to
access directly it just depends
so um so this is a pattern that we don't
like
obsess over in this course because i
think that
it's fine to think about object-oriented
programming as a way
of compartmentalizing changing state
so like have the mutation happen on
particular objects as opposed to
globally
and um have objects interact with each
other by kind of calling methods on each
other like that's really the important
part
and the protecting against other users i
think is something you could learn about
in another course
or we could talk about it now um it's a
fine thing but i don't think it's the
most essential part
of object-oriented programming um and uh
if you do this kind of all the time with
every single
attribute that you include then you can
just like generate a lot of code and
it's hard to see
kind of what's the meat of this uh class
because you've got a bunch of other
stuff that doesn't really do anything
um okay that's nice of you so josh has a
question can you please explain the
difference between remove
and dell methods
i don't let you know the difference yeah
i can
so there's a remove method on certain
objects but not many so for example
a list a is a list an instance of the
list class
and there's a remove method on there
which does a particular thing that's
list specific
it goes to the list and it removes the
first element that's equal to whatever
you pass it
del is something that's really general
it applies to any object and what it
does is it tries to remove an attribute
from that object it actually i think
doesn't work on a lot of built-in stuff
we'll find out in a second what's on
list site
it works on i think you can say dell a
sub zero
oh that's true so if i try to get rid of
the remove functionality
it will say oh no right yeah it's like
built in elements
if i try to
okay so what is a now if i del a
zero then that will get rid of the one
so that's kind of like remove except for
we've picked an index as opposed to a
value to remove
um but del is actually pretty general so
as you can see
it's not a method it's not using dot
notation but instead it's its own kind
of statement
and you can delve from all kinds of
stuff but i basically never use it
because
i think it's almost always better to
just use the methods that are built into
the class
so it does exist maybe you want it
sometimes
and maybe you could never use it
and do everything that you want to do
the next question was about explaining
parts 10 and 12
of homework 3 all right homework 3 was
already due
and there were some extra questions
that you didn't have to do but i think
are interesting
and they were about data abstraction
where
um we had an abstraction about an
interval
and that interval basically described
there's some number but we don't know
what it is
so instead we're saying like oh it's
between three and seven
and that means we know it's in there we
just don't actually know whether it's
four or five or six
that was the idea behind this question
so we haven't done it yet
the first part was to build an interval
abstraction
because we could probably just do that
if you want the lower bound then you
return the intervals
at index 0 if you want the upper bound
then you could return the element at
index 1 and that's because we
constructed it in this particular way
there was some notion of multiplying i
wonder if we need that for question 10
probably yeah let's let's add this
notion of multiplying oh it's given to
us excellent
all we have to do is fix the data
abstraction violations
which i think would be that you get the
lower bound
of x times the lower bound
oh it's going to take a while to type
sorry
we could have the lower bound of x
times the upper bound of y
we could have okay so let's talk about
what's going on here because it's
actually really
important um
when you multiply two numbers together
there's only one answer
but when you multiply two intervals
together basically what you're saying is
i'm multiplying some number and i don't
know what it is but it's in this range
with some other number and i don't know
what it is but it's in this other range
okay we got rid of the abstraction
barrier violations
what would it mean to have an interval
from
[Music]
negative 1 to 1 and another interval
from negative 2 to 2 and multiply them
together
it tells me negative 2 to 2. why is that
well we don't know what the number for a
really is it could be negative 1
and b could be negative 2 at which point
if i multiply those two numbers together
i get 2.
well this was kind of a lousy example
let's have this go from negative two to
zero
okay see what happens when you multiply
okay so even though
uh like it's not obvious how you get to
the number two
well the way you get to number two is a
is negative one
and b is negative 2 and so you've
multiplied two negative two numbers
together and you can get a positive
number
how you get to negative two i guess is
maybe a is actually one
you don't know it's like somewhere in
that interval and you could multiply
that by negative two and you would get
negative two
it's also possible to get like anything
in between you could get a half
because uh this is one oh sorry
this is a negative one and this is uh
a half i do that right no
if a were negative one and b were
negative a half then you'd get a half
that's like in that interval somewhere
okay finally i got it right
here's something weird what happens if
you multiply
a by a it says you could get anything
from negative one to one but
i argue this is wrong because
if you take some number and you multiply
it by itself
you never get a negative number right
anything squared is
greater than or greater than or equal to
zero
that's just like a fact yet somehow
we have code that says if i multiply a
by a
i could get anything from negative one
to one so
something has gone wrong and that was
what this like uh
question was about so let's read the
question and uh
then try to understand what's going on
so
sometimes when intervals are computed by
different but algebraically equivalent
expressions
you get different results and the
problem is multiple references to the
same interval
the multiple reference problem is a
formula to compute intervals
using this system the system that has
things like mole interval
will produce tighter error bounds if it
can be written in such a form that no
variable that represents an uncertain
number is repeated
why is it that multiplying a times a
according to the system that we've built
gives you the wrong number what would
the right number be
well i think the right number would be
if you take some number between negative
one and one and you multiply it by
itself you can get anything from zero to
one
but you can't get anything negative and
the reason this gets it wrong
is that this code assumes
that x and y could be different numbers
but in fact if these are the same
interval they're really referring to the
same number you don't happen to know
what it is
but it can't be different for the x
and the y it couldn't be that some
number which is
between negative one and one is both
negative one and one at the same time
that's not what intervals are
intervals are about one number and we
don't know what it is
so for that reason when you write all
this code and you think it's going to
work it actually doesn't work correctly
because you have an implicit assumption
that
x and y are different intervals but in
fact if you pass the same one in
then then you're kind of using intervals
wrong
that's the story of question 10
multiple reference problem yeah i
haven't seen question 12 which i think
was also part of tan's
original question after considerable
work
eliza p hacker delivers her finished
system several years later after she's
forgotten all about it she has a
frenzied call it seems that lem has
noticed that the formula for parallel
resistors can be written in two
algebraically equivalent ways okay i'm
pretty sure this was supposed to come
before question
10. but here's two different ways of
writing down what should be the same
equation right because if you write r1
times r2 divided by r1 plus r2
that's the same thing as writing 1 over
1 over r1
plus 1 over r2 except
that this refers to r1 twice
and this only refers to r1 once
so if you use the system that we've
built
combining with multiplication and
division
r1 and r2 but you've got r1 in there
twice
according to the way this multiplication
function that we wrote works
you're going to have like a different
value for r1
somewhere in that range in one part of
the equation than you do in another part
of the equation
and that is broken so i think that
the point of this example was that it
only works like this
interval computation system that you've
built only works
if each interval only shows up once if
it ever shows up twice
then you get the wrong answer yeah i
think that's the nugget of it
it's not how i would have interpreted it
by the way but i think the nugget is
that when you have the same interval
you are assuming that you're choosing
the same value from that interval
and then the rules change
yeah and so you'd have to write a new
system
a follow-up question was whether this
has to do with programming or python
or it's just about this particular
interval example
yes this has nothing to do with
programming except for
you do need to think about what you're
representing in the world
when you write your program and here's
an example of that it's like if you just
like
assume everything's fine um but you
forgot that the interval you're
representing
only can be one number at once then you
might run into trouble
okay what's a static method and when
would you use it
a static method is just a function
and you would write it like any other
function like if i want to be able to
square a number
i would write that
what if this function was really kind of
associated with a class
in some way and so i wanted the way that
people access it
to not be
what am i doing to write
square 12 i really wanted them to write
like a
math dot square
12. and why would i want it this way
well it's basically just a way of saying
like
i want to group a bunch of functions
together and i want to use a class to do
it
and have attribute notation kind of take
care of that
for me well
if i make a math class and i put square
in there something's gone wrong
because normally methods start with self
but there's like no self there's not a
math out there
this is really just like a different way
of using classes to just group
stuff together and if i want square to
be a regular function
but happen to exist inside of a class
then there's a decorator to do that i
think it looks like that
and what's the story here well now i can
square stuff
uh if for some reason i made a math
i could square stuff with that math
and it wouldn't try to like fill in a
self for me
so all this does is get rid of
any kind of interesting self behavior
and you leave out self entirely which
means that this is reduced to just being
a regular function
and so if you didn't want to like have
fun
regular functions live inside classes
you wouldn't need this at all but
sometimes
organizationally you want that because
you want people to refer to it in a
particular way
at which point you might use a static
method the last question was
is there anything you don't like about
python's object system
good question uh sorry i just sent you
the question i have one minute
yes the answer is yes i don't like how
um undisciplined it is um i
there are things i like which is unlike
java you can actually write code without
classes
and that's nice it's nice you just
getting your hands dirty i don't
like sort of the the sloppiness of it
that you can
you can it's not quite as precise as i
would like
um like for example michonne asked about
the public private i actually think
that's
john's right we're not adversarial but i
i
i tend to think that that kind of
functionality is nice but so but there's
other things i really like about it
yeah it's really minimal and
that's not ideal in a lot of settings
especially
when you're trying to collaborate on
like really large programs across many
people
i think the minimalist flavor of
python's object system kind of
limits the ability to scale this to
really large
programs now people done it anyway but
they've often done it by building
a lot of extra
a lot of extra infrastructure on top of
the language like you come up with some
system for defining
who is allowed to call what that isn't
built into the language
and that's just a shame right it's
better to have it kind of built in
but it's a reasonable decision it's just
a compromise
like having something that's simple can
be good because then people can learn it
faster
and uh when you read somebody else's
code
you're not faced with a bunch of like
tricky stuff that you've never heard of
at the same time it's uh
it can be a barrier to like really using
the language for
something extremely ambitious so like i
was at google for a while and there was
a lot of python code
but there were rules about how you were
allowed to write your python code
and like extra comments that you had to
put everywhere that were pretty
elaborate
in order to basically force some kind of
additional
structure into the language that wasn't
there and
that you know that seems like uh
indication that the language was not a
good fit for