61a lecture 28 q a
while we wait for people to get on let
me say i think that this tri
construct is incredibly important um
if you do anything i think you mentioned
this john at the beginning that if you
do anything
like in cloud computing where you have
big jobs running for days
on end if you don't handle exceptions
it's a nightmare because your code keeps
crashing you come back in the morning
and nothing happened
so being able to handle all those
exceptions and let the jobs keep running
is i'll tell you we've done some really
big processing over the years and
without that
construct i don't think we would have
ever gotten through it
um i really like that construct and i if
i recall i don't think it was presidency
for example yeah i think you're right
um it's uh it's certainly
available in kind of most modern
programming languages
or something like it yeah you know um
the the nice thing about try statements
and exception handling is that you don't
actually have to think about
all the things that could go wrong yeah
you just have to say what should happen
if something does go wrong
and um that kind of frees you up not to
anticipate every possible
quirk that might happen in some system
um
but you do have to have a contingency
plan basically if you know you
you try something that doesn't work out
like what should happen instead
yeah yeah yeah yeah it's one of my
favorite constructs in python i just
we've just used it so much over the
years and it just it made life so much
better
yeah good question so um why
is exception handling slow
i would say that the interpreter for
python is really optimized for the thing
that happens a lot
which is you make a function call you
return from a function call
make another function call that makes a
function call you return from those
and there's like a very clear order
which is basically every time you make a
function call you add a new frame
every time you return you go back to
where you were and
the whole interpreter is set up to make
sure that both of those operations are
pretty fast when you
raise an exception you're actually
kind of going somewhere out of order
sometimes
and so
it you know python has to make a lot of
checks along the way to figure out
exactly where
the next thing uh is that like the next
line of code is that should be executed
and what the environment is
and it also like builds up a lot of
information along the way so whenever
there's an exception it remembers what
line that exception happened on
and any like information associated with
that
and you know that information has to get
passed around so there's just like a
fair amount of what i would call
bookkeeping
in order to figure out exactly how to
handle the exception within the
interpreter
and that just you know takes a while
takes a lot of instructions
yeah i mean generally speaking this is
true you i think most modern languages
have
essentially a debug mode and an
optimization mode
where as you're writing the code and
testing and testing and testing it it's
okay if it's a little slow but then when
you go
to say okay we are now ready to go live
you simply can turn all those things off
but the nice thing is
you don't have to remove the code you
just have to sort of flip that one
flag at the command line and most
languages have that kind of command line
you can leave all the code in there for
when you want to come back to it and
then just at run time they all just get
ignored
so that's a pretty typical thing that
debugging is slow which is there's a
conditional wrapped around everything
essentially
but slow is relative i mean yeah still
on the order of some some number of
microseconds
so uh even if you do hundreds of these
you're never gonna notice it it's only
if you do
tens of thousands of uh raising
exceptions and catching them that you
would like notice
as a human that your program is slow and
and you know it's often the case that in
big programs you're doing you know
millions of things so you do have to
think about a little bit
but um but don't avoid it because you
know
someone told you it was slow yeah that's
a good point john you really will only
feel this when you're when you're
running jobs that take
days weeks months to run not if it takes
seconds to run
yeah there's nothing to worry about
you're done right so the scale at which
we are working at is not a scale that
you have to worry about
so um i think we kind of left this out
of lecture but there is a
optional clause in a try statement
called finally and
um what does it do we could talk a
little bit about why
what it does and why it's there
so um the story is that you write try
you have code that will always run uh it
might not run to completion
but you know this part always runs
maybe this one too
why do i say maybe well if an exception
is raised while executing this line then
you never get to this line but
assuming things are going along smoothly
you would do the whole try block
and you only end up in the accept block
if an exception was raised here
and then there's this thing called the
finally block
and here is code
that is supposed to always run that's
the story
is that whether there is an exception or
not
uh there might be something that you
really want to have happen
have it happen at the end and uh make
sure it happens
so this will always
run at the end so you might wonder why
don't you just put it
here well this line won't always run at
the end because if an exception is
raised in the first line then you'll
never get to the third line
so you might have some things that you
want to run
even if there's an exception or there is
not
and the classic thing to put in here is
is releasing resources so oftentimes a
program
will take claim of some file or some
internet connection
and decide like i'm the program that's
using this right now even though there
might be other programs running on the
same computer
um you know some program can kind of
assert its uh priority and say i've
claimed this
resource and uh you want to make sure
that
even if something goes wrong when you're
processing that file or using that
internet connection
that you release that resource so that
some other program can use it as well
like it would be bad if
you know your uh your browser crashed
and that meant that
no other programs could use the internet
right that would be a problem so
um so that's kind of a classic use for
finally is just to like make sure
that you clean up whatever resources you
acquired you let them go
in this course we don't talk much at all
about resource acquisition
and releasing that's more of a topic for
61c and 162
but so that's why we don't really talk
about this clause in this course is it's
just like it doesn't come up as relevant
very often
but that's what it is
good question so the story is when you
write a try statement
and you have accept and then you name a
class of exception
um like zero division error
or something like that and then you put
a name
and this name could be anything and the
question is what is it bound to
and when does that happen um
well let's do an example
um
watch what happens so i'm going to say n
is n i'm going to run this
and it says n is division by zero
that's the stir representation of some
object
that object is called n and
to answer your question n is bound to an
object that represents the error itself
so why is it that an error is an object
well
objects are just like uh behavior and
data
bundled together in this case i think
it's the data that's important
you want to know um you know what line
caused the problem
and and that kind of thing and so that
data is bundled into n
so if we do this a little bit more
interactively
let's say we want to return and
return an error
so if i say a is return an
error let's call it e
then now i've returned to this object
i can look at it i can play with it i
can see what attributes it has
i can see what happens when i call stir
on it or wrapper on it
um there isn't like a whole lot more to
it
but you could imagine there are errors
where you do want to keep
information about it like you know what
was the file that you were accessing
when your hard drive crashed or
something like that
and that's why these objects exist
so e is
sorry is instance e exception
that's true it's also a little bit more
specific than that it's
a sub class of exception called zero
division error
um so in that sense it's both a
exception and a particular kind of
exception and that's something you might
want to check
so here we are in fall 2019's final exam
um question
seven which in this case is called
mull it over and it's about scheme oh
someone evaluated define the
time symbol as whatever the plus symbol
evaluates to
okay plus symbol evaluates to a
procedure that adds
a plus symbol gives me a procedure that
adds and now i've defined
times as a procedure that adds so
now when i multiply 2 by 3 i get 5
instead of 6. let's
fix it okay so we're going to implement
some notion of multiplication small xy
which multiplies integers x and y
hint minus 2 evaluates to negative 2.
okay um i think the story here is that
we need to implement multiplication
using addition because we lost the
ability to multiply but we still have
the ability to add
so if i were to multiply 3 by 4 i should
get 12
how might we get there well i think one
way is that we could
accumulate a result by adding threes
four times that's basically what
multiplication is
okay so then there's this tricky bit
about how to handle
negative cases so uh when you multiply
by a negative number
you want to kind of negate the whole
result and uh we're indicating the
result of having
four negative threes added together
all right so this says if y is less than
0 then we'll just negate the result
of multiplying x and y together
but we'll negate y how about that
so i'm claiming that negative 3 times
negative 4 is the same thing as
negative 3 times 4 negated
keep x the way it is negate y
and then negate the whole thing so
now once i've kind of gone through this
i know that a
recursive call will have y being a
positive number or zero
oh we have a case for zero so now we
know y is positive
and that means we want to
have at least one x so
i think one way to do this is to
add x to the result
of multiplying
x minus 1
by y
no that's wrong multiplying
x by y minus 1.
okay so y is negative now it's positive
and we always work our way towards zero
eventually we'll hit this base
case where y is 0. implement
mall expression which takes an
expression e that contains only calls to
star
and numbers it returns the normal value
of e under a scheme interpreter with an
unmodified multiply sign that multiplies
so here instead of doing the work
we're supposed to build up some kind of
multiplication expression
and it says mole
is a function that uses mole x y
on s to give me a single number using
reduce which we did actually talk about
today in lecture so this would be
repeatedly apply this procedure to pairs
of values
where we would then multiply 2 and 3
together
to get 6 and then multiply that by 4 and
then multiply that by 2 to get 48
so that's what mole does is it takes a
list of numbers and multiplies them all
together
but mole expert is something else molex
per
takes an expression full of numbers and
multiplication signs
and evaluates that expression correctly
assuming times actually worked okay if v
is a number
then
we return its value
otherwise e must be an expression
it must look like that or a more
complicated version would be like that
so it's a list that starts with a star
and then it's got a bunch of other
stuff in it that's supposed to be
multiplied together and we see some
examples
is that it might start with a star and
then have three numbers in it or it
might have to start with a star and have
two numbers in it
we have to figure out what to do about
that so
i think one thing we could do is for
each sub-expression
get a number and then we could just
multiply all those numbers together
so we could call them all but
in order to multiply
uh these things we have to first
make sure that we've turned each
sub-expression into a number
that's basically how python and scheme
both work because the way you evaluate
this whole thing
is you evaluate the parts so we get 2
here
and we get whatever that is 24 there and
then
we start multiplying so we would
uh call
mall expert over each subexpression
except for the times doesn't need to be
converted at all that
just kind of gets ignored so i think
here we have a
slot where we can say i don't actually
care about the
multiplication sign at the front what i
really care about is all those other sub
expressions
i don't care about this but i do care
about that and that i want to call mole
expert on both of those um
map is built into scheme and it works
just like
it would in python except for without
the lazy evaluation feature that we
talked about in python
how long is this oh we're getting close
implement startemo which takes any
expression it returns an expression like
e
but with any calls to star replaced with
calls to
maul note that star takes an arbitrary
number of arguments while mall
takes exactly one argument a list of
numbers you should account for this
difference
so we take in some expression which
isn't just
stars and numbers it might have some
pluses in it or some other things
dividing or whatever two
and um builds an expression
where this star
is substituted with a molex y
oh no sorry with a mole no
so what would this actually look like if
i and this says if you evaluate it you
get 75 but what is the actual expression
itself
well if i start a mole
uh times one
two times three four
what should that actually do
that should give me back uh
mole of
a list containing one and two
and mol
of a list containing three and four
but why do you need why do you have to
explicitly make the list john why not
just
have it be the list
well good oh i see actually in the in
the in the skeleton of the code i think
it's going to force you to do that
uh yeah so the question is why didn't we
just write
this
yeah and then three four so
this expression says call one
on two oh
yeah you don't want to do it as data
yeah you're right
okay uh
fun times let operator be
something
how about the car of this expression
that will tell us whether we're timesing
or plusing
and the rest well i don't know yet but
i'm just kind of guessing that maybe
it's the cutter of the expression
okay if i see at times then what am i
supposed to do
i'm supposed to build a list
which has mole in it
i'm just building this thing
it has
another element a second element
which starts with the symbol list
and then how do i get the one and the 2
and the mole 3
4 well there i think
those came from the original expression
so at that point i think i'm fine to
just
map the star to mole procedure that i
already have
sorry this is so bad oh no that made it
worse
over the rest of the list
so then i end up with two elements the
mole element and the
list one two blah blah blah element
i put those into a list so that gives me
the outer parentheses
and i've built the structure that i want
so i guess the key to cracking this nut
was to
you know try to use the description to
describe
like some expression that would actually
be equivalent
and that turned out not to be so trivial
john did we have to do this with the let
statement couldn't i have just
used the extracted the car and the
critter on the fly
in the in the conditional yeah
definitely the case that instead of
writing up
we could have just written carvey and
instead yeah another could have been
written
okay um and
you know why is it this way well i guess
it refers to op multiple times and it
refers to rest multiple times so maybe
it's nice to give a name to them i think
that's all that's going on here yeah
okay
all right sure so
good question what does map do
in general if you have a list
and you have a procedure
then the idea behind map is that you
could apply the procedure to each
element in the list
and accumulate the results in a list
i'm still stuck on the fact that this
seems wrong
uh oh because of the one it shouldn't be
squared i
should have that makes me very nervous
what happened to the one oh because you
redefined multiplication john
thank you
that'll that'll teach you to write the
divine star to be plus
yeah we're gonna start this interpreter
over and steam over again multiplication
is back
so the question was can you describe the
difference between cons list and
and why you would use them okay
so um just kind of like multiply is
built out of
a bunch of additions you can think of
list as built at a bunch of cons
cons is like the most fundamental
operation and what it does is it just
adds one element
to the beginning of an existing list so
if you want to
build a seven element list you got to
call cons
seven times if you're just using cons
um so the rule with cons is you can have
anything here though like if you're just
building a list of numbers this will
always be a number
this is an element in the resulting list
the first element
and then here you are
writing any expression that gives you an
existing list there is the empty list
here's a longer list
but the cons itself is really just
always adding one element
list is there to make sure that you can
build a long list without having to have
a bunch of different procedure calls so
if you only had cons then the only way
to build six seven eight nine
would be to have four calls to cons
which just seems like a ridiculous
constraint
so uh list is there
to build an arbitrarily long list it
takes as many arguments as you want and
they all become elements in the list
so that's the relationship between cons
and append cons always takes two
arguments element and a list
and gives you back uh one longer list
list always just takes elements if i
give list
a list i end up with a list of lists
so if i put cons 9 nil in here
this evaluates to a list and that as an
argument to list is going to give me a
list within a list
so lists arguments are all elements
whereas khan's
argument first is an element but this is
the rest of the list
okay and that brings us to append
appends arguments are lists
they're not elements and the goal of
append is to put
all the elements in the list that you
pass it into a longer list
so if i have a list one two and i have a
list three four five
then i end up with one two three four
five
so just think about domain and range
cons takes an element and a list
gives you a slightly longer list list
takes a bunch of elements
gives you a list append takes a bunch of
lists
and gives you a list so they all return
lists but they all take different uh
pieces of that list in order to
construct them
so delaney they all they all sort of do
the same thing it's just what the inputs
are slightly different depending on how
you want to build the list but the end
of the day they're all about building a
list there's nothing fundamentally
different at the back end
when you're done with these things yes
python has the same kind of structure
insert append square bracket
show me a list and we can have created
it using any of these techniques
right any of these constructs rather
it's just a question as john was saying
of like how tedious is it
yeah and the right way to make a
selection is to say what do i have now
if you have an element and a list you're
gonna use cons
if you have three lists you're gonna use
append if you have four elements you're
gonna use list
right so what do you have and and that's