sixty one eight lecture No.23
announcements
lab ate is due today
ante's due Friday
the checkpoint
containing phases one and two is due today
you can earn an early submission bonus point
for submitting the whole thing
by Thursday homework 5 is released its due next Monday
the only required part of lab
nine will be to finish homework 5
which should give you some good practice
for the upcoming midterm
the midterm is next Wednesday
it will have a similar format to midterm one
but there will be no questions of the form
what would this mysterious function do
instead we'll focus on
just implementing functions that are described for you
as well as some possible questions on
environment diagrams
the textbook content is sections through 2.9
excluding several that we haven't covered this semester
or were explicitly declared as optional
I like these sections
feel free to read them
but they're not going to be covered on the exam
and in terms of lecture content
this is everything
through last friday's lecture on composition
excluding the binary numbers and circus lectures
that happened at the end of September
proctoring will be the same as it was from it term one
you'll record your screen and your head
using zoom or loom
or another recording technology of your choosing
this time around you might consider using zoom
web recording
if you prefer that to loom
we found in the exit survey for midterm one
that some people had loom
crash on them
or cut out early in
various ways that caused extra stress
you might find
that the zoom web recording is more reliable
and of course zoom is also the recommended choice
for local recording if you don't have a stable
internet connection
if you want an alternate time or you have a conflict
please fill out
the alternate time request form by Sunday
we're starting from scratch
in assigning alternate times
so if you fill this out from interim one
you do need to fill it out again from interim two
because people have been moving around in course
conflicts vary
so let's just do it all from scratch
you can use the midterm one study guide and the midterm
two study guide
which again is one page front and back
of all the important slides from the course
I just finished updating it with some new examples
that hopefully will be hopeful
and here are some pictures of trees
and some examples of attribute assignment
so this
study guide is only going to be useful if you actually
read it in advance
I would suggest that you do that
from intern one
we put a limit on the number of pages of
notes that you could create
for yourself but we are now removing that limit
you can use as many of your own notes as you want
I would not recommend generating a lot of notes
I think
maybe two pages of notes is about the right amount
but if you want to take more notes
or if you have
already taken more notes and you want to use them
that's fine
but these do need to be notes that you create yourself
please don't
share your notes with everybody else in the course
other than your own notes
you can only use
course material that's been posted publicly
if you would like to store your notes electronically
you must use a google doc
you must also give edit access to this google doc
to see a 61 a ed
berkeley rd to you
so we can check out what's going on there
if you use paper which I recommend
then you do not need to share your notes for this
you can just keep them for yourself
again you can use anything on csixtuna
org or the sixth una piazza
and you can execute code using code csixtuna
org or python tutor
however you cannot use the rest of the internet
you cannot use search engines or qa sites or RedDit
and you cannot communicate or collaborate with
anybody else do not text your friends during the exam
you might think there's no way we could catch you
and yet we do
and when we catch people communicating during the exam
they get enough in the whole course
don't let that happen to you
just take the exam by yourself
you can request an exemption from the proctoring policy
some people did this already for midterm one
if you'd like to
request this going forward from interim 2 in the final
because you found out that proctoring is
problematic in some way
you can do this by Sunday
if you already filled out this form from intern one
you do not need to fill it out again
anyone who's been exempted from proctoring
will remain exempted for the rest of the semester
so I hope that's some helpful information
about the exam
I'll share some more info about
any student led review sessions
as soon as I know about them
and one final announcement
is that the staff will be holding
conceptual help off sours
Wednesday and Thursday of this week
here's the zoom link
where if you want to ask
about concepts in general
as opposed to specific problems
you can ask there
or listen to other students
ask those questions and hear the answers
from a couple of tas
that have taught this course for a long time
okay today's lecture on decomposition
is really just an illustration of how to put together
ideas that we've learned about already in this course
to do something new
searching for the right place to eat
large programs are complex programs
it's hard to think about all of their parts at once
and so they can benefit from a modular design
which means that the whole program is broken up
into small fairly independent parts
now they might not be completely independent
because different parts of the program
have to work together
to achieve the behavior of the whole thing
but modular means that there are components
that could be switched in and out
and are separated by various kinds of abstraction
barriers
the goal of a modular design
is to achieve separation of concerns
different parts of the program
are concerned with different
parts of the behavior of that program
so this is a general design principle
which encourages programmers
to isolate different parts of the program
that address different concerns
so that you don't have to think
about all the requirements of the program at once
a modular component
can therefore be developed and tested independently
to make sure that it accounts for whatever concern
it's meant to address
without worrying about the behavior
of the rest of the program
and we've tried to illustrate this principle
with the course projects
so in the game of hog
there are three different modular components
a hog game simulator is concerned with the game rules
the ordering of events within the game
and whatever state tracking is required
to determine who won
but it knows nothing about commentary
the game commentary functions are concerned with
describing different events that happen
during the game
and whatever state
tracking is necessary to generate that commentary
and neither of these components are concerned with
what the players actually do
those are the concern of the player strategy functions
which have various decision rules
and capture information
about strategies
like the margin of
points that she'll use
to decide whether to take advantage
of free bacon
so different aspects of the game state
and different pieces of the program's logic
are all handled by different parts of the program
now they interact because
commentary functions are pass to the play function
and strategy functions are pass to the play function
but the play function doesn't need to know much
about how they work
it just needs to call them
the ants project has a similar modular design
there's an ants game simulator
that you didn't have to write
but it handles the order of actions and
tracking of the overall food of the colony
and figuring out whether the game is over
but this part of the program really has no idea
what the ant and b actions actually do
those are handled in all of the action functions
each of which is defined independently
to describe what special
about an ant or a b
and these characteristics make the game interesting
but writing an action function
can be done without worrying
about the order that actions will occur in
or how much food the colony has
or whether the game is over
and writing an action also doesn't need to know much
about how the game is laid out
there's a separate part of the program
that worries about tunnel structures
how many there are
how long they are
and sets up all the entrances and exits
this part also keeps track
of the locations of all the ants and bees
and most interesting programs have
some kind of structural decomposition
and by decomposition I don't just mean
that long functions are broken up
into smaller functions
I also mean that different aspects of the program
different concerns
are isolated to different parts of the coat
and when you build one part of the program
that part should have to know as little as possible
about other concerns that aren't its concern
so the game commentary functions
shouldn't be dependent on the rules of the game
in fact your design is more modular
if changing the rules of the game
only changes the hog simulator code
it doesn't change the commentary code at all
let's apply this idea of modular design to an example
restaurant search
here are the data
and we'll try to
build a program that lets us
look up a restaurant by words in its name
and also show related restaurants
for each restaurant we know its name
the number of stars that got on yelp
and the price category that yelp gives it
and these are actual examples from the yelp database
that were released a few years ago for academic use
here's another entry about la cascada takaria
which has three stars on average
and a price category of two
I think in yelp stars go from one to five
and prices go from one to three
each business not only has a name
but also some complicated unique string
called the business id
and we'll have a different one of these dictionaries
for every restaurant near
the border of berkeley campus
and we also have reviews which give a business id
telling us which restaurant the review is about
a user id which is a unique indicator of who wrote it
this doesn't have an email address or anything
but it does tell us
whether the same user wrote two different reviews
how many stars they gave the restaurant and some text
cafe three or cafe tray as I like to say
used to be the bomb diggity
when I first lived in the dorms
but sadly
quality has dramatically decreased over the years
says user xvocu as z etc
this reviews from 2012
the data I have is a little bit old
because yelp stopped publishing an academic dataset
that includes berkeley restaurants
their new academic dataset
doesn't have anything from berkeley
so we're gonna use some older data
because it's more interesting to see
cafes and restaurants
that actually exist around campus
here's a review for a different business
this business id matches the one for la cascada tacaria
an user 80 fourd etc
gave two stars to la cascada tuckeria
saying excuse me for being a snob
but if I wanted a room temperature burrito
I would take one home
stick it in the fridge for a day
throw it in the microwave for 45 seconds then eat it
not go to a restaurant and pay like $7 for one
said this user in 2009
so given that I have a file full of these
business names and a file full of these reviews
how can I build a restaurant search application
that lets me look up a restaurant by name
and show related restaurants
well there are
many questions to be answered
in order to finish this application
what does it mean to look something up by name
what does it mean for restaurants to be related
what should we do with the price and the stars and the
business id
how should we represent businesses and reviews
well let's dive in and try to focus on modular design
so here's my file of restaurants
and in fact
there's more information than even what I sit
a longitude latitude categories addresses
not just for cafe iii but also jasmine tai
fondufred and a long list of other ones
there are 133 restaurants in this data set
and what about the reviews
we have 17,000 reviews
let's say things like
the pizza is terrible
but if you need a place to watch a game or just
down some pitchers
this place works
and we have the business idea they're talking about
but we don't know the name of that unless we match it
up with one of the businesses in the other file
having taken a peak at the data
I think we can dive in and write some code
we need a function that searches
so that we can call search
on tie and get back a list of all the tie restaurants
and then for each restaurant in this results
we should be able to look at the restaurant itself
and also
what it's similar to
I think a good way to represent whether something
similar is using a method
let's get
three different similar restaurants for every r
now for this to work we need to have a search function
we pass in a query
and we need to decide what it means to match a query
well I think of the queries in the name
then we should return that restaurant
r for r in all restaurants
if query in our dot name
now we haven't defined yet what a restaurant is
or how to get all the restaurants
so this code might not work but it has the right idea
one of the most important concerns of assert engine
is always the ranking that it gives to the results
so what orders we return the restaurants in
alphabetical by location
maybe the most popular one first
may be the one with the highest star rating
this decision gives us an opportunity for modular
design
we can just pass in a ranking function
and return a sordid version of the results
that uses the ranking function
in order to pick which ones come first
so that nice piece of modular design
comes with a consequence
every time I call search
I need to come up with a ranking function
so it would be helpful to have some default
how about by default
we order them by their number of stars
now sorted gives you back the list of results
from least to greatest according to the key function
so this would give us
the one with the lowest stars first
unless we put in a negation sign here
in which case the lowest by
negative stars is actually the one with the most stars
okay we're making progress
but we need to know what all the restaurants are
and how a restaurant works
let's start with the latter
representing a restaurant
is naturally done with the class
and we already see
some of the attributes
we need to track the name in the stars
which we'll assume we get from the file somehow
and are passed in here
I think this is a good
opportunity to think about how we're going to keep
track of all the restaurants
instead of having some global name
we could use a class attribute
which we initialize here
and populate here
all that append self
puts whatever restaurant I create
into the list of all restaurants
so now I think my search function will work
but what about r dot similar
that's something we need to define as well
how do I find the k
most similar restaurants to some restaurant
well that sounds complicated
I think a good step in the right direction
is to write down
a dock string
return the k most similar restaurants to self
and for now let's leave it blank
I think we've written enough code that we should
test our progress
so let's not worry about the file just yet
and create some restaurants
tie delight has two stars
tie basil has three stars and top dog
has five stars
man that place is delicious
and we run our program
we found a bug
instead of referring to all restaurants
I was referring to the built in all function
which does not have in a pen method
on other bug is that when I print out a restaurant
I see some nonsense
I can fix that by just adding a repper method
and how I don't
we return
angled brackets around the name of the restaurant
okay so when we search for Thai
we find Thai delight and Thai basil but not top dog
that looks good
and we just need to finish this notion of similarity
we need to implement
the similar method of the restaurant class
which takes in a restaurant
and a number of similar restaurants to return
and finds the most similar k
there are many notions of similarity
they're close in distance
they have a similar raiding a similar price
maybe
they're similar because the same people review them
meaning the same people go there
whatever the case is
I think we have another
opportunity to introduce modularity
by passing in a similarity function
that takes into restaurants
and tells us how similar they are
now the job of the similar function
its concern is not to determine the similarity
but determine the k most similar restaurants itself
why don't you try doing that
implements similar
a restaurant method that takes a positive integer k
and a function similarity
that takes two
restaurants as arguments and returns a number
higher similarity values indicate
more similar restaurants
and the similar method is supposed to return a list
containing that
came
most similar restaurants according to the similarity
function
but this list should not contain the restaurant itself
it would be silly to say the most similar restaurant to
tie delight is
tie delight
so we'll define the similar method
which returns the camo similar restaurants to self
using similarity for comparison
and what we'll do
is build a list of all the restaurants except for self
and then sort it according to some key function
and then there's an opportunity
to manipulate the sorted list
sorted is a built in function that takes some iterable
and some key function
and returns a new list containing
all items from the iterable
in ascending order
according to the custom key function
and you can use a reverse flag
but we didn't use that in our example
why don't you spend a minute and try to fill in
this implementation
pause the video and I'll go through the answer in 321
others is a copy of the list of all restaurants
and we need to remove
this restaurant which we do using the remove method
and what do we pass in to tell it what to remove self
that's the element of the list of all restaurants
that we do not want to include
in the list of similar restaurants
the key function for sorted
just like the key function for max and min
must be a one argument function
referring to an element of the others list
so how do we make sure
that others is ranked according to its
similarity to self
well we write down
a function of one argument
that computes the similarity
between self and r
I've negated it
so that most similar restaurants come first
and the least similar restaurants come at the end
now that we've sorted them all
we don't want to return
the list of all other restaurants
but instead just the top k
which we can do with the slice
let's finish our restaurant search program
by reading in some files
but first let's pick a default notion of similarity
let's say that the similarity between two restaurants
is the number of people that reviewed them both
so reviewed both takes a restaurant r
and another restaurant s
and returns the length of the list of ours reviewers
that are also ss reviewers
that's just one notion of similarity
two restaurants are similar
if the same group of people reviews them both
so now
we need to make sure that a restaurant has reviewers
and we'll read those from a file
instead of creating three restaurants by hand
we'll read all the restaurants
for a line in open restaurants
jason will iterate through all the lines in the file
here's the file
this
format is called json or javascript object notation
which can be read by python
just by importing the json module
and calling jason
load string on the line
that gives us a dictionary with key's open
url neighborhoods etc
in order to construct a restaurant
we need to pass in the name
the stars and we don't want the number of reviews
instead we want the list of reviewers
that's going to be complicated to compute
so let's give it a name
the reviewers
is what we get
when we look through all the reviews
and find the user ids
of the people that reviewed this restaurant
I think
we're going to have to read through all the reviews
first and then look up the reviews for the restaurant
and recall that the
reviews are each given a business id
which also appears in restaurants json
so we'll use that to look up the reviewers
so this dictionary reviewers for restaurant
has to be built by going through every line
in the reviews file
constructing a
python dictionary from the json line
which business is it
well we get the business id
and if we've never seen this business before
then I think we should put that business
into this dictionary
and the value associated with that business id
should be a list of all the users that reviewed
let's use their user ids
because that's all we know about the users otherwise
if we've seen this before
then looking up reviewers for restaurant biz
will give us a list
to which we can append that same value
every time we create a restaurant
it's added to the restaurant dot all list
and that means we should be able to search for Thai
food using real businesses
oh we had a bug here
where I was talking too much
and I forgot to assign reviewers
and now it works
this says Thai basil cuisine is similar to gypsies
tretaria italiano and top dog
are those restaurants really similar
well
they're similar in the sense that students go there
so I think we should change this to something like
shares reviewers with
folks who go to Thai noodle two
also go to la cascada takaria
folks who go to jasmine Thai
which used to be on the north side before it closed
also review other restaurants on the north side
interesting
so it looks like we're done
building our restaurant search engine
we finished our
restaurant search application but it's too slow
to find all the tire restaurants
and lists all of their similar restaurants
doesn't happen instantly
in fact it takes about 0.7 seconds
and things are even worse if we look at cafes
since there are more cafes
it now takes
1.7 seconds in order to list all of the results
why is it so slow
we could go through in time each part
or we could just think about what's happening
in our program
we go through each restaurant
to see if it matches the query
that's linear time
for each restaurant we call similar
on every other restaurant
that's also linear time
and what about computing the similarity itself
here we go through every reviewer
for restaurant r
and check if that's a reviewer for restaurant s
and how does it do that check will
it goes through every reviewer in restaurant s
to see if it's x
so this operation is actually quadratic time
it's comparing
all pairs of a reviewer an r and a reviewer an s
to see if they're the same
I think that's what's slow
which gives rise to the question
could we figure out
the number of users that reviewed both r and s
in just linear time
indeed we could
here's the trick
instead of just keeping a
list of reviewers for each restaurant
we'll keep a sordid list of reviewers
and then we'll write down a linear time procedure
that checks for the amount of overlap
between two sorted lists
given two sorted lists with no repeats
we want to return the number of elements that appear
in both lists
let's start with an example
if I have this sorted list and that sorted list
the way we'll find
all of the elements they have in common
is to pass through both of them together
starting at the beginning of each
if one of these elements is smaller than the other
we know it doesn't appear in the other one
because it's smaller than this
and this is smaller than everything here
so one must not appear anywhere in this list
therefore I can advance
in the second list because one is smaller than three
three and three are the same
so I found an element that appears in both
and I can advance both of these positions
four is smaller than five
so it's also smaller than seven and eight
meaning it doesn't appear anywhere in the other list
so we can discard it and move on
likewise five doesn't appear in 67910
because it's smaller than six and everything after six
so we can move on
six is smaller than seven
and now we found another pair
so we remember that we found a second
element that appears in both
and we advance both
eight is smaller than nine
which means
eight doesn't appear anywhere in the first list
and now I've reached the end of the second list
which means I'm not gonna find
any more elements that appear in both
now that you have a picture
try to implement that procedure
I recommend that you pause and I'll go over the answer
in 321
we'll use I to index into list s and j to index
into list t
and we'll keep going
as long as I is less than the length of s
and j is less than the length of t
if I've found an element that appears in both
then I increment the count
and move forward in both snt
if the element I'm considering in list
s is smaller than the element in list t
then I know it doesn't appear in list t anywhere
and so I can move forward in s
otherwise I move forward in t
let's see if it speeds things up
it takes one and a half seconds
to list out all the cafes
and their similar restaurants
but what if we were place reviewed both with a new
implementation
here's the modular way to do it
we should define the overlap
between two sorted lists generically for any two lists
whether they're
lists of reviewers or lists of something else
and here's the code from the slide
and then reviewed both should call fast overlap
on the particular lists
that are needed in order to compute reviewer overlap
instead of one and a half seconds
now it takes only 0.7 seconds
so we've made it twice as fast
at least for that one run
and what about Thai food
is that faster than 0.7 seconds
yes it is now it only takes half a second
and that means that our program is responsive
enough to make it interactive
we can do that by saying forever
search for whatever the user types in
and print out the results
in order to indicate that it's time to type something
let's put a little prompt there
so I've started my restaurant search engine
and I can look for Thai food
or I can look for a cafe
or I can look for coffee
and learn all about berkeley's restaurants that way
sets are built into python
most anything that sufficiently generic
and applicable to many different situations
is built into python
so if you find yourself implementing a function
that computes the size of the intersection
of two sets well probably that's built in
sets in python are just another container type
like a dictionary or a list or a tuple
set literals are enclosed in braces
but a set can't contain two of any element
no element of asset can be equal to
another element of asset
also sets are not ordered
python gives them some order when it displays them
or when you iterate through the elements
but you don't really have any control over that order
instead you put elements in a set
and then when you iterate through that set
you get any old order that python decides
so if I build a set one two three four and four
and I look at what's in that set
there will only be
four unique elements
rather than the five elements I tried to put in there
and they'll come in some arbitrary order
the main use of a set is to check whether some
element is in the set
and this is a constant time operation
checking whether some element is in a list is a
linear time operation in the length of the list
but
checking whether some things in a set is constant time
regardless of how many elements are in the set
you can figure out how many elements there are
using len and you can take the union of two sets
or the intersection of two sets
so to figure out how many elements
two sets have in common
you could take the len of the intersection
of one set and another set
union and intersection do not change the set
there are other methods for updating the set
but union in intersection create new sets
and leave the old sets alone
so s has not been mutated anywhere here
if you want to learn about set mutation
you can read about it in the python docks