61a lecture 17 q a
okay so i i think the question is about
the
the relationship between yield from and
how that's essentially unpacking a for
loop
yeah the yield from is just a
convenience
there's no real reason why it's in the
language but it is
um it takes two two lines and turns them
into one
so uh going back to the example from
lecture
which was trying to yield all the
prefixes of some string
s if s meaning
f s is not the empty string um
it said yield from
prefixes of
everything in s up to the last letter
and then yield s itself because s
is a prefix of s depending on how you
define prefix but that's a fine way to
think about him
um and then we need to call this on
something
like uh i don't know dogs so that should
get dog and doo
and d notice that this result
is not a list if we'd want to do
something with it we'd have to
pass this in or call next on it or
something like that
i believe the doc test just called list
on it which is basically get all the
contents
and we got all this stuff yield from can
always be replaced with a for statement
that says the following
for some new variable
in the thing that we're yielding from
yield x so that's what yield from does
is it goes through all the elements
of some iterable and yields each of them
so it's just a syntactic shortcut that's
all it's essentially saying look this is
a
this is what you will find often not
just in python but in a lot of
programming languages that
things that are routinely coded by hand
are eventually incorporated into the
language with a little bit of a shortcut
it's
it's abstracting out some complexity
here
um yeah exactly once you know what it
means it's a little bit easier to read
before you know what it means and it's
hard to read right and
uh there's a question in the chat do we
always need a yield statement after a
yield from
and the answer is no we could have just
commented out that yield and it just
wouldn't have returned
the list as part of the prefix i mean
that would have been incorrect
in terms of the functionality of
prefixes but you can just have
i mean essentially a yield from is a
whole bunch of yields
and so in this example if we had
commented out yield s it would have
it would have worked fine it was just
given the wrong answer
yeah good question the question is for
the correct
implementation here what is prefixes
s of all of s without the last letter
this is an iterator over all of the
prefixes
of this so if this were dogs
this would be dog and prefixes of dog
would be all three d-d-o and d-o-g
so um
yeah it's not just like the first prefix
it's all of them
and uh that's why what we're doing is
we're yielding the d
the d o the dog and finally we're
dealing yielding the dogs
hey john there's a question in the chat
sorry to interrupt and
why when you read we get comments dot
yield ass and when you ran it it
returned an empty list
a great question so the question was if
we comment this out
what's the behavior and we showed you
right here
it ends up yielding nothing why is that
well we've written something that
just yields the prefixes
for the like smaller version
so if this is dogs we're yielding
whatever we get by calling prefixes on
dog
which in turn would yield whatever we
get for calling prefixes on do which
would return whatever we get for calling
prefixes on d
which would return nothing we've reached
oh
sorry which would return the result of
calling prefixes on the empty string and
that would
yield nothing so the base case here is
like if there's no letters then
there's no yield therefore we're not
producing anything
and since we don't produce anything in
the base case and all this ever says
is yield whatever the next recursive
call would yield
we end up not yielding anything at all
so in general if you like ever have a
function where your yield
from an empty list that's not going to
yield anything at all
yeah good question so if an iterator is
not a list what is it
um there are lots of different kinds of
uh iterators so
you know it more by its behavior than
it's
like what it's constituted of an
iterator is something that you can call
next on and get more elements
in the case of a list the iterator for a
list
is more than just a list it's kind of a
reference to the list along with
a position in that list that tells you
where you are
so that if you call the next thing the
iterator advances
meaning that if you called next again
you'd get something else than you did
the first time
so in that sense it's it has different
behavior than a list
because it's both a list and like a
marker for where you are
but list iterators are not the only kind
of iterators
you could have an iterator through the
labels in a tree you could have an
iterator through the prefixes in a
string
you could have an iterator kind of
through anything and it's just
a description of something that lets you
go through multiple elements
in some order by calling next on the
iterator and getting the next value
and you can do that over and over again
so it's quite an abstract thing as
opposed to
feeling quite as concrete as for example
a list
well the question about when should you
use the built-in python
python functions is an interesting one i
imagine if you ask different people
you'll get different answers so i'm
going to answer and we'll see
what uh john has to say so my view is
languages are not static
and they change and so this
functionality comes in and out so for
example if i want to write some python
code and put it on my website
and i happen to be using the latest
greatest version of python and i
grab some function that just got
introduced i don't know if somebody
using an earlier version of python will
be able to run my code
and that's not great i don't i don't
like that i like my code to be
standalone and not rely on
somebody having just upgraded so now you
could say look this requires python
three point whatever and
that's the way it is so i i prefer to
write code on my own
but there are limits to that i'm not
gonna go re-implement some
gnarly like if i want to use an iterator
i wouldn't implement that myself
um but i like to implement my own code
in part to make it compatible and also
because
i just like to know what my code is
doing i always get a little worried when
we use code that's all canned up and
you know we don't really understand it
so i i like to do things
i i tend to do things more um
on my own but if you are doing rapid
prototyping and you just want to get
something built
sure using all the built-in functions is
great it saves you from writing a lot of
code and doing a lot of debugging
yeah i think that's a great answer i
think everyone who's building software
has come to a point
that they've written a ton of code and
then realized oh this is just like a
special case of some general thing
that's built in i've basically just like
rewritten all the mechanics of a
dictionary or something like that
when in fact i could have just like used
the one that's built in
and it would have been one line and
that's okay
um happens to all of us and you know is
the version that you wrote better or the
built-in one better
uh it depends it depends on how it's
going to be used
uh like connie said especially if
something's just recently been
introduced then it's probably worth
avoiding it for a while if you want to
be
kind of compatible with everybody else
but using the built-in
functionality means that your program
might get better
without you having to do anything at all
like if you're implementing your own
system for time zones
this is fine except that like you know
what if some
island somewhere changes their time zone
this happened in the 90s
the christmas island decided to change
its time zone like you have to go in and
update that
whereas if you use the like built-in
system for handling time
zones then it would just get fixed for
you in the next version of python so i
think there are
generally advantages to using the
built-in stuff
or relying on open source libraries
whether it's part of the language or
it's like part of some community
development
rather than just like redoing everything
yourself
for the long term but like if you're
just getting something running like it's
totally fine to just rewrite stuff
yourself
and ignore yield from and nothing bad
happens
i'm going to go back and quickly answer
your other question that i
i know you know the answer but just um
for
posterity's sake the question was what
happens if you invert the order of yield
s versus yield from s like what's the
difference we could just quickly look at
that
and see that if the yield s comes
afterwards that means
s which was originally dogs is the last
thing in the list
if instead we had yielded that first and
then yielded all the prefixes
then we'd see everything in the opposite
order so
really you know python is going to go
through and do these things in the order
that you write them
and that will have an impact on exactly
what happens
one more thing i wanted to say about
this example is that what if we didn't
know about yield
like what if we were just in the
business of building lists
could we still get this behavior and the
answer is yes it would look something
like this we start with
a list we go through and instead of
yielding
we would append to that list
and then for every x in the list of
prefixes
i think we would append that x
and then when we were all done we would
return that result
and in fact in the base case we'd want
to return an empty list
so in either case i think we want to
return the result
and here we get something that you know
kind of does the same thing and if we
inverted the order
then we'd get it in the other direction
going from d to dogs instead of from
dogs to d
um and uh a lot of code looks like this
and kind of avoids this notion of
yielding in general
and that's fine um there are sometimes
efficiency benefits to yielding
there are sometimes some like
interesting concurrency benefits to
yielding
so it is something that does get used
more and more as people
advance in their like sophistication of
programming
but it's not like you really need it in
order to get stuff done in the first
place you could just explicitly
build the list instead of yielding it
piece by piece
okay so the question was in the
countdown example why is it the case
that you have to yield from
count down k minus one and this was if k
is greater than zero
and then we yielded k how come we
couldn't just yield
countdown k minus one well let's just
try both ways to see what we get
and then i think we'll understand um if
i list
out the contents of the iterator that i
get from counting down from five
i'll get one two three four five oh i
think i was supposed to count
down okay um
if instead i yield this what i'm
yielding is an
iterator rather than a number so what
i'm gonna get in the contents of my list
is not a bunch of numbers but instead
one number the five that i yielded and
this generator object
and what's this generator object well
you know like if i
get this result and i get result one
here's this generator object this is
something i can get the next thing
from and so i can get that four it's
like buried in there somewhere
it just took an awful lot more work to
get it
than in the other version where i just
ended up with a bunch of numbers
so essentially the from is doing the is
unpacking that
list that is that is now sort of stored
up in the generator
because what is yield from it's just a
for loop that iterates through the
result
yeah and if you don't iterate through it
all you do is you have that sort of core
generator but the result as john just
said is still there
it's just sort of that lazy evaluation
that you have to now unpack it
yeah good question so the questions
about this example and why is it the
case that when you get the length of
uh the result of listing out the
contents of an iterator
twice you get a different thing each
time first time you got three things
next time you got zero things
this isn't something having to do with
len this is having to do
with how list interacts with an iterator
when you call list on an iterator you
end up
building a list of all the contents of
that iterator
but the iterator is used up as a side
effect
of calling list on it so
if i have
an iterator over these values
um i can get one thing out of it
but then if i get another thing i get a
different thing
list is kind of like calling next over
and over again and putting all the
results in a list
so as soon as you call list on t you're
going to get everything that's left over
in the iterator
that hasn't been used up or returned
already so we've already seen the one
we've seen the two
therefore calling list on t will just
show us the three
and now t is used up i can't get the
next thing in t because we're already at
the end
and so if i try to list everything
that's left and t i'll get an empty list
so your version was start with this
get all the contents of that which is a
list containing one two and three
if i do this i'm changing t
this is uh every time you get elements
from an iterator
you're changing that iterator which
means you can't really use it again
so if you get the length of this you get
three you get the length of this you get
zero
so think of these iterators as one use
disposable operators
once you've gone through the list either
next next next x next
or the list of it is you're essentially
enumerating the list
it's gone right so by the way you could
have implemented this yourself
you could have written a function that
every time you access an element
the next element you delete that element
from the list that's essentially what's
going on here
yeah and so once you it's a funny thing
about iterators by the way is that once
you look at the list
it's it's sort of like uh what is it
it's like snapchat right the image comes
in
you look at it and then it vanishes it's
gone that is beautiful
yeah god you got to be impressed by
somebody my age making a snapchat
reference that's that's i think you know
you have a little credit for that
perfect snapchat analogy
great question yes this is a form of
mutation so this is why we teach
iterators right after we talk about
mutable values
is that at all iterators are
mutable they always change whenever you
do anything with them
meaning we call next on them so the
question is is there like
real applications of yield as opposed to
just returning
uh i see it a lot um
it often appears in cases where your
program is interacting with something
else
so there are lots of cases where you
want to return a list of things
right instead of just returning a single
value
but sometimes that list of things that
you want to do something with
isn't all there at the same time
so classic examples are you're like
reading
contents from the web and you want to
start
doing stuff with each element of
the you know like each page in a website
you want to be printing out it's like a
title or something like that
you'd write a function that gets all the
pages
in a website and uh returns them so that
some other function can
print out their title well it takes time
to get all the elements
of all the pages in a website because
there's like network traffic and you
might have to discover where they are
and so that's a classic case where you
would be
yielding each page as it becomes
available
and that means that whatever is printing
out the title can start printing stuff
right away as soon as the page is
available
instead of having to build a list of all
the pages in some website which might be
huge before you ever kind of start work
on anything else
so um yeah there are other cases in
which there's this kind of like pipeline
of information flow
where stuff sort of is becoming
available incrementally and you want to
yield it as soon as it's available
that's where it's used a lot i think
that's exactly right i was thinking of
the example you can tell the difference
in john and my
research john does natural language
processing so he talks about text
i do images in video so my example is
we take a video and we have to
decompress the video to do an analysis
of it
decompression of video is very very slow
um but i want to start processing as
soon as i get the first few frames
so as i'm decompressing the video i'm
shoving frames out the other end
and then i have an algorithm that's
doing some analysis and it's shoving it
out so when
i think it's exactly right is when you
have these different pieces
in a data flow but the processing is not
exactly the same so maybe you have some
slow steps some fast apps
and i don't want some i don't want to
sit here waiting for this really slow
process because
i can start working as soon as i get the
data and so that with return you
couldn't do that
right return says i'm going to hand you
back all this data
when i'm done the yield can do it
incrementally
the next question was is a generator
always an iterator but an iterator is
not always a generator
iterators are not always generators
there's lots of different kind of
iterators
and generator is just a particular type
of iterator
and what makes it a generator is that it
came from a function that yields
as opposed to being from a list or
something like that
so iterators describe anything that you
can iterate over
whether it's the elements of a list or
the yielded values from a
generator function or anything else
whereas
generators are or more specific but the
way you use a generator is the same as
how you use an iterator
it's just talking about where it came
from the next question
was about the summer 2020 midterm
question two uh okay so this says
uh schedule takes a galaxy which is a
string
and then there's some number that you
want to sum to and some max digit that
you're allowed to use
and so a galaxy looks like something
that's a bunch of digits maybe with some
question marks
for example here's some digits and some
and then there's a completion of a
galaxy which is a string full of just
digits
where we've replaced each question mark
with a digit and
uh the total sum of the whole thing is
supposed to be
this value sum2 so here's a legal way of
doing it which is
that you could fill in this question
mark with 0 well this has to stay at 2.
this question mark was 0. this question
mark was 0. this has to say 1. this has
to stay a 1 and this could be anything
we want
but all the digits including the ones
that are provided and the ones that we
added
have to sum up to five so here's all the
ways of doing it
okay um
let's take a look it seems like we'll do
some recruiting
uh we have a helper which has
a galaxy
um the fact that there's a galaxy here
in a galaxy here means that maybe we'll
be changing this along the way like
filling in digits for example
here we have a sum so far which could
tell us whether we've
reached the sum that we're trying to
eventually achieve
and the index i guess means that we're
going to walk through here
element by element
okay so we'll call
schedule helper
on the original galaxy
the sum so far i think is zero we
haven't done anything yet and we'll
start at the beginning
and we'll see what we do if it's the
case
that we're done then we're going to
return a list containing galaxy okay
that's good
but this means that the galaxy that gets
passed in here has to have all the
question marks filled in
if we're going to be returning it so we
know we're going to be kind of filling
in things as we go
if it's the case that maybe we've
reached a sum that's too big
then then we have a problem so i think
there's probably some base case like
some so far is greater than sum two then
we
have a problem there might be some other
base cases that we have to think about
as well
and i'm not sure what's going on here
yet we'll think about that later
here's the kind of main recursive loop
which is that we build a list
we go through every x in
something probably the digits
from zero to nine or something like that
uh and we fill in a question mark
that seems like what modified galaxy is
going to be all about
um so
i kind of feel like this is going to be
the case where there's no question mark
and this is going to be the case where
there is a question mark and then you
have to like try all the possibilities
so it might be something like if
galaxy at
index does not equal
a question mark then i think we have to
just use that first
value so we'll call schedule helper
on exactly the same galaxy we had before
the sum is going to change we have the
old sum
plus uh whatever the
first element of galaxy is
or the current element of galaxy is
and uh what else let's advance the index
so we keep moving
what if there's a question mark so here
this
is in fact i'm just going to rewrite it
lf galaxy index
equals question mark and i think this
will do the same thing right
uh oh wrong way
we're gonna find all the different ways
of doing this
um go through the digits
zero one two three four five six seven
eight nine
we're gonna build a new string
which is galaxy up to but not including
the index
plus a stringed version of x
plus the rest of galaxy after the index
that might work so let's just like look
at what this does
for an example before we go on would be
nice to know that it works
so if i have something like 2 3 question
mark
5 6 and i have an x which equals 4
is it the case that if index equals 2
and galaxy equals this thing
that i get what i want
when i evaluate this expression
it does so we basically just replace the
question mark with a 4
there in this long line
so what do we do well we have to get
some more answers in there
uh i'm gonna recursively call schedule
helper
on this new modified galaxy
and a new sum so far
because now we've got an x in there and
we're moving forward
and we do this for all the index like
why is it the case that i called
schedule helper here
this is where i'm going to fill in all
the other question marks that are later
on
and make sure that i got the sum right
all right now i think we need to get
this base case of when we have found
a fully complete galaxy so this would be
like if
index equals the len of galaxy then
we've gotten to the end and
if galaxies
well okay how do we do this let's make
sure we got the right sum
sum so far equals
sum two that might do the trick then
maybe we're done
nope
uh index out of or
index greater than equal to the length
of the galaxy so if you kind of like get
to the end and you don't have a sum
that's big enough then i guess you need
to stop
what on earth
sorry zoom is in the way i can't even
see what broke
oh i don't think you're supposed to use
oh parts of the size
max digit yeah you can't always go to
10.
you should probably read the question
first okay now it works
so what got us here well we kind of kept
track of what
information we needed to maintain along
the way and there were like some pretty
good clues in the question of what to do
based on the name some two and some so
far
and it took a minute to kind of think
through the base cases
and i think we could have figured this
out without running the code just by
kind of like considering different cases
uh reading the question carefully but
since we had it all set up we just ran
the doc test instead to
get a clue about whether we had done it
right or not
during the q a i said we could do this
with yield
instead of building a list but we never
actually did that so
um let's do it we're going to return a
list
of the results of everything that
scheduler helper
yields and then we can worry about
yielding so here
we would yield just galaxy that's
equivalent to returning a list of galaxy
here we just wouldn't do anything
one way to stop a function is to write
return but it would also be fine just to
kind of
do nothing here just don't yield
anything
and what about here well schedule helper
is going to
yield a whole bunch of different values
so this would have to be replaced with
the yield from
and here we could get around building up
a list
and just say that every time we call
schedule helper
will yield from that
so what happens when we run this we get
the same result
great question so if you have a for
statement
or for loop is that the same as
creating an iterator and then calling
next on it repeatedly
yes the behavior is identical
i think there are cases in which python
tries to like
find a faster way to do it like if you
iterate over a range maybe it's doing
something fancy underneath i don't know
but from your programmer's perspective
the behavior is identical to
create an iterator out of this thing
that you're running the for loop over
and then call next repeatedly binding
the name
x to the next value each time
yeah good question is there any way to
reset an iterator once you've gone
through the elements or do you just have
to make a new one and the answer is you
just have to make a new one
um there are
um the reason for this
is that it might be that you're trying
to write a program where you're kind of
forgetting the past
because maybe the stuff that you've
iterated over is so big it's like whole
video files
that you can't store them all in memory
at once so this idea of like resetting
would require you to remember everything
you had seen before
and that's exactly what you might be
trying to avoid an
iterator so it's up to you to write your
own program
about uh remembering where you were i
think there might be some like built-in
stuff
in the python standard library to to
remember
an iterator and kind of cycle through it
but i don't know exactly what it looks
like
the next question was is there a
relationship between yield from
and recursive functions like to yield
from always have to be recursive
i don't i don't think of it as recursive
i think it was
iterative because you're just unpacking
a for loop john
yeah that's right so i don't think yield
from has to be recursive or anything
like that you know the simplest
possible yield from would be like yield
from all the elements of this list and
there's no recursion there
and uh it works just fine so you have to
start with a list
one two three but then if you call f on
that
and you get that result this is a
generator object
where you'll get the one the two and
then the three
it happens to be that you can uh
can mix together recursion and yielding
if the goal of your recursion is to
build up a sequence of things
which is not totally unusual you know
our first examples of
recursion where like count the number of
ways
that you could partition up a number
using parts up to size m
and then we just did a homework problem
which was
actually list out all the ways and so
you know it's the same basic recursive
structure in both cases
except for counting you just return a
number whereas
if you're listing out all the
possibilities then you have to either
return a list or you have to
yield yeah good question so can yield be
used within a list comprehension
or inside of another larger expression
the answer is no and
this is also true of return and
assignment statements and def statements
there's a lot of things that can't be
embedded inside of a larger expression
because they're not expressions
themselves they're statements and so
they have to kind of just like show up
on their own
line so you never have like
return x for x in
some list because return x is not the
kind of thing that you can embed
inside of a larger expression and the
same is true with yield you can't have
that there either
yeah good question so is there is there
a way to kind of do two things
here right in a list comprehension
and the answer is you only get space to
put one
expression but that expression
could be a compound expression so
um you know one expression is the number
two
but another expression is the list one
um because this whole thing
the list one two is actually just one
expression that's got parts within it
you could try to get each part to do
something
it is legal in python to say first i
want to get the result of printing one
and then i want to get the result of
printing two
and use that to fill in this blank and
now
i've kind of like done two different
things
but i've done it by calling a function
which is something you're allowed to
embed
inside a larger expression as opposed to
writing down a statement like print or
yield or sorry like a return or yield or
def
where you're not allowed to embed that
inside something larger
yeah okay so the question is how would
it be that like new stuff
appears in an iterator as you're reading
from it
um this was an example from earlier in
the q a
and what might it look like if you have
something that's like
read pages from a website
well every website has like a root page
so maybe we should call this root it
would be something like i don't know
google.com or how about the new york
times
uh you would have to have some function
that
reads that right and
so
you'd like call that on the root
and get this page
and you'd want to yield this page but
and that means that like whoever called
read pages can immediately start acting
on this
right after this is done but then i
think you'd want to go through
for get all the links
in this page
and you'd want to yield
from the result of reading all the pages
from
that other page that you got
so how is it that we're like
getting new stuff along the way well
you're kind of not
in some sense all of the data that you
will ever
process is known is defined
when you call read pages the first time
it's
whatever's at www.newyorktimes.com and
everything
that it links to but
actually writing out that list of
everything linked to from the new york
times
will take a really long time and so
um there's a lot of this result that we
haven't discovered
we immediately kind of yield the front
page and that means that something could
print the title right away
as soon as this line is executed but
um we haven't really found all the other
pages yet
so they're there but our program doesn't
know about them
okay that makes sense cool all right
thanks folks
it's been a pleasure talk to you soon