61a lecture 29 q a
hey john while we wait for somebody it's
been a while since i've written
uh a compiling interpreter but i
remember we used to use these um
it was lex and yak and flex and bison
the sort of you
where you can specify the grammar and
then it would build it for you is that
still
sort of popular in use yeah so we're
doing a very unusual thing in today's
lecture which is to describe
how you would write a parser
kind of from scratch yeah and um
right so so these other tools
aren't kind of procedural instead you
just describe the grammar
and then there's a generator that builds
the parser for you
now if you actually looked at that
parser it would look kind of like the
code that
that we looked at today so um so that's
kind of what how a parser works but
do people actually sit there and write
parsers no especially for something as
complicated
as python um you just wouldn't do it
because
there's too much like chance for error
right right so i think there's
there's like there's another level of
abstraction there's like you know it's
sort of cool like there's this
code that where you can have this higher
level description of your language that
then writes the parser that then
compiles or interprets the code
yeah i mean basically you know the field
of programming languages attract a lot
of really good programmers you can
imagine why so
there's really nice tools for that yeah
hey can you tell me what so the last
tools that i use were flex and bison has
that
is that still the popular ones are
things that moved on since then
i don't know it's a good question i
think they're still around
but um but there might be new ones i i
don't think that the
ideas have changed too much yeah i think
that's my understanding too but it's
been a little while
okay so the question was in scheme read
there's a pop and shouldn't that pop
remove something from the end rather
than the beginning
well maybe pop was a bad name for it
but what this source object is is not
actually a python list
but instead it's this um
where is it it's this thing called a
buffer oh i guess it's in a different
file
and this buffer has a notion of pop
that doesn't remove things from the end
it removes them from the beginning
so maybe we should have cop told called
it something else but that's the answer
to the question
why is it the case that popping is
removing stuff from the beginning of the
line
it's because what you're removing from
is not a list but a buffer which
basically tells you about the future
and when you pop something from it you
get the first thing
and sondra that the term pop and push is
generally referred to
stacks and cues and pop i always think
of pop is
what's at the very top of something but
it i think it is overloaded depending on
what the underlying data structure is
right we could definitely blame python
here which has a kind of unconventional
notion of popping being from the end but
that's okay it's a question of where you
define the fro
like you the end doesn't have to be that
and anyway it doesn't matter but yes
it's from the front in this particular
case so we didn't really go over this in
a lecture but it is definitely worth
looking at this class buffer the
implementation doesn't matter much but
its behavior does
basically you get this um iterator over
a bunch of symbols like open parentheses
and pluses
and numbers and close parentheses and
stuff like that
and then the goal here is to give you
the next thing
and remove it or just peek at the next
thing but not remove it yet
and there's a way to print it out which
is used in some error messages
yeah great question so the question is
in scheme read
you hit a or for parsing in general
you hit a base case when you've reached
a symbol or a number
something that's not a combination and
not a composition of stuff but just like
one thing
what happens when you reach that base
case how does it kind of work its way to
the next open parenthesis
so let's look at an example i'll try to
answer the question if you have
something like
plus
1 minus 2 3 whatever
you're trying to figure out what this
thing is right now it's just
a bunch of symbols i'm going to separate
them by spaces so that you can see them
all
so now we have one two three four five
six seven eight
nine things to worry about the original
call
will be to effectively the whole thing
and
it begins with an open parenthesis so we
make a recursive call
on uh the rest
so um
with an original call to scheme read
we've begun another call
which by the way
um if you look at the structure of this
thing it doesn't actually call scheme
read it calls
read tail which basically just calls
scheme read a bunch of times until it
finds the matching closing parenthesis
so that's going to be the story is that
once you see an open parenthesis you
keep reading the next thing
until you find a matching closing
parenthesis
if when you read the next thing it's a
base case well that was in another
recursive call
you made a bit you reached a base case
you return like oh this is just a plus
symbol but where do you return to
you return to the process where you were
going to
read all this stuff until you found the
next closing parenthesis
so that's kind of the story is like when
you hit the base case you return
but where you're returning to is an
ongoing reading
of some long expression that you know
started with an open parenthesis because
you read it at the beginning
and you're just kind of going to keep
reading stuff until you find a closing
parenthesis
uh how do we peek at the next item in an
iterator without removing it
oh great question the answer is you
can't which is why we have this buffer
class that we provided so we can just
take a look at it really quickly
it kind of turns stuff into lists as you
go
so you get a bunch of iterators coming
in
but what it does is it just stores
everything that it's seen
in this thing called lines and when it
needs to see something new
it will go ahead and get more stuff from
the source iterators
but um
but not necessarily advanced so you kind
of like keep track of the whole list of
things that you've seen
and where you are and that's the story
is like if
if you have a data structure that allows
you to peek at something without popping
it off then you can do it but a standard
iterator wouldn't be able to do it for
you
you could read this whole implementation
if you want it's like a little bit long
and the reason it's a little bit long is
so that it can print out
the whole code and where you were in the
code which is helpful for error messages
john how is this different than a stack
or a queue
um well in this case we're never
really adding stuff like we're removing
stuff from the beginning and we're
adding stuff to the end
so it's a lot like a cube yeah um
except for like it's a cue that
remembers what you've removed
just in case you need to print it out
okay so and i don't think that the
built-in python
queue i think it's the deck class allows
you to do that yeah there's no memory
that's right okay all right so it's that
little memory that it wants you to have
that's the
and the only reason you'd have that is
just so you can like print out
you know uh yeah we were here yeah
gotcha
okay yeah good question so here we are
we're in calcuval
um if it's a pair meaning
we're now evaluating something that
begins with an open parenthesis
then what does this line mean x second
map calcul well to figure that out we
got to know what an
x is it turns out it's a pair which we
figured out here
so let's go take a quick look at what a
pair is and
what its map method does
skiing reader
here's the pair it's got a first and a
second
it's a linked list or like a scheme
linked list um so the first can be
anything
but the second should be another
instance of pair
or the or nil
to represent the end um
uh i guess we didn't talk too much about
this kind of thing but this just lets
you get like the length of a list or
use square brackets um
did we talk about this at all i don't
think i i think maybe we left that out
this semester but it's not that
important
um but what is important is there's a
regular old method called map
and what it does is it takes in a
function it calls that function on every
element of the list that this pair
represents
and then returns a new list which is
really a pair
instance so it's a linked list kind of
structure with all the results of
calling this function
so and we can read this pretty
straightforward like you
call fun on the first element if there's
a second element
um then you
[Music]
recursively call map on the second
element
and you build a new list that's got this
new first element in it
this doesn't say expo.map calcaval
instead it says
expert.second.map.calcoval
i think it's worth looking at an express
an example so this example here which
looks a little bit funny
is really add to to the result of
multiplying four
and six
this thing if we put it into
you drop the paren john reader
oh my goodness if we put this into the
reader we can see what it looks like
from python's point of view it's a pair
that starts with a plus
and then a 2 etc
if i get the dot second of this object
it's all this thing which really only
has two elements it's got the number two
and it's got this sub expression times
four six
so the point of mapping calcaval over
this is that we are converting the
2 to a 2 and we're converting the times
6 into its value
and then it's time to add
that's what calc applied this so the
point of this is it's the recursive call
that takes all the sub expressions and
finds their values
i probably could have just said that one
sentence and it would have been more
clear
always more clear it's always the last
sentence but you still have to get there
john
yeah good question so the question is
should you regularly use
map to process to make recursive calls
if your input is a list and i think
that's not always the case
it really depends on what you're trying
to achieve so you've written some
function
let's say s is an instance of
a pair like it's a scheme list
whether you use map or not really
depends on whether you're making
recursive calls
on the elements of s in which case map
is appropriate
or if you're making a recursive call on
the rest of s in which case map won't do
that for you
you just have to explicitly call f on
s.second
um so yeah i think that
eval is unusual and that it's not linked
list processing
where you're just like doing something
the first element and you're doing a
recursive call to the rest of the list
instead what it's doing is making its
recursive call on each element of the
list
and that's why we used matt the next
question was
what is the main decorator
yeah so this main decorator is
um something that's specific to 61a
and it just says if you run the file
this is the function that should be
called
so if i run the whole skel.pi
file it's not going to call as scheme
list instead it's going to call
redevelop print loop
and uh do whatever's here
um the other way that this would work is
just leave off the definition of read
about print and just while would be the
body of the code and then it would
run it this is a cleaner way to do it
having everything in a function
yeah exactly so we'd get the same result
if we just did
that um the only issue with this
is that if you import this file from
another file then this would run which
you don't always want
um there's a there's kind of an ugly
convention in
python which is that um most
times when you see like commercial
python code you'll see them right
that
which i felt like we'd spend so much
time trying to explain what this was
that uh it would ruin the course so
that's why we introduced the main
decorator i got a bit of an exaggeration
john
i also i find that syntax hideous so i'm
glad you you put in a nice uh
clean version of it
and by the way it's just defined in this
ucb
file which was written long ago when i
started teaching this course
and um it's got this kind of same
weird notion of name equals main kind of
buried in there so that's all it does
the next question was
wouldn't a parser for python need to
track
indentation instead of just ignoring
white space
yeah that's right an indentation is part
of the grammar
of python meaning that the parser needs
to
not just ignore all of the spacing and
indentation like we're doing for scheme
but it has to track it
i mean that's why most languages have a
notion of a begin and an
end right so i guess python has the
notion of a begin
that's the colon but the end is
implicit in the indentation um i've ever
never liked that i i prefer to have like
a an explicit open close
begin and curly bracket curly bracket um
i think it makes the code a little bit
easier to read but yes in this regard
you have to keep track of it
otherwise you don't know when the body
of anything ends
yeah i say thank you yeah same i think
like it's better to have something to
keep track of
beginning and just to make it clear john
do you know if there's a reason for that
i mean it's a little bit of an unusual
convention in python
uh i agree it's unusual uh i think there
was some story i read once about how
they decided this
and i believe it involved having
someone's
spouse read a piece of code when they
weren't programmers or something like
that they're like oh yeah this makes
sense to me or whatever but uh i
i don't know how true that really is but
yeah well let's let's let's make it true
i like stories like that
um well if you know if you like explicit
punctuation telling you where things end
and i'm sure you'll love scheme because
it's got lots of closing prints
oh man but that's a whole nother world
to hurt
[Laughter]
the next question was what programming
languages are typically used to write an
interpreter it is it's a great question
i think that
um for
depends on what your goal is if you're
building an interpreter that you know
thousands of people are going to use and
they're going to run big programs on it
and the primary concern is usually speed
and resource use
at the time that python's interpreter
was written
c was the obvious choice for writing a
program that would run fast what's kind
of fascinating is that now the fastest
implementation of python is not the one
that we all use but instead a separate
one called pi
pi which is a python interpreter written
in python and
it's quite a bit faster than the python
interpreter written in c
it has achieved this speed through some
very clever engineering where basically
like
the python code is not interpreted the
python code that runs the interpreter is
not interpreted but instead kind of
compiled and optimized in various ways
um you know like i said programming
language folks tend to be pretty clever
at programming
um so
[Music]
there's yeah there's basically that
story of
you know what's the right programming
language in order to
make this interpreter fast um
an interesting trend in the programming
language community
is that for any general purpose
programming language
oftentimes people will try to write an
interpreter for that language
as one of the first large programs
written in that language
why well it's kind of like a natural
target
and uh people you know the people
writing the interpreter
that they don't know they don't write
many other things except for
interpreters so so that's how it goes
so that means that interpreters have
been written in many different
programming languages
and um and you know they
different programming languages can be
surprisingly well suited for this
um i'm not sure there's like an obvious
best one
except that if i were to commit to one
it would probably be
something that's kind of an evolved
version of scheme called a racket
and there's this wonderful community of
programmers and developers
that that still contribute to this
language called racket
and they've set it up so that people can
create variants of the language
like really easily and there's all kinds
of tools to make sure that like your new
variant actually works correctly and
stuff like that
um and i think that's led to a fair
amount of productivity
they've got versions of the language
that are good for teaching they've got
good version of language that are good
for
you know like building websites and
stuff like that um so
yeah so occasionally there have been
some like standouts and i think c
was one because it was just fast and i
think
racket is a modern one because it
happens to work well
yeah i'm i'm surprised to hear that the
python interpreter
is faster than the c although i imagine
with the same clever engineering
you can make the c faster because i
don't it's hard to somebody's asking the
question is
is c still faster than python even with
pi pi
upgrade i can't imagine the python is
going to be faster than c
um no though there's an interesting
project called
cython which is a subset of python
so you can't do everything you can do in
python but you can do most of it
so the code more or less looks like
python code but it can be compiled
um i think the way they compile it is
that they
uh translate it into c yeah and then
they run a c compiler i believe that is
why it's called
cython yeah but that means that a lot of
times when people are trying to write
fast code
within like a python ecosystem where
they've written most of their
code in python already they just switch
to this language which is not actually c
it looks more like python but it can be
translated into c
and uh that's how they kind of run their
part that needs to write their part that
needs to run really fast
i see i see a follow-up question was
if you're going to write a python
interpreter in python don't you also
need a python interpreter written in
something else
yeah that's right so in order to get
this um
this uh python interpreter written in
python to work
they had to run the interpreter using
the c version of the interpreter that
already existed
and uh once they've done that then they
can run their own interpreter so
you get these very strange cycles but
your your intuition is exactly right
that you kind of have to have something
that already runs
in order to build something new right
yeah and john's right the the folks
who do programming languages for a
living are incredibly clever
yeah it sounds like it thank you um by
the way if you get a chance
take a pl course i i'm sure there's one
offered here yeah john
yeah it's numbered 164 and it's a good
course yeah i mean it's
it mean i don't know if it's the most
practical course but i i think thinking
about the nature of different languages
and
is really really cool and understanding
how these things really work is super
interesting just from a
sort of purely intellectual perspective
yeah okay thanks molokai uh michonne is
up next
sorry about amazon that's all good
um so we talked about like the languages
that you could use but is the structure
for for writing interpreters like the
same like is it still
this recursive structure or are there
other ways to do it as well
yeah good question this recursive
structure that i've shown you
is the simplest and probably the slowest
way to
interpret code most of the stuff that
actually happens in your computer these
days
doesn't just do this but instead
makes transformations to the original
program
along the way and this is actually how
python's interpreter
works is that it
takes a piece of code that might run
many times
and generates some like efficient
version of that and then runs that many
times which is like a step that we
haven't talked about in this course
because it doesn't change the answer
just makes it run faster
if if you want to go really deep into
this
there's the original textbook for this
course called the structure and
interpretation for computer programs
has a fifth chapter that was never
covered in 61a
even when uh
yeah even when the whole course was
scheme
um so the fourth chapter is about
interpreters and that's basically what
we're covering now
but the fifth chapter was about how you
get
a programming language to actually run
on a
chip using a limited instruction set
that doesn't have things like procedure
calls and stuff like that
and you know they did a very nice job of
laying out how you would get from
a high-level language to a low-level
language
and so you know people who are excited
about this idea of building programming
languages should all go read that
that chapter you can read the whole book
too you'll find many
things familiar from what you've learned
in 618
when did you switch over or when did we
switch over from teaching scheme in 61a
to python
uh we switched in 2011. wow that's late
um and yeah that was the first time i
taught the course
yeah i didn't just teach it but i kind
of redid it
and uh that was a lot of work
yeah yeah that that came pretty late
because most most of us had switched
over
a lot of people switched over to java
for a while before python came on the
scene but then once python came on the
scene it was clear that was the right
place to start
yeah berkeley was definitely a holdout
you know there are some i think there's
still folks who are a big fan
of scheme and i know that's reasonable
it's something um but i kind of like the
idea that the community around python is
so big that if you want to build some
like random thing in your
free time you can kind of google about
it and there's always some guide
uh that we we did see a big uptick in
kind of student independent projects and
hackathons and stuff like that right at
the same time so
you never know about cause and effect
but it does seem like they're probably
related
joey asked a good question which factors
do you consider when picking languages
for a coding project
well i'll tell you what i do i although
i work probably at a different scale
than john does
is so part of it depends you know am i
just trying to hack something together
to try something out
and if i'm doing that it's almost always
matlab or python because those are just
the ones i'm comfortable with and i can
code really really fast in
and they've got a lot of built-in
libraries so i don't have to
re-implement everything from scratch
so if i'm just you know passing around
on a research project it's always python
or matlab
and then if i'm if i think i'm probably
going to deploy something
on server or web-based probably you know
you want to stay away from things like
matlab because those are proprietary
and you can't really run those in the
software so then you start thinking
javascript
maybe python and job some combination of
python and javascript
then every once in a while we're doing
things where we really really need speed
we're doing things that are
computationally super intensive
and then you just bite the bullet and
you implement in c um
and well usually what i do is i
implement in python
make sure it's working debug everything
get it all working
and then translate it into c because
writing c code from scratch
is a little can be a little excruciating
because you have to do all the memory
management
and i find a little bit harder to debug
the code um so i guess it's a
combination of and
one more thing too is the scale at which
you're going to be writing so if you're
writing something really really big
you stay out of programs like matlabs
they weren't built python is
reasonably good for large scale uh and
then the last part of that
is every once in a while we do something
where we really have to be
cross-platform
so i know that this is gonna have to run
on linux mac and and um
and windows and then you do java i hate
it i don't like java
it's painful but if you really really
want cross-platform
i go to java
yeah i guess one way to summarize it is
you actually want to solve as few
problems as possible
right so you look for languages that
have already solved
many of the things that you'll encounter
if that's cross-platform or if that's
kind of
deployment or whatever yeah
that was that was a really nice
condensed
version of my answer
what do you mostly code in john
um we wrote a lot of python these days
yeah because the there's
the support for kind of machine learning
uh deep neural network stuff is just
better there than anywhere else
so okay uh delenia asked an interesting
question
what are your priorities when learning a
new language
you know here's the thing you're going
to discover pretty soon is learning a
new language is
for the most part pretty easy because
once you know the basics you know all
the languages i mean there's a few
exceptions like ml and prolog
and haskell that are a little quirky but
once you know
a handful of languages it's like a
couple of days
and then it's really you can write in
that language quickly it's a question of
how good is the code and how easy it is
but
a combination of stack overflow and just
your base knowledge so i
i haven't i think python is probably the
last new language i've learned
in recent memory i don't know that there
i think the combination of
javascript matlab python c and java
i don't know that i i guess uh r i
learned recently are
the statistical programming which took
like all of an afternoon frankly
i mean it gets pretty easy after a while
yeah i mean uh reading a book often
will leave you with very fleeting
knowledge you just gotta go build
something yeah you just gotta start
coding yeah that's exactly right
so uh if i really just want to learn the
language for the languages sake then i
usually just re-implement the hog
project because that's always uh
that always makes me happy but usually
when i'm trying to learn some language
it's because i'm trying to do some
particular thing
in advance that actually matters and i
just like learn what i need to know in
order to do that
yeah it's source equals buffer input
yeah so the question is what is this
line um
which calls this function which makes a
buffer out of the result of tokenizing
the lines of an input reader
the reason there's three parts to this
is that they all do slightly different
things that you need to compose together
this gets you the text
this breaks the text into tokens which
we talked about like individual numbers
and parentheses and stuff like that
and buffer gives you a way to walk
through them one by one
and remembers where you were just in
case you need to print out an error
message
so those are the three parts and the
part about reading
is i wish it were simpler but i think
it's unfortunately not
yeah if you look at the input reader
oh
it is simple oh yeah just the input
command
oh good because it's all built into
python yeah so python has this
this notion of input where if i call
input then if i type something