61a lecture number 36 q a
none of the questions were about the
lecture but we had some good questions
yeah good question so um questions about
how having is used having is really
designed to
filter out whole groups so
for example you know the
the second option here
select star from records group by
division having count star greater than
three
is going to uh give you all the rows
from records
where um there are at least
like you're gonna get one row per
division but only for the divisions
where there are at least records
three records or more than three records
that have that division
so that is like a well-formed thing
let's look at this other example you
suggested
which tries to filter within a group i
don't think this is going to do the
right thing
so still you'll get one row per division
it's going to evaluate this thing that
says salary equals max salary
what that's going to do is it's going to
compute the max salary for the group
it's going to find the salary
for a particular element within that
group
because when you perform a max
it tends to select the record
that has the max i'm guessing this will
always be true
and what you'll end up with is one row
per
division and this having clause won't
really do
anything at all so if what you want to
do is filter out
individual rows from records before you
perform a group you need to use aware
for that
yeah i mean anytime you're mixing an
aggregation
with a selection of a single record
it's really not something you can trust
um
and uh yeah i guess i'd have to look at
the example to tell you what's going on
in a particular implementation
but probably what it didn't do is just
filter out rows before doing the
grouping instead
what it did is it grouped and then it
kept some of the groups but i think in
this case it would probably keep all the
groups
okay yeah so the question is how do you
find the rows that
have the maximum value
in them actually this will in sqlite do
that
for kind of a quirky reason um it's not
that the salary equals max salary will
do the trick
it's that just computing max salary will
order the rows
within a group and then when you select
star
uh where you're really selecting a
particular row from a group it's going
to select the first one
and because you ever took a mac
somewhere it happens to be that that
first one will be the one with the max
salary so
um it's true that this will work not a
behavior we want to rely on
instead if what you want to do is figure
out what the max is for each group
and then select a corresponding row with
that max
i think that's a two-step operation you
want to create a table
with the max's so something like select
max salary
comma division from records group by
division
now you know um what these things are
called but you should
give that a name max's
and now you have a table that's one row
per division
and tells you what the max salary is in
that division
obviously this won't run because i don't
have a records table
loaded but then you do a second step
where you would select star
from the result of joining together
the records and the maxes
and here's the case where you'd make
sure that
you only want the records that have the
right division
so you uh
let's say we call this a and this
call this b now you're going to have one
row from the max table
one row from the records table you want
them to match
a dot division equals b dot division
and you're only interested in the rows
that have a maximum salary for that
division
so that would be the a dot salary equals
b dot salary
b salary here is representing the
maximum salary for the division
adot salary is the salary for that
record this would filter out all the
rows
where somebody is in the division but
doesn't have the highest salary within
that division
okay so now we've filtered out the rows
that we want
and we can perform a group
so doing it in two steps like this
obviously is longer than relying on this
ordering behavior
but i think it's more explicit about
what's going on the next question was
about
the fall 2019 final exam
question 6 c
all right let's get a sense of where we
are really quick just by reading through
a palindrome is a sequence that has the
same elements in normal and reverse
order
we've already implemented pow which
takes a positive integer n and returns a
positive integer with the digits of n
followed by the digits of n in reverse
order so we could like build a
palindrome out of some prefix
um we did contains which contains
non-negative integers a and b
um it returns whether all of the digits
of a also appear
in order among the digits of b okay that
might be useful
so uh 3 5 7
is in here somewhere because there's a 3
and there's the 5
and there's the 7 but 7 5 3 is not in
there because they're in the wrong order
all right and now we're going to
implement big
helper function for biggest palindrome
the biggest palindrome function takes a
non-negative integer n
and returns the largest pounder integer
within
with an even number of digits okay that
sounds important
that appears among the digits of n in
order
okay so largest palindrome integer means
uh
longer is larger but also like to break
ties we're gonna
have a kind of large first digit
um if there's no even length calendar
then we should return zero okay
you may call pal and contains
but we're not allowed to turn things
into strings or
lists or tuples or use square brackets
or anything like that so it sounds like
we got to just use
integer manipulation like dividing by 10
and stuff like that
biggest palindrome calls big on n
with zero as some starting value for k
and this is the helper function that is
going to track
something about what we've seen so far
and is also
taking digits from it if n
is 0 then the biggest palindrome within
it
is 0. here we have
choices there are two of them
so you can kind of look at the structure
of this expression and see
there's two options we're going to
recursively call big keeping k the same
or we're going to recursively call big
making k
bigger somehow um
all right if contains k
k remember contains the way it works is
that the numbers
that you're looking for come first
and then the numbers that
may contain k come next
um if contains k something
then we will uh
return something otherwise well it's not
clear what we'll do here but we'll have
to try to figure that out
and otherwise we return the max of
choices
here's what i think i know so far at
some point you're going to ask whether k
is contained in uh
n in order to
decide if it's the case that we've found
a
palindrome
so and and here it's kind of like do we
use the last digit or we don't is the
typical pattern that you see
when you're recursively searching for
digits that are inside one number and
not inside the other so i'm not totally
clear how to solve this but i think we
can start
making some progress um since
we're dealing with numbers and we can't
use strings or wrappers it's more common
that we'll peel off
elements from the end so i think the way
this would go
is we would say okay i'm gonna include
the four
i'm gonna skip the three i'm gonna
include the five
now i've kind of built this thing up
which has a five and a four
at the end and what's left over in n
is three four two five let's say
that as i've gone through and decided to
keep the four and the five
i now know that i need to build a
palindrome
that has a four and a five in it so when
i get to this point
i realize oh there's an option which is
that i could
uh
have the palindrome 4554 as one of the
palindromes in here
but only if after i've removed that and
n is just three four two five if it's
the case that
k is contained within these digits where
k
has to be the numbers that i've seen so
far backwards
okay so if it's the case that k is
in n where k is the digits that i've
decided to keep so far
in reverse order then i think we have a
new choice
which is that um
we could
have the palindrome i think it's called
pal
made up of k
so if k was 45 then we'd build 4554
and that would be something that is
contained within
n and how do i know that well i've found
the four and the five and the suffix
already
and i've checked to see that the four
and five appear in the prefix
and so i know the whole thing is there
now how do we write down the logic of
discard the number that's at the end of
n
or keep it i think it would look
something like
if i just want to keep k the same that
means i'm not really including any more
digits
that means that i'm going to make a
recursive call ignoring
the last digit of it
otherwise i will make a recursive call
with the last digit of n being peeled
off but in this case it will be captured
as part of k and what would that look
like that would look like keeping k
as it is and then adding in the last
digit of it so if we look at how this
might go
originally n would be this whole thing k
would be zero
one of the recursive calls we would make
would have n
be everything except for the four
and k would be four that sounds pretty
good
and the recursive call from there using
this case would be that we ignore the
three so now
k is four but n is three four two five
five
a recursive call from there using the
second case would set
uh k well n would
obviously go down to three four two five
but k
would be set to whatever it was before
four times ten is forty
plus 5 is 45
then we could hit this case which says
if 45
is in here which it is then we have an
option
of 4554 as one of the palindromes within
yeah great question so how do you
approach this problem what are the steps
um one is to recognize that there's a
tree recursion problem
you could do that from the syntax
because there's two calls to big
or you could do that from the kind of
nature of the problem which is they were
doing some search
among all the possible like subsets of
digits in here which one's the biggest
looks like a tree recursion problem and
um
so you have to look for a way to distill
that into a sequence of choices
and uh a common sequence of choices that
you have is keep the last digit or you
don't i mean we've seen that
in a few different examples um
but uh and so it happens to apply here
sometimes it's not not clear what kind
of sequence of choices you need to make
but that is a big part of solving a tree
recursion problem
so um yeah how you
figure out what that choice is is think
about all the different possibilities
that you need to consider so all the
different palindromes within here
and how would i enumerate that set well
all the ones that have a four
at the end and all the ones that don't
is a way of
partitioning that set using an operation
that i could repeat over and over again
so that's how you kind of figure out
what choice you're going to be made
making and
i guess that got us as far as thinking
probably what we're going to do
is call big where we keep the last digit
and big
where we don't now is the hard part
which is
how are we going to represent this
notion of keeping the last digit
it's not like we have a list called
digits where we're appending the last
digit to
it instead what we're doing is we're
effectively reassigning k
here k either stays the same or
k includes one more digit than it was
before
so whenever you make a recursive call a
good way to think about what you're
doing
is that you're assigning these formal
parameters to new values
so i guess that starts to explain what's
going on here
the last piece is very problem specific
how would you know that you've found a
palindrome
and therefore you want to consider that
as one of the choices
you know this two these two lines
wouldn't show up in any other tree
recursion problems they're really just
about
palindromes because it happens to be
that one way of describing a palindrome
is that you find some digits within
half the number and then you make sure
those digits also appear
in the other half of the number in
reverse order how would you discover
this
i guess um hopefully the definition of
the palindrome would get you there like
how do you describe a palindrome is it's
like it's some digits
and then those digits also have to be
contained in the other half of the
number
in reverse order
and by the way this question down here
would be out of scope for this semester
which is um is palindrome
constant or logarithmic or linear
quadratic that was the
lecture on efficiency that we made
optional you'll do a lot of that in 61b
so don't worry about that kind of thing
yeah so the question is how do you
control the order of the columns in the
result
in the sql statement and the answer is
well
however you list things out in the
select
uh clause at the very beginning is going
to determine the column order
so if you write something like this
sorry
we're not even in sql i guess it doesn't
matter because we'll just talk about it
if you write something like this uh
then you're aggregating so you're going
gonna get one row
because we're not grouping and that rule
will contain
some name and then
uh the minimum salary and then the
maximum salary
and the order will be the name and then
the smallest salary
anywhere in the records and then the
largest salary all anywhere in the
records
and you might wonder like what is the
name well um
this is the thing that's not terribly
reliable i think if you're aggregating
in two different ways
then you can get them in or you can get
the max depending on the implementation
so um you know really it's not clear
what name you would want this to provide
but i don't know exactly what it would
do um
i'm not even sure that the order of the
columns will be what determines that it
could be something completely different
too
right yeah so if if you just like edited
this a little bit
and you put the max first and then the
min would this affect the name like
could but not in any kind of reliable
way so uh
yeah i mean anywhere you're in the
territory of mixing together
aggregation and not aggregation um
i guess like the the really simple case
is actually reliable where you just
aggregate in one way and that one way is
a max
then you're all right except if there
are ties you don't really have any
control over which record you get so
even you're not even
you're not really all right there um and
uh
then um yeah if you have two different
aggregations then who knows what will
happen but this will give you some name
i don't know which one and then the max
salary and then the min salary as the
three different columns um
if like you ever wanted to
build a table and it had one column
order
and then you wanted to build that same
table with a different column order
well i think the answer would be create
table to give a name to the first table
and then select the columns from that
table again just in a different order
yeah i think that's probably going to be
uh implementation dependent
it's also sort of a weird thing to do
like what is i mean
if you can't think of what the right
answer is you probably shouldn't be
asking the question in the first place
all right great question so i think just
for the sake of the recording maybe
we'll zip through the whole thing and
then we'll address your question at the
end i know it takes a little bit longer
but it might be helpful for some folks
so here's um summer 2019
question number eight the ingredients
table describes the dish and part
for each part of each dish at a
restaurant
so chile has beans and onions in it and
soup has broth and onions in it
the shop table describes the food shop
and price
uh for each part of the dish sold at
each of the two shops okay so you have
to buy the ingredients
you can buy them from different shops
and then you have to put the ingredients
together
in order to make the chili cool
you can assume the shops table will only
ever contain two shops a and b
but otherwise um it should be the case
that
like we don't hard code chili in here
there could be any ingredients for any
dishes
select a two column table with one row
per food
that describes the lowest price for each
food
okay so that's really just in here
[Music]
and
if you want to get down to one row for
each food
then you have to group by food
and in general it's fine to select the
thing that you group by
because you know that they'll be the
same for every row in the group and so
there's no like ambiguity there
and then you need an aggregation
expression in order to get the
lowest price
it doesn't matter whether you capitalize
this or not but it is conventional to do
so
okay select a two column table with
one row per dish that describes the
total cost of each dish if all the parts
are
purchased from shop a okay so
in order to describe um dishes
and prices we're definitely going to
need to join the ingredients table
and the shops table
do we need the alias well it turns out
that all the names are different
for all the columns dish part food shop
and price
so it doesn't hurt to alias but you
don't actually need to
you can refer to the different columns
in the
join table just by their original names
how would we do this well first we want
to get down
to rows where
we're describing uh
to make this dish i need beans and those
beans
are bought from shop a and have price
two
so let's write some conditions to get
that it has to be that part equals
food meaning we're not talking about
chili has beans in it and by the way
broth has a price of 5 3 that wouldn't
be useful information
we really need to know that we're
talking about beans here and we're
talking about beans there
and we want to make sure that we're
talking about the right shot
a goes in quotes because it's not the
name of a column it's the name
it's the value in a column and um
so this refers to a whole column or the
value within that column
this refers to an explicit value if i
wrote a here
it would break because there's no column
called a
okay so now we have the right rows
the joined rows are chili beans beans
shop prices okay
not two
so now we need to group by dish
why buy dish well we want run row per
dish
right yeah chili soup and beets
now we want to know which dish we're
talking about and we want to know the
sum of the prices
you can write just some price and what
it will do is find the two different
rows the chili beans
beans a tube row and the chili
onions onions a three row and sum the
two and the three together to get the
five
but the dish is still chilly in both
cases okay so
not what you asked about but now we've
talked about it
in two different ways select one column
table of all foods that have
a different price at each store
oh okay so we have two options here
there's one with a where
and there's one with a group bar
um group by might work if we
group a buy the food
and then make sure that the min and the
max are the same then i think they would
have the same price
so uh i think this is also not the one
you asked about but
the one that occurred to me first
select food from shops grouped by food
having okay so now we have one row per
each food
but we only want rows for the foods
where the min price is equal to the max
i think that works it's kind of a hack
okay
what's the most more explicit version
it's when we
join the shops table with the shops
table
in order to have a row that describes
uh the price at one shop and a price at
another shop
here we go um
yeah uh john i think you're doing uh the
opposite they should they should have a
different price
well thank you price not equal
different price thanks
okay so these shops and say your shops
is b
um here we can no longer write just food
because there's two different food
columns so we'd have to
pick a particular food it doesn't really
matter which one we do
because we're only interested in
combined or joined rows
where ada food equals beta
it's the case that they're from
different shops there's really two ways
to write this
you could write it kind of a long way
which would be
a dot shop
equals a
and a dot shop equals b
oh sorry and b dot shop equals b
that's one way to do it and then we'll
have to check this uh price thing so a
dot price does not equal
now there are actually different ways of
expressing
this thing it said that we could assume
there's only two shops
so um we could write it this way
but if we wanted to instead just say
they're different
you might be tempted to write a chop
does not
equal b dot sharp
which would give you the right rows but
i think it would give you a duplicate of
each one
and the reason is you'd get a joined row
that was like uh you'd get an onions a3
onions b2 and you'd also get a row
that said onions b2 onions a3
they would both have the property that
they're different shops with different
prices
and so you get two different onions
ropes which you don't really want
so one trick to deal with this is to
assume that
since these have different names one of
them will come
before the other alphabetically at which
point
you'd only end up with the onions a3
onions b2 row but not the onions b2
onions a3 rho because a comes before b
so if you saw in the solution that this
was a less than rather than
not equal to that was there so that you
wouldn't get onions onions broth broth
but instead just one onion so one
yeah that's a little bit of a clue just
john
yeah but it kind of does show up a fair
amount that uh when you're
trying to find within one table
matching rows that you have to worry
about duplication so that is something
that's like worth learning about sql
yeah i thought your previous solution
was a little bit longer but more
explicit which i think i like
better oh great question
so if you didn't even say anything about
the shops
and you just found rows with different
prices
would this be enough this assumes that
each
shop only sells beans at a particular
price which i think is a reasonable
assumption
even if it's not stated here
uh probably should be stated here
um then do you need to make sure that
they're from different
shops well you kind of know they're from
different shops because they have
different prices so you don't really
need to say that they're from different
shops i agree that that would be fine
the next question was about fall 2019
question 7c we went over this question
back in the lecture 28
q a but here we revisit it just to talk
about the one trickiest part
you have this expression that looks like
this
and you're not allowed to times anymore
right
and so you have to turn this into a mall
instead
but mall takes a
list of values a single argument whereas
times takes multiple arguments so that's
like the thing you're trying to deal
with here
is converting from a procedure call
that let's say has three arguments into
a procedure call
where you're only calling it on one
thing well
uh let's review that really quick
let's say we have uh
times already and we know how that works
and let's say we have mole
which takes a list of numbers and
it multiplies them all together
so if i want to call mole i can't call
it on one two three
i have to call it on a list
containing one two three
the key part of this is that it doesn't
work to say i call
mole on one two three
why because this is a call expression
and a call expression says call one on
the arguments two and three but one
isn't a procedure until you get an error
so um converting this
here's your expression
into this expression
is a little bit more involved you have
to con the mole
onto uh another list
where uh i guess
the easiest way is to build a list where
i have the word list
and then i have the one two and the
three and let's see what i got
oh i got the wrong thing cons mole onto
well actually i don't want to cons i
want to have two elements
i want mole and i want the list one two
three
okay so that's how you build it but what
if we wanted to build it out of the
parts
of this expression well um
that's like a little bit more involved
we still want a two element list with
mole and in this case we want the second
list to start
with the word list but then the rest of
it should be