lecture 24 q a although i don't think
any of the queues were actually about
lecture
they were all about past exam problems
okay here we go so this is a mock
mid-term
from spring 2017 which you could find
on the resources page and
number four you are an apocalyptic
society
and have been charged with making an
engine or a
generator that computes all of the n
perfect
numbers however in this apocalyptic
society
built-in and user-defined python
multiplication is forbidden in any form
okay so we cannot multiply
you have a blueprint for building a few
engines from
a natural number generator
so here are some perfect squares and
here are some perfect cubes
and this blueprint is supposed to help
us figure out how to make
perfect squares i think by adding
together
odd numbers for a while so if you add
together the first three odd numbers you
get nine
i think that's what i'm supposed to be
reading from this all right let's see
how we're getting these cubes
what's that second row doing john uh is
it the sum
of the two no well it's definitely sums
of things yeah but uh
but there's a gap that's interesting
what's that gap doing there
uh we skip multiples of three
maybe this is one of those annoying
like math problems isn't it uh maybe
they're skipping every third
one so this is one two skip the three
four five skip the six
seven eight seven nine
okay and then
uh once you have
done that still not clear why that's
particularly useful
what kind of question is this if we add
one and seven we get eight
yeah i saw that and what's 20s and if we
add 1 and 7 and 19 then we get 27.
okay so if we do this operation of
summing up every other one
then we get the cubes i see but what's
the
yeah i see the every other one to get
from row two to row three yeah
yeah it's kind of the same pattern as
you had in the two gen case
yeah but what's row two yeah
well row two i think is this uh so this
appliance operation except for
ah um you don't skip every second one
you skip every third one
right so after discovering this
mathematical pattern which we did not
formally know about and
it seems like a lot to ask for uh
a midterm but i guess a mock midterm
it's okay
because here it is okay so now it's your
job to build the perfect engine
and power society out of the apocalypse
good luck
okay so we have natural numbers can i
say if there's an apocalypse
i'm not going to be making an end
generator i'm just saying this is a
ridiculous promise
okay so so we have this notion of
skipping um
which uh i bet is important
so let's say we already have a bunch of
numbers
maybe they're the natural numbers maybe
they're some other sequence
and we want to skip some we're not quite
sure what n means yet but we'll try to
figure it out okay so if this says
if n equals one meaning take every one
then i think you just yield from jen
otherwise you're gonna have to skip some
okay so uh
if you're taking every one then you just
yield from jen otherwise
you got to only yield every other one or
every two out of three or something like
that
what a strange question i still am not
totally sure what create skip is let's
see if we can figure this out
yeah the comment says a generator that
yields all natural numbers might be
helpful
right oh that's the that's how we start
with the
the base sequence oh yeah i see i see i
see
yes yeah i'm not sure but now we need to
like build up these tiers you know
yeah uh so
we need to skip something
i think we need to we need to skip every
end
yeah uh starting with our trusty
natural numbers and then wow
while n is greater than one
we need to decrease it
so presumably for the square that only
happens once and then the cube it
happens twice
that's the one two and then three yeah
yeah so the way you describe
the second sequence from the first is
you're summing everything you've seen in
the first sequence
but you're skipping every nth
one so we might as well start at zero
and it's not time to skip yet
we're gonna go through all the elements
in gen
if it's time to skip then we don't
really want to do
anything at all i think but we do need
to change skip
back to one otherwise we need to
change current to be whatever it was
before because we're kind of taking sums
as we go
plus the element
in the sequence
skip increases
and we can yield the current
i can't actually promise this is right i
think that's the basic idea
is that there's like some pattern or
basically you're summing as you go
but you're skipping some elements along
the way so if i'm
summing everything from 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
and yielding the sums then i'd get a
pattern that's like
go through all the elements add to the
sum so far
and then yield the sum that i have so
far except for here we're not summing
all the elements we're summing every
other element so we have some mechanism
that says
keep this one in but skip that one keep
this one in but skip that one
so if n were two meaning we skip every
second one
then um we would
start with skip equals one which means
we're not going to skip the first one
but then we'll add one to skip
the second time through skip will be two
which is in so we'll skip the second one
switch skip back to one and then we'll
do it again austin confirmed that john
is a
rock star because i think it looks like
it's right
miraculous yeah good question so what's
what's cur equals curve plus lm a better
name for kerr would be sum so far yeah
and it starts out at zero and then it's
not about
indices it's about the total that you've
seen for
all the numbers so far yeah that's a bad
variable name
okay so what's going on with this while
loop and why is this
n greater than one well i kind of just
extended from these two examples
and hoped that it would work for
anything else i mean i
have not thought at all about perfect uh
what's next after cubes
quads quads or whatever so i'm just
guessing this
pattern extends but what i saw here
was that you have to kind of do this
sum and skip operation once
for squares and you have to do it twice
for cubes and so uh
when n was square we wanted to go
through and do this once
that's why i got n greater than one
feels like it's a little too early for
that question
that's a rough way to start let me tell
you
so this is a question from
the summer 2020
practice midterm question three
called close which takes end
smallest and d
and a sequence is near increasing if
each element but the last two
is smaller than all elements following
its
subsequent element that is element i
must be smaller than elements after it
but not just but you can ignore i plus
one
so it has to be smaller than everything
except for maybe the next one
implement close which takes a
non-negative integer n and returns the
largest
near increasing sequence of digits
within
n as a number okay so we're treating n
as a sequence of digits
and the arguments smallest and d are the
parts
of the implementation which we get to
use if we want okay so we can use
recursion
and we basically get to pass in three
things
and something called smallest and
something called d
and they have these default values but
when this is actually used
then we just like start out with these
at 10 and maybe we'll change them later
in the recursion
but
yeah for example if you want to find the
largest
sequence what does it mean a larger
sequence this is basically largest
integer
where when you look at the digits there
were digits within here
and they have this property of being
near
increasing which means one has to be
smaller than everything after it except
for maybe the five
which happens to be right next to it
if n is zero it has no digits i think
that
therefore we need to return something
with no digits
now we have a recursive call that says
uh close n divided by 10 smallest d
uh no seems like a hint to me
to say we're not using the last digit
in in n and that seems clear from this
expression so um this kind of hints at a
recursive strategy let's
think about the strategy first then we
can think about the code
a recursive strategy would be
either you use the last digit or you
don't
if you use the last digit then
everything before it
has to be smaller than it because it's
going to go with the end
except for the thing right before it
doesn't need to be smaller than it but
everything
before that needs to be smaller than it
because that's how you get this property
that like
for every element everything after it is
larger
except for the element right after it
this near increasing idea
so uh i said that recursive
decomposition would be either we use the
last digit
in the result or maybe we don't if we
don't use the last digit i think life is
pretty easy
we just pretend it's not there and run
the same operation
on everything else that's um
that's left over so it might be that the
largest sequence within this number has
no 7 in it at all
and therefore it's just the same as the
largest sequence within 98535
are there any examples of this no
what a poorly constructed question but
it is certainly possible
that you wouldn't use the last digit of
the input
and
and there just happened to be no
examples of this but i think
we could imagine that happening so for
when might it happen
uh let's invent a new case
okay so if you have the one there then i
think the best you could do
uh with the one is so the biggest thing
you could have is 71.
but without a one
right you could have four five six seven
which is even bigger
that would have been a nice example for
them to provide to us which they did not
do
um so yeah like you could ignore the one
and then find the biggest
increasing or near increasing sequence
within the rest or you could try to use
the one
but if you use the one you have this
constraint which basically says
anything before the one before it has to
be smaller than one
at this point a student asked to clarify
what the question is even asking
so let's go back and just talk about
what this question is asking
you start with some sequence of numbers
you start thinking about all the
different numbers that are contained
within it
like one number that's contained within
it is seven
another one is 57
another one is just five
another one is 837.
so it's asking you to consider
all of these possibilities another one
is 900
or 9557 or whatever
and another one is 550
so if we just wanted to list out all of
those possibilities
life would be a little bit easier so
like uh
everything in n would be
if n equals zero then there's
only really one possibility otherwise
we would have to either keep the last
digit or not
so we'd have everything in
n divided by 10 is in n
but then there's other stuff within n
which is
okay so let's say for
for rest in everything divided by 10.
um
that number is an n but there's
something else that's in n2 which is
uh if i stick the last digit on there
so um here's just like a simpler problem
which is yield every
every number within n
and notice here there's no john's not
putting any constraints
on the relative we're going to get a
little bit more complicated in terms of
the order but this is just
all possible numbers inside in order
dropping or including a number
yeah yeah exactly and so here's only a
subset
of the possibilities i didn't write them
all out because there just really are a
lot
um the
question is asking you to find among all
of these
what's the largest one that
has this kind of funny property where
the digits are increasing
meaning each digit is larger than the
last digit
except that you're allowed to skip one
when you're
when you're checking this so for element
i it has to be smaller than elements i
plus 2 and i plus 3 and i plus 4
but it doesn't have to be smaller than i
plus 1.
so for example in this number
this is element zero has to be smaller
than element
two and element three well there is no
element three but if there were would
have to be smaller than that
but it doesn't have to be smaller than
element one john i just noticed it's not
asking for the biggest number it's
asking for the longest sequence
okay well the nice thing about uh
integers is that the longer they are the
bigger they are
i mean saying longer sequence is
actually kind of problematic because
it doesn't tell you how to break ties or
if they just said the largest one then
it would tell you how to bring it up but
yeah it should just be the largest one
right because of the ties okay so
yeah step one figure out what this
question is asking step two
since it's a recursion question try to
think about
how you would do it and here's the plan
that i suggested
it was one forget
about the last digit and
just uh find
close of n divided by 10.
or use
n divided by 10 n percent 10 the last
digit
and make sure that
the everything before it forms
a near-increasing
sequence according to the definition
and then at the end we'll just uh
return whichever is longer
among one and two
so we just don't know which one is going
to work out so we'll just try them both
often times recursion problems look like
this
you're considering many possibilities
break them into two groups
decide uh what's the best thing from
group one
what's the best thing from group two and
then compare them in the end
and that's the best thing overall
now we have to think hard about strategy
two
if i decide to use the last digit then i
have to think about
making sure that the rest of the digits
i include before this one
actually obey this property
so it might have been the case
when you make a recursive call that
you've already
included some digits the very first call
hasn't included any digits but it might
be that you're now calling close again
after having included some digits
and you kind of need to know what's the
smallest thing that you've committed to
already and if the smallest
thing is smaller than the current digit
then i don't think you're allowed to use
it
but if it's not if smallest that you've
used so far
is bigger than the current
digit the kind of last digit of the
current n
john how are we controlling for we don't
care about i plus one
we only care about i plus two to the end
well i think that's why we have two of
these i think maybe we'll stick the most
recent digit in here
and smallest will not be the smallest
digit we've seen so far
but the smallest digit we've seen so far
except for the one that we just saw
right that's the best i could come up
with
okay so now we need to figure out
what's the small what's close um
something goes here something goes here
we're going to multiply that by 10
we're gonna add in this last digit
look familiar it's a lot like this
except for um
what this is going to do is give us kind
of the longest sequence that i could
make
if i included n percent 10 the last
digit of the current
n along with anything that i've
committed to so far
and then since i'm looking for the
biggest one i'll just like take the max
max of integers should basically do the
right thing in terms of finding the
longest sequence
and if i wasn't allowed to do this then
i'll return
just the one that i was allowed to do
which is ignore the last digit and use n
divided by 10.
this is a doozy okay uh it's supposed to
cop
it's almost post-apocalyptic john except
you can multiply here so you know it's
not that bad
so if i were thinking about this as just
a loop
then i would say um
i need to assign d to be the digit that
i
just included and
i would need to assign smallest to the
smallest thing i've seen
so far including everything
in the like long ago part of the number
and including the digit that i had just
seen because now i have a new digit that
i have just seen
um but not including actually n percent
10 that will come later
i think this would look something like
min of smallest
and d i got to tell you my confidence is
not
terribly high so before we try to
yeah aaron is right this is not an easy
problem
okay well okay so it worked that
increased confidence it really is
moderately yeah this is a tough one
um so
yeah so what are the elements here
whenever you're doing recursion
you need to track some state like what's
the rest of n
that you're gonna process that part i
think is fairly straightforward
you carve off a digit each time and deal
with smaller and smaller digits
but in those recursive calls you had
either
decided in advance that you were going
to put some
digit on the end or not when you put a
digit on the end
then you have to pass information about
that digit that you put on the end
into the arguments of the recursive call
in order to make sure
that you don't uh do bigger ones along
the way
uh john there's a quick question in the
chat about mixing return
and yield my recollection was you didn't
used to be able to do this but did they
change that in python 3
yeah so mixing return yield is where
um return kind of behaves differently it
basically says
stop the sequence inside of a generator
function
so you can write return and that
basically means
uh don't yield anything else after this
which is a different
notion of return than what you're used
to which is why i would say like
i mean i've never mixed them in any code
that i've ever written but it is allowed
yeah i think you can do it in python 3
but i do think it's a weird thing to do
just conceptually okay
let's let's solve a simpler one
more complicated than this but less
complicated than this let's get rid of
this notion of near
increasing and just uh look for
the longest increasing sequence within n
we would need to keep track of some
notion of
what's the smallest thing i've done so
far
um so what does this do
return the sequence of digits within
and sorry the largest sequence of digits
within and that is increasing
so how might it work if i call
increasing on here's some digits
let's see what we got we could have two
then
four then seven and eight
that's pretty long try one more
uh we could have three four five six
seven
that's pretty long
i didn't check too carefully but it's
about right
how will we do this one if n
equals zero return zero
otherwise if
um the last digit of n
is less than whatever is the smallest
thing i've seen
so far then i might want to include it
so i'm going to just write this as maybe
i'll
use n percent 10 in the result
maybe not
if and if the last digit is not
allowed because it's bigger than
something that i've already decided i'm
going to use
then i just can't use it so that means
the best i can do is find the biggest
increasing number
within n divided by 10.
okay so now we're going to have this
notion of no and yes
no says i ignore n percent ten
this is the same as that which is why
this had kind of a funny structure
we'll talk about that later it is
important that when you're looking for
the smallest thing within
and ignoring the last digit you still
respect
how whatever digits you've decided to
keep already
along the way so you have to pass in
this notion of what's the smallest thing
i've already decided to use
and then if you decide to use n percent
which is smaller than the smallest now
you can still find more digits
but they're not allowed to just be
smaller than the smallest thing you had
previously seen
now they have to be smaller than
n percent 10. it turns out that this
could be
simplified because we know that this is
smaller than that
so i could trim this down and i'd get
the same result
but i'm going to leave it like this just
so we can compare it with the other
thing
in a minute and then here i would say
well
maybe i found the best thing without
using this digit
or maybe i found it with using this
digit
works for my two examples must be right
that was a joke because it might not be
right but i think it looks okay
so uh so what now
if you can understand this then you can
eventually understand this
but i agree that like close is just a
much like a considerably more
complicated version of increasing
so i would focus on understanding this
first what's going on here
let's just look at the mechanics we
either use one or we don't
in the in the choice where we don't we
just kind of pretend it's not there
and then we either use six or we don't
and in the choice where we don't we just
pretend it's not there
and then we either use eight or we don't
in the choice that we do
now we have to make sure that everything
else that we choose from here is smaller
than eight
so we're going to have eight in the end
but we make a recursive call
that is i want the longest increasing
sequence
within eight seven
two four seven you know everything
that's left over
except for all of the digits there have
to be smaller than eight
and that's how i got this number so if
that makes sense
then look at the difference between this
and that the difference between this and
that is that
like we're just tucking away the most
recent digit
and we're gonna include it in this
notion of smallest
one step later than we otherwise would
so you're allowed to
ignore the five when you're checking to
make sure that one is small enough
because that's just the rules of how
this works
here's uh we're in spring 2019 midterm
two
question four we're not going to solve
the whole problem we're just going to
talk about
a particular assignment statement and
it's strange behavior
so a student observed that if you
have l dot rest comma l equals
l.ref.rest
l.rest.rest you actually get different
behavior
than if you switched the order of l and
l.rest here
here's the reason the way you
execute this statement is you evaluate
everything on the right like we said
and then assign the results to
everything on the left
um but
when you assign to everything on the
left you do do it in order
so you're going to be changing l.rest
and then you're going to be changing l
which turns out to be different than
changing l and then changing
l dot rest because l rest will be a
different thing than it used to be
if you change l first
this by the way is exactly why i don't
like the simultaneous assignment
operators even when they're
straightforward i find them a little
evil
i just prefer to have it sequential i
never ever use these
simultaneous design operators and my
perspective is a little different
i think they're great as long as you
have you know different unrelated names
on the left
but here is a particularly diabolical
thing where you have l dot rest in l
which is referring to a part of a hole
but if you change the hole first then
you're talking about a different part
like a part of a different hole
than if you change the part and then you
change the whole
yeah i think this would really only show
up if you were
changing an attribute and you were
changing the name that you were using to
refer to that attribute
at the same time which you know i think
it's a
fairly rare scenario but here it is
good question so um the question here
is in the fall 2017 midterm two we're
not going to do the whole thing we're
just going to analyze
if you have a garden instance and you
look up its
smell and you call that which one do you
get
do you get the instance attribute or do
you get the method
and the answer is you get the instance
attribute this is a general
property of python's object system which
is that you always look for instance
attributes
before you look for class attributes and
if you find an instance attribute
even if it's a function that's the one
you use so it's not like functions are
special in any way
you're really evaluating this expression
first
which is if i have a garden what's its
smell
and you look for anything that's an
instance attribute and if you find a
smell there
then that's the thing you're going to