lecture number 14 q a here we go
man that is a hard question how do you
think abstractly
well let me i i don't know the answer
that let me give you a couple of
thoughts and then we'll see what john
thinks so first of all
i think computer science is very
different than other fields
um there's not in a lot of fields you
know memorization and pattern matching
sort of work
right you you say things like you know a
biologist you just have to memorize a
whole bunch of stuff and just tell me
what i taught you and that's that's not
really
we're in the problem-solving business
and every problem is a little bit
different
yes you learn these basic skills that
come to bear so
break out of the habit of trying to
sort of remember a solution to your
problem right that that's not really
going to work
um it's really about taking the parts of
the solution
and putting them together in a distinct
and novel way so it's more of the if you
will the the the the raw material
and then you're gonna sort of mix it all
together in new ways so so so break free
of the you know oh
i've seen this before i've seen this
before that's number one
number two for me and everybody's a
little bit different on this i don't
like to think in front of the computer
like when i'm thinking about problem
solving i need a piece of paper and
pencil or i need to go for a walk
and just get away from the computer
because once you start coding you get
really bogged down in the
you know all the little nitty-gritty
things you got to make sure that
the solution to the problem is clear in
your head
and the implementation is separate in
some ways for me in fact it's very
different you know because i can think
of all kinds of solutions that would
take me
days months to implement so get clear in
your head
what the problem is and don't worry too
much about the underlying implementation
um and then the last thing i'll say is
it's just practice
it's just you just you know the more
problems you solve the better you get at
it so this is your first class
in fact it's only week five of your
first class in your first four years and
i mean nobody expects you to like out of
the gate you know be
um solving these problems off the top of
your head so it's just it's sort of a
slow process it'll take time
next year you'll be better at it the
year after that you'll be better at it
and you'll keep getting better at it
because you'll keep solving problems and
the problems will get bigger and bigger
so be patient
yeah i think that's great advice
actually what hani said
reminds me that there's something really
different about an online version of 61a
from the on-campus version which is
how people approach discussion
where we used to print out the
discussion worksheets and
everyone would put away their laptops
and pull out a pen
and kind of start writing down first
diagrams
and then a description of what they're
trying to achieve and eventually code
but code is just one language to
describe
the process that you're trying to to
capture
right in a recursion problem or anything
else
you could also describe it in english
you could try to describe it in figures
or diagrams
and all of these are helpful because
that's uh how people really think right
is that they um
you know nobody like thinks in code we
we think in
um you know physical metaphors and uh we
rely on language
that we've been learning since we were
babies and stuff like that so
um yeah so pulling out a piece of paper
isn't as common
i think now but it's still a good idea
and
going back to the original question of
like how do you think abstractly it's
um that's very broad but there is a
more specific skill relevant to this
class and all the computer science
classes you might take later
which is to accurately
describe the things you have to work
with
and then a lot of the problem solving
that happens in computer science is how
do i get some new things
done with some pieces that i already
have available
and the weird thing is that unlike
carpentry where like your set of tools
is basically always the same
in computer science your set of tools is
always different you have like a
different set of functions that you can
call
in recursion you're kind of like
building the tool as you're using it
which is a weird thing but knowing
those things that you can do is
really the first step to trying to do
anything new with them and so
every function really just has three
things that you need to know about it
it's domain so like what kinds of things
can you call it on
do you call it on trees do you call it
on numbers do you call it on positive
numbers do you call it on
lists of numbers whatever its range like
what kind of thing
will it return and then its behavior and
its behavior
is a concise description of what it does
what's the relationship between the
input and the output
and if you can think of a function in
terms of those three things then it's
much easier to use
because you can check and see like oh
can i call this function well
if it's a function that takes trees is
it arguments
and i don't have any trees then i can't
call it and when i do call it i better
call it on a tree
not the trees label or the trees
branches or something like that
and uh after i call it what do i have
left well that's the range
and um and exactly what is this new
thing oh it's a tree that's bigger or
whatever
the function does so um yeah thinking in
terms of those three elements can help
you
get to know the functions that you have
to work with and then you can
reason about like oh exactly how do i
want to put these pieces together
i'll add one more piece to that i like
that description a lot which is that
problem solving and coding is not linear
you don't just
you know start here and end up here and
you just take equal steps
it's a very meandering process you know
often what happens is
you go down the shore and you're like oh
scrap i screwed up this data structure's
not right the subtraction barrier is not
right
i need to pull back a little bit and try
so it's a very sort of
iterative process you know you sort of
build a little bit you realize
ah you know we didn't really think
through this issue over here
let's back up a little bit fix this
little thing go forward and let it build
so it's
nobody expect you to start here and end
up here or just take a straight straight
shot so don't worry if there is this
sort of back and forth deleting code
it's like writing i mean think about
writing a five-page essay
you don't just start at the beginning at
least i don't and in writing get to the
end and be like
done right i mean let's see what do the
editors say the best writers are the
ones who know how to delete
um right so i think it's a very sort of
iterative
[Music]
fits and burst type of thing so don't
get discouraged if you find yourself
doing that
and actually this relates back to the
question in the chat
before we started recording which is
like how often do you correct
uh old code and i find one of the best
ways
to debug something is actually just to
rewrite it even if it's my own work
to think like oh is there a different
way i could have expressed this and if
so
what would it look like in that case and
sometimes it turns out that you find
like oh
this piece that i thought i needed i
don't need because i'm writing it a
different way
and that can clarify the implementation
a lot so um
so the strategy of like start with
something and then continue adding to it
until it works
might succeed for some simple problems
but basically doesn't succeed well for
more and more complex problems as you
proceed through the course
and instead like getting rid of
everything except for the essence
is usually the way to go
the next question was what is an
exclusive or
gate or an xor gate and can you build up
everything from that
so i showed you one construction of a
circuit
that starts with a two table and says
build
a boolean expression for each of the
outputs using
only and and not yeah
that is not the only way you can do it
there are other ways of doing that
what i like about that one is that it's
a very sort of methodical process right
uh express the problem build the truth
table and
or and not rather and then pour
everything together draw the circuit
it is by no means the only way to do it
um it is by no means the optimal way to
do it
right so an x or is let's see if i can
get this right it's um
true if one of the one or the other of
the
inputs are are true but not if both of
them are true
right so think of the truth table 0 0
would be false did i get that right john
xor yes
yeah 1 1 is false and then 1 0 is true 0
1 is true yeah so which is another
boolean out it's just another
boolean operator and you can build
expressions like that it's just that the
process that i described is a little bit
different
um i off the top of my head i
don't know how to build an xor out of
transistors but i'm sure you can
um i think it's probably two transistors
in a
resistor or something like that but i'd
have to sort of sketch it out to see it
but yes you can you can
you can physically implement an xor um
and there are other types of operators
too that are beyond and or not those are
sort of the building blocks and then
there are these
things that go off to the side but
perfectly fine by the way and i'm sure
and absolutely there are in this
computer right here there are xor gates
those are very useful um i just
described one particularly simple
way to design circuits because it led to
a very clean formulation without having
to do a lot of things you know
the next question was would courses
cover circuit design
is it 61c or 16a and b
um the circuit design is mostly in 16a
and 16b
um 61c
has an interesting level of abstraction
that's between
python and circuits which is called
assembly language
and um yeah the details there
are that you need to do more than just
describe
the relationship between inputs and
outputs you also need to describe
for example like what to do next and
whether to load something in
from memory that was stored before and
whether to store something and where to
store it
so these primitives actually also have
circuitry
associated with them so if you want to
do more than add but you also want to
like manipulate memory and have
sequences of
instructions and decide oh i'm done
doing this for a while i'm going to do
this other function and implement
function calls and stuff like that
well there's circus associated with all
that and hardware associated with all
that
but then you need a language to describe
exactly what to do and then you get a
programmable computer
and that language that is implemented
not in software but in circuitry
is called an assembly language which is
kind of the lowest level programming
language
so that's what you get in the 61c so if
you really want kind of the whole stack
61ab gives you the high level software
programming 61c gives you this
very low level but still software
representation of an assembly language
and then 16a 16b will tell you about the
circuits
and by the way back in the day this was
before my time
people programmed in assembly language
there were no high level languages there
was no python no c
no java none of this stuff and so people
programmed in that
what we would now consider a low level
um description and so you had to know
like where are the registers for
the store and what is the address and it
was incredibly difficult uh to do and so
we've been creating these abstraction
barriers right where now we have this
high level language where we just
put in some some code and then it gets
compiled down it gets converted to
assembly and then it interacts with the
hardware so there are several levels
still
between you and things actually
happening on the computer
um and you can i think that that
sequence is really interesting to sort
of see how it all unfolds
the next question was if you pass all
the tests
for the cats project but the gui still
doesn't work
should you submit or keep trying to
debug it
if you pass all the tests you might have
bugs in your code but we won't know
about them
so in that sense they won't affect your
ability to get credit
um it's less interesting to have a
program that doesn't seem to work
now it's hard to tell whether when the
gui doesn't work
that's because there's some issue with
your code
or whether there's some issue with our
code because we provided the gui
uh it seems to have worked pretty
robustly in the past but i'm not sure
um yeah i didn't teach this course over
the summer they always make changes
maybe they broke something and then it
might be that actually that there's a
configuration issue with your computer
that we didn't anticipate
um or yeah so like the way in which it
connects to the server or something like
that
is um is uh hard to get around yeah so
we have had students in the past that
have like particular antivirus software
that interrupts the
multiplayer server or something like
that
so yeah if i had to guess
probably if you're passing all the tests
then the problem is not with your code
but i can't guarantee you that's the
case but that's probably what's going on
and um will we debug it hopefully
yeah so there's definitely stuff that we
don't check for that
um is important and this is true of any
test suite is that it's basically
impossible to prove that a program
does what it's supposed to do if that
program is just written in python with
no constraints
there's an interesting branch of
computer science called verification
that is about making sure that you can
prove that your
program really does what it's supposed
to do but the trick there is that you
have to express what it's supposed to do
in language that the computer can
understand
and then you also tend to have some
restrictions on what
how you write your program to make it
easier to verify
so these techniques still aren't used
very often in practice except for
with very low level programming like
making sure that a circuit board does
what it's supposed to do
so anyway yeah it might be the case that
there are some issues that we didn't
detect but you could certainly just
submit your project
and not worry about that so yeah the
question is about like how do you
approach add trees
which takes in two trees and returns a
new tree where each corresponding node
from the first tree is added with the
node from the second tree
if a node at any particular position is
present in one tree but not the other it
should be present in the new tree as
well
so you could kind of pretend that a tree
that's missing some branches relative to
the other tree just has zeros everywhere
i think it's one way to think about it
um and
[Music]
apparently this is a lot harder than
previous tree problems that's exciting
it's an ominous warning
so
let me just try to get set up here
address
i think since these are both trees they
both must have a label
they might have different lists of
branches but they both must have a label
so um we can guess at what's the label
of the final thing that we want to build
which is that the result label
is the result of adding together the
label of t1 and the label of t2
and i always like say in words what i'm
trying to do to a tree before i start
trying to program because that helps me
make sure
that i'm kind of combining the right
types of values so you can't add
two trees together if you do you won't
get an error but you will get the wrong
thing
so instead you want to get the labels
and add those together
now what about all the elements i'm not
going to use this built-in zip function
because that seems like it's more
complicated we could try that later if
you want
but i think we want to go through and um
for each corresponding pair of branches
we want to add those branches together
and then we'll get
uh new branches so
um yeah
so maybe we'll start with no
branches and
i think it would be helpful to have an
index of which branch i'm on
and then i want to go through all the
branches
that exist in both trees so
one way to do that is to say well i is
less than
the len of the branches of t1
and i is less than the length of the
branches of t2
and we might think of a more concise way
to say that later but this is a
a fine way to say i want to go through
all the i's
where they exist in d1 and they exist in
tt
and what would we get we'd get a new
branch
that is the result of adding together
uh branches t1
r with
branches t2 i
i'm doing this in kind of the most
explicit way possible now what does it
mean to add these two things together
well we actually need to like add their
labels and
add all of the elements in the rest of
them fortunately we have a function that
does that it's called add trees
um so to make this fit on the screen
i would call this b1 and b2 maybe
and then we'll just call add trees on b1
and b2
uh what do we do with the new branch um
we'll learn in friday's lecture that
there's other ways to do it but
one way is just to redefine result
branches to have all the
branches that were in there before plus
there's a
new branch so we'll build a list
containing just that branch
and um add that in so that will give me
a longer list that's got all the
elements of this plus one new element
which is this new branch now we have a
bunch of branches
and if we had some guarantee that t1 and
t2 had the same structure then we'd be
done i'd say
but being done means we need to return a
tree that's what add trees does
so we'd call this on result label and
result branches
the tricky part is that maybe it was the
case that
i was didn't didn't capture
all the branches in t1 because there
were fewer branches in t2 or something
like that
um so what do you do about that i think
that um any branch that's in one but not
the other
doesn't really need to be added to
anything it just needs to be included
in the result um so
which ones did we leave out we left out
i think
all the branches of t1
from i onwards
so let's just kind of check with an
example if this had four branches and
this had two branches
then after you do this iteration i will
be equal to two
and will reach here and if
t1 had four branches then we do want
branch two and branch three
which is exactly what would be captured
by this slicing expression
so we could write something like that
and what if it was the case that um
there were more branches in t2 than they
were in t1
well then we'd need to put those in the
result
something like that might work
the question to ask yourself is why are
both of them there
if only one of those can be true right
you can either have
extra in t1 or t2 so why are we allow
why are we allowing both of those in
there
yeah there's the implementation again if
you want to think about that
and i think i'll just quickly check and
see
if this works except i'm not sure that i
have print tree to find anywhere i might
have to grab that
yeah i gotta get print tree where's
print tree
oh it's in there somewhere
there you are print tree
i'll put that in my file of important
functions related to trees
gonna try this all again
what am i trying again i want to run
these
oh runs forever that's not good let's
see why that is
oh you're not incrementing i john in the
while loop
rookie mistake okay now it works
so i mean there's lots of ways to clean
this up uh
we could
um for example
have this like be a minimum
of these two values
we got it slightly better um we got the
coleman
we could have given names to branches
t1 and branches t2 because it seems like
we call that just a ton of times and it
might just simplify things if we'd given
them names
we could replace this while statement
with a for statement
the whole story about zip i think um
we could talk about really quick so
uh what zip does
if you give it to this
is give you a way of iterating over both
of those
lists um kind of uh
concurrently so the one and the seven go
together and the two and the eight go
together and the three and the nine go
together
the nice thing is that if you zip lists
of different links then it just kind of
works its way up until
you get to the to the part that you want
so
um
right so instead of all of this
we could have gone through uh b1 and b2
and the result of zipping together the
branches
of t1 and the branches of t2
and we'd end up
getting rid of that line
now we've kind of lost track of our
notion of i
and that can be worrisome but we could
reconstruct it actually
so i could be just the len of the result
branches and then this would probably
work
yeah it looks pretty good um
and yeah finally could you somehow like
get this
into one line and usually it's the case
that if you ever start with a list
and then you are adding just one element
at a time to that list
you could instead write it as a list
comprehension
so this could have been add trees
b1 b2
we're going to have to give it some
shorter name for
b1 b2 in
this zip still doesn't fit
how disappointing make it fit
okay so those are the result branches
now i'm just fiddling around but
whatever you probably get the idea
um and then you can delete all this
stuff
there's a great line by um i think it
was um
one of the guys who wrote c in unix and
he said
debugging is twice as hard as writing
code
so if you are as clever as you can be
when you write code
you will by definition not be able to
debug your code um
yeah so and i mentioned this because
john did something really nice here he
he wrote code that was not particularly
elegant sorry john
a little bit longer than you might want
but it was very logical you could see
what he was doing in every step
he got that to work we make sure and now
you can go back and start tightening it
up and cleaning it up and making it more
elegant
if you want to but sometimes that
slightly longer code
slightly more explicit is actually
preferred because it's a little bit
easier to
deal with i'm like if i looked at this
i'd have a hard time parsing this code
whereas the previous code was
you could see what was going on it was
good yeah i was just trying to show this
kind of different ways of solving the
problem and there was a tint about zip
so i forgot i'd tell you what it was
you know zip is an abstraction that most
python programmers really get used to
because it shows up a lot that you want
to like pair things together
in this way but if you're unfamiliar
with it then this looks completely
confusing
so it just like takes a while to get
used to or familiar with this notion
that you would take
you know the first two elements first
elements and pair them together in the
second elements put them together in the
third elements to get them together
once you're used to that notion because
you've seen it a dozen times
then this idea of like oh call ad trees
on all the corresponding pairs
is easy to read but at the beginning if
you've never seen the term zip before
then it's really hard to read so
kind of depending on your comfort level
and the comfort level of whoever might
read your code it can make a lot more
sense to kind of write things out
explicitly
um or you know if you've all been
programming together in python for years
in your community then you could write
it this way because zip is kind of a
common verb
in that community and it's not
necessarily confusing
and this works for assignments too i
mean we may tie your hands and say you
have to use zip
that doesn't mean your first
implementation has to do it just figure
out how it works
and then you can back your way into the
constraints
and that sort of helps you think about
you know how we're solving the problem
without one hand tied behind your back
if you're not comfortable
with a particular concept but at least
you have it working at that point
and it's worth noting that a lot of
expressions that existed in the
other implementation still exist here
like we didn't actually have to change
this code as long as we kind of captured
what was going on
so that's generally true there's lots of
different ways to
write the same thing but they often
share the same elements
a follow-up question was whether you
could write the same implementation just
using recursion
yeah great question so we are using
recursion already in the sense that
we're calling ad trees
within the body of fat trees there's one
part that we're not doing recursively
which is that we're
iterating over the branches so this is
kind of a mixture
of iteration and recursion could we make
that part recursive too the answer is
yes
but we'd basically just write a helper
function that
does this process of building up the
result branches
we just build it up recursively um
so
it's actually not so bad
what do we need we need the
branches of one and the branches of two
we pass those in
or actually let's just stay consistent
we'll pass in t1 and t2
um
and if it's the case that
the one of these is empty
then there are no branches in the result
otherwise we're going to have to
construct
uh the like
first add tree and then
add that on to the the rest so
the first thing i think would be the
result of calling ad trees
on
branches t1 0 almost got it right
and branches t1 2
and
then what do we do with that okay i'm
going to move this in just so it fits
um we want a list that that has that as
its first element
and then the result of build result
branches
on oh i guess we do need a list of
branches here
so here bs1 and bs2 are the branches
of two trees
are the remaining branches of
trees well i'll leave it like that uh
so we're getting close
you see there is like a fair amount of
iteration here to get it right
that's not right and that's not right
and that's right maybe
uh and then we just need to
kind of forget about the first element
of both of these
make it fit and then we get rid of this
expression
and replace it with a call to the helper
function that we built
and perhaps we've then built something
that works
we did not build something that works
john i don't want to put pressure on you
but you got three minutes
okay so now it works uh yeah
so if you really wanted like to take
some
iteration and turn into a recursion
there's always a way
here's one possible way um
this would be done rarely in practice i
think uh if you just
like are going through a sequence of
something then use a list comprehension
or for statement or a while statement or
something like that
recursion is really wonderful for
recursively processing trees
so uh the the add trees here is really
an important recursive call that's the
reason we learned recursion
and uh this is just kind of an exercise
in knowing that it's possible
a student then suggested that instead of
returning an empty list in the base case
you return the rest of the other tree
fine idea yeah although now you have to
know which one
is you can't just do the min though yeah
it might work
there you go good idea yeah
all right that saves some effort okay
we added a lot of trees thanks folks