61 election No.36
announcements
entries into the optional scheme
workers of art contest are due Monday
which is tomorrow
we will have a lab this week can do Tuesday as usual
this lab is just focused on
preparing for the final exam
so it's a great way to start preparing
by starting to review
some of the material from this course
we do have lab parties on Monday at three pm
and seven pm
homework nine about sequel was posted long ago
before thanksgiving
let's do this Thursday
and we'll have a homework party on Tuesday
if you lost any composition points on the ants project
and you want to get back
whatever points you lost by revising
your work you need to do that by Sunday
well this week we're trying something new
the discussion handout will be about review
and we'll have tutorials as usual
but we also are opening up some longer tutorials
normally they're 25min
we're gonna try some 45min ones
if that sounds interesting to you
then go to the sign up and switch
or you know
if you just want to attend your regular tutorial
that's great
even if you want to
attend your regular tutorial
and join one of these 45min ones
you could do both
the system will only let you sign up for one at a time
but I'll bet if you get in contact with your tutor
you can figure out how to attend both of them
and right now
there are several slots available for these 45min
review tutorials
so if you want a little bit longer review
this Wednesday
then maybe sign up for one of those
and the final lecture on Friday
will not be lecture videos
instead we'll run a synchronous zoom webinar at 2pm
it will be recorded and the recording will be posted
if you don't want to come
but it should be a nice way to conclude the course
to actually
have some live questions and have us answered it
here are the important links lab orientation on Monday
discussion orientation on Wednesday
the usual extra q amp a Wednesday and Friday
we won't actually have lexure
videos posted for this Friday
but I think we'll hold the q amp a anyway
for anyone who wants to go over past problems
and we have conceptual office hours this week
Thursday at one pin
today's lecture is nice and short
it's about scheme
it answers the question
why would anyone use scheme instead of python
by introducing you to a feature called macros
which allows you to actually extend the language
by adding new special forms
so that you can customize scheme to work
how you want it to work
it's an optional topic but it's really good practice
because a lot of scheme problems do involve
manipulating scheme expressions as if they were lists
and that's the key to writing a macro as well
so even though it's optional material
I recommend watching the videos
there's only three of them they're pretty short
and you'll learn something cool
okay here we go
macros are a feature of scheme
that allow you to define
new special forms in the language
in python we have a certain inventory of expression
and statement types
and the same was true in scheme
we had defined
lambda if cond and or etc
everything else was a procedure
now macros allow you to extend that inventory
by inventing new kinds of special forms
that means that we can
change the way the language works
inventing new ways in which the flow of evaluation
proceeds through a program
sounds fancy and it is
it's the kind of feature
that makes people fall in love with lisp programming
and the reason it works well in lisp
languages like scheme
is that it's easy to view code as data
programs are just lists
macros perform code transformations
so the way that will invent new special forms
is to describe how to take the parts of a special form
and construct
a regular piece of scheme code out of them
and then evaluate that scheme code
so a macro is an operation
performed on the source code of a program
before that source code is evaluated
macros do exist in many different programming languages
but they're by far the easiest to define correctly
in a language like lisp
where the code is just data
in scheme there's a special form called define macro
that allows you to define a transformation
over the source code
for the special form that you're trying to invent
so here's an example of a macro called twice
you can see it looks a lot like a procedure definition
but the way in which
a twice expression gets evaluated is quite different
the content says that when you're twice an expression
you build a list that starts with begin
and then has that expression twice
once you've defined this macro you can twice anything
and here we're twicing the expression print two
what happens behind the scenes because twice is a macro
is that it evaluates the body of the macro
on the expression you've typed here
before that expression ever gets evaluated
so we construct a new expression began print two
print two and then this expression gets evaluated
which means that it will print two choice
now there's something interesting going on here
if twice were just a procedure however it were defined
print ii would have gotten evaluated
before twice were ever called
and that means two would have been displayed once
and that value ii would be gone
because once you print you can't get back the value
so there is something that twice can do
that on regular procedure can't do
which is to take this expression
and duplicate it before it gets evaluated
and then evaluated twice
so the evaluation procedure
of a macro call expression in general
like this one
is that we evaluate the operator sub expression
if that evaluates two
a macro defined by the defined macro special form
then we proceed a little bit differently than regular
procedures
we call the macro procedure on the operand expressions
without evaluating them first
then we evaluate the expression returned from the macro
procedure
so macros take in expressions and return expressions
instead of taking in values in returning values
so let's talk a little bit about print
when I print two I see two on the screen
but if I define x as print two
and then I look at x I see that x is nothing
once you've printed the two is gone
if I wanted to print two twice
then I could ride print two
and print two
but in order to put that into one expression
I need to use the begin special form
the begin special form just says do all of these things
let's say that I was stuck with only procedures
and I wanted to define twice
I'm going to write the same body that I had
on the slide
begin the expression and then the expression again
now twice print ii doesn't work
I get two displayed
and then I construct an expression that says begin none
none the value of print ii
if I wanted to construct
began print ii print ii I would have to quote this
so it's not like it's impossible to do this
with the procedure
I just have to think about quotation
in order to make sure that this doesn't get
evaluated in advance
but even this version hasn't printed anything yet
the only way to
print would be if I evaluate the results of calling
twice on the quoted print ii
the idea behind
macros is that this quotation and evaluation procedure
is taken care of for you
so if instead of defining this as a procedure
I define it as a macro
then instead of typing twice quote print 2
and evaluating the result
I can just twice print 2
and I see two display twice
so something simple and something
profound has happened at the same time
the simple part is that all it does is make sure
that twin two doesn't get evaluated
for example by quoting it
passing in the expression to twice
and then evaluating the result
the profound thing is that we've
changed the way the language works
twice is now the kind of special form
that doesn't involve evaluating the arguments first
and that means we have complete control
over when and how
things are evaluated inside of a macro
let's look at how this can be useful
let's say I want to define
a procedure that checks whether something is true or
false
if I pass in a value I can write if the value is true
then I passed the check
otherwise I failed the check
and if for instance
I had a x -2 and I wanted a check
that x is greater than zero
I would have failed that check
so this is a reasonable way
to add little tests inside of your scheme program
but unfortunately it doesn't tell you what failed
when something failed it would be nice of its head
here's what failed
but in order to do that
we need access to the expression that was evaluated
instead of just the value itself
so let's define a macro
first
we'll just name it check in order to be consistent
but this doesn't take in a value
it takes in an expression
instead of just writing down what gets evaluated
I have to construct this expression piece by piece
you check expressions by building a list
which contains if
and then it has the expression that we want to evaluate
and then it says either past or failed
here I have double quoted
to say that I want the result of evaluating this
to be this quote past
and now I've built a macro
that behaves just like the procedure that I had before
so if I start scheme and I load this file and I define
x to be -2 and then I check to c
is it the case that x is greater than zero
it will say failed
so I've done all this work to define a macro
it was slightly more complicated than their procedure
and it doesn't do anything new yet
but we could get it to do something new
by
not only saying failed
but also saying what expression failed
so in the case that this fails
I'm gonna build a new list
and it's still gonna say failed in it
but then it's also gonna show you the expression
now we run the whole thing
exactly as before
divine x to be negative to
write down what looks like a procedure call
but in fact it's not a procedure call
because when it fails it tells you that it failed
this is a false value
but also the expression that caused it to fail
and that's something that would
not be available to a regular procedure
before we conclude
let's quickly look
at the expression that was constructed by this macro
you can do that by removing the dash macro
and now we just have a regular procedure
this regular procedure
can take x as -2 but when it's called
we have to explicitly quote the expression
as if we were calling a macro
is x greater than zero
constructs the following expression
if x is greater than zero than it just says past
otherwise
it builds this list failed and then the expression
if I were to evaluate that
then I would get the fact that it failed
but of course
if instead expert two and I evaluated the same thing
then I would see that it passed
so we've built from scratch
a macro a new special form called check
that checks whether
an expression evaluates to something that's true or
false and when it evaluates to false it shows you
the expression
scheme doesn't have a four statement
now it will we're going to create a four micro
we'd like to define
a macro that evaluates an expression
for each value in a sequence
for example if I say four x in 2345 square x
I should get the squares of two three four and five
how convenient
we'll build this mac growing two steps
first we define
what it means to map a function over values
if values is null there's nothing in the mapped list
otherwise we cons applying fun
to the car of valves
to whatever we get when we map that function
over the kutter of valves
and in this case
we would be able to produce something like the four
statement just using map
but it requires a little bit more work
I have to say map
and then I have to give a lambda expression
in order to capture this body
and then I have to say what I want to apply it to
so having a four expression in the language
doesn't mean I can do new things
it just means it's much
more straightforward to state what I want
because I don't have to explicitly write out
the word at lambda
so defining the macro
means saying what happens when you have four
and then a symbol and then some values
and then an expression to evaluate
for each of those values
what we do is build this expression
it's a list containing map
it then contains lambda x and then that expression
and finally it contains the values
spend a moment and see if you can write out
the general macro definition of four
that allows us to transform these three expressions
into this one long map expression
I'll show you the answer in 321
there it is we build a list that starts with lambda
and then has the symbol that I'm using as a placeholder
for every value
that has to go inside a list
because that's how lambda expressions work
now experor will be bound to this whole thing times xx
and so I just place that
into the lamda expression that I'm constructing
as a list
and finally I write down the values
and then when I run this here
for these three expressions
I will build this map expression and then evaluate it
and I'll get the result for nine sixteen twenty five
so there's another way in which you can
extend the syntax
of the language
mixing together something that gets evaluated
something that never gets evaluated
is just the symbol to use as a placeholder
and then an expression here that gets evaluated
for every element of this list
and now we've discovered that scheme
has four statements after all
now that we've talked about
what macros are and how to define them how to use them
let's talk about how your
scheme interpreter would need to change
in order to support macros
in fact there's an optional question on project four
about macros so if you've finished project four
and you're looking for something else to do
to extend your interpreter
here's a good thing to add
because it doesn't take a lot of code
but teaches you exactly how macros work
and there's really two parts to solving this
one is to
implement how the defined macro special form works
that's actually the easy part
it's almost like defining a procedure
the slightly more involved park
happens when you have a call expression
where the operator the first expression
evaluates to a macro
a call to a macro has a different evaluation procedure
that a call to a regular procedure
so if you look here it says implement defined macro
by implementing due defined macro
well what is that about
well remember schema val
checks to see
if the first symbol is in the special forms
define macro is one of the special forms
and so it's going to call that do define macro function
in your scheme interpreter
and what that's going to do is create a new macro
just like you would create a new lambda procedure
and it will bind it to the name that's given
in the definition expression
the interesting part
about macros is really what happens when you call them
what happens when you use a macro
is you write a call expression
where the operator evaluates to some macro
so for example the symbol far for
is bound to a macro procedure
in the example that we just did
so here we get to the else case
where we tried to evaluate a call expression
we evaluate the first expression in the
list of expressions that forms the call expression
maybe it's the symbol flr
when that gets evaluated you get a macro
well that's a special case
normally what you do in a call expression is you'd
evaluate all the operands next
and then call the procedure on the arguments
that are the values of the operands
but macras are different
instead you apply the macro
to the expressions that are in the call expression
before you evaluate the
those expressions might be symbols they might be lists
anything is fine
but they are pieces of scheme code
which serve as the arguments to the macro
the macro then returns something
which is a scheme expression
and that has to get evaluated too
so instead of the usual pattern of
evaluate the operator
evaluate the operands
call the procedure on the arguments
instead you get evaluate the operator
apply it to the operands
to get back an expression that you evaluate
and you can write all of that in terms of scheme apply
and schema val
just like you would with regular procedures
but the particular order that things happen in
is a little bit different
and that's what it would take to complement macros
in your scheme interpreter