61 a lecture No.19
announcements
lab seven do Tuesday
homework four to Thursday
and were releasing a new project
the ants project is do next Friday
but you need to get started by next Tuesday
to earn the checkpoint
and you can uninterlace submission
bonus point for submitting the whole thing
by next Thursday
there's also an extra credit problem on the project
so it's possible to earn even more extra credit there
this version of project iii is shorter than usual
this semester is more stressful than usual
it's harder to get help
there's a lot going on in the world
and it's harder to work with your peers
now this project started out at a reasonable size
and then every semester
it seems to have grown a little bit
as people think of more questions to ask
and what we've done is really just trim it back
closer to its original size
it's still quite a large program that you have to write
larger than any project you've done before
now it might be more manageable
because your experience has grown
throughout the semester
but still
I encourage you to leave plenty of time for this
large project
so that you can make sure you get it done
by next Friday
or better yet
by next Thursday and get that bonus point
and what's the project about well it's about ants
in particular
it's a re implementation of a game I like called
plants versus zombies
the version we build in 61 a is called
ants versus some bees
and your job is to build all the logic
about
how the different characters in the game interact
which is a
natural application of object oriented programming
and inheritance
I'll let you implement the game yourself
and then you can play it
this Thursday we're going to have an advising panel
we've been running some 1 on 1 advising office hours
but the same question sometimes come up
again and again
so we thought we'd have
a larger forum where many people could attend at once
you could ask questions about anything you want
industry clubs research with your masters program
classes whatever
and we'll have some members of the core staff
on hand to answer your questions
so this is just informal pure advising
but gives you a chance to understand
what's available at berkeley and how to get involved
we'll still hold 1 on 1 advising office hours
they're now going to be drop in
on fridays from one to do 30
on the office hours
q
we've just posted an anonymous serving
it's really short
it's not required
but it would be really nice if you filled it out
here's the whole thing
and all these questions that the bottom are optional
so if you want to give us an indication
about how you're feeling about the course
whether you're behind an lecture or caught up
how you're feeling about assignments
and the hint videos
as well as giving us some suggestions
about how to improve the course
I would appreciate it
we'll try to implement
these suggestions as soon as we can
so please complete that survey by Monday
and finally midterm two is coming up
it's two weeks from Wednesday
so next week you can focus on ants
the midterm will be the following week
it will have a similar format and style to midterm one
although if there were things that you didn't like
about midterm one
you can tell us about that on this synonymous survey
and we might be able to adjust them before midterm ii
is written
this exam will cover content through this week
but next week there will not be new content
and the week after
when you actually take the test
there won't be new content either
my sense is that some people are a little bit behind
in lecture and so
I want to give you a chance
not just to hear about these topics
but solve a homework problem on them
or hear about them in lab or discussion or tutorial
so that you can really be prepared to do well
on the exam
so if you look at the upcoming schedule
there's the midterm
here's where we are
these three topics will be on the midterm
this topic is going to be
completely optional this semester
it won't be included in any
homeworks or labs or discussions or exams
I think it's interesting
you'll hear a lot about it in 61 b
so we're just delaying it until then
these two lectures are really
about review of everything you've learned
about objects and values
so I do recommend that you watch those
when they come out
because they'll help prepare you for the exam
and this lecture
is optional it's always been optional
but it's often students favorite part of the course
so I would definitely recommend watching that lecture
but you don't need to learn anything from it
that will be applied to the midterm on Wednesday
so that's what's coming up
today's lecture about inheritance
is about a topic that could be overused
so you do need to know about it
but I wouldn't recommend
using it everywhere that you possibly could
but it can be an awfully useful technique
when it is applied appropriately here we go
let's recall attributes
so attributes are part of objects
and there's all this new terminology
about functions and methods and attributes
I'd like to just review it
so all objects have attributes
which are name value pairs
classes are objects too
so classes have attributes
an instance
attribute is the attribute of an instance of a class
and a class attribute is the attribute of the class
of an instance
so there are two different
places you could find in attribute
in its instance or in its class
now here's for the tricky part
we have the set of all class attributes
and the set of all things that are functions
functions aren't
particular to object oriented programming
but methods are
so a method is a function that's also a class attribute
in the python object system
functions are objects
bound methods are also objects
slightly different kinds of objects
that has a function with its first parameter self
already filled in
already bound to an instance
dot expressions evaluate to bound methods
when you have a class astribute that's a function
and this is a very common pattern
where you have some instance here before the dot
and after the dot you have a method name
then that method
is the function named
with the instance filled in as the self parameter
let's just quickly
review what happens when you evaluate
a dot expression
you evaluate this
by evaluating the expression on the left of the dot
which yields an object
name is matched against the instance attributes
if an instance attribute exists with that name
its value
is returned as the value of the whole dot expression
if not then name is looked up in the class
which yields a class attribute value
and that value is returned
unless it's a function
in which case you get a slightly different
version of the function
you get a bound method
or you get the function with its first parameter
bound already
to the object of the dot expression
attribute assignment statements
change the values that are bound
to attribute names within an object or a class
so you can assign to attributes
assignment statements
for the dot expression on their left hand side
are attribute assignment statements
so they affect the attributes of the object of that dot
expression
if that object is an instance
then assignment sets an instance attribute
if the object is a class
assignment sets a class attribute
so let's say I have the account class
here I've just shown you part of it
interest in this definition is already
a class attribute because it's defined
directly within the class
or as holder and balance
are instance attributes
because they're set on the new instance that's created
and passed to in it
so account is a class
and tom account is an instance of the class
if I say tomacount interest equals 0.08
that's setting an instance attribute
because the
object of the dot expression is an instance
so this expression evaluates to an object
this whole thing
doesn't look up interest
on that object and go find it in the class
instead we just
directly assign
to the attribute of the object that's here
so this is attribute assignment
that adds or modifies the attribute named interest
to the tom account
in this case
the instance didn't have an interest attribute before
and so the assignment statement will add one
that's an example of instance attribute assignment
class attribute assignment
arises when you have an attribute assignment statement
meaning there's some expression with a dot on the left
and the object of that dot expression is a class
so this will go and change
the interest attribute of the account class
which in this case already existed
and so we go change it
okay so here's an extended example
of how attribute assignment statements affect classes
and objects
let's say I say jim account is an account with jim
now I'm going to introduce this new object
which has a balance and a holder
and this instance
is an instance of this class
now the account class has interest
and that's accessible from all the instances
but it's part of the class
it also has withdraw and deposit methods
and an initment
so here we see
the instance attributes of a
gym account are just the balance and the holder
and if I create tom account
well
then it will have its own balance and its own holder
the balances happen to be the same
but they could change later on
here we've looked up interest on tom account
which means looking in tom
account to see if there's an interest attribute
there's not so then you look in the class
there it's found 0.02
and so that's the value we see
jim account has an interest of 0.02 as well
next I can set a count dot interest as 0.04
that changes a class attribute for the account class
so we can see that change reflected up here
the interest is not bound to 0.02 anymore
but the attribute value is now point o four
if I look up the interest on tom's account
I'll find that point of four
and on jim's account I'll find the same
even though these were created back when
the account class had a different interest rate
so it's not the case
that an instance has its class attributes locked in
when it's created
instead they can change over time
and the instances will reflect those changes
next we see jimacount interest set to 0.08
this is an instance attribute assignment
that adds an interest attribute to the jima count
okay so now I see interest reflected in two places
both in an instance and in the class
if we look up jim accounts interest
we'll see 0.08 which is what we just set
if we look up tom accounts interest
we first look in tom account it has no interest
and so we look at its class
and it's currently set to 0.04
so now we see
that we're able to specialize a particular instance
of the account class
giving it its own special interest rate
which you know might happen in a back
somebody gets a higher interest rate than somebody else
let's say now we change a count dot interest to 0.05
well that's an
class attribute assignment statement
that will change this to 0.05
finally we can check the interest rate for each
instance tom's account has an interest rate of 0.0 5
which just changed
because of this class attribute assignment statement
jim
still has an interest rate that's a special case 0.0 8
so by assigning to the class
you don't arraise all the special cases
they're still there
onto a new topic inheritance
this is a new feature of the python object system
and it's a feature that exists in almost every
object system in every programming language
so inheritance
is a method for relating multiple classes together
because not every class exists in isolation
sometimes one is just
similar to another one
and we want to express that relationship
so the most common use case you should think
about when using inheritance
is when you have two similar classes
that differ in their degree of specialization
so the specialized
class might have all the same attributes as
the general class
along with some special case behavior
the way you express this syntactically in python
is that in addition
having a class statement with a name and a suite
you can also put in parentheses a bass class
and the bass class is what this class inherits from
so conceptually what happens is that the sub class
the one that we create with this class statement
shares all the attributes with its base class up here
the subclass might override
certain inherited attributes in order
to change its behavior slightly
but anything that's not changed stays the same
so using inheritance
when we write down a subclass of an existing class
all we do is we specify what's different
about this subclass
from the base class
everything else stays the same
let's do an example
so
let's say we have a checking account
it's like an account
but special in the following way
when you create a checking account
you still give it a holder
but its interest rate is lower
than the interest rate that you would get
on a normal account
so you get less money every month
when you deposit is the same thing as before
you add money to your checking account
when you withdraw money from your checking account
you incur a withdrawal feet
I mean the bank has to make some money somehow right
so when you withdraw a $5 from your bank account
and there's 20 in there
what's really left over is a balance of 14
okay so most of this is
the behavior is shared with the bass class account
so all this different
is that we have a lower interest rate
and when we withdraw money
we have to pay an extra dollar
okay
here's how we write the code for this checking account
we say there's a class called checking account
its base class is account
another way of saying the same thing
we'll create a class called checking account
that inherits from account
so this is a bank account that charges for withdrawals
we set that withdraw fee to be a dollar
we set the interest rate to be point o one
instead of the usual point o two
and then we also have to change the withdraw method
because writing down withdraw fee
might
seem like it's helping us get in the right direction
and it is
but we haven't ever said how to use the withdraw fee
so we have to write down a method that does that
and we'll write down the withdraw method
so the withdraw method takes some amount
and what it does is it withdraws
from the current account
the amount that was specified
plus whatever the withdraw fee is
for this current account
now why do I keep saying current account
when it says self right there
or remember that self
is the name we use to refer to the object
on which this method gets invoked
so when we actually call withdraw right here
self will be bound to this checking account
which is currently called ch
and was originally created
with this call to checking account
okay so we'll withdraw $5
amount will be five
we'll add in the withdraw fee of one
which is shared among all checking accounts
because this is a class attribute
and then how do we actually do the withdrawing
well that's the interesting part
we refer to the
method on the bass class called account withdraw
now since we're looking this up on a class
as opposed to on an instance
we're not going to get a bound method back
we have to supply this self ourselves
okay
since we put account here as the base class
we don't need to say anything about depositing
that just stays the same as it was before
we don't need to say anything about in it
so checking accounts start out with $0
okay so let's talk about looking up attribute names on
classes the bass class attributes aren't copied
into the subclass
instead is part of the process
of looking up an attribute by name
that gives you the behavior that an attribute
of a subclass that isn't changed
is just the same as whatever the bass class was
so to look up a name in a class here's what you do
if it names an attribute is in that class
then return the attribute value
remembered attributes or name value pairs
if not
look up that name in the base class if there is one
now the bass class is just a class
so we recursively are doing the same thing
we'll look there
see if that attributes in the class
if so overturn its attribute value
otherwise
we'll look up in the bass class of the bass class
okay so let's talk about exactly what's happening
when I create a checking account
I pass in tom as the holder
since the checking account class we just defined
doesn't have an in it method of its own
we look up the name in it
we don't find it in checking account
but we do find it in account
and so that's the one that gets called
and that says the balance to zero and the holder to top
when we look up the interest rate
while there is a special interest rate
for the checking account
so that's where we find it
and is 201
when we deposit
all that depositing happens from the accounts method
so here's what we do
we try to evaluate this operator expression
which is a dot expression
which means we look up deposit
on this checking account
which check in the instance
no deposit attribute there
we check in the checking account class
no attribute deposit there
so then we check in the account class
and it has a method called deposit
so we get back a bound method here and we call it on 20
depositing $20 in the account
and finally when we withdraw
while we find that in the checking account
and that gives us 14
okay let's just write the whole thing down
so that we understand what's going on
so on the right you see
the account class from last time
so in addition to the class that we have
we're going to create a class checking account
which inherits from account
it has a different interest rate
and as a fee associated with all withdrawals of $1
and the way that fee gets used
is that we write a withdrawal method
that withdraws not just the amount but a dollar extra
okay now
it's reasonable that we could just copy this over right
then say
okay the first thing we're gonna do is we'll add one
to amount and then we'll go through
and we'll check and see if the amount is too big
if it is and we'll say insufficient funds
if we're okay then we'll change the balance
and we'll return that balance
this would be correct for a while
but the problem is
if we made changes up here
they wouldn't be reflected down here
so that's why instead in the example that I showed you
I said let's actually
just use the implementation we have already
a count up withdraw
that's this function right here
and what does count out withdraw take
well
it takes self an account object as a first parameter
and the syric 2nd
parameter is the amount that we want to withdraw
which is whatever amount was passed in here
plus the withdraw feet
let's quickly verify that this works
so if I have one account
that's an old kind of account for john
and then another account which is a chicken account
for my good friend jack
so a is an account b is a checking account
they both have a balance of zero
let's add a balance to each by depositing
into 100 a and depositing
100 and b
now both those did the same thing
because they're both using
the same deposit function over here
but if I withdraw $10 from a I have 90 left
or if I withdraw 10 from b then I have only 89 left
because I use this withdraw feet
next we'll talk about designing
object oriented programs
some of the choices you'll encounter
and some guidance for how to come to a useful solution
okay
here's the checking account class that we just defined
and let me just
reiterate why we did certain things that we did
so first of all
it's important to continue following the guidelines
that you saw earlier in the course
don't repeat yourself
use existing implementations whenever you can
and try to avoid copying and pasting coat
2nd
attributes that have been overridden
should still be accessible via class objects
what am I talking about
well
to override an attribute means that in the subclass
you're giving an attribute the same name
as exists in the bass class
so here we see the checking account class has withdraw
which also exists in the count class
but even though we've overridden that name
meaning the checking accounts will call this withdraw
instead of the original withdraw
we can still access them and use them
using the class object
so here's the account class
an account dot withdraw will give us the original
withdraw method
as opposed to this new one for checking accounts
so we can still defer to the old logic
and we just make this small change of using
a withdraw fee
you can also look up attributes on instances
whenever possible
and this is a good idea
so what am I talking about there
well when we compute
the total amount that we're going to withdraw
amount plus self withdraw fee
we had several options here
we could just write amount plus one
hard coding with the withdraw fee
but then we could never change it
we could also write amount plus
checking account that withdraw fee
which would get this one
this attribute here
but it wouldn't allow for the fact
that some chicken accounts might have a special
withdrophy
so the best way to do this is to look up withdraw fee
on the instance itself
which means that if
that instance has a particular withdraw fee
will use it if not we'll use the one from the account
okay
so here we have attribute a look up on a bass class
and here we have
looking at an instance attribute
and that's preferred to looking up checking account out
withdraw fee because it allows for specialized accounts
either through further subclasses
or by giving instance attributes to particular accounts
the other thing you need to think about when
designing an object oriented programming
is when to use inheritance
versus when to use composition
what's composition
well that's when one object
has another object as an attribute
and that's a very common pattern as well
so obdicurated programming
shines when we follow the metaphor
that is we treat objects like real things in the world
this helps us think about them clearly
so inheritance is best to represent
is a relationships
meaning a checking account is a type of account
so checking out is a specific type of account
so checking account naturally inherits from account
and thereby has all of the attributes of that account
composition
when one object has another one as an attribute
is best for representing has a relationships
so for example
a bank has a collection of bank accounts
that it manages
so in that case
a bank has a list of accounts as an attribute
but a bank won't inherit from account
and an account won't inherit from a bank
they're related
and that one has the other is an attribute
but they're not related according to inheritance
so let's design it in a bank real quick
a bank
won't inherit from account
because a bank has
accounts
and what will it look like to use a bank
I'll create a bank
so now we have a new bank
and bank is gonna do things like create accounts for us
so if I go to the bank then I might open account
give them my personal identifying information
hi I'm john here's $10 please open an account for me
and the bank will remember that it's open that account
and it will return it
and my good friend jack
might go to the bank and open an account as well
and jack only has $5 with him
and the bank manager says oh that's fine
but you're gonna have to open a checking account
so john has just a normal account which means
john's interest rate this should be 0.02
or as jack's interest rate
with his checking account will be 0.0 what
okay so what are banks to or banks
hey interest
on the money that you keep with them
so let's say we just paid that interest
and now we can check and see what john's balance is
and balance has the $10 that he had before
and an extra $0.2 because
he had 2% interest on his $10
okay so now we have an interesting problem on our hands
how do we implement the bank
well let's look for some clues
about how to implement the bank
by this example that we've drawn so far
and we'll write the implementation
so bank is constructed with no arguments
what's gonna happen when we open a bank
we're gonna have to remember what accounts
are held by that bank
when
I go to a bank and I open an account
that's a method
where itself is bound to the bank
and then we also see that we have a holder
an amount and some kind
of account that we open
which is optional
so let's say by default we open a regular account
what happens when we open an account
well we have to create that account
how do we do that
what we'll call kind
which is a leather account or checking account
pass in the holder
because that's how bank accounts work
we'll deposit into that new account the amount
that was given to us
next
we have to remember that this is one of our accounts
as opposed to an account in another bank
so we're gonna add this as count
to our list of accounts
and then we can return
okay what's the last piece of the implementation
we have to be able to pay interest
paying interest
takes no arguments beyond the bank itself
so how do we pay interest
well we have to go through every account that we have
so we'll call it a
and how do I get all of the accounts that I have
well that's called self accounts
and for each one
all deposits some extra money in it
which depends on its current balance
and the interest rate for that account
let's see if all of our tests pass
and they do so we've implemented the bank
not using inheritance
so every finished will not quite yet
we need to provide some protection for our bank
because we don't want our bank to get into trouble
if it ends up paying out too much interest
so we should probably write a function
about whether it's too big
to fail
and when would that be true
well probably whenever we have at least
two accounts
so is this bank too big to fail
certainly is I mean it holds both john and jacks money
test pass
let's stress test our
understanding of attribute look up and inheritance
by working through a slightly more complex example
here it is I suggest that you pause the video
and try to figure out what happens
after you run all of this code on the left
and then evaluate these three expressions on the right
what are their values
if you finish that
try to answer the question of which
evaluates to an integer
bidazi bidazizi bida zi da zi
or none of those
so like I said please pause and work on it on your own
we're gonna go through the solution in 321
in order to solve a problem like this
you need to figure out what
happens when you execute these three class statements
and then these three assignments statements
let's take a look
when you execute class a you create a new class
a class is like any other value
in the sense that it can be assigned a name
and the name that it gets assigned in the global frame
is capital a because that's the name that we gave it
now the class itself has two class attributes
z is -1 due to this assignment statement
and f is the function that returns b of x minus one
this function like any other function
does have a parent frame
all of the functions in this example
have parent frame global
so I'm not going to write them in
so this structure was created
by executing the first class statement
the second class statement
creates a class b that inherits from a
and forever this class will know
that it inherited from a or that a is the base class
it also
has some attributes due to the body of this class
statement so n is bound to four
and in it is bound to a function that initializes self
in the global frame
this class is given the name capital b
finally the third class statement creates a class c
which inherits from b
since b inherits from a
any instance of c will have access to the contents of a
except for when it's the case
that some name is repeated
so ah the class c
or an instance of the class c will have an f
that's different than a's
because f is overrated
there's another definition of f
which in this case is the function that just returns x
this whole class has given the name c
capitalized in the global frame
and then we execute these three assignment statements
calling a introduces a new instance of a
and we'll call it a
since there's no in it
method within the class definition a
there are no instance attributes that are set
this a instance is just a blank slate
now we create b of one
calling b introduces a new b instance
and the in it method for b is called automatically
with self bound of the instance and y bound to one
and then we have some expression about self z
which depends on y
so since y is a true value
we're going to call self. f on y
which f does it call
well b doesn't have any f
so then it looks in the bass class and calls this f
which creates another b
oh my goodness that's complicated
let's not worry about it just for the moment
and instead focus on the fact that z is sent self z
equal to something
and it's whatever is the return value of this call to f
whatever
the attribute contents of this b instance may be
that instance itself is assigned to the name
b in the global frame
and now we have attribute assignment
to an attribute of lowercase b
so I look up b in the current environment
it's this instance
setting n equal to five
means that I add an attribute here
this has no effect on bees class or its space class
instead it's just a change to this particular instance
now I think we're in a good position to review
some of these
eventually we're going to have to fill in what z was
but let's solve the first two here before we do that
so c of 2.n here's an expression that has to
evaluate to some object
in this case it evaluates to an instance of the c class
here's the c class so we build a new instance
and what happens when you build an instance of the
c class is that you automatically call the in it method
for the c class
since c has no in it we look in its base class
here's the in it which is this function here
so we're calling this with y bound to
2 if y which is 2
is a true value
then we'll sell self z to be self f of y
now what is self in this case
self is the c instance that we just created
so we're going to add a z attribute
you can see here in my slide that it's going to be two
why is it two
well we look up self.f
what's the f function for this c instance
there's no f attribute here
so we look in the class
there's the f attribute is the identity function
so we call the identity function on 2
we get back 2 and that gets bound to self c
so z is 2 here
but the interesting thing is that c ii
having been created
is only used to look up the attribute in
so when we look up the attribute n on this c instance
since n is not an attribute
we look in the class
n is not an attribute here so we look at its base class
n is here so the value of c to n is four
if we had instead asked what c 2 dot z
we would have gotten two
alright is it the case that a dot z is equal to c
let's figure out what a dot z is
a is this instance
it does not have a z attribute
so we look in the class
there's a z attribute as -1
so the left hand side of this equality is -1
c refers to the c class
c is an attribute which does not appear here
so we look in the bass class no z here
so we look in the bass class and we see a z is -1
so these are equal because in fact
we're referring to the same attribute
in two very different ways
okay a.c we already figured out his -1
and what's b.c well b is this b instance
and it has an instance attribute called z
we never really wrote down what it is
but I'm pretty sure it's not gonna come out -1
I think it's time that we figure out what it does equal
so when this instance was created we passed in one
as the value for y
self is bound to the instance itself
we checked that y was true and so we called self.f on y
since b is an instance of the b class
f refers to this because we look here there's no f
so we look in its class there's no f
and so we look in the base class and there's f
which is the function that returns b of x minus one
b of x minus one creates a new instance
of the b class
but this time we call the constructor
on whatever x was that's 1-1 is zero
so now we're calling this on zero
for the second instance of b
since zero is not a true value we set self
z equal to a c instance
where we pass in 0+1 is one as the argument
so we're about to construct a c
instance where we've passed in
one as the argument of the constructor
c has no constructor
so we look in the base class and we find
this constructor
why is bound to one and one is a true value
so we set self z for this c instance to be self.f
now since self is bound to the c instance
self dot f is looked up here
and then in the class for c
and there is an f
there that just returns whatever was passed in
which in this case is why equals one
ta da
okay so it's quite clear that this is -1
and this is some b instance
and those can't be equal
and now we can move on to which of these
expressions evaluates to an integer
b.c is a b instance
b that
z is a c instance
b dot z dot z dot z
is one
and one dot z is nothing at all that would be an error
so only this expression evaluates to an integer
and that integer is one
multiple inheritance is when
a subclass has multiple bass classes
okay here we go
let's decide another kind of bank account
this is called the savings account
it's similar to an account
the only difference is that there is a deposit fee
how does that get used
well every time you deposit
then we'll return account that deposit
of the amount minus the deposit feet
so you deposit $10
you really only get eight
more dollars in your bank account
a class may actually inherit from multiple bass classes
in python
so let's say we have a really smart bank executive
who thinks I've got the perfect idea for an account
we'll have a nice low interest rate of 1%
so we don't have to pay our customers to much money
we'll have a dollar fee for withdrawals
and a $2 fee for deposits
but people will come flocking to us
because we'll give them a free dollar
when they open an account
this is a really good account
they call it the as scene on tv account
and the way we define this count
is actually quite simple
because we already have checking in savings accounts
so the as scene on tv account
inherits from both the checking account
and the savings account
when it's created
it takes in an account holder
remembers that account holder
but instead of setting the bounce to zero
you get a free dollar
and that's actually the whole implementation
okay so a class can inherit for multiple bass classes
what happens when I create
an eye has seen on tv account
well I start out with a balance of one
that's an instance attribute
when I look up
how to deposit money
I'm going to find the deposit method
that's in the savings account
so that's the savings account method
that when I deposit $20
I actually only put in 18
because of the dugality deposit fee
I had one before so now I have 19 bucks
and when I was draw five
well I pay
a checking accounts withdrawal fee of a dollar
such a deal and deep
okay so
it turns out that there are multiple different
withdraws and deposits
but in this case
it's easy to figure out which one gets looked at first
so as seen on tv account we'll get
withdraw from here and deposit from here
and really
the only thing that it's inheriting from account
is the interest rate
so because this inherits from this inherits from this
we find the withdrawal method here first
there is a particular order
in which we look at all of these
and all you need to know
is that you look at the subclass
before you look at the bass class
the last topic of today is just a word of warning
that multiple inheritance
tends to make programs complicated
so it should be used very rarely indeed
if you want to design clear programs
now it's hard for me to show you why this is the case
so instead I'll just show you an analogy
about human inheritance
so let's say you have a grandma grandpa
granddaddy and grandmammy
and they give you your mom and dad and then there's you
this is how we naturally think about family treats
okay so an ant is a sister of your mom so someone else
who was a child of grandma and grandpa
so that's what an ant is
there's also something called a half ant
what's a half ant
well a half ant is someone who shares your grandma
but doesn't share your grandpa
so seems pretty simple so far
if your half ant has a kid with some other guy
then you have a half cousin
but the thing to realize is that
this tree is just growing exponentially at each layer
which implies that there are many
many more people in previous generations
than there are now
but that's actually not true
100 years ago
there were many fewer people
on earth than there are now
so it can't be the case that these trees just grow
wider and wider with different sets of people
there must be some overlapping in the treat
so there's actually terminology for that
sort of overlapping
let's see what it is
so if your half ant
was the child of your grandma and not just some guy
but instead your granddaddy on your other side
well that has a name that's called your double half ant
and if your double half ant has a kid
that's your double half cousin
getting complicated already due to multiple inheritance
ah but I can get worse
if you have a double half ant
of course you could have a double half uncle
on the other side
if grandpa and grandmammy decided to have a kit
and what happens if that other guy
that your double half ant was hanging out with
is in fact you are double half uncle
then that's not just your double half cousin
that's your quadruple half cousin
who shares all four of your grandparents
moral of the story