61 electra No.31
announcements
homework seven is due to date
and next week is a big week because there's a lab
and it's a lab about a new topic
the sql programming language
which we'll begin to cover today
there will be another lecture on that Monday
and get another one on Wednesday
the lab doesn't cover all that stuff
but it does cover
content from today and Monday's lecture
and while it's due next Tuesday
I recommend you do it Monday
we have lab parties
and if you get it done on Monday
then you can worry about the rest of the assignments
going on in this class
for the rest of the week
there will be a small homework
we've shortened it a bit from its usual length
by making part of it optional
just because there's a lot going on on the world
and I know you could use a break
it's to next Thursday and it just lets you practice
manipulating scheme expressions
but the big thing that's going on
is there's a scheme project
we'll have a project party next Tuesday
to help you make progress
you definitely should finish checkpoint one by Tuesday
that's when it's du
checkpoint two by Friday
and the whole project does not do next week
but it is do the following Tuesday
and if you finish it the following Monday
you get an early submissioned bonus point
which I definitely recommend getting
it's even better if you're farther than just checkpoint
one on Tuesday
in fact a great goal
would be to finish up the project next week
then you can have thanksgiving week off
it's a big project but if you make progress every day
you'll get through it
and this is really the home stretch of 61 a
you finish the scheme project
then there's just one more homework
do after that on sql
and it covers the only three
lectures that are left in the course
today's lecture next Monday and Wednesday
and we will have finished covering new content
we will have more lectures but they're all optional
I hope you watch them
but
the design of the course is to make sure that you have
enough time to review the material
get comfortable with it
and get ready for the final exam
so I know there's a lot going on next week
la band a checkpoint Tuesday
homework Thursday another checkpoint on Friday
if you miss checkpoints there are only points like
one point each
so it's not totally catastrophic
but it is really a good recommendation that you
stay ahead of the project
don't leave it to the last minute
and hit these checkpoints
so that you can turn the whole thing in
early on Monday the 23rd
and I know that's a lot but if you get through it
then you can have a nice thanksgiving
and the rest of the semester will be pretty relaxed
so keep it up
thanks for working hard
and here we go learning a new topic
declarative programming with sql
today we start a discussion of declarative languages
and we'll use as our canonical example
a database management system
so database men in front
systems are important
heavily used and interesting
systems in general
is an area of research within computer science
that works on things like operating systems
that's probably their most important and most
used application
but the runner up to that is a
database management system
and these
systems have huge deployments across lots of companies
for lots of different applications
they hold data and they process it
so database is a collection of tables
and tables are where you put your data
and then the database management system
helps you keep track of those tables
create new tables delete the old ones make updates
all these different operations
that you might want to apply
to your data
a table is a collection of records
which are rows that have a value for each column
so here's a table
which contains the latitude
longitude and name of different cities
berkeley is at latitude 38 longitude 1 22
Cambridge here
what we might wonder
is it Cambridge Massachusetts or Cambridge england
the longitude tells us it's in Massachusetts
and Minneapolis has a very high latitude
which is why it's very cold there
this is a table which has columns and rolls
a column has a name
this one's called name
and a type it's full of strings
this column's called longitude and it's full of numbers
a row has a value for each column
so all the rows have the same structure within a table
they all in this table have three values
and the first two values
the latitude and the longitude are numbers
and the name is a string
so there's regularity in the structure of the data
in a table now
a database can have multiple different tables
with different structures
a structured query language or sequel
is perhaps the most widely used programming language
in terms of the number
of people who write programs in it
why is that
while software engineers use it all the time
in order to access data
for their programs
and lots of people who
aren't software engineers use sequel as well
in order to extract information
that they want to use in order to make decisions
so companies organizations
I'll keep their data in databases
and the structured query language
is the language that almost everybody uses
to access that information
sql is a declarative programming language
what's that
well in a declarative language
sql is the most common example
but there are many others such as prologue
a program is a description of the desired result
that you want your computer to generate
the interpreter's job is to figure out how to
generate that result
for you
that's different from an imperative language
such as python or scheme
or instead when you write a program in that language
it's a description of some
computational process or processes
that you want to be carried out
the job of an interpreter in an imperative language
is to carry out the execution
and evaluation rules
in order to have a correctly interpreted program
and you've done this in your project
so there's more flexibility in a declarative
language interpreter
we'll see what I mean by that in time
but here's a place to start
in an imperative language
if you write a quadratic time algorithm
by specifying that computational process
it's probably gonna run in quadratic time
but in a declarative language
you just say what you want
and if there are multiple ways to compute that
one of which runs in quadratic time
one of which runs in linear time
well it's up to the interpreter to
choose among those options
in order
to compute what you want as efficiently as possible
so a lot of the interesting research
and declarative languages
is in making decisions
about how to compute the desired result
given that there are many ways to compute it correctly
but some of them are faster than others
okay so what are these languages actually look like
we're going to focus on sequel
in sequel you can have statements such as
create tapal cities as
select 38 as latitude one
22 as longitude berkeley as name
okay so what's happened so far
is we've said we're going to create a table called
cities
we're going to have columns latitude longitude and name
and in the first row we have thirty eight
one twenty two and berkeley as the values in that row
we want to union this with other rows
so that we can select 42
71 Cambridge
we can select 4593 Minneapolis
and with a semicolon at the end of our statement
we've created this table
given a table
you can also create other tables
so here's another sequel statement
select west coast as region name from cities
where longitude is greater than requal to 115 union
select other name from cities
where longitude is less than 115
hundred and fifteen is somewhere
not too far away from san diego
and this is supposed to define
what's on the west coast versus what's not
executing this statement will give us another table
with a region column that says west coast or other
and a name column which is the name of the city
berkeley's on the west coast
now I'm going to go
through all the
details of what's going
on in these different statements
but the point that you should take away it right now
is that
these are statements about the structure of the
thing that's created
and they don't necessarily say how to compute it
that's up to the language interpreter
the next video is going to teach you
about a new programming language
called sql the structured query language
I like the video but it's out of date
so instead of re recording it
I'm going to tell you the part that's out of date
we have a brand new way to run sequel in the browser
that's a great way to get started
if you press code
it will bring you to code csixtuna org
which has a python interpreter a scheme interpreter
and a sequel interpreter
the sequel interpreter does take a few seconds to load
but once it's loaded
it's a really nice way to interact with sequel
and also has all of the tables from the
lecture examples built in
so when the following video
gives you an array of options for how
to interact with sequel
they're all valid
but this one's valid too
and it's designed for this course
to help students learn
so I suggest you try it out
time to learn a new programming language
the structured query language
sequel is standardized based on a specification
except both by americans and internationally
but the only people who don't accept it
is the people who actually
build database management systems
so there are lots of different variance
of this language
but mostly the language behaves in the same way
regardless of which database management system
you're using
although these
different fenders that produce these big software
packages are competing with each other
and so they add various features
that the other ones don't add
we'll focus on a part of the language that's universal
a select statement creates a new table
either from scratch or by projecting a table
a create table statement gives a global name to a table
so you can use select in order to create a table
but you need to create table in order
to give it a name
that you can reuse
and that's all we'll really focus on
lots of other statements exist
and allows the lead explain insert for place update etc
actually there are several more
and they're important
if you're actually going to use one of these
systems in a large
industrial application
but they're not too important for
understanding the heart of how sequel works
most of the important action is in the select statement
so we're going to focus almost exclusively on how
select works
a code for executing select statements
fits on a single sheet of paper
so you can build an interpreter for this language
quite easily using python
and will go over the details of that
in the next lecture
but first we have to learn how to use the language
we're going to take a break
from fibonacci sequences and integer sequences
and all of that
and instead focus on a theme for the day
and that theme is dogs
I love dogs
don't actually own this many dogs
but I picked this picture off of the internet
because that dog right there
looks an awful lot like my dog
if you want to follow along which I highly recommend
you should install sequel light
which is the simplest and free
database management system
you can download it here
there's an online version of sequel light
at this address
or if you want
you can use the sequel example python program
from the textbook
which you can find here
it's certainly not as feature complete as equal life
because it's only supposed to demonstrate
how to interpret
the essence of a select statement
but it will run
all of the examples that we'll talk about in this
lecture in the next
so that's one option for you to get started
our first step is to get some data in some tables
and so we'll use a select statement for that
using literal expressions
in order to declare which data we want
how select statement always includes a
comma separated list
of column descriptions
a column description is an expression
optionally followed by as
and a name
so I can say select
expression tells me what I'm selecting
and then as name name tells me the name of the column
and if I put a comma there
and some more expression as names
then I'll have multiple columns in the result
so this would create a two column table
as and the name are optional
you can have more of these
whenever you're done declaring different columns
you should put a semicolon at the end
all of sequel statements end in a semicolon
if you select literals
which are expressions like the No.2
or the string berkeley
that will create a one row table
but if you want to create a multi road table
you can union together two select statements
the union of two select statements is another table
but it contains the rows of both
you can only union together
tables that have the same number of columns
and the same type of information in each column
but the two select statements that your union together
don't need to have the same names for the columns
it will just use the names
of the first select statement
in order to name the columns in the final result
okay I promised your dogs
let's pretend I have a lot of dogs
so many that I need to put them in a database
and I like to name my dogs alphabetically
naturally so that I can keep track of them
and I also really like us presidents
then I might have a dog named abraham
and a dog named barack
and I might put those into a table
so a select statement
with literals abraham and barack will create
a one row table
with two columns a parent column and a child column
and the values that go in those
are the values of the literals
abraham the string and barack the string
now if I have more dogs which I do
then I'll need to union
instead of putting the semicolin at the end
and write out
the other rows
that I want to include in the final result
so if I also select abraham comma clinton
that will add another rope that says
abraham is the parent of clinton
and over here
I'm just drawing the family tree of all my dogs
delano's the parent of herbert
filmore's the parent of abraham
filmore's the parent of delano
filmore's the parent of grover
and eisenhower's the parent of filmore
there is no
interesting historical allegory going on here
I just picked this structure arbitrarily
and I picked the names because they go from a to h
so over here on the left is a valid sequel statement
and it will create a table with seven rows
two columns a parent and a child column
and
these are the data that will be stored in those ropes
now
sequel is often uses an interactive language
you just want to see what's in the database
and so
by default the result of a select statement
or a bunch of select statements
union together
won't be stored
the result of a select
statement is displayed to the user instead
if you want to store it
give it a name and be able to use it later
you need a create table statement
so create table just says create table
give the name of the table and then as
and you can write any select statement there you want
so here's one big select statement
if I write create table parents as
conventionally I will indent this
although that's not necessary
spacing is totally arbitrary
I've only spaced things out in this way
so that it's easy to read
this is also a fully correct
sequel statement
that creates a table cult
parents with this data inside
and if we wanted to draw that out explicitly
we might write something like parents
with a parent column and a child column
and all this stuff inside
now that we know how to create tables from scratch
let's talk about projecting tables
so select statements can project existing tables
into new tables
a select statement can specify an input
using a from claws
so I told you that select statements look like this
expression is name expression is names
these together
are all just descriptions of the columns of the result
select statements can have other
things than just column descriptions
the from claws says which table
are going to take crows from
in order to create these columns
a subset of the rows of the input table can be selected
using a ware claws
so I could say from somewhere
where some condition holds
and then I'll only get
some of the rows from this table
and in what order
while an ordering over the remaining rows
can be declared using an order by claws
so now we can see
that there are lots of different parts
to a select statement
column descriptions determine how each input row
that remains after you
filter it with where and order it with order by
is projected into a result row
so every select statement creates a new table
with rows and columns
the columns are described here
the rows that we choose are here
but the input rows get transformed or projected
into the output rows
so imagine I have my parents table
which I already told you about
and then I read another select statement
select child from parents
parents is the name of the table
that contains these data
where parent equals abraham
well here are all of the different child parent pairs
where the parent is abraham
and the children are barack and clinton
so by executing this select statement
will get a table
with a child column with barack and clinton as the rose
if instead I said to select parent from parents
where parent is greater than child
comparison of string values
will choose their alphabetical order
so this has parent is later in the alphabet than child
what will be created in the output table
we'll have a table with a single column
the parent column
which will contain
all of the different parents
that come later in the alphabet than their children
fillmore comes after abraham
fillmore also comes after delano
there aren't any other cases like that
and so we get fillmore twice
so here we can see it's possible to have the same row
in terms of its values
repeated multiple times in the table
let's actually execute these different statements
and watch how they work
I'm going to use the online sequel interpreter
here is the create table statement for parents
if I execute it
then parents is defined
I could select
all of the columns as shorthand for all of the columns
from parents
in order to see what's in that table
and it says that parent and child are the two columns
and here's all the data within
so if I want to select the child
from parents where
the parent is named abraham
executing that will give me barack and clinton
if instead I want the parent
where the parent
is greater than the child
we see that fillmore appears twice
it's certainly also possible
to investigate all of these examples in sequel light
from the command line
I can create the table that I talked about before
and then select star
from parents to get the entire table
which is printed out
as values separated by vertical bars
if I only want the child
from parents where the parent is abraham
I'll get bar rock and clinton
select statements can perform arithmetic
in a select expression
column names evaluate to row values
and arithmetic expressions can
combine row values and constance together
to create new values
we're going to do an example based on
chairlifts at ski resorts
let's say that every lift chair has a number
and it also has the number of single riders
and the number of couples riding the chairlift
so this table would describe for example that chair 101
has two single riders and two couples
here shown in green and blue
chair one oh two is three different couples
and one oh three is mostly single riders
okay let's say I wanted to check
the total number of people on each chair
I would write select the chair number
and then an arithmetic expression
single plus two times couple
which is going to evaluate for each row
the total number of people on the chair
so here is a row
this chair has 2+2 times two equals six people in total
matching this picture
and in fact
it turns out that each row has six people in total
just in different configurations as we can see
now at no point in evaluating this select statement
did I mix together
numbers from different rows
instead I computed this output row from this input row
this output row from this input row etc
and I used the names of columns
to select the values in each row
and then combine them here with a constant
and do some multiplication and addition
here's the discussion question
given the table ince
that describes how to some powers of two
to form various integers
compute the following
well before I show you what to compute
let's take a look at this table
so this gives the word names of various integers
it turns out that each positive integer
can be expressed as a sum
of powers of two
and in fact
there's only one way to do so for each integer
this table is just enumerating how to
express each of these integers
as sums of powers of two
where the first four powers of two are one two
four and eight
so for example
we can make seven
by adding together one and two and four
or I can make five by adding together one and four
so the four column either has zero
if zero isn't included in building up this number here
or it has a four
and you can probably
start to see the pattern
of how to construct integers out of
powers of two
just by scanning what's going on in these columns
okay so on to the questions
write a select statement for a two column table
of the word and value for each integer
so it should say that the value for three is three
and include this value for every element here
and when you're finished with that
write a different
select statement
for the word names of the powers of two
so given a table with this structure
how would you build the words one two four and eight
but leave out
five and seven because they're not powers of two
think about it for a moment
then we'll go through it together
here's the table of vince
if I start sql light
I can load that table and look at it using select star
from its
notice something quite interesting
these rows don't appear in the order
that I wrote them out in the first place
when your union together a bunch of select statements
you get no guarantees about the order of the result
that's up to the declarative programming engine
which tries to compute the result efficiently
now one thing that union does is it discards repeats
and the way that it discards repeats in some cases
is to sort all the rows
to look for whether there's repetition
and that's exactly what happened here
so you can see that it's
written all of these in an
alphabetical order according to the word
which is not what I asked for in the first place
but that's what I got
and this is one of the properties of declarative
programming languages
there's no particular procedure
that's defined in advance
that tells me how to compute the result
of unioning together a bunch of select statements
instead it's up to the system
to create the correct result
and this is the correct result
in whatever way it chooses
and that might involve building the table
in a different order than you might expect
okay moving on
to the question of how to write a select statement
that gives the value for each word
well I need to sum up all of the numbers in each row
and I do that by using their column names
so one plus two plus four plus eight
as value and I select these from the ins table
now even though
these are names that appear in this column
that doesn't matter
it's always the case that a select
statement's expression
will be referring to a column names these one
two four and eight appear
the 2nd question was how do I select only the words
from the ins table that are powers of two
well in order to do that I need to write a wear clothes
that's true only for the rows that are powers of two
and I can find those rows by finding rows where
one of these numbers is positive and the rest are zero
one way I thought to compute that
was just to add up all of the values in the rows
but divide out
two here so that it looks more like 0 0 1 1 0 0 1 1
and divide by four here so that these all become
ones as well
once I've done that
I can check whether exactly one of them
is one by computing the sum and checking its equality
and there they are the powers of two