61 a lecture No.29
announcements
homework six is due to day
homework seven will be posted to morrow
it's due next Thursday
there's just more scheme problems
midterb two regrade requests are due on Monday
and that's all that's going on right now
but next week we'll release project four for the course
so things are going to get a little bit busier
but the version of project for this semester
won't be quite as involved as it has been in the past
just to help make sure that you can manage your time
and focus on the stuff that's most important
today's lecture is directly related to project four
because in project four
you're going to build a scheme interpreter
and today will be the first of two lectures that
describe how you structure an interpreter
for a programming language
we're now going to shift our focus in this course
to talking about programming languages
and interpreters
where an interpreter is a program that takes as input
the code written in a programming language
and executes to that code
in order to create the behavior
described by the program
and there are many different
programming languages that have been invented over time
and so far in this course
we've talked about python a great deal
and scheme a little bit
I taught you about scheme for two reasons
one it's a delightfully useful
simple and effective programming language
that still gets used today even for new projects
and it's a dialect of lisp
which is used even more broadly
either as a standalone application development language
or as an embedded language
that implements part of a program
that also uses some other language
but the second reason
is that it
is a programming language that's very powerful
but has few rules
and so you will be able to
build an interpreter for the scheme language
by writing down a python program
that describes
all of the rules of interpretation for the language
and interpreters bring together
many ideas in this course
programs or trees
and the way interpreters work is through tree recursion
expressions often have lists of sub expressions
the input to a interpreter is another program
which is kind of like a higher order function
and interpreters can be modular and extensible
part of your interpreter program will describe
how interpretation works generally
and another part
will encapsulate all the details
of how the different parts of the language
actually execute
so with that introduction
let's talk a little bit about programming languages
a computer typically
executes programs written in many different
programming languages
there are what are called machine languages
in machine languages
the statements are interpreted by the hardware itself
computers have a central processing unit
which can execute a fixed set of instructions
and has a limited availability of its own memory
and then ways to access more memory
in the
caches and main memory and discs of the computer
but to extend a machine language
you actually have to change
the circuitry of the computer
which does not happen very often
these languages are hard to program in
operations refer to specific hardware memory addresses
and there's basically no abstraction mechanism
no way to give things names
and no way to implement procedures or functions
that's all left to high level languages
which have statements and expressions
that are interpreted by another program
or they are compiled into another language
interpreting involves reading the program
and executing its behavior
while compiling involves translating it
into another language
such as a machine language
so that it can be executed later
and many modern languages do a mixture of both of these
compiling parts
just in time in order to be executed
as if they were being interpreted interactively
but those details you can worry about in a later course
the important part is to know
that high level languages provide means of abstraction
such as giving names to values
and functions and objects and classes
that's all part of high level languages
now people describe different levels of height
some languages are higher level than others
but those details you could try to study
in later classes
the important thing to know
is that there isn't a piece of hardware
in your computer
that was designed for scheme or python
instead machine language
code needs to actually execute all of the behavior
and an interpreter or compiler in between
the high level language like pythonor scheme
and the low level machine language
needs to implement all of these means of abstraction
but it's very common that
high level languages will be built on top of other
high level languages
a machine language might be used
to implement a compiler
for the c language
which is a high level language
used to build the interpreter for python
for example
high level languages are easy to program it
because they provide means of abstraction
and they also abstract away certain system details
so that you can write the same program and have it run
on different machines
made by different hardware manufacturers
or run inside different operating systems
created by different companies or organizations
in python what happens is that it's actually
compiled just before its run
into something called python three bite code
you can see this bite code
using the dismodule that's built into python
and then there's an interpreter
that runs this lower level language
which is quite similar to a machine language
but also abstracts away some system details
so the story of how a program in a programming language
gets executed
can be kind of complicated
but the distinction between
what your machine can execute
and what you as a human tend to write
is an important one
everything we've learned in this course
is about high level languages
that are used to build software today
sometimes people invent new programming languages
a powerful form of abstraction
is to define a new language
that is tailored to a particular type of application
or a particular problem domain
for example
there is a programming language called airline
that was designed for concurrent programs
how is it the case that people can use
atms all around the world
and the balance of their bank account
is stored in some particular place
but if you try to
withdraw money from
two different atms in two different cities
for the same bank account at the same time
there's no way to trick it into paying you twice
that's a kind of concurrent communication problem
that would benefit
from having a specialized programming language
an airline is also used for example
to implement
chat servers with many simultaneous connections
where lots of people
are talking to lots of other people
and the program has to keep it all straight
another problem
specific language is the media wiki markup language
which was
designed for generating static web pages that you see
on Wikipedia
it has built in elements for formatting text
linking one page to another
and stitching together multiple pages into one
so that a large page can be broken out
into modular components
it's a programming language
perhaps not as full featured as python or scheme
but it still needs an interpreter or compiler
in order to be used to generate
the Wikipedia pages that people read
a programming language
has a syntax
which is the description of all legal statements
and expressions in the language
so that's the form of the language
and then also the semantics
which is the execution or evaluation rules
for all of those statements and expressions
the meaning of the language
and these two together give you a programming language
to create a new programming language
you either need to write down a formal specification
as a document
that describes the precise syntax
and semantics of the language
or you need to build an
implementation of an interpreter or compiler for
the language which serves as the reference
to describe the syntax and semantics
any input into the canonical implementation
that doesn't cause it to crash
would be legal syntax
and its behavior would define the semantics
scheme is a language that started with a specification
and an implementation of the interpreter came later
python began is a canonical implementation
and then a formal description of how it works
was developed over time based on that implementation
most programming languages that are used in practice
for large communities
have both a specification and an implementation
let's talk a little bit more about what
parsing and tails
so parsing is the process of taking text input
which represents a computer program
or some other
formal language expressions
and turns those
into some sort of object
that represents the expressions
while validating
their syntax
a parser takes text and returns expressions
and it does it
through an intermediate
called tokens
so lexical analysis is the process of breaking up text
into tokens which are words or individual symbols
and then we do a sycantactic analysis
to figure out how those symbols nest
into hierarchical expressions
so let's look at some examples here
let's say I typed in the following three lines
open per end plus one
and then on the next line
minus 23 and on the next line
we have another sub expression times four or 5.6
and then closing prentices there closes this one
then we finally have the closing prentices
for the original
opening prentices to lines before
the process of lexical analysis
breaks up each line
into the right pieces for input into syntactic analysis
these are the pieces that represent all numbers
or special symbols like prentices
or symbols in the language such as plus
so this line becomes these three tokens
white space is ignored
this line becomes 1 2 3 4 tokens
so notice that 23 is all one token
because it's all one number
so lexical analysis is doing some work
it's figuring out that two and three
next to each other really means the number 23
now notice that this has ignored the white
space in the front
so part of
lexical analysis is figuring out what to discard
and it's put together 23
okay let's look at that 3rd line
how many different tokens are there in this line
1 2 3 4 5 6
so each closed parenthesis is its separate token
because it's a special symbol
that has some meaning in the language
and these need to be balanced
that's going to be the job of this syntactic analyzer
to figure out
but the lexical analyzers figure out that 5.6
is really all one token
so this is an integrative process
it goes through each line and breaks it up into tokens
it checks for malform tokens
it determines the type of each token
so it's figured out that this is a symbol
whereas this is a number
and it processes one line at a time
that's lexical analysis
syntactic analysis
processes all of these lines together to give us
an expression in the language
that we're trying to parse
so the result will be
a pair where the first element is plus
and the rest of the pair
is everything else in these three lines
which can be printed as plus one minus two
three times four
five point six
now we've done more than just to lead all the wide
spaces and put it on one line
we've actually figured out the structure of this thing
balanced all the parentheses
meaning we verified
that they were balanced in the input
and
created this nested pair structure
which happens to be printed out in a nice clean way
and scheme expressions
so this is a tree recursive process
it balances parentheses
it returns a tree structure represented by pairs
and it processes multiple lines
so recursive syntactic analysis is
a standard problem in computer science
it shows up all the time
and we're gonna build a particular kind of parser
for the scheme expressions that we want to parse
it's called a predictive recursive descent parser
and that's special because it only needs to inspect
k tokens to decide how to proceed
meaning what sort of structure is going to build
and it does this for some fixed k
meaning it never needs to look vap far ahead
in order to
understand what's going on in the program right now
so let's try a recursive descent parser
on the English language
can English be parsed be a predictive recursive descent
well how about this sentence
the horse race past the barn fell
what
well actually this is a well formed sentence in English
it's just a little bit unusual
here let me tell you how to read this sentence
think about raised as a synonym for ridden
like I raised my horse means rode my horse
and that was has been omitted from this sentence
which you can do
the
boat that I was sailing
is the same as saying the boat I was sailing
so that can be dropped
and so now
think of this
sentence as the horse that was ridden past the barn
fep poor horse
so this whole thing is a sentence subject
it was in the original version of the sentence
is just a little bit easier to read
now that I've changed the sentence slightly
to have exactly the same meaning as it had before
now the reason this is a hard sentence to read
is that when you read the horse race past the barn
you've assumed
a structural analysis
that as this is the verb this is the subject
and this is a modifier of the verb
telling you where the horse raced
but it was not the horse that was racing at all
somebody was racing the horse
but we had to look all the way down here
to the word fell in order to resolve
that structural ambiguity
so English language
is not something that you can
parse for the recursive descent parser
but fortunately
scheme expressions are
so syntactic analysis in scheme expressions
and in programming languages in general
can use recursive descent parsers
and what it does is it identifies
the hierarchical structure of an expression
which may have some nestings
each call the scheme read which we saw briefly before
consumes the input tokens for exactly one expression
the base case is that you find just a simple
or a number
but there's a recursive call
whenever you see
an open parenthesis
then you know that's a combination with
expressions within it
and each one must be schemebread itself
so when I have an expression that's nested like this
my first call to scheme read
will notice that
I've started a combination
and therefore will have a sequence
of sub expressions
until I close that parenthesis
the first one is a base case just plus
the next one is a base case just one
but the next call to scheme read
is going to do a bunch of work
it's going to read the whole next expression
which is this thing in parentheses
the next call will read the next sub expression
and then finally it will have found the end
of the expression that it started in the beginning
that's how scheme read works
okay so let's read the code really quickly together
scheme read some source tokens
if we ran out of tokens
then that's called an end of file error
otherwise get the first token
source dot pop
if it's mill that's a base case
if val is not in dilimeters
meaning it's not one of an open parana clothes parana
quoth or a dot
then we would just return that value
so that's when we get
numbers and symbols as a base case
otherwise if we've just opened up
a combination with an open parenthesis
then we have more work to do
what do we do
or we return the remainder of the list in source
starting before
an element or close parenthesis
okay
so if we run out of text here that's a syntax error
but if we find a close parenthesis to match the open
parentheses and that's a base case and we're done
otherwise we find the first element the rest
and return a pair containing the first and the rest
and first is a recursive call to scheme read
which means that if I read
nested expressions it looks like this
what happens is I find this
recursively call reed tail
which it calls scheme reed
to read this expression
which is used as the first element in this pair
then the second element is a pair of three mill
giving us the rest of the list
okay time to create a programming language
called the scheme syntex calculator
it's a simple one but that's where we start
when it's something that just
performs arithmetic just like a calculator would
okay so the source code is on the right
we're gonna go through almost all of it today
but let's see what this program does first
so I run python
in order to start up my interpreter
for the calculator language
now notice that we don't have the normal python
prompt here instead we have a calculator prompt
calculator allows me to type in scheme expressions
and as long as the operators are just plus
minus times and divide
it will evaluate those for me
so it just multiplied one
two and three together to get six
just adding gives a zero just like a skim
and we can have nested combinations
so there's one plus two and four divided by eight
hopefully add two and one half together
we get two and a half
and this can span multiple lines
and I can use whatever spacing I want
so if I add the result of one negative twenty three
four
and two point five
and that's it then I'll get -12
so here are some more examples
you can see that there are
some aero handling that happens as
part of the interpreter
we'll talk about this later on
let's talk about how to get
the core functionality working
so we rely heavily on the pair class
to represent expressions in this language
and the pair class represents scheme pairs and lists
a list is a pair
whose 2nd element is either a list or nil
so there's only one class
that represents both pairs and scheme lists
it's something that has two instance attributes
first and 2nd
first can store anything
it's the value in the first element of the pair
the 2nd can also store anything
but when it stores a well formed list
then the whole thing is a well formed list
so for a pair to be a well formed list
2nd is either a well formed list or nil
the empty list
and some of the message that exist on the pair class
only apply to well formed lists
so let's take a look
if I create a bunch of nested pairs
remember this is back into the python interpreter
with the triple carrot
I create this structure and I print it out
I get the scheme list representation
that's the string version of a pair
and the length of this
is a method as a special method on pair
that only applies
when pair represents a well formed list
this well formed list has three elements
Paris can also represent
non well formed lists or things with thoughts in them
here's an example is just the pair one two
it's not a well formed list because two is not a list
or nil
and likewise
if I nest this thing inside of something else
I still have a dotted
expression something that's not a well formed list
and that means I cannot take the length of it
okay so this is a pair class implemented in python
used to represent scheme pairs and lists
scheme expressions
such as plus one to the combination
are represented as scheme lists
meaning that the data
representation in the language is the same as the
source code representation
and that means that the language is called homo iconic
meaning this source code is just data
in the built in structure in the language
okay so now we know what we're going to use
in order to implement this stuff
let's talk about the two elements of the calculator
language its syntax and semantics
its syntax is that it has
primitive expressions and call expressions
that's all
a primitive expression is a number
and a call expression is a combination
that begins
with one of the four operators in the language
plus minus times and divide
followed by zero or more expressions
so we can add together three primitive expressions
or a primitive and a call expression
so that's the syntax of the language
those are the things we're allowed to write
so expressions are represented as scheme lists
which are just pair instances
just like we just saw
but they're encoding tree structures
so let's look at an example
and think about how it's encoded
and how we can think about it
so here's an expression
three times the sum of four and five
times the product of six seven and eight
think of this as in coding an expression treat
that's what it's going on
saying is we're going to multiply three things here
there are one two and three
and the first one is just the No.3
the second one is the samba four and five
and so this is a tree structure that's expressed
by this expression
but if we actually look into our interpreter and see
how this expression is represented
it's represented as pears
and pears have a first and 2nd attribute
and when they are linked together in this way
they form lists
so the whole expression
is three followed by
something followed by something else
and that's something in something else
are the two branches of this tree that follow three
so if we look at this branch
it's a plus and then four and five
that's this expression here
and time 6 7 8 appears here as another scheme list
so we have a scheme list
that has a number as its first element
a scheme list is its 2nd element
and another scheme list as its 3rd element
and by nesting things in this way
will form expression treats
okay that's the syntax
of the language and how we will represent it in
programs let's talk about what it means
the value of a calculator expression is defined
recursively
how primitive is a base case
a number evaluates to itself
a call expression
evaluates to its argument values
combined by an operator
now how do we get those argument values
while those are the values of the operand expressions
now how do we combine argument values
well
if the operator is plus then we just sum the arguments
if it's times then we take a product of the arguments
minus has some special cases
if there's only one argument we'd negate it
if there's more than one
then we subtract the rest from the first
and divide has a similar structure
if there's one argument we invert it
so divide two becomes just one half
if there's more than one
then we divide the rest from the first
okay
so here's an expression and here's an expression tree
we've used only the two simple operators this time
the way in which this gets evaluated
is that first we have to find
the value of all the up brand sub expressions
here and here
which means recursive definition
those are call expressions themselves
and so plus four five
is the sum of four and five
which we'll give last nine
what's the product of six seven and eight
that's three thirty six
and what's the product of these three arguments
three nine and three thirty six that's 9072
okay
enough talk let's actually implement this language
by creating interpreter for it
so the eval function
evaluates an expression in the language
represented as a scheme list
it computes the value of an expression
and the value of an expression
in the calculator language
is always a number
the eval function itself is a generic function
that dispatches on the type of the expression
whether it's a primitive expression or
a call expression
so the implementation
the code is actually going to be on the left
and then we'll
match that up to the language
semantics that we just introduced
so here's the program
it says cal gival
is the function that takes in an expression
that expression will either be primitive or call
expression
if it's primitive
meaning the type is either an end or a float
then we evaluate it by just returning that same number
so a number evaluates to itself
according to the language semantics
and here's the lines of
code that actually implement that fact
otherwise
if it's the case that the expression is a pair
meaning it's a scheme list
then we get the arguments to the call expression
by mapping the calcute valve function
over the rest of the list
now what is this expert this point
well it should be a list that starts with an operator
such as plus and is followed by a bunch of
other expressions that are the operand sub expressions
so evaluating each of those
gives us all of the values
that are the arguments that will pass it
when we evaluate the operator
and then finally we're going to call another function
calc apply
that takes the plus and applies it to the arguments
so a call expression evaluates to its argument values
and we get those argument values by recursively calling
calci val on each sub expression
combined by an operator
and this is expert out first as the operator
that gets combined with its arguments using some other
function calc apply
which will look at on the next light
so what are the important parts here
wherever recursive call
returns a number for each operand
so an operandic sub expression could be some complex
expression a call expression
but we reduce it to a number by calling calcavel
calcupi does the work
of figuring out whether we should add or multiply
or subtract
expert out first
is a symbol representing what operation to take
and the arguments will be a scheme list of numbers
then we get by calling calcuval on each sub expression
okay
the one part we've left out is calc apply
so the apply function apply some operation
to a scheme list of argument values
in calculator
all the operations are built in
and they correspond to these four built in operators
in other programming languages that allow
different kinds of abstraction
we might have to worry about user defined
operations and names for things
and we'll get there
but for now there's only these four things we can do
so here's the implementation
it just decides which operator were looking at
and then carries out the combination method
that combines the arguments in that way
so I've removed a bunch of the source code
we can look at the whole thing in a minute
but the basic structure is that
calcoply takes in some operator
such as plus minus times are divide
and some arguments
and then it does what it's supposed to do
so for plus
it adds together all those arguments starting with zero
for minus it's either going to subtract
all the rest from the first
or negate the first depending on how many
arguments there are etc
so part of the language
semantic says that plus sums the arguments
that minus does something else
and times and divide
and all of those
have corresponding
source code in the implementation of calc apply
okay
so let's look at these
calcaval we saw almost all of the details up already
the only difference is that we call simplify
in order to turn eight point o into just eight
and we write out a string for the type error
like calcoply has more going on
so let's look at the whole thing
and at the same time we can
run some examples
so
if the operator is not a string
then we should complete
type air two is not a simple
if the operator is plus
then we reduce starting with zero
and adding in everything else
if it's minus
then if there are no arguments at all
we should raise a type bear
otherwise
if there's only one argument we should negate it
-2
finally we reduce by subtracting
all of the rest of the arguments from the first one
if I start with 10
and then I subtract one two and three
I end up with four
multiplication just reduces the list of arguments
using multiplication as a means of combination
and division is very much like subtraction
we can't divide nothing
we can invert a single argument or we can divide
out of 1024
a bunch of numbers
and so dividing out to
five different times gives us only 32
for me
otherwise
we should say that something is an unknown operator
christian mark is an unknown operator
so we've covered all the cases here using calk apply
in order to do all the work
of figuring out how to apply an operator
so there's just one
important piece we have yet to cover
and that's the user interface for the interpreter
how should it be hate
so interpreters typically have what's called a reed
eval print loop
so the user interface for a programming language
is this interactive loop where you enter an expression
and then it gets evaluate
so here's the process of a redeveled print loop
print a prompt telling the user that
the computer's ready for its input
read text input from the user
parse that text into an expression
or statement
evaluate that expression
if any errors occur report those errors
otherwise print the value of the expression and repeat
printing another prompt
so that redevelop print loop
is a way that a person can interact with the program
ming language
by typing expressions into its interpreter
and seeing the values
and that's exactly what we're doing here
so as you can see we type in an expression
it gets evaluated
what code is actually doing that
well we have a read about print loop
which forever
tries to read in some text from the user
and while there's more text remaining
it parses the expression using the scheme read function
which gives us back an expression
represented as a scheme list
and then call as caucaval on that expression
in order to evaluate it
and prints the result
now notice that print will only happen
if there aren't any exceptions raised during
calcive out because if there are exceptions
then this won't actually have a valley
now throughout the program we raise exceptions
exceptions are raised within
all aspects of an interpreter
lexical analysis syntactic analysis evow and apply
so for example
when we reach the token two point three point four
which is not a well form number
we might get a value error
syntax analysis is in charge of making sure
that structurally our expressions are correct
so having an extra close parenthesis over asan
syntax errors are an unexpected token
eval make sure that we're only dealing with
two types of expressions
primitive and call expressions
and so for instance it can detect things like
noticing that there's an empty combination
which is not a number or a call expression
and then apply
actually does quite a bit of error checking
because it actually knows
which operator is being applied
and what are the rules for those operators
so it can find that if there are no arguments to minus
we should raise a type error
that says minus requires at least one argument
so in the version of
calculator that we've built all of these things apply
we get a value error
we get a syntax error
we can get a type bear
and we can get a type bear
that tells me
specifically for this operator that I've chosen
I need at least one argument
and if you look at the source code
these are raised all over the place
oh here's a raising of the tight bear
here's another type bear
but some of these are even in different files
and some of them
will actually be raised by python itself
so what happens if I divide one by zero
then I'll get a zero division error
which is something that happens
when you use the built in division function
that we're using to implement divide
so divide
is carried out by the built in division
or the built intrudive operator
and both of those are able to raise
zero division errors when they run into trouble
now handling exceptions happens all in one place
in contrast to raising exceptions
which happens all over the place
so an interactive interpreter
should print information about each error
so that when those errors occur
the programmer whose generated them
can figure out what to change
in order to get rid of the error
and a well designed interactive interpreter
should never really halt
it should stop
evaluating the current expression
and print out the arrow
but then give the programmer a chance
to revise what they've done
so the user should have the opportunity to try
again in the current environment
instead of having the whole program crash
and that's exactly what happens here
so as you can see
I'm able to continue entering expressions
the only way I can quit out of this game calculator
is by pressing in my
system control d which says this is the end of the file
and then it will say calculation is complete
and finally the program will end
now how do we control for all this
well we put both the parsing and evaluation
within a tri statement
that knows to look for syntax
type value and zero division errors
all the things that can occur
and just prints those errors out
and then since this is all embedded within
the suite of a while statement
we'll go back and try again
so the only way to stop is to reach the end of a file
or a keyboard interrupt at which point it will print
calculation is complete