61a lecture 19 q a
hey john let me ask a question while we
wait for somebody to chime in
when object oriented first started this
notion of inheriting classes was very
popular and
i think sort of was a big motivating
factor and you had this nice lecture at
the end
where you you talked about how
complicated it gets
like what's the what's the thinking
these days with object oriented
i've always found that once you get
beyond one or two classes of inheritance
it just becomes unruly
like where are things these days uh
good question i think that um there are
definitely people who think that
inheritance should be completely avoided
yeah um a more but that's sort of an
extremist view i would say
a more common belief is that
inheriting methods is fine it's
inheriting
attributes that's complicated because
um yeah if you don't know where the
attribute was originally declared then
it's hard to kind of keep track of
what's going on
so i i see programs where
yeah like functionality defined by a
bunch of methods
is inherited sometimes even multiple
inheritance inheritances allowed there
but you just want to be careful about
like having attributes defined in one
place
and then having a subclass that like
tries to ignore some of those attributes
because it's different enough that you
don't want them all
that gets messy pretty fast and it's
usually better to just use composition
instead
yeah that sounds about right i have to
say i think i'm much more likely to use
composition than inheritance that's
really common
sure so the question is about this
complicated example
and what's going on um and in particular
there was an example at the end about b
dot
z dot z dot z and why is that right but
four z's is wrong and two z's is wrong
and one 1z is wrong
once you have the right picture then
solving these problems is not so bad
so let's say that we had already gone
through the work to draw a picture like
this about what's going on
then let's talk about how dot
expressions are evaluated
this dot expression b.z.z.z
is taking the dot z of something but you
don't know what it is
until you compute it and to compute it
you have to evaluate b dot z dot z
but you can't do that until you know
what b dot z is you can't do that so you
know what b
is b is just a name so that's something
we've been able to handle since the
first week of class
we look in the global frame we see that
b is this thing
this object is a sketch of what it would
look like to have an
instance with a particular class so this
has the b
class and a bunch of instance attributes
in this case there's one called z
and one called n we're gonna access the
one called
z which brings us to
this object happens to be another
b instance so this thing one way to
refer to it is
b z how did i get there i went to b
and then i went to it's z and i got to
this object
now it also happens to have a z
attribute
it's not like this is related to this
one in any way they just happen to have
the same name
okay so when you look at what's bs.z.z
we have to follow this and figure out
what we get and then we get this object
so is the answer b.z.z
an integer no b z dot z
is an instance of the c class so it's
some object that's not an integer
but it happens to have an attribute
whose name is
z and its value is one so if you
evaluate
b's z
[Music]
z z you get a number
a number one so that's why which of
these evaluates to an integer happens to
be b
z zero z as opposed to one of these
other ones if you were to take
that integer and look for its dot z you
would get an error
integers don't have z attributes and if
you were to do either of these other
ones what you'd get back is one of these
objects along the way so b
is an object b dot z is an object b dot
z z is an object
it's only b does easy z that gives you a
number okay so sometimes there are these
long chains
and uh we're just following them
basically looking at this from left to
right
what's really going on is that we're
figuring out what object to finally get
the dot z
of but to do that we have to figure out
what object would to get this dot z of
what object to get this dot z of and so
you end up working from left to right in
order to find the answer
by the way don't ever write code that
looks like this ever
this is a good pedagogical example but
this is not what your code should look
like
that is that is certainly true okay
so now let's back up a little bit and
figure out how we got here
in the first place we started with this
long example and maybe we'll work our
way up to a
z equals b dot z by saying there's a
class a
there's a class b there's a class c
there's an instance of
a there's an instance of b and then this
doesn't create a new instance at all
this just is an attribute assignment so
this is changing the b
object to have an attribute called n
which is value 5.
this expression does create a new object
but i'm not sure that's the interesting
one so
when you execute a class statement you
get a new class
when you execute this class statement
you get a new class
you get a new class so this has all
happened before we actually
made an instance of anything when you
make an instance
that creates some object now we're
giving it a name
using uh an assignment statement so this
is called a
and remember that when you create this
thing you have to execute its
appropriate init method it happens to be
that the a class doesn't have an init
method
so there's kind of nothing nothing
special about this
object it has no attributes at the
moment
this one on the other hand when we
create b we're
um calling the b class
oh sorry somebody needs to mute i think
hold on i'm gonna start muting people
when we call b then um
we create an instance of the b class but
we do have to
um call its init method because it has
one
and this is what always happens when you
create a new object
you um start it out as a blank slate and
then you start
passing it in as well as any arguments
to
the original constructor so y would be
bound to one
self would be bound to this b instance
and then we check if
y is true which it is so we set self.z
to something and i put this dot at that
because
we actually don't really need to figure
out what this does um
in order to answer the question of
whether a dot z equals b
z okay so
let's see what we can learn about this
structure
if we look at a and try to find
its dot z we first look at its
instance attributes it has none
so if we're looking for its z we look
next
in its class it's an instance of the a
class
so we find that it does have a z the z
is the value negative one
so that's what a dot z would evaluate to
what about b z
sorry b is this thing when we look up
dot z for the b object we look first at
its instance attributes
and it has one i didn't bother to figure
out what it was yet
but i'm pretty sure it's not negative
one um
so b dot z will give you whatever this
object is if we finish the evaluation
um we would have to go through and
figure out what self.f returns
and uh we did that eventually in lecture
it returned
this other b instance so what this is
evaluating is
is a dot z which is negative 1 equal to
b z which is this b instance
and the answer is no like a number is
never going to be equal to
uh some object
yeah so let's sketch this out and then
we'll answer your question and the
question is about if you're using
composition instead of inheritance how
do you access the attributes of the
elements of something so if you have an
account
which has a balance
and we have a bank
which is not a subclass of account it's
just its own thing
and when we create a bank we'll just
have
a set of accounts which starts out as
empty
and then we have like open account this
is a little different than what was in
the lecture but it's pretty close
so um
what open account is going to do is it's
going to create a new account
with whatever name was passed into the
bank so the bank gets the name and uses
the name to
create an account and now uh
how do we figure out how much money is
in that account
this is sort of the minimal example if i
have
a bank and i
open an account for
myself i don't have a name for that
account
i can't access it directly because it's
not in the global frame
the only thing that's in the global
frame is the bank
but the bank has a list of accounts
and there's now something in that list
so if i go into that list of accounts
and get the element at index zero
whose account is that that's john's
account
and how much money is in it zero dollars
because we haven't deposited anything
into it
so the answer in general to your
question of like when you're using
composition how do you access
attributes of the parts is often using
some like chain of dot expressions
where instead of having a name for this
account
you have an expression that's like some
compound expression for this account
that goes in and gets part of the
goldman
the bank finds his list of accounts gets
its thing
and then gets its balance now we could
have had a
method that does this instead that would
have been fine
um but this is kind of the minimal
example of how you would
access some piece of the composed bank
you can think about the account as just
being as john just said one level
removed from you instead of having a
global variable
that where you created the account it's
now stored in a list
inside of another object
so now look at the command object
goldman
list accounts get the element sub zero
what is that
that's now an object of type account and
now you can do whatever you want with it
you can you can access the
member function you can access the data
it's as if you as if we had just written
uh john's account equals goldman dot
account sub zero
that's that object now now it's all the
same thing yeah so just levels of
interruption you have to follow
yeah good question so the question is
can you use a syntax to refer to a
method
that just states which class contains
that method
then the method name and then call it
where you explicitly pass in the object
that you want to call it on and the
answer is yes so um
if you have an account there's really
the normal way of depositing into it
which is that you would refer to the
method
by using a dot expression with the
object that you're interested in
and you could think of this as shorthand
for
find the class of a
and deposit into that using a
as the account itself and 12 dollars as
the amount
in fact uh you could write this out if
you really wanted to
get the type a is a an account and
deposit into that
12 now you wouldn't write this
because it's just like a more
complicated version of this
it's allowed because this happens to be
just a function
this function you've defined here and so
you can call it as a function
but there isn't really a good reason to
do it uh there happens to be when you're
using inheritance
occasionally a reason to reference
things that you've overridden
and this is one way to do it and so
there's like an occasion where you would
actually
do this kind of thing but it is allowed
otherwise it's just not something that i
think is
is normally done yeah i think it would
be considered poor form if you wrote
that
it's i think you should avoid that
because it's just it's not something
that most programmers would would
would sort of do and you know i mean
even though things are allowed doesn't
mean you
shouldn't necessarily do them but it
does illustrate you know what is this
doing
it's basically doing that it's getting
some function
and filling in a yeah
good question so what is super which is
some built-in function
that really is quite magical in my
opinion
um in terms of what it does so it's
better to describe what it does instead
of how it does it
but what it does is it says when you
look up this method
for uh
this is kind of related to self let's
say self is a checking account
when you look up its withdraw method
skip the one that's in the checking
account class
and go find the one in the account class
instead
we could have said this explicitly we
could have said go find the one in the
account class if we kind of knew where
to look
this is asking python to find it for you
saying you know python you know about
you know what the parent
the super class of or base class of
checking account
is so why don't you go find that version
of withdraw
that's what this says and um this
actually wasn't always the syntax in
python there was like a different
version of this in python 2 i think
it works fine people do use it and
it's a very subtle thing it's basically
saying
i want something that's just like self
except for it ignores the withdrawal
within the checking account and all goes
and finds the one that was there before
checking account was ever defined which
um you know you could say that
explicitly go find the accounts withdraw
or you could have python look it up for
you is it weird john that you don't have
to pass self when you use the
supernotation
yeah so that's an interesting thing is
that super isn't
referring to the account class it's like
referring to a version of self as if
account where it's
class instead of checking account where
it's class so it's doing two things at
once it's going and finding the account
class
and it's also filling in self for the
withdraw method
so that you don't have to pass it in
explicitly
it is a lot to just like have a
built-in function call with no arguments
and somehow it does all that magic
that is what it is so you know you don't
have to memorize this we don't
test you on it or anything like that
this one is a little bit more explicit
but it does mean that you have to be
redundant you have to say like oh
the account is this base class and
that's the thing that i want to get the
withdrawal function from
yeah great question and that's exactly
right so if there weren't
a duplication or an overriding of
withdrawal
where it existed in both checking
account and the base class account
then you wouldn't need super this is
strictly a thing for when you have
inheritance
and you're using the same method name in
both the subclass and the base class
although i would argue you probably
should still do it as sort of a built-in
documentation
so that the user doesn't have to like
you know scroll through your class to
figure out which one it's sort of nice
the thing i like about the making the
explicit is you're telling
somebody which one is it going to as
opposed to relying on
some default and then what if somebody
actually comes in and puts up a draw
function later on
i mean do you so sometimes it's good to
make things explicit even if there's a
default um
response you know yeah
but one thing i would say is like if you
have a deposit twice which is like
totally new
which is fine your your subclass can
have totally new stuff in it um
and what you want to do is deposit this
amount twice
you can just write self.deposit that
amount
and then do it again you don't really
need to use any supers here or anything
like that
and you can trust that python will look
it up for you correctly
yeah good question so the question was
in this example
if we made an a but we passed in some
argument when trying to construct an a
would you get an error
and the answer is yes since there's no
in it
um it's not expecting any arguments
so um by the way i've always thought
this was weird that python let you build
a class without a constructor
it is kind of a funny thing but if we
have no constructor if it's just like
no constructor here
yeah strangely enough if you had an
account
that you've managed to create correct
successfully
while it doesn't have a balance you
could give it one later
so while this is possible it's rarely
terribly useful
the next question was do you have to
call init init with the underscores or
could you call it something else
you have to use the inet it's not a
convention because
when you call the constructor it has to
know which function to call
and that's a special name and it always
has to be underscore underscore net
underscore underscore
the next question was whether you're
supposed to know all of the special
method names in python
like underscore underscore init
underscore underscore
and some other ones that we haven't
covered yet like underscore underscore
stir
underscore underscore and the general
answer is that we will cover this
on wednesday tell you what you need to
know and what you don't know but here's
our answer
well you have to know the constructors
because you can't really build a class
without you can't build an object
without them
and the str function is just what
happens when you call
print on an object that's not
fundamentally defined
and so you should know how those
functions work and and then but there's
no
so yes you absolutely should know how
the the constructor and the print
functions work or the str and the init
functions yeah
so we'll go over the stir and wrapper
functions in wednesday's lecture along
with a couple of others
you don't have to know all of the
special method names there's like a
long list of stuff that's built into
python
and uh we'll give you a kind of overview
of what they all are in wednesday's
lecture but
you're not expected to memorize them all
but the ones that create
string representations are particularly
important and as well as in it
okay so um the question was
why does this multiple inheritance
version of an account
give you only 19 when you deposit 20
well in fact you've paid a
two dollar fee somewhere
because there was one dollar in there
already
so depositing 20 should get you to 21.
but instead it got you to 19 somehow
why is that well let's look back at the
code
we came up with a savings account which
has a deposit fee of two dollars
and what happens when you deposit into
your savings account
is that you actually deposit the twenty
dollars minus two
so we deposited eighteen dollars we had
one that's how we got to nineteen
why is it that this deposit got called
instead of accounts deposit
well um when
you're finding which method to call you
look
in the class first of the thing that
you're
depositing into and if you don't find it
there
then you look into its base classes
and then only after you've looked into
its base classes do you look in the base
class of the base class which would find
you the accounts deposit method which
doesn't do this
nasty thing of taking out a deposit fee
so um yeah so basically you're finding
methods
here well there kind of aren't any
except for the init
then here then here and then the account
class and why the account class even
though it's not listed here
well that's because it's the base class
of these
that's right in general and multiple
inheritance
you'd look in both of these before you
ever looked in
the base class of one of these so think
of it like a tree
there's the account class at the root it
has two subclasses checking and savings
and then you have a subclass you're just
going to work your way back up the tree
and if you're wondering whether it ever
gets messy to figure out which thing
happens first
the answer is definitely yes in fact
like
python's now on its third version of how
to resolve this question and because
there were bugs in the first two so
uh don't worry about it this is beyond
the scope of the course but
multiple inheritance does leave lots of
uh computer scientists scratching their
heads about what's exactly going to
happen which is why in general you
should try to avoid it
yeah i agree i think one level of
inheritance is is more than i even care
for but i don't think
you should be very careful when you go
beyond that yeah so the question is
is this slide have anything to do with
midterms this did come from a past
midterm um so the
we won't ask this kind of question
because um
you know you could just run it and see
what happens um
i think this semester we're just going
to focus more on getting things done
rather than knowing exactly the
mechanics but exactly the mechanics of
how the object system works as we've
described it is part of the course
so you should know it um but i would
guess there's more of a focus this
semester on like
you know building things implementing
things rather than tracing through a
complicated example
because of the online format and and
that's fine for
life as well because you know getting
things done is is more important than
understanding
my very convoluted code uh but you know
there will be cases in which you find
some complicated things out there in the
world and you have to trace through them
so that is a useful skill to develop
yeah good question so how do you keep
track of what's an instance attribute
and what's a class attribute and which
one's which
i think instance attributes are just
generally more common
because usually when you're creating
objects you really want to focus on
what's true about this particular object
and you just store that state as
instance attributes but it's not like
class attributes
don't show up once in a while so you
certainly have to know about them
uh this particular case where an
instance attribute and a class attribute
share a name
does show up in practice usually when
you're trying to get something to do
a different behavior than was originally
intended so you want to
like change the way this particular
instance works so that it behaves
differently than
whoever wrote the class and that you
know
that is to be avoided when possible but
sometimes when you're building off of
other people's code and you can't get
them to change it then you have to
change it yourself by adding an instance
attribute that's got the same name as
their class attribute
so it's not like this never happens uh
in practice but
it's the rarest of the three cases so
most common everything's an instance
attribute
second most common yeah there's class
attributes out there but they have
different names than the instance
attributes
and then the third case is it is
possible that you have a name collision
and you should know what happens
yeah so the question is about this
maximum subsequence question
from lab four question five
uh if you try to trace it you get quite
confused because there's just like a lot
of calls going on and how does it all
fit together
so how else might you understand the
implementation
well i'd say at the outset that it's
often the case that tracing through
uh tree recursion is not something that
humans
can tolerate like it's it's just
really messy sometimes um so the right
answer is to shift the way in which you
approach understanding
uh implementation to get away from
tracing and instead just treat the
recursive calls as abstractions they do
the thing that they're supposed to do
but how they do them is not your problem
and then like you can put it together
but this is not
not like obvious or easy so um so maybe
we can talk about that with a particular
example so
maybe while i read this maybe hani can
uh say whether that makes sense to him
i i'll add one more thing to it so
john's absolutely right that
tracing tree recursion is very hard you
have to hold a lot in your memory
um so one one way to fix it is as he
just said
is to just think differently about it
it's not about tracing it's about
thinking about the fundamental nature of
um
the the functions and they just do what
you want them to do and the other is to
just use toy examples
so if you have really small inputs you
can sometimes hold on to the recursion a
little bit easier
as opposed to something like this that
has you know a ridiculous
number of steps so um i do think that it
does require a slightly different way of
thinking as opposed to just drawing the
environment map and mapping everything
out
line by line yeah
that is actually great advice is like
you know
think about maybe a two or three digit
example if you want to trace it
don't trace a five digit example for
something that's going to do something
with every digit it's just going to get
too messy
so how would this go return the maximum
sub queen sequence of a
length at most t that can be found in
the given number
n
[Music]
well if t is zero then i think we only
have one choice
which is to not take any of the digits
of n at all
but then we have to decide like are we
keeping the first digit of n
or i guess the last edge of n is the
easiest thing to access because we can
access it like that are we keeping the
last digit of n
or not so um
i think it's helpful to pick a value for
n
so let's say n is one two three
and t is two something like that
what would n percent ten give you just
mark it up
like this will give you three that part
i think is worth tracing
and the rest if we divide by 10 gives
you
12. i think you know those pieces
you should trace explicitly now what do
you do
well you're either going to take two
digits from 12
or you're going to take one digit from
12 and the 3
at the end so that would be like keep
the 3
but then you'd have one less digit for
the rest of it or
you'd forget the three and you keep both
the last digits now
you know you can think ahead you can say
okay what i should do is
is keep the three because it's big but
python doesn't know that yet
so avoid the instinct of solving the
problem for
python and instead just like let the
computer
work through the details itself so you
have the components
now it's your job to say well i have two
options
option one let's say like
keep last digit is option one
which would mean that three is the last
digit
of this new number how do you get it in
there
you add it but then this expression here
needs to be all the other digits and so
it's got to have a 0 in its one's place
that's where that times 10 came from
and how do you get the rest of the
digits well that's where you make your
recursive call
get your maximum subsequence of the rest
using t minus one because you already
used up
a digit the last digit and you don't
need these parentheses i was just trying
to kind of guide things as we go
um this i think you could trace in the
following way
instead of looking at the body of max
subsequence
you should ask yourself if i pass in 12
and 1 into here what am i going to get
and you know the behavior of this thing
you know you're going to get 2
so 2 times 10 plus 3 is going to give
you 23.
that's the degree to which it makes
sense to trace is to pretend that this
is some black box that does its thing
but you don't know how it does it
but you do know what its result is which
is like what's the biggest digit in 12
well it's two and then the other option
is would be leave the
how about drop last digit which means
you're not going to use last you're just
going to use everything in rest but you
get to use t digits
and if you wanted to return the biggest
one then you just take the max of these
two
when you're tracing through this you
want to say like oh what's this going to
return
well this is 12 and this is 2 so this is
going to return 12.
and so uh what's this going to return
well the max of 12 and 23 is 23. so at
least in this example it seems like it's
going to do the right thing
that's the kind of tracing that i would
do in a tree recursive problem
and we realized that we never went back
through the body of max subsequence
again
instead we just asked ourselves what is
this going to return and stop there
so there's that big leap of faith right
where you have to just
trust that what you're doing is doing
the right thing and by the way if you're
wrong well then the code won't work
and so it like that uh hold on
oh i think there's another one yeah
oh how about that there we go
sorry a good chapter
yeah so anyway that's uh that's kind of
the story
is don't don't try to trace through the
next call because you're just going to
get confused
if you want to let python draw the
environment diagram for you so you can
watch it happen that would be fine
but doing it by hand is really really