61a lecture 31 q a
so uh the question is if you already
have
some procedure that takes x and y
like adds them together and you
then want to convert this into a
procedure
that takes only one argument and holds
the other one
constant could you do that by saying
lambda x is a procedure which
takes x and calls g on whatever that
x is and three
and here we have indeed created a
procedure now
we either need to call it or give it a
name i think we should just give it a
name
that seems easier so now we have a one
argument procedure that adds three to
things
so if i call f on seven then i get ten
so like the longer version of this would
be
if instead of setting this equal to
three we set it equal to
some y and where is that y well it's
coming in here
now we have kind of a curried version of
g
so if we call this h h is the kind of
thing
that you have to call in order to get a
procedure and then when you
call that procedure then you're finally
adding three and seven
together i think they're equivalent yeah
those are the same things
one more level of indirection for you
yeah the next question was what
validate procedure does in the scheme
project
it's a python function so here's what it
does
is it um you call it and
it raises an error or it returns none
so you can never really do anything with
the result of validate procedures so you
wouldn't use it inside and if
you just call it to make sure that the
argument that you have
is really a procedure as opposed to some
other weird list
yeah good question so the question's
about this uh
data eight module called data science
which
we built for the course here
and whether it's really just running sql
under the hood
it's not but we borrow the names for a
reason
i think that these standard operations
that you perform on a table
like joining or wait i guess we'll do
joins on
monday but like uh the where to filter
it
and select in order to get particular
columns
um there are standard operations
and because sql is the most popular
programming language in the world
those are the conventional names for
them at this point i mean
sometimes maybe instead of calling it
where you might call it filter
but i think the sql names are kind of
the most common names that people have
for these different table operations so
you see them showing up
in lots of different modules not just
the data eight one
as the description of how you manipulate
tables using another programming
language
and this notion of declarative
programming and manipulating tables
is not specific to sql like it it shows
up in lots of different programming
languages
um oftentimes what is happening is that
you're just running you're like
converting python into sql
and then running that sql that's
actually not what's happening in data
eight you're just kind of running python
code
but we set it up this way so that you
could convert it to instead run sql if
you wanted to
in fact we had plans to do that for a
while but we never really got around to
it
uh yeah a good question so the question
is if you have a list of values
like you have uh
my values are one and two
and what you'd really like to do is add
one too but instead of
passing in each of these we want to say
i want to add
all the stuff that's in the list of
values well this won't work
because plus expects two arguments
and uh here we're passing only one it
expects numbers here we're passing in a
list
so what do you do and the answer is that
there's a built-in procedure called
apply which says uh apply plus to these
values and then it basically
constructs that and evaluates it
yeah so just a like follow up on this
example that we had before with apply
let's say we wanted to define
uh sum which takes a list of
let's call them params and what does it
do
well we want to like add
and then have like all the params in
here well
we would just write apply plus to the
params
and the next question i have appreciated
the terms linear
a list of values are used in the letters
added together
so i don't think we're doing a lot of
runtime complexity
so we're not going to go into too much
detail here but here's the basic idea
when you measure runtime complexity you
measure it as a function of the size of
the input
yeah so how many numbers do i want to
add
okay that's the size of the input um i
want to sort of list
how many elements are in the list i want
to select something from a table
how many rows are in the table right so
the size of the data
is how we specify the complexity
if something is linear in the size of
the input
it means that every time you add an
element to the size of your data your
uh complexity increases linearly
proportional to that so if i double the
size of the input
my runtime is double if i quadruple the
side of the input
my runtime is 100 volts right so if you
think about
measuring a slot that has the size of
your data on the horizontal axis
and the run and how long it takes to run
on the vertical axis
linear literally means it's linear right
it grows linearly with that that's good
that's really nice it means things don't
get out of control
it's not great but it's good uh
logarithmic
means that it does this it slows down
um as as the data gets larger that's
really really nice quadratic is the
opposite
it means that if i double the size of
the data my complexity increases by a
factor of four
because it's two squared um so the so
the quadratics think about sort of a
point like a
a parabola as you increase n
your complexity starts going faster and
faster and faster
really that is exponential it goes with
2 to the power as opposed to n to the
power
so there's sort of a couple of
categories of runtime complexity there's
constant time
that's amazing no matter how big the
database is it takes constant time
there's a logarithmic time very very
slow growth very good
linear good polynomial which means n
squared n cubed n to the fourth n to the
fifth
okay but it's going to be problem for
large databases
and then exponential which is a disaster
because
or or um factorial which is a disaster
because as soon as n gets to even a
relatively small number
the whole thing breaks down so those are
sort of the rough categories
and that's what what john meant when he
was referring to quadratic versus linear
and i think maybe the reason that
surprised you is that we
made the um
the lecture on efficiency optional so if
you missed that along the way that's
fine this semester you'll do lots of it
in 61b
if you take that class but if you want
like a 45 minute
version of what honey just said which
you don't need but if you really want it
then there's that efficiency lecture
sitting there in the schedule from like
some time before midterm too
the next question is what is this thing
called nosql
and how does it relate to sql i'll give
you my spiel on this and i'm curious
what john thinks so
sql is an actual database
program but it's also been used to refer
to a class
of types of databases so there are
databases are called nosql
which just means they're not using sql
um
and then within sql there's mysql their
sql their sql lite those are all
essentially variants on the same basic
underlying
uh database management system with some
bells and whistles either included
or excluded i think we're you can we're
just learning sql it's
you don't have to worry about which
specific version of it is
yeah and the funny thing about nosql
databases is that oftentimes they still
use something that looks almost exactly
like sql
in order to access them yeah but they
don't come with the same
guarantees about what happens when
multiple different programs
access the database at the same time
that's basically the main story about
nosql is that in order to make sure that
nothing breaks when multiple different
computers are all accessing the database
at the same time
you have to slow some of those processes
down
like some stuff has to wait for other
stuff in order to
make sure that like nothing gets
confused along the way
um and nosql tends to relax that
um in in various ways and so
uh the nice thing is that if you relax
these kinds of constraints
then you could have applications grow up
to a much larger scale and still be fast
you know but the downside is it might be
the case that if you check your email
it doesn't show you all the emails that
have been delivered yet
because um you know of some like weird
synchronization issue
and you know you'll see it eventually
but you might not see it right away so
um it's it's a great topic
for taking a database course or a data
management course
there's a new one being developed here
that's just being piloted
this next semester we also have a
standard database course that focuses
more on sql but doesn't talk too much i
think about
the nosql variants but you know it's
more branding than anything else they
called it nosql to try to make sure that
it was
distinct in people's minds but it's not
like what you learn about sql doesn't
apply
in fact all the operations that you
learn in sql are basically the same
there as well and i'm not a database
actor my understanding
is that sql does start to break down for
very very large databases um because of
the guarantees and you do need to move
to
something that is not as strict if
you're going to have these
google size facebook size massive
database with
databases with terabytes and petabytes
it's just you have to do something a
little bit
uh different to really get them together
i don't know where things start breaking
down specifically but
really really large databases tend not
to be sql isn't that right john
yeah but people have also figured out
how to get very
quite large databases to to run in like
a standard sql-based
uh database like you know last time i
checked uber's data was still running
through sql and like they had a whole
lot of cars driving around and so you'd
think that was maybe too big but in fact
it's not because it's nicely partitioned
in into different cities
and so um so it turns out that like they
can manage their
their data using sort of a more standard
classical method anyway um
it's uh the right thing to do is learn
sql well
and then learn these variants once you
kind of know the
the core that everybody else knows yeah
i think that's exactly right
the next question was is sql a fast
language or is it slow
sql is a fast language in the following
sense
you you can write a query
that in principle appears to have to do
a lot of work
and the database engine will figure out
the fastest way to execute that
and it will execute it quickly in the
sense that
um you know most database engines are
written in some programming language
that's supposed to run very fast like c
or something like that and so
uh you usually don't pay any kind of
time cost for using sql
in a big application because that's like
a fast way to do it
it's not fast in the following two ways
one
if you're actually like computing
something inside your sql query like
you're doing
tons of arithmetic well that's usually a
bad idea
um you know it's it's a language that's
meant to express
operations over whole tables that
doesn't involve
like going through each line and keeping
a running total
but like you know if you're ever like
trying to write something procedurally
in sql
sometimes you can't even do it and if
you did do it it'd probably be slow
so you know you have to kind of stick
with the right model which is
you know take the table process all the
rows aggregate them
we'll do that next wednesday and then
now you've built your new table
so um the other way it's slow
is that if it's the case that many
different computers are all trying to
access the same database at once
it tries to ensure
these various consistency properties
that
um mean that some of them have to wait
for other ones to finish
so basically like you can't have two
programs writing to the same row at the
same time you can't even have one
writing to the row and another one
reading to the row
and um so in that sense it can be slower
than
some nosql variant but that you know
that usually doesn't apply because
usually you don't have a program where
like
thousands of different computers are all
accessing the database at the same time
but sometimes you do
um and there's a third way it's slow
which is that if you don't set up your
database right
then it can be much slower than it needs
to be so there's a whole topic we won't
get to in this course
about indexing the data in order to make
sure that common queries are fast
a lot of this actually just happens
automatically in a modern
database management system so you don't
always have to think about it much but
sometimes you do
and in that case like there is
performance optimization that happens in
databases
where you have to kind of look and see
oh why is it slow but then usually you
can make it faster as opposed to being
stuck with it being slow
and no sql databases have the same thing
you have to think carefully when you're
building the database and how to make
them efficient
um so they have the same indexing
limitations as well
but there's nothing about sql that's
kind of inherently slow in the way that
python might be
where like the basic operation could be
done faster by some other programming
language
the next question is why does sql
conventionally capitalize
its keywords like select and where
and how come we don't do that in 61a
i'll let you listen to the whole answer
but we don't do it in 61a basically
because i forgot
but you know the more recently created
examples do use
all caps for select and where and it is
a common convention so you might as well
pick it up
i don't know that john do you know the
history of it's true that all simple
commands are all
always caps i don't know the history of
that it just makes me a convention but
maybe there's another story behind it
yeah i don't know either i mean people
were writing sql queries
long before there were text editors that
automatically highlighted the syntax for
you
and stuff like that so the
capitalization scheme is a nice way to
distinguish between
you know what's part of the language and
what's specific to
your database you know like because
you're just interleaving names like
select with names like
person where person describes some
column in the table
and so this capitalization scheme kind
of keeps those distinct which i think is
good
sql was designed to be a programming
language that not just programmers would
write
but like it was meant to be accessible
to
you know analysts who maybe didn't know
that much about programming
but needed to access the database so i
think the history of some of these
design choices was motivated by making
it like
appealing to a general audience i guess
they succeeded in the sense that a lot
of people use this programming language
but it's um
it's a little funny and it's it's all
caps character
and in this class like we don't always
capitalize everything
in my demos because uh
yeah i don't know i just didn't think
about this convention very much when i
started
building these demos uh but i think you
know capitalizing the keywords like
select
and uh where is usually a good
convention you might as well do that
yeah my recollection john is back in the
days when we wrote fortran
code there was also a convention of
capitalizing i wonder if it came from
there
yeah they're kind of from the same
vintage i guess yeah they're about the
same ventures too
by the way i i use all caps whenever i
have constants
in my code python code matlab code c
code
and like so you will see that kind of
capitalization
used in classic comparative programming
to
to sort of have things stand out it's
not functions but it's things like
constants for example are often done
with all caps
yeah so the question is how could you
have a row but not fill in all the
values
there is a way to have missing values
um in a sql table but it makes your life
a lot more complicated
if you're ever missing values so i mean
effectively you can put like a none
value in there and how do you do it i
don't actually remember at the moment
but
certainly it's possible to like build an
empty row
and then fill it in later we'll talk
about the commands for
changing a row next friday in the
optional
lecture where we talk like so far we
never changed any rows right we just
had a table and then we built a new
table and we built a new table but once
you built a table
you know all the values were there and
they never changed
but it is possible to perform mutation
operations on a database table where you
basically say like oh
this person's name changed from steven
to steve
and you can make that edit and there's a
command
called update which does that so it's
certainly possible to fill in stuff
after you create it and it's also
possible to have empty
cells like basically non-values um
but but john's like a good idea to avoid
it
it's a yeah this is one thing with sql
tables
generally is they have uniform
columns you can't just sort of pick and
choose now there's other databases where
you can have
variable number of columns per row
and varied data types and sql is a very
disciplined language which
allows it to sort of be efficient so i
think it's at its best when there is
data
and it's the same format and and and so
i
i tend to think of that as i didn't i
knew that there was a none option but i
don't i don't know how to do it either
but i
i don't think i've ever done that when
i've done cpr always it's always when
i'm using a database like that it is
fully populated
yeah but sometimes you just you know you
don't know someone's address so you need
like a blank in there and that
that does exist but we won't talk about
it in this course
the next question was about courses does
it make sense to take
61b and 16a
in the same semester john has more
experiences than i do but
let me let me just share a few thoughts
one is i think part of this depends on
your comfort with math
so if you feel really comfortable with
discrete math and linear algebra
and things like that maybe it's okay i
think it's a lot
i'm told john will know more about this
that 61b is is a lot of class
and i think 16a is also a fair amount of
class
um so i think part of it sort of depends
on your comfort level with the
underlying material you can go look at
the syllabus now and see you know how
foreign it all seems but i don't i'm
curious what john recommends
yeah so the combination of 16a
and 61b is reasonable in the sense that
i wouldn't say no student should ever do
this like it's a reasonable combination
but
61b tends to be quite time intensive
um 16a is always
at least somewhat time intensive you
know there's a lot to learn in that
course
but also depending on students math
background it can be quite intense just
because
it's often their kind of first college
math class
and then again for other students
they've already taken a college math
class they kind of know the rhythm
or um yeah or if
you had kind of strong preparation in
high school then it could be smoother
so one thing i would say is that
finding the pace that's right for you is
much more important than doing what's
good for like
the average student so if it turns out
and this isn't really
particularly advice for you this is just
kind of general advice it for any
student that discovers like oh it's
better to kind of take one technical
course a term instead of two
um or uh you know only one programming
course and a math course
but you kind of don't want the math
course to be too intense if the
programming course is intense or
whatever it is
that gives you kind of a comfortable way
to understand all the material
not fall behind kind of master things as
you go
even if they're brand new that's the way
to do college
i think cramming in a bunch of stuff in
a semester is almost never a good idea
um unless you know if you're familiar
with all of it a little bit
um and so you can handle you know a lot
and actually like learn the material
then it's fine to take more courses
but um taking so many courses that you
can't keep up
is just not a good idea ever yeah but i
want to emphasize something here and
then there's a question in the chat
which we'll respond to
is there's there's depths and breadth in
your education
and it's easy to get breadth just you
know take a
bunch of courses you know but you really
also
you want to think a little bit about the
quality of this course it's not about
just getting through it's not about just
getting the grade it really is about
understanding the stuff
and particularly early on in your
academic career everything builds
on previous courses these these courses
don't stand alone
you're building a scaffolding that you
eventually have to climb up against
um and so it's really really important
to make sure that
it's high quality um light touch at the
beginning
in my opinion is sql databases used
internally in programs
what comes to mind is lightroom kettle
photo catalog that keeps track of
thousands of images and several gigabyte
data
uh i don't know about lightning in
particular but i imagine the answer is
yes
um the sql is used internally to keep
track of these types of databases john
probably knows more about this
yeah the particular database management
system we're using in this course sqlite
was designed to be embedded in the sense
that it's part of a larger application
that's not necessarily written in all
sql
but does do data storage using
the sql approach and
it all gets stored in a file so
you know instead of a programmer having
to invent their own file format for
storing all these records about you know
photos
and when they were taken and whatever
you just
use sqlite and python we'll see next
friday
has a built-in sqlite interface which
means that you can
within a python program send data to
your sqlite database
and make queries and get the data back
out so
and this is very common it's not the
only way sometimes there's a good reason
to
invent your own kind of data management
approach usually if what you're doing
with the data is so simple that all you
have to do is just like
write down a big column and then like
read that column
then you're not going to use sql but as
soon as you have
multiple tables that might reference
each other
then there's kind of no reason to invent
your own way
of doing this you just embed some
existing sql based system like sqlite or
you know there's there's other options
too
great question so like what are the
constraints on what values you can put
within a column in
in sql here there is actually quite a
bit of variety
when you look at different database
management systems and
sqlite's kind of an outlier and that
lets you sort of
not specify too much about what the data
format is in advance
whereas a lot of popular database
management systems require you to not
only say like
this is going to be a string but to
decide on the maximum length of the
string that you'll ever put in there
um and uh if you can do this in advance
if you know like oh this is going to be
a
you know 14 character string because you
know it's someone's driver's license
number and they're never longer than
that
then that can add to the efficiency of
the system but
it leads to problems if all of a sudden
like you know some uh
some state decides they're going to use
even longer license
driver's license codes and they don't
fit in your slot anymore so
there's no one answer to this question
of like what are the constraints
it will depend on the database
management system sqlite you can learn
about the constraints there
um i think strings can have arbitrary
length
and uh so there's nothing kind of really
special about them
but you have to kind of relearn this for
whatever other database management
system you're using whether it's mysql
or postgres or something like that that
you run into in the future
yeah i think if i recall john sequel has
a very strict you have to define
everything like
how big the integers are going to be how
big the strings are going to be
everything has to be defined up front
yeah i think both both mysql and
postgres
do this and yeah anything that's really
designed for very
large database data sets that are going
to be accessed
by multiple programs and this is kind of
the central hub for a whole service
tends to make you decide
a lot about your data in advance yeah
where sql light is sort of design
designed for moderate size stuff you
know it can fit on one computer pretty
easily
um and there they give you some more
flexibility yeah yeah that's right
hmm a good question so is the standard
to like
create an empty grid and then fill in
the values
or do you always sort of build it um at
once
i i'd say what's common is that you
often create a table with no rows
but a particular set of columns like
you've come up with their names
and you know how many columns there are
and then you add the rows one by one
but when you add a row you add it with
the data in it i think that's the most
common way
that tables are built that's not what we
did today in lecture instead we kind of
built the columns and the rows all at
once but we will do this
on friday i'll show you how to kind of
build a table more incrementally
and as far as like building a grid and
then adding stuff later
i think that's relatively unusual
typically you don't know how many rows
there will be in advance
because you know it depends what happens
in the course of the program and so
tables grow over time you add more rows
because you know
you add a row every time some new user
shows up or something like that
and so you know the columns in advance
but the rows get added incrementally
the next two questions were logistical
so i'll just answer them here
one was can you work alone or do you
have to work with a partner no you can
work alone
and if you're working alone and then you
find a partner you could merge your work
with them that's okay
the second was are there checkpoints for
the challenge version and the answer is
no there are no checkpoints for the
challenge version
you just have to complete the whole
thing by the deadline or get an early
submission bonus point
and then i'm gave some opinions about
the challenge version in general here we
go
just for everybody out there thinking
about doing the challenge version
you know the regular version is plenty
of work you don't need to do the
challenge version
in fact maybe you do the regular version
and then do the challenge version in
your own time
uh over winter break would be a more
reasonable thing so only if you're
finding that the projects are just kind
of too simple and too structured for you
and um and you're tired of doing it that
way then yeah maybe do the challenge
version but
don't do it just because uh just because
it's there
yeah good question so it's like is there
any way to have a value in sql
be something that's kind of changing all
the time or could be
mutated by another program i think the
answer is no i think the way these are
set up
is that they're just kind of static
values in the table
another program can go change those
values so it can like change
you know someone's name from you know
henry to hank or something like that
but um but i don't think there's a way
to have
the values themselves be kind of mutable
things that change over yeah like on the
fly like every time you query a cell it
generates a random number i don't
i don't think you can do that or salts a
data by adding something
i don't i don't think you can do that in
sql but what does often happen is you'll
have a table
where each row is like a different
version of the same thing
and you have a column for what version
it is and then you have a column for
what the value is now
and uh every time you kind of make an
update you know your
encryption key changes daily or
something like that
then you'd add another row to this thing
which says oh now the current value is
whatever for this particular day and so
even without
dynamic changes you can get that kind of
dynamic flavor just by kind of storing
more data
you can change you can change a cell you
can change data in a table
it's that's fine i mean it's not it's
not like once you add a row
no the data can't change you can update
that
um the other thing you can do is instead
of having age of a person
be the row you could have
a row represent a person at a particular
time yeah
and that means they have an age at that
particular time where one column stores
the time
you know in 2006 i was 26
and then there's another row that says
in 2007 i was
27 and um so in that sense
you can you can keep track of changes
over time just by more rows
by having your row not represent the
thing that's changing but instead what
the thing was like at a particular
snapshot in time
and have the time be one of the values