61a lecture 30 q a
just before i started recording we were
talking about the first interpreter and
compiler uh i just did a quick google
search and
it the first hit is with from chris
hopper
talking about the first compiler uh
if you don't know who grace hopper is
you should search for her name
um and read about her she's this really
remarkable woman who was in the
was it the navy john i believe so yeah
yeah
in the navy who was one of the most
influential computer scientists in the
early days
there's this great um youtube video of
her i think on
david letterman show talking about
computers and it's wonderful just
wonderful she's fantastic
i never saw that i should go find it
yeah look for letterman and i think it
was letterman and grace hopper let me
let me verify that
yeah it's letterman it's from the
obviously like the 80s or something
and she she's fantastic and letterman is
an idiot
um which is you know what makes it so
great
[Laughter]
we can keep talking about grace popper i
can talk to her about her for like
another hour that's some fun with that
by the way for the for the young women
on the call there is a yearly grace
hopper
conference uh for um new computer
scientists
of all stages and it's a wonderful
yearly program
to attend and many people from berkeley
go
so uh yeah and i think there's a lot of
resources to help support uh travel and
yeah there's support from the department
their support from
grace hopper conference itself um so
people find a mix of ways to go but a
lot of folks do end up going
yeah before i got here we used to send
just dozens and dozens of students and
they just they wouldn't stop talking
about it when they got back
okay so uh this week's lab
is about building an interpreter
just like a small one so um
the one that you'll build is kind of
like the calculator that we did on
friday
except for that it has one extra very
important feature
which is that you can define procedures
and then
call them so here's an example
is defining a procedure that adds x and
y and then you add x and y okay not that
exciting
but you could for example build a
curried version of mole and then call it
twice and then end up multiplying the
values together
so there's this diagram which
describes how you get from the input
that would be this to the output
that would be this which involves all
these steps
so um
the lexer is the part that finds the
individual pieces those will be
the name add the open parenthesis
the number three the comma the number
four
and the closed parenthesis it does a
little bit more than just like pick
every character
because for example it treats add as a
whole name
and if you have the well we don't have
any two-digit numbers but if you have a
two-digit number it will treat it as
just one thing
the parser is the next step that takes
as input the output of the lexer which
gives you all these different pieces
and builds an expression and the
expression is represented
according to however the interpreter
wants to represent an expression but
expressions are always tree structured
meaning like there's this whole
expression and it's made up of
this operator and these operand sub
expressions
and then eval does the work of
evaluating the expression so the nice
thing about a parser is it gives you a
tree structured thing
and evaluation is a tree structured
process and what do i mean by a tree
structured process
well in order to evaluate this you have
to evaluate
this and this and this
so um like every expression
either is a primitive where you just
evaluate it immediately that's kind of a
base case
or it's a combination like this is
or like this is one huge expression and
the way you evaluate this is you
evaluate its parts
so that would be this part and this part
and this part
and then if it turns out that the
expression you've evaluated as a call
expression
then you have to apply the value of the
operator
to the values of the operands
so the reason that this has arrows going
back and forth
is that sometimes the process of
applying
a function means you have to evaluate
some stuff
and there's really only one case here
what you evaluate
is the body of the expression you're
applying
so eval the whole thing means you have
to eval that
eval that eval that now you know you
have
a function and two numbers you apply
this function to those two numbers what
does that mean well that means create a
new frame
where y is bound to three and a oh sorry
where x is bound to three
and y is bound to five and then eval
the body of the procedure of the
function
once you hit the base cases and kind of
pass the return values up eventually you
get the value of the entire expression
which is then automatically printed out
so that's the print part
is really simple just like make sure
that whatever the value of this whole
thing is is displayed
a great question so like when you're
writing scheme
and you're calling some f you're calling
it on
uh plus two three
are there cases where you need to quote
this or don't need to quote it
like what's the story there well
i'll give some simple cases first and
then maybe we can think of some other
ones together
if you have a sub expression like this
this actually says call one as if it
were a procedure which is not
so the reason you often see a quotation
mark before
a list of numbers for example is that
you'll get an error regardless of what f
is even if f isn't defined yet
um well i guess then you'll get the
error about f not being defined but
you know whatever this is absolute value
you're going to have this problem that
says int is not callable
and so you got to quote that now this
will still give you an error which says
that
it doesn't like the way that we called
abs but
um let's say we were doing something
more useful like the cutter of this list
now we finally have something that works
um
the simplest rule is if you're trying to
do work in order to figure out what to
pass in
then you shouldn't quote it so if we're
like building something up
then we don't need to quote that because
we need to evaluate this whole
expression in order to get the data
the list one two three before we pass it
in and if instead
we're just trying to pass data
indirectly then we should quote it
so that's like covers most cases
and the only case that really doesn't
cover is when you're trying to treat
code as data which occasionally people
do in scheme
and that's one of the interesting things
about the language it's also one of the
things that's very new
so uh don't worry if it's a little
disconcerting now
but like um you can't get the cutter
of a number
but you could get a cutter of a list
and why might you want to do this well
maybe what you really want to do is like
take this expression but change the plus
to a times
well you could do that by putting
the time symbol on the front of the rest
of two
three so like this thing
kind of thing is possible you can build
up expressions
by treating them as lists at which point
you need to quote it
and here's probably the most tricky part
about this whole quotation is when do
you quote
symbols and when don't you quote symbols
and the answer is
do you want to pass in what this is
bound to or do you want to pass in the
symbol itself
so if i didn't quote it what i would be
putting in this list
is a procedure that multiplies which
isn't
like something that would ever show up
in
the source code of a program this is no
longer an expression
this is some mixture of numbers and
procedures
and if what i really wanted was an
expression then i would have needed to
quote it so basically the story is with
symbols
do you want to pass in the symbol itself
or do you want to pass in what it's
bound to
um if you want to pass in what it's
bound to then just write the symbol and
it will be evaluated for you meaning get
the value
of whatever it's bound to and if you
just want the symbol itself then you
have to quote it
and in python it's not exactly the same
but we have a similar type of contract
which is strings
right when you put things in quotes
those are not interpreted those are
literally passed around
it's not exactly the same thing as the
quote but that's same concept is that
you're not interpreting what it is
you're just you're
encoding it directly yeah exactly
um in the lecture videos you introduce a
new frame
class to handle the scheme environment
would it be possible to
populate python's environment directly
or is that not possibly
or a bad idea is that not possible or a
bad idea
would be possible to populate python's
environment directly oh i see
yeah it's a good question so like how
would you create
a python frame to represent the scheme
frame
well you'd make a python function call
and so you'd make this python function
call
with the right formal parameters
and the right arguments and then you
would
get a python frame somewhere in the
python interpreter
but you can't really refer to that
python frame all you can really do
is use it to look up python
names so the reason why
in the scheme interpreter that we use
here we're going to
explicitly represent frames using
dictionaries
is that you can give a dictionary a name
you can write code in python that says
here's exactly what i want to do with
this
uh frame i want to use it next i want to
pass it in to apply
i want to look up a name within it i
want to bind a new name within it
like you have full control whereas if
instead you were trying to use the
python interpreter's notion of frames
the only way to create one would be to
call a python function with the right
arguments and you'd have to like create
a function that has the right
formal parameters but then even then you
couldn't really
do anything with that frame you couldn't
give it a name
and pass it around and say oh i want to
add one more
symbol to it or something like that
that's a cool idea though john that you
could
use frames as objects that you could
sort of move around
and say evaluate in this frame
right and uh scheme has a feature that
does exactly this
that we don't talk about it wasn't even
covered in the
version of 61a back when everything was
in scheme this is kind of
very i remember that yeah um but uh
yeah there's this there's this notion of
um
yeah calling you can call
something in a particular environment
and have a
symbol bound to that environment and you
can pass environments around so
like in python we say functions are
first class meaning we can give them
names they can be arguments you can do
anything that you want well in scheme
environments are
first class too if you really set it up
that way and
why would you ever want this well it
turns out might be useful for building
an interpreter
the most common way that is used is
actually to implement something like an
exception mechanism because
like then you know exceptions are all
about deciding kind of what
environment to go to next when something
goes wrong and you can try to do that in
scheme
just just by like writing the rules of
how exceptions work
as long as you're allowed to give a
symbol to a particular environment
yeah great question so the question is
every time you apply a user-defined
procedure in scheme
you're creating a new frame but how do
you keep track of all the non-local
symbols
like the rest of the environment
and uh it's a great question you can do
this
in scheme and the answer is that this
new frame that you create
knows about the frame
that was the current frame when that
procedure was
defined in the first place and therefore
the frame that you create gives you
access not only
to the local symbols but also the
non-local symbols
and um yeah i guess we told this story
early on of what an environment is it's
a sequence of frames
it's got some first frame and then it
has a parent and then it has a parent
and then it has a parent eventually get
to global
and that is exactly the same story that
applies to scheme and that is the
structure that you built
is that when you build a new frame it
has a parent which is some existing
frame
and it has a parent which is some
existing frame or eventually you get to
the global frame which has no parent at
all and when you look up a symbol
well you look in the first frame and if
it's not there then you check the parent
so basically you're just writing code to
um simulate that whole story about
environment diagrams that we've been
telling since the beginning of the
course
and to do that you have to create a
frame object which doesn't just have the
local names it also has a parent
and there's a follow-up uh here does
non-local even exist i don't remember
covering it in schemes
so so there's no non-local assignment
that we'll talk about it does exist but
we just left it out because we've got to
leave out some things
if you really care it's called the set
exclamation point
but there is non-local lookup in the
sense that
if i define
f of x which returns a procedure that
takes y
and adds x and y together
and then
i call f on 2 and i call add 2
on 5 i should get seven what
add two has done is
been bound to some procedure
that really has two parts you can only
see one you can see the code
but there's another part to it which is
what is the frame
that was the current frame when this was
created
it was a frame in which x was bound to
two so that's why this
adds two it doesn't just add anything
together um
x is kind of like filled in already and
so
um the name x here is non-local you
obviously don't see it there
where is it well it's in the enclosing
scope
john when you print out add two why
wouldn't it show me the binding of x to
two would isn't that what would have
happened in python
it would it would have been but it would
have shown that as is plus
2y uh good question i think
you you in python you don't get these
substitution effects because
there's mutation everywhere and stuff
could change so really it is just
storing the code
and the environment in the environment
yeah in this subset of scheme that we're
working in
it would actually be legal just to kind
of replace this x with a two
and and like nothing would break as long
as there's no mutation
because that's that whole story of uh
you could replace
an expression by its value without
changing the answer um so that would be
like a nice feature is how do you
display this
such that the x is filled in but we
didn't try to implement this
okay but the way this game interpreter
actually works is it really just
remembers the code
and the procedure and so when it
evaluates this
it evaluates the plus and the x and the
y and it finds the plus in the global
frame it finds the x and the f frame and
it finds the y in the lambda frame and
puts them all together
and remind me john is am i
misremembering that lisp
doesn't have the set exclamation mark
some kind of there's some version of
whisper scheme that
has said we're not allowing this is that
yeah maybe in the early days there was
only set
car and set coulder that's what yeah
there used to be only that's what i yeah
and not set bang
and so if you wanted to mutate something
then you had to build a cons
this might be the case and um
yeah and then what about disallowing
mutation entirely i think that was never
really a lisp thing that's more of like
a
haskell thing oh maybe that's what i'm
confusing it with haskell
yeah okay
all right well i suspect you'll have
more questions when you actually do the
scheme project
you know this lecture is really just
kind of giving you an overview of what's
going on in the project
if you ever get to the point in the
project where you're wondering like what
am i doing right now like it tells me
you know i'm on question 8 and it's
telling me i'm supposed to implement
this function but why
i don't understand it at all that's a
good time to refer back to this lecture
and try to orient yourself
or to just try to read the code for the
whole project because
you know this is where a lot of stuff in
the course comes together like
we learned about trees because
expressions are tree structured
we learned about linked list because you
know this sequence of frames in an
environment
is like a linked list and we learned
about
how execution works in python is pretty
much the same in scheme
and now you really get to just write all
those rules in code so it turns out that
everything that you
like crammed into your mind in the first
few weeks of the course
now you just write a program that does
it for you you still have to think about
it in order to write code
but what's cool is that it really is
just a sequence of deterministic tips
and you can prove that to yourself by
by writing an interpreter that does
those steps and it and it makes the
programs behave like they're supposed to
behave so yeah don't don't miss that
part
don't miss that forest through the trees
as you work through the project but
instead you know try to figure out
what's going on and ask questions if you
don't get it
all right thanks everybody have a great
start to the week i think wednesday is a
holiday
right john and wednesday's a holiday
that is true
good happy veterans day and we'll see
everybody on friday