61a lecture 34 q a
yeah good question so if you have a
select
statement with a group by clause and the
group by has
three different column names
separated by commas what happens
um so so we have select something
something
grouped by column name
column email column
uh city or whatever
bad example name city
and uh what's an interesting
characteristic
shoes if
you had some big table full of people
and
you know they had names and they had
cities where they're from and they had
shoe sizes or whatever
if you just group by name then you'll
put all the johns in the same group
if you group by name comma city
then if there are john's in one city
berkeley and
john's in another city oakland they will
be in different groups
but there still might be multiple johns
in oakland
to group by three different columns
means
that you're separating the
oakland johns with a large shoe size
from the oakland johns with the small
shoot size
so basically what this does is it finds
all combinations
of a person's name what city they're
from and their shoe size
and makes a group for each of those
combinations
and um at that point there still might
be two
john's in oakland with the same shoe
size and so it's not like these groups
necessarily have
one thing in them but the more columns
you include here
the more groups you're going to get and
those groups are associated with
unique combinations of values for each
of these three columns
yeah let's talk about latin
so um
let does a lot like define where you're
defining
symbols as opposed to um procedures
so this kind of define
except that when you define
x will remain bound
like no matter what you do next whereas
let
only binds a symbol to a value for a
little while
and what do i mean by a little while
well until you reach
the closing parenthesis of the let
special form
so um let has
always two parts the
new symbol bindings that you want to
create and then
some expression that you want to
evaluate and the value of the whole let
expression
is equal to the value of whatever this
last expression is
and this part here is just
there in order to let you set up some
symbols
that you will use in this final
expression
so i could let x be equal to
one plus two now i've like
done some work already right i've bound
x to the value three
i do that by writing a pair
where the first element is
x and the second element is
some value some expression which gives
me some value
and then i can use x so i could figure
out oh
what's 3 times 4
and it will tell me 12.
so this is particularly relevant because
there's an extra credit problem
in scheme which is supposed to translate
this and how would you translate this
into an expression that doesn't involve
let
well you could use a different mechanism
for binding
symbols to values you could use a
lambda expression so when i say
lambda x times x4
i'm basically saying like x is going to
be bound to some value
and then i'm going to compute this
result oh that's the same thing with let
let says
x is going to be bound to some value and
then i'll compute this result
but where do you set up the value for x
well that would be in the
call to the lambda function
here's where you say x is
1 plus 2 then this will give me that
same value 12.
so these are equivalent
it's just the lead is convenient because
you kind of set things up first
and then you compute what you want
whereas this kind of does it backwards
this says here's what i'm going to
compute
and then i have to put all the values in
so this is a great example because it's
exactly what let does it's a local
variable
think about it the scope of it is only
within if you think about the scope of a
variable in a function
it's only scoped in the function it's
the same thing with the let and this
very nicely illustrates that i like that
example
right so in either case x is not bound
here
okay so two things what happens when you
have a lambda
that has more than one line like it
computes one plus x
and then it computes 2 plus x
well the answer is that both of these
are body expressions but when you call
this
on say 5 you'll get 7. it really did
compute
6 along the way but didn't do anything
with it
and so it was basically lost at the end
the value
of a call to any procedure is the value
of its
last sub-expression if there are more
than one
so like what's the point of having these
well you could
make scheme do something with it like
print it out
and then you'd see that the six really
was computed and now we're printing it
out and now you see both
so the answer to what do you do in the
case that there are multiple
body expressions is that you evaluate
each one in order
but you just return the value of the
last one
okay so a second question was what is
going on here
let's take a look this says
create a procedure which takes an x
evaluates a which is like something that
must be defined already
otherwise this would crash and then
you let the symbol a equal
x and you evaluate a again
but this a might be different from this
a because
this a is bound to whatever x was the
value of x
whereas this a must have been there
already so if i evaluate this directly
it'll
or sorry if i call this on let's say 12
it will give me an error that says
unknown identifier a but
if i define a to be something
then i can evaluate this this will
evaluate to seven
this will evaluate to twelve
since there are two expressions we never
really see
the seven if we change this just a
little bit in order to print this out
we would see the seven
and it's basically showing that you know
within the body of the same
procedure a could be seven and then it
could be twelve if
a the second time was inside a let the
rebound day
the question is here's some demos from
today's lecture
there's this line that's like build a
connection
to some database and then you know we
give it a name
give it any name you want db or n or
something like that
what would happen if you evaluated this
same expression a second time
would that give you a new database or
the same database
or would it erase the old one like
what's the story
and the story is that
this name which describes the name of a
file on your
file system is
a database that won't ever kind of just
get erased
instead it's persistent even if you quit
python and start python again
it will retain whatever information was
in it
before if you evaluate this expression
multiple times then you just get
multiple connections to the same
database
with the same data in it and that's okay
actually databases are designed to have
multiple connections
and what do these connections mean that
means different programs might all be
changing the database or querying the
database at the same time
but that doesn't mean that the database
is going to get refreshed or changed or
something like that
it basically just stays there and
accumulates
information over time and you can if one
program changes it and then another
program queries it
that second program is going to see the
changes from the first program
so i think within a particular python
program there really isn't
a good reason to have multiple
connections usually those multiple
connections come from multiple python
programs or maybe they're not all python
but you certainly could do it and i
don't think anything would break
i guess the question is what happens
when you define something within a let
for example or like you have a define
that's deeply embedded somewhere um
i i guess i misspoke about let earlier
you can have multiple expressions and it
just evaluates the last one it's the
value of the whole lip
kind of like uh kind of like a lambda
um what would happen if
this expression here wasn't just
evaluate x
but it was define a to be x
and then we compute x plus one well the
value's the same the value is just
whatever
x plus one is but we have a
defined expression in here and so we can
look up what a is
and it tells us a is nothing because it
all happened kind of within the let
on the other hand if you
define a here and you wonder what
x plus a is you could refer to a
within this expression because you just
defined it
so you defined x to be 1 you defined a
to be
x which is one and now you're adding
one and one together and you get two
so um i think the answer to the question
of what happens when you have an
embedded
defined is if it's within a lambda or
a procedure or a let then it kind of
defines it within that scope
otherwise it could actually be defining
it
more broadly so if i say something like
if
2 is greater than 1 which is true then
i'm going to define y to be 7.
otherwise i'll define y to be 8.
and then i could say what's y and it's
7. so it's not like the define
only ever works within the scope you're
in it's
let's or just like procedure calls like
define
uh set something in the local frame
and um right it
as long as you're in that frame you can
access it and as soon as you leave that
local frame then you
can't access it anymore all right so
we're going to look at this test case
together from question 14
and let's just step through it
see what we learned no i think all the
action starts here so we define z to be
zero
and then what happens when we let a be
the result of dividing z to be
z plus one well when you define
z well we can see it right here when you
when you evaluate a
define expression it does have a value
that value is a symbol
so if i said something like define a
to be defined z0
what is a now it's bound to the symbol z
it's as if i had said define a to be the
symbol
z i'd get the same result
so here we are
using a let expression
to assign a to
some value and that value happens to be
a symbol the symbol z
now what is z after we do this
definition
it's 1. what was
a in here a was bound to the symbol z so
if instead i had written that
then i would have seen z but really what
this is checking is to make sure that
you're actually
evaluating the define expression and
when you evaluate the defined expression
then z should change
okay so we got to go back to the
beginning because i kind of did this
twice
now z is bound to one a is not defined
what would happen if we wrote this
expression
this expression says bind
x to 1 and y to 3
and then do two things define
x to be x plus one so now x is bound to
two
and what would happen if i listed out x
and y
well i'd list out uh two and three
so i guess like um whether we had
written
this thing or we had just written
that thing alone we'd get the same
effect which would be that z is one now
instead of zero
yeah interesting so um the question is
about group by where you're writing some
arbitrary expression not just a
column name but you know any old thing
so i put uh
one two three and five in a table
if i
wanna know well okay let me do the exact
uh question that you did which is like
how many of these are bigger than one
and how many of these are not bigger
than one
well i could write an expression that
says is uh n
bigger than one and i could also count
how many
different values fall into a group
oh come on
n bigger than one count star
from the numbers table group by
and here i'm going to write some
arbitrary expression n greater than one
what happens i get two groups
i get a group where i've grouped
together all the rows
where n is not bigger than one zero is
kind of representing
false value here in sql
and then i've grouped together all the
rows where n is bigger than one
where one is representing a true value
and then these counts are
how many different rows were less than
one and how many are sorry were
not bigger than one and how many rows
were bigger than one
so it is certainly possible to group by
some arbitrary expression
or you could even have a comma separated
list of multiple arbitrary expressions
and you know would you do this
i think there's a reason it's built into
the language
it really depends on what table you have
and what you want so if it turns out the
table you have
doesn't have a column for bigger than
one or less than
or not bigger than one but that's like a
really important part of
what computation you're doing then it
makes sense to have like a group by
there
i think it's a little more common just
to
um have another column in your table
which would have these values in it
about whether something is bigger than
one or not and then group by that
just to make it a little bit more
explicit but if you want to kind of skip
that step of adding yet another column
then you you can do it this way
yeah john raises a really good point is
that
if that information something being
greater than one is important
well then store it don't compute it so
there's that sort of you can
i think of the computation as well okay
i've got to do this every once in a
while but if it's something that i
constantly need
that's what a database is for right go
ahead and store that information and
then just query the database so there's
there's that interesting sort of
question always do i compute it or do i
store it
and there's a trade-off right storage
costs a little bit computation costs a
little bit
and so you have to decide sort of what's
important
well like if you had a database that had
really detailed zip codes you know these
ones that have like
multiple numbers and then what you
really want to do is group by zip code
well then you might write a group by
expression that finds only the first
five letters
of the zip code and group by that and
then you'd have grouped by the kind of
regular zip code that you're used to so
this kind of stuff does happen
i think we did walk through this in the
earlier yeah i think we did this
yesterday or monday yeah john yeah but
we'll do a fast version now just
like to remind everybody you have to
evaluate this
so that's one you have to evaluate
that but in order to evaluate that you
have to evaluate this symbol and this
number
so now we're up to two three
four now
i have to call cube on three
that's not an instance of eval that's an
instance of apply
but part of the apply process is to now
evaluate this expression so we've done
four so far
this expression is something that gets
evaluated so that's five
we have to evaluate this that's six we
have to evaluate this seven
eight nine so i counted nine evals in
this particular example
in april i think if you go back i don't
know if it was wednesday or monday
uh we did a much more detailed version
of that you'll see it on the video on
the first website
yeah we did something like cube the cube
of plus one two or something like that
yeah yeah yeah yeah
before we answer this your your battery
level is terrifyingly low
uh it is but i don't
like to live in the moment john that's
ridiculous
oh well unfortunately the answer to this
question is pretty short which is that
you don't have to think about recursive
sequel either this semester or in most
of your life
so uh it was a topic that we taught for
a couple of semesters sort of
experimentally
and therefore there's some old practice
problems about it but
um it's fairly unusual that you'll see
a recursive uh select expression
in sql out there in the world like you
know
i don't think i've ever seen that if you
dig around on github long enough you'll
find some but
you'd have to look pretty hard so dig
around in github
long enough you'll find everything
[Laughter]
um so right
the this course used to teach another
um declarative programming language a
variant of prologue
which has a fair amount of recursion in
it and we were kind of
trying to capture that old flavor in sql
and
it's possible to do recursion but it's
just so restricted
and the syntax is so bizarre that uh
it wasn't very enlightening i think to
to spend a whole
week studying that so uh
yeah i'll just let recursive sequel go
and ignore all those problems
and if you really want to read about it
um you can find old versions of the
class
where we used to teach this i'll show
you how just in case someone wants to
follow up
um if you go to instix berkeley.idu you
can find all the old versions of the
course so probably around 2016.
we had some recursive sequel in there
let's see
uh yeah there it is recursive select so
if you want to watch a whole lecture on
it you could but i
i don't think it's the best use of your
time yeah i agree
the next question was can you have a
select statement inside of a where
clause
let's go back to our very simple
one two three five table and the
question is can you have a select
statement within the where clause
the answer is yes but we don't cover it
in this course so you don't have to
think about it again if you want to just
kind of stick with the course material
if you're just curious it's a fine thing
to wonder about
sql allows for some sort of bizarre
things to happen
so when you evaluate a select
you really should be thinking of that as
producing a table
but if that table happens to have only
one
row and one column then select is
basically happy to treat it like an
individual number
so you could write things like uh
select star from numbers where
uh the result of selecting
the max n from
numbers okay so what would that give you
that would give you like
a table with just one
row and just one column that has the
number of five in it you know sql is
basically happy to let you treat this
like the number five um so then you
could say something like this
is uh greater than
n and it will tell you that's one two
three
and basically just treat this whole
thing as the number five
again you don't need to know that for
this course but sometimes it's handy so
if for example you wanted like
uh all the rows
where the name like you wanted the name
of everybody whose height was the
maximum height you might write something
like this
yeah good question so how would you uh
if you had a table of numbers how would
you
create a table of prime numbers um
and one intuition is that you need to
know the primes
in order to know the primes basically
you need to know the prime so far in
order to check whether something's
something larger is a prime and that's
one approach to finding out whether
something's a prime number but it's not
the only one
a more brute force approach is in order
to figure out whether 12 is prime
you just divide it by every number 1
through 11
before it not just the primes but
everything the primes
below it or in there somewhere and you
make sure that
uh you know if 12 were prime then
only one would divide it evenly so
basically none of these other numbers
would divide it
so i think probably the trick uh to
finding a table of primes from a table
of numbers
is to first join the numbers with the
numbers so now you have pairs of numbers
then you can group by the second number
to ask yourself is this thing prime or
not you figure out
um how many of the numbers it's been
paired with divide evenly into it