61 election No.22
announcements
there's a lab this week do Tuesday
the ants project is due on Friday
but you need to finish phases one and two by Tuesday
you can earn an early submission bonus point
by submitting the whole project
by Thursday which is what I recommend trying to do
homework five is posted its du on Monday of next week
and should be a good review for the upcoming midterm
lab next week will only have one required part
which is to finish homework five
there will be some
optional problems that give you some more practice
if that's what you'd like for the midterm
but there won't be any required lab problems
in addition to the required homework problems
that are due next Monday
it's your last chance to fill out the weak eight
anonymous survey
we'd really appreciate your input
and midterm two is coming up
a week from Wednesday at 7pm pacific time
it will have a similar format and style to midterm one
cover content up to an including last fridays lecture
and today's lecture about efficiency
will not be covered on the exam
or on any assignments or labs or discussions
it's just an optional topic this semester
in the past it's been required
but we just cover this topic for one lecture in 61 a
whereas you'll hear a lot about it in 61 b
so it's a good idea to watch this lecture
get a flavor for what efficiency is
all about but if you take 61 b
then you'll learn all about it there
and you won't have missed anything
measuring efficiency
this is not about objects in particular
but about how to
understand how long your program is going to take
to run
so let's go back to our first example of tree recursion
which was a way to compute
elements of the fibonacci sequence
using tree recursion with the following implementation
element zero is zero element one is one
everything else is the sum of the previous two
thanks fibonacci for making this sequence so popular
if I want to compute fib five
that involves summing up the results of fib three
and fib four and fib three means summing up one and two
here I've marked the base cases
with their returned values
so to compute fib three I have to do all that work
to compute fib four I have to do all of that work
and the actual computation
proceeds in a pattern that looks like this
so this tree shaped computation
actually begins by calling fip five
which calls fip three
which calls fip one
which actually returns the No.1
the next thing to return is this called a fib zero
fib zero and fib one are some to give you fib two
and then we can
finally return from the call to fib three
and we proceed
by computing the rest of the values that we need
in order to finally return from fibb five
so we want to understand
how long it takes to run this computation
and the first thing we'll do is just count
the number of calls
to fip and see how that grows
fib in if an equal zero or an equals one return in
otherwise
return fib and minus two plus fib and minus one
I know this is slightly different
from what was on the slide
but it will do the same thing
if I run this code
and ask where what fib five is
it will tell me it's five
fib six is eight
fib seven is 13 etc
now what I'm going to do is define a decorator
called count which takes in a function f
returns a new counted version of f
which when called on in
not only returns the result but also
increments the call count attribute
which is an attribute
that will use
to keep track of how many times this function
was called
now for counted
we have to start out with a call count of zero
so that we can increment it later
and then we can return that counted function
so we could decorate fib you know at count
but instead we'll just do it here in
the interactive session
so fib is a counted version of fib
if I call fib on five
I can then ask how many times was this called
and it was called 15 times
now this is cumulative so if I call fib five again
the call count has gone up to 30
now if I call fib on some
large end such as 30
it will do quite a bit of computation
and come up with 832,000
but the actual number of times I called this function
was 2 million times
2.69 million calls to fip just to compute this result
and many of those calls were returning zero
some were returning one
some were returning large numbers
until we finally got to the result that we wanted
so we can see why this took a while to call
so the point of this example is to start to understand
exactly what happens when you call a function
and how that relates to the time that it takes
for the function to return
and we've started out by just
counting the number of times that we call something
but over the next two lectures will develop
more sophisticated ways
of talking about the running time of a program
memorization is an extremely useful technique
for speeding up the running time of a program
here is the simple idea
just
remember the results that have been computed before
so instead of recomputing things
when you need their values again
you just keep them around
here's another decorator
it's called memo
it takes in a function
which may take a while to compute
but we also keep a cash
of the values that were returned by that function
before
in the memoized version of f
we check conceive first
if the argument that was passed in is in the cash
if it's not in the cash then we add it to the cash
meaning we make a mapping between the key n
and the return value f
even
now we actually have to call f
which was originally passed in
in order to compute this return value
but once it's in the cash
we're never going to compute it again
instead we'll just return the return value
that's already in the cash
once I have returned to the memoized
version of this function
I will have automatic cashing build in
so we keep
dictionary between
keys and values where the keys are arguments
and the values are return values of f
and this memoized function has the same behavior as f
if f is a pure function
if it's a non pure function
then
we don't actually call f every time we call memoized
so it might have different behavior
so that's something to keep a lookout for
you can only really memoize
pure functions and expect their behavior
to stay the same
let's see what happens when we use memo to speed up fib
so a memoized version of f
keeps track of a cash
takes in an argument in
if in not in the cash
then we put it in the cash
with the return value of f event
we return what's in the cash every time and we return
memoized
fib 30 used to take a while to compute
but what if we change fib
to be a memoized version of fib
then we can compute fib 30 rather quickly
in fact we can compute fib 50 rather quickly or fib 300
which is a very large number
but it's not that hard to compute
all we have to do is compute
fib two ninety eight and fib two ninety nine
which we do almost instantly
with this memoized version of fib
so let's see if we can understand what's going on
I've restarted python so fib is slow again
what we're going to do is replace
fib with the counted version of fib
so we can see how many times it actually gets called
we'll give another name to that counted version of fib
so we can access its attributes
now I'm going to change fib to a memoized
counted version of fib
and
we can even count that
and we'll call fib on 30
which completes instantly
there were 59 calls to the mammalized version of fib
some of which reached the cash
and some of which
actually called the underlying original fib function
which we called counted fib in this example
and its call count was 31
now why 31
well there are 31 different arguments that we pass in
thirty twenty nine
twenty eight all the way down to zero
and so that's
exactly how many times we call the original function
now what about 59
well let's take a look at what's going on
here's our tree structured recursive process
and we're going to keep track of actual calls to fib
times when we called the memoized version of fib
and found the result in the cash
and times that we had just skipped entirely
there must be lots of times that we skipped it entirely
because we made so many fewer calls than we did before
so we call fib five which calls fib three
which calls fib one
which returns one
that's an actual call to the fib function
so is this called a fib zero
but the next time fib one is called
we just get
the value that we've already computed from the cash
so this doesn't
count as a call to the underlying fib function
but does count as a call to the memoized version
fib two returns and then fib three returns
the next thing that happens is that we call
fib four which calls fib two
which is already in the cash
which means we can skip over
these calls to fib zero and fib one entirely
they never even happen
and that's because this structure is something that's
repeated from what we've already done before
so we find fib two immediately
and when we
call fib three we find that result immediately as well
skipping these recursive calls
so with fib two in fib three
we finally can return from fib four
and then return from fib five
so as you can see for each value of n
fib is called exactly once
and for many values of n
fib the memoized version of fib is called a second time
in order to finish the computation
but fib four is never called a second time
and neither is fib five
let's look in an example
of a function we can define in two different ways
one of which is much more efficient than the other
exponentiation is built into python
I can raise one number to the power of another
but let's write an exponentiation function recursively
our goal will be to have it so that
one more multiplication lets us double the exponent
that we're using an exponentiation
here's an implementation that does not meet this goal
this says to raise b to the power n
if n is zero return one
otherwise multiply
b to the n minus one by b
this is a correct definition
but if I double in
I have to do twice as many multiplies
because each time I make a recursive call
I'm only reducing n by one
and this functions implementation corresponds
to the following mathematical definition
for b to the end
but this is not the only
mathematical definition of b to the in
here's another one
more complicated
but the additional complexity
will also give us additional efficiency
this says that b to the n is one if n is zero
and then has two different cases
for whether n is even a rod
if n is even
then I can erase b to the one half n power
and square that result
so if n is 16 I raise b to the eight
and then I square b to the eight to get b to the 16
if n is odd then I use the definition I had before
here's an implementation
this is a more efficient version of exponentiation
that has two different recursive cases
depending on whether n is even
in which case you square the result
of exponentiating b and n divided by 2
where I know that n is evens
so floor division will give me the exact result
and if n is odd
then I use my old definition
this is not a tree recursive function
even though I see two different
calls to exp fast in the body
only one of them is ever called
so this is an instance of linear recursion
and sometimes the problem size is reduced by half
meaning one more multiplication
in this case by calling square
lets us double the size of the problem
that we're handling
an x fast runs faster
let's take a look
this environment is called a jupiter notebook
you can read about them online
it's a common way that people use in order to execute
python code when the output is a graph or a chart
so here's our definition of exp the slow way
and something that's built
into this notebook environment
is that we can time how long it takes to run something
so if I raise two to the 104th power
the time it took was ['two']millisecond
if I raised two to the 100th power
it only took me 100 microseconds
but if I run it again
I'll get a different number each time
so if I run it a bunch of times
I see it hovers around 100 microseconds
two to the 104th power tends to hover around
200 microseconds
running it a bunch of times this way is inefficient
so I've written some code to run it a bunch of times
using the built in timet module
which can repeatedly call something
and in this case
we're going to compute the median time that it takes
to execute some line of code
and here's the result
two to the 102th power
takes a little less than half a mill a second
two to the 104th power
takes a little less than one mill a second
this looks like a straight line
the term we used to describe this is linear
the time that it takes to compute two to the n
under this implementation is linear in n
now it's a little bit bumpy
because all kinds of interesting things are
happening inside of a computer
but the word linear is used
even if there are slight deviations from the line
to describe the general trend that appears
when you plot the time it takes to compute something
as a function of the input size
and here's the fast definition
we can draw the same plot
and we'll see
that the overall numbers are quite a bit smaller
for 1600 instead of taking
['four']millisecond
it takes only ['point', 'zero', 'four']millisecond
also this shape of the curve is different
this shape is called logarithmic
the difference between going from 200 to 400
in this case is just about point 002
and what about the difference
between going from 400 to 800
well that's another point
oh oh two
going from 800 to 1600 is another point o o two
every time we double the input
it just takes a constant amount of extra work
and that's because we're making recursive calls on n
that's only half the size
that's called logarithmic time
so to summarize
a lineared time function
requires one more unit of work
for every one bigger end
that means doubling the input doubles the time
and 1000 times the input takes 1000 times as much time
1024 is two to the 10th power
logarithmic time is much better
doubling the input
just increases the time by some constant
and 1000 times the input
just increases the time by 10 times that constant
so it takes 10 times as long
to do 1000 times as much work
and these terms linear and logarithmic
are used to describe the general shape
of time as a function of input size
even if there are wiggles and bumps along the way
the order of growth
of a functions time
that it takes to compute its result
is a general category that the function falls in
such as linear or logarithmic
two functions that use linear time
might not take exactly the same amount of time
to compute their result for the same input
but they both scale in the same way
the general shape of their scaling curve
are as both a line
and logarithmic functions
all have that same characteristic logarithmic shape
and there are other shapes as well
quadratic time
describes a function
that processes all pairs of elements in a linear input
or all pairs of values in a sequence of length n
so for example
here's a function that computes the overlap
between the elements in a and the elements in b
by going through every element in a
and every element in b
and checking to see if they're the same
it adds a count when they are
and returns the count to the end
so the overlap
between three five seven six and four five six five
is three because five five are the same
five five are the same and six six are the same
to compute this result
overlap compares all pairs of an element in a
and an element in b
and that's a quadradic amount of work
based on the input length
here the input length is four
in the amount of comparisons is four times four or 16
the amount of extra work required
to process a length of four versus a length of three
is this whole row
and therefore
if you compare the input size
to the time it takes to compute the result
you get a quadratic shape
so here's what happens when we pass
in ends from the range 20 to 200
and compute the median time
required in order to return the result
75 takes ['two']millisecond
whereas 150 takes nearly ['eight']millisecond
and the curve slopes upward
in a familiar looking parabola
another upward sloping
order of growth is exponential time
here things are even worse
a tree recursive function can take exponential time
because the unmemorized fib function
has to do 60% more work
just to compute n
that's one larger than the previous n
so computing fib two just requires this much work
fib three requires all this additional work
fib four
requires all this additional work on top of fib three
and fib five has to compute not only fib four
but all of this additional work as well
assuming we don't memoize
so a tree recursive function like this
without memorization
will take what's called exponential time
here are the common orders of growth that arise
when analyzing functions
there are others
and there's also a formal system
for analyzing functions and proving
what orders of growth they belong to
but we'll defer all of that for a later course
and instead focus on
understanding what these categories are
and what their implications are
on the run time of a program
all of them describe how time scales with input size
and all of them describe general trends
as opposed to the details
of exactly
how many microseconds it takes for a function
call to return
so exponential growth is really slow
quadradic growth is slow but common
linear growth is very common
logarithmic growth is great
and scales to really large inputs
and constant growth is the best of all
that happens when the input size
doesn't affect the time
for example and python
the number of elements in a dictionary
does not affect how long it takes to look up a value
by its key how that works is a topic for a later course
but the fact
that it is a constant time operation to find a value
by its key
is an important property of python dictionaries
each of these categories
can be described by a simple equation
where we have written down the
general time that it takes to process
an input of size n plus one
in terms of the time that it takes to process an
input of size n
using some constance a and b
to account for the fact
that there are many details about how long it takes
for something to run
that we're glossing over
as we talk about the general shape of time
as a function of the input size
so for exponential growth
the amount of time it takes to compute
the result for an input of size n plus one
is something like a times b to the n plus one
which
compared to the time it takes for an input of size n
requires an additional multiplicative factor of b
so that's the key characteristic of exponential growth
incrementing the input size in
multiplies the time by some constant
the bigger the constant the worst this is
but basically for any constant it's pretty bad
quadratic growth is not quite so slow
quadratic growth says that for an input
of size n plus one
it takes something like a times n plus one squared
in order to compute the result
which in addition to the time it takes to compute
the result for size in
also requires an additional additive term
now
adding to the time is better than multiplying the time
but still the problem
with quadratic growth is that the amount you add
for just going from end to end plus one
is a term that depends on in
so incrementing an increases time
by end times a constant
linear growth for a problem of size n plus one
requires n plus one times some a steps
which compared to solving the same problem for size n
is just an additive factor that doesn't depend on it
incrementing n increases time by a constant
logarithmic growth is the one that scales
to really begin
here we write down an expression
for the time it takes to compute the result for
n plus n or two times n
is some constant times the log of two in
which compared to the amount of time
it takes to compute the result
for just in add some constant
so doubling in only increments time by a constant
if it's possible to reimplement some function
in order to change its order of growth
from exponential to linear by memoization
or from linear delagorithmic
as we did for exponentiation
that can substantially change
not only the speed of your program
but the size of problem that your program can handle
without seeming like it's taking forever
there are precise mathematical definitions
for the terms linear constant
quadratic and so on
and these definitions are useful because
they allow you to prove properties
of functions
without ever running those functions
on particular examples
and one important component of the theory of computing
is this practice
of proving characteristics about functions
by reasoning from mathematical definitions
now that's not a topic in this course
but it is covered extensively in future courses at
berkeley
and it's a
standard part of the computer science curriculum
rather than telling you all the definitions
which are welcome to look up on your own
I will show you this standard notation
that's associated with those definitions
because it's used so commonly
that it might surprise you
if you've never seen it before
so for these common orders of growth
exponential quadradic linear
logarithmic and constant
the most typical way to describe each order of growth
is with either big theta or big o notation
big theta notation looks like this
and there's a different expression
for each order of growth
so quadratic growth is big theta of anne squared
whereas linear growth is big theta of ant
and yes
computer scientists really do wander around saying
big theta
log rhythmic is log n and constant is the tricky one
you write big theta of one most commonly
and what happened to the n
well increasing n
doesn't effect time in a constant growth function
and so you don't put n there at all
another common set of notation is big o notation
which is even more fun to say than big theta
and the expressions look the same
so big theta of b to the n or big o of b to the n
now these actually mean something slightly different
big o describes the upper bound for the time it takes
for a function to run
so this is like saying at most quadratic
whereas this says
something about a lower and upper bound
both at most
quadratic and at least quadratic time is required
now to use this mathematical notation effectively
you have to be quite precise
about what you're describing
what is n in relation to the problem
if n is just the input number
then things are simple
but n might be the length of the input sequence
and that means there are lots of sequences all
with the same length
so are you describing how long it takes
for a length end sequence in the worst case
or best case in average case
across all different sequences of length end
that's something you'd want to specify
if you are going to go prove properties
about functions
and all that will become important in later courses
but I think in this course
the important thing is to recognize
that there are different general patterns of growth
in the time it taped cs for a function to complete
the most common are the five that I've shown you here
and when people discuss logarithmic growth
sometimes they don't say logarithmic growth
instead they say big theta log in or biggo log in
space or memory is another resource
that gets consumed by programs as they execute
and so it's something that you need to worry about
now the consumption of space is taken up by values
so a long list takes up more space than a short list
but it also gets taken up by frames
so you need to know how many frames exist
because of different function
calls in your program at the same time
and this will involve some new concepts
so the new concepts we need to keep track of are
which environment frames do we need to keep around
during evaluation
and which ones can we just let go
so here's the story
at any moment
there's a set of what are called active environments
and values and frames in those active environments
consume memory or space
any memory that is used for other
values and frames not in an active environment
can be recycled
and the python interpreter does this automatically
by reclaiming this base that it used before
when it knows that that information is no longer needed
so which are these active environments
well an active environment is for any
function call currently being evaluated
meaning we called it but it hasn't returned yet
there's another case much less comment
which is a parent environment of a function
that exists in an active environment
so this situation occurs
when you've defined a function within another function
and so it's parent frame
is not the global frame but some other frame
as long as you need that function
you also need its parent frame
and all of the other frames in its parent environment
so fortunately
python tutor can visualize
which frames are active for us
here's our definition of fib
which computes fibonacci number number six
and there's a setting
which I'll show you
that says don't display exited functions
so in this way
it will actually delete the frames of anything
that has already returned
so when we call fib six
obviously it hasn't returned yet
because we have some work to do
and that's going to involve calling fib four
which has to
complete before we ever try to finish fib six
and fib four involves calling fib two
and so all of these are active frames at the same time
fib two calls fib zero
fib zero actually returns
and once it returns
it's no longer active and so it's just gonna disappear
and in its stead
we have replaced it with a frame for fib one
so notice we had f one and f two and f three
we created f four
but then got rid of it
because we didn't need it anymore
and now we're up to f five
so if we continue this process we'll see that once
fib four was done computing fib two
the fib two frame was removed
and now we have the fib three frame
which is the other part of computing fib four
so that goes on for a while
and eventually the fib four frame has gone entirely
and we only have the original f one frame
because we're not finished computing fib six
and we have the f
11 frame that was created for computing fib five
that does some work
eventually that gets deleted
and fib six can finally return the value of eight
and then there's no more work to do
in our code
we can also see how many frames are being used
so let's define a higher order function called
count frames which takes in some f
and defines a counted version
which takes some argument in
what it's going to do is increment the open frame count
it's also going to keep track of
the maximum number of open frames at any time
so if the open count is actually larger
then the max count
we can change
the max count to be the open count
now we'll get the return value
by calling f on n
now it's time to close this frame
which just means subtracting one from the open count
and then we can return the result
the open count starts out at zero
the max count starts out at zero
and we can return the counted function
so if we define fib really quick
we already know that it makes many many recursive calls
but what we don't know
is how many frames are open at any given time
or what the maximum number of open frames is
so we can figure that out by calling count frames
on fib
then calling fib on some numbers such as 20
so it's computed the 20th fibonacci number
and fib dot open count should be zero
because we've
returned from every call to fib that we've made
but the max count will tell us
a maximum number of frames that were open at one time
and the answer is 20
so that's an indication of how much
space is used by this function
it doesn't need to open 6000 frames at a time
only a few
now how can we understand why the number came out 20
well
here's the tree
shaped process that we use to compute fib 5
and let's say we've done all this work already
we still have to do all this work
and we're about to return from this call to fib one
well we can
figure out which calls have an active environment
it's this one this one this one and this one
which haven't returned yet
the ones over on the left
have already been called and returned
so any memory used by these frames can be reclaimed
and then over here these haven't been called yet
and so we don't need to worry about that
so the maximum count of frames open
is the longest chain you can find in this tree
which in this case
goes from fib five to four to three to two to one
is length five