sixty one eight lecture No.28
announcements
for lab and homework this week
you'll need to use scheme
you can use code cs sixty one eight org
or we distribute a scheme interpreter
with every scheme assignment
including the lab in the homework
and here's the direct link
so if you save this file and run it from the terminal
then you'll be ready to read the scheme files
or use scheme interactively
lab 10 was extended to Wednesday
so that it wouldn't be due on election day
homework six is due on Thursday
let's take a quick look together
it's only three problems
and none of them are particularly involved
they just help you get started with scheme
today we'll have a homework party on zoom as usual
click here for details on piazza
that will run from seven to 9:00pm
and on Thursday
some tas intuitors are going to hold
conceptual office hours
I think these are one to 2:00pm but I'm not sure
so I'll just let you check piazza for details
and we'll update this announcement
once those details are all settled
take a look at your midterm to
and please
let us know if there's anything we need to regrade
by Monday
and finally please don't forget to vote
if you're in the us
today's lecture is going to be about python again
we're going to touch on just one more python topic
that will be important
and learning how to interpret
programs in another programming language
today we'll talk about exceptions
so the topic of the day in general
is about handling errors and how to do
so sometimes computer programs behave in non
standard ways
because for instance
a function could receive an argument value
of an improper type
that it doesn't know what to do with
but there are lots of other
problems that you could have
some resources such as a file
might just not be where you'd think they are
a network connection
could be lost in the middle of data transmission
just anything
conceivable could go wrong
in the course of executing a computer program
what you see here is an excerpt from
grace hopper's notebook in 1947
when she was working on one of the first computers
and she was documenting her work
and the computer shut down because there was a moth
in relay No.70
so this was noted as the first actual case of a bug
in a computer causing it to shut down
the moth found in the mark ii
so the point is
there's lots of different issues that it can arise
and you need to write your programs
in such a way that they're prepared to handle
these problems
not necessarily the moth problem
although you should
not always assume that your hardware is reliable
how a program handles
errors depends on what sort of program
you're writing
and how people interact with it
so if you're building a web service that
you know
everyone in the world is supposed to be able to use
whether they
understand how computers really work or not
then you want to make sure
that your service keeps running
regardless of what errors crop up
if there's a huge power outage and one
half of the world
you'd
still want as much of your service to keep running
on servers in the other half
now on the other hand the python interpreter
is a program that stops immediately when an
error arises
and that's because the programmer who's using it
needs to know about that error as soon as possible
so that they can address it in their program
so just different kinds of programs need
different sorts of policies
in order to handle their errors
there's no one right way
but it's always the case that you have to think about
how errors are going to be handled in any program
the way that we handle
errors in python is called the exception mechanism
so it's a built in mechanism in a programming language
to declare that an error has occurred
and then elsewhere
you say
how to respond to various exceptional conditions
various issues that have happened
that are just not the standard way in which a program
is met a rut
so we have special vocabulary for this
and special syntax in the language
and special objects
we say that python raises an exception
whenever an error occurs
or whenever we want to signal to something
non standard has happened
exceptions can be handled
by the same program that raised them
preventing the interpreter from halting
so the default behavior is that python will halt
so unhandled exceptions will cause python to halt
execution and print a stack trace
that's that long error message
that tells you what line and what file
cause the error that happened
and all of the function calls that were in process
when that occurred
so these unhandled exceptions are what we've seen
all the way through the course
but as of today we'll learn how to handle exceptions
so that python doesn't always have to halt execution
it could recover from the problem when keep going
so here are some key tips for mastering exceptions
one is that exceptions are a type of object
and you know how the object system works
so exceptions will have classes with constructors
just like any other object
they're special because they enable
non local continuations of control
these are not like non local assignment statements
they're a little bit different
the idea is that
when you have a chain of function calls
so f calls g and g calls h
normally what happens is that h
returns and then we continue
executing the body of g
and then when g returns that's when you go back to f
so you always
finish returning from functions in the order that you
called them
but exceptions can change the rules there
so exceptions can shift control directly from h to f
by passing g along the way
meaning that
you can return to a different place than you otherwise
would now it's not quite returning anymore
it's raising an exception and handling it
which is going to feel a little bit different
but the point is
that when one statement is executed
and then the next statement is executed
they may be in
functions that are separated by other functions
in between that's non local continuations of control
also by the way
exception handling tends to be slow
so it's not something that we use
for the standard approach to a program
only for non standard situations
so there are two parts of the exception mechanism
raising exceptions and then handling them
let's first talk about raising exceptions
so the easiest way to raise an exception
is with an assert statement
and we've seen these throughout the course
so assert statements raise a particular kind of
exception called
an assertion error
so I say assert I give some expression
if that expression
is not a true value but a false value
that an assertion error is created
using the string as an argument
and that's what gets raised
so assertions are designed to be used liberally
all over your program
if once you've decided that your program
needs to run a little bit faster
and assertions are slowing you down
you can turn them all off
so you can ignore
all assertions in order
to increase efficiency
by running python with the dash o flag
where o stands for optimized
so if you just run python three dash show
that means none of your assert statements are going
to be executed
you can always
tell whether assertions are enabled or not
buy our bull with a special name debug
and we can try this out
okay so we'll start up pipe on three
and we'll assert false
error
and what happened there was
that we raised an assertion error
so now we know this is the class of the exception
that was raised
and then following the colon is the message associated
with the exception
and assert true has no effect
now instead I run python with the dash o
then I'll notice that debug is a false value
and if I assert false error
nothing will happen at all
before in normal python
I saw an assertion error raised
but now I've turned off assertions
now you can also raise any kind of exception
not just a sushion error with a raised statement
so exceptions are raised with a raised statement
that says raised expression
if you want to attach some sort of message
to that error that you're raising
you have to do it by making it a part
of the exception instance that you raise
so expression must evaluate to a subclass
of the base exception
which is the base class for all exceptions in python
so we can put a class there
or we can put an instance of one
and exceptions are constructed like any other object
so for instance if I wanted to put
a type error that says I've passed in a bad argument
and I would raise type error and pass in a message
because that's what type errors take on construction
now there are some built in different classes of errors
a type error
is something that's meant to indicate
that a function was
past the wrong number
or type of argument
a name error
means that a name wasn't found when it was looked up
in the current environment
a key error
means that a key wasn't found in a dictionary
and a runtime error indicates that something else bad
happened
so it was just a catch all for troubles that happened
during interpretation
raised by the interpreter
okay let's see a few of these in action
so I can raise
a tight bearer
that says bad argument
and what happens when I do that is that I get a
stack trace
that's what this part is called words has what line
different things happen
and then it says the name of the class that I created
the tight bear
and it says bad argument
which is the same kind of thing
that you get if you pass in a string
into the absolute value
this says tight bear again
and this has a more descriptive message
because the more descriptive and error message
you can give
the easier it is for your user to understand
what went wrong
so that's a type error
there is a name error hello is not defined
what us we were interested in having a key error
so if I look up hello
in the empty dictionary and it will tell me
there's a key error
and what about a runtime error
well let's define a function that calls itself
since I don't have a base case this will run forever
and at the bottom here it says
maximum recursion death exceeded
and that is a runtime error
now that we can
raise exceptions we need to be able to handle them
and we do that with a tria statement
so a tri statement handles exceptions
it has the following syntax
first you say try
that's the whole header line that begins the statement
then a tri suite can contain arbitrary statements
but you get executed
now during the course of executing the tri suite
it could be the case that something goes wrong
that an exception is raised
and therefore
control may be transferred to the except suite
based on whether
this tri statement handles
the kind of exception that was raised
which is determined by the exception class
so here's the whole execution rule for this statement
first we execute the tri suite
if nothing goes wrong that is no exceptions are raised
that's all we do
but if during the course of executing the tri suite
an exception is raised that is not otherwise handled
and it's the case
that the class of the exception inherits
from the exception class that's given
in the accept line
then the except suite is executed
with name bound to the exception
and we say that the exception is handled
meaning that your interpreter won't halt
instead you can just execute that except suite
which does whatever we wanted to do
in exceptional circumstances
okay so that's how we handle exceptions
with the tri statement
and this can prevent our program from terminating
so for instance
I can write the following tri statement
try to bind the name x to one divided by zero
what will happen when I divide one by zero
I'll raise a zero division error
so
I'm going to have an except claws in my tri statement
that says when there's a zero division error
in the tri suite which is up here
then I'm going to handle it
and bind it to the name e
at which point I will print handling a
and then the type of e
which will be a zero division error
and then I'll bind x to zero
now why might I do this
well
x will never be bound up here
because the error occurs when we're in the middle
of executing the assignment statement
one we're still in the process of evaluating
with on the right hand side
so this is a very typical pattern
that when we're trying to bind a name to a value
and it doesn't work out
we're gonna bind the name to some default value instead
that's not required
it just sometimes makes it easier to program
because then we know no matter what happens
x will be bound to something
after this tri statement is executed
okay so we execute it
and it prints out handling a zero division error
but if we look at what x is bound to now
it's bound to zero
and that's because of this line
okay so there's the first example of just the simplest
tri statement we can come up with
you can have multiple tri statements in your program
they can be nested within each other
and what happens when an exception is raised
will control jumps to the except suite
of the most recent tri statement
so that innermost tri statement
that handles that type of exception
let's look at a demonstration
okay so
let's define
a function called invert
which takes in a number x
binds y to one over x
prince a message
never printed if
x is zero
and then returns why
okay so that's what inverting does
if we load this file and we invert two will get 0.5
and this is printed
because x is not zero
but when x is zero
then we raise a zero division error
y is never bound and the print statement is
this print expression is never evaluated
and so we never print anything at all
okay and then let's also define invert safe
which will
handle all zero division errors
so it takes in x
it tries to return
invert x
if it's the case that there is a zero division error
oops
we will handle it
so the except lines has
we're handling zero division errors
what should we do
well let's print out that we handled it
and let's return zero
okay so now we can invert
safe two
and what will happen will invert safe will call invert
invert will compute 0.5 print out never printed
if x is zero return
0.5 which is returned from invert safe
and nothing ever happens with the except part
because there never was a zero division error
or an error of any kind
but what happens when we invert save zero
well this is never printed
because even though we got all the way down here
inside invert
we raised in exception
that exception was handled here
we printed out the fact that we handled that error
and then we returned zero
and why does this hate division by zero
well that's the message that you get
in a zero division error division by zero right there
okay
so there's a basic example
let's look at some slightly more complicated examples
and see if we can figure out
what python would do
what would python do
so here's the same
program
except instead of why I used result this time
and invert safe is slightly different
because it's just going to return a string version
of e instead of returning zero
same thing okay
so what happens about invert safe one divided by zero
well what's going to happen
is that before we ever even call invert safe
we figure out what we're calling
and then we evaluate the operand to figure out
what we're calling it on
and what we're calling it on
doesn't have a value
because dividing one by zero here
what raise is zero divisionary
so this tri statement is never executed
because this function is never called
because before we ever have a chance to call it
we already have raised an exception
so the answer is invert safe zero
one over zero will raise a zero division error
we haven't handled that case
okay what about try invert safe zero
except zero division error and print handled
let's try it up
so we're gonna try to invert safe
we're gonna handle
a zero division error
and we'll just print out handled
we execute that tri statement
it doesn't say handled
notice no exclamation mark
instead it just says handled division by zero
which is what we get from this line
when invert safe handles this exception
the exception is gone
it's already been handled
and so it's never raised to this outer tri statement
so this one is outside of this one
because this line try
was executed before this line try because try
first we first execute this try
which means we
call invert safe
and invert safe has its own inner tri statement
what about invert safe one divided by zero
what sort of problem does that cause
well we should have another zero division arrow right
not quite if we invert
safe one over zero
then what we get is a name error
because the operator is evaluated before the operator
so we never even get a chance to divide one by zero
because we've already failed to figure out
what inverts safe meets
let's look at an example of where we might
use exception handling
this is an
important higher order function called reduce
reduce is
there to reduce a whole sequence of values to a single
value
here is a description of the reduce function
there is a built in version of reduce
in the inter tools module
but we can also write our own
it takes a function
a sequence in an initial value
and combines the elements of the sequence pairwise
using the function
which takes two arguments
starting with the initial value
for example if we are reduced using multiplication
two four and eight
starting with one
that's the equivalent of multiplying one by two
wrote multiplying that result by four
and then multiplying that result by eight
which gives us 64
so f is a two argument function
s is a sequence of values that can all be the second
argument to that function
f an initial has to be a value that can be the first
argument
the last constraint is that the return value of f
must also be able to be the first argument to f
because when you call f
you're going to pass that value right back
into another call to f
if we reduce power
1 2 3 4 starting with an initial value two
what will happen is that we'll raise
two to earth progressively larger power
so we start out by raising two to the power of one
which gives us two
we then raise
that two to the power of two giving us four
we then raise four to the power three
giving us sixty four
and sixty four to the power of four
is all of a sudden a very large number
so that's what it means to reduce
we'll end up getting 16 million
just by raising two to the first
and then the result of the second
then the result of the third
then the result to the fourth
let's implement this function
reduce takes f a sequence s and an initial value
the point is to combine
elements of s using f
starting with initial
and the example that we looked at was to reduce
using mall
two four and eight
starting with the No.1
and that's supposed to give us 64
or for instance we could reduce using ad one two
three and four
starting with zero and that would give us 10
from operator
in torque ad and mole
the simplest
implementation I could think of is to say for x and s
initial equals f
of initial and x
and then we return initial
that passes the dock tests
we could also write this recursively
so for instance we'd write
if not s so it's empty then we'll just return initial
there's no more work to do otherwise
we get the first and the rest of s
and we return the result of calling reduce on f
the rest of s
and then updating initial to be f of initial
and the first value
that passes our doctors as well
now how way we use reduce
well for instance
let's say we want to write a function divide all
which takes enumerator and a sequence of denominators
and divides the numerator by all the denominators
that's just reduce
when we reduce with a division function
all of the denominators starting with the numerator
so
we can call divide all
on 1024 is our numerator
dividing out two and four and eight
and the result will be 16
that's what's left over
when you divide by all of these numbers
now what if there's a zero in the middle of this
there's a zero division error
and let's say that's not what we want divide all to do
what we want it to do
is compute the result of dividing by all the ds
but if there's ever a zero division
error
we'd like to instead return infinity
that's how you get infinity in python
so in our new implementation we get inf
or infinity in that case but we still get 16 there
the advantage of using error handling in this way
is that our implementation of reduce
doesn't need to know anything
about zero division errors
instead we write a function
where we know we're calling reduce with
another function
that may raise a zero division error
and so it's this function
that knows what's getting passed into reduce
that handles the error
therefore we've created a separation of concerns
divide all knows all about dividing
reduce knows all about reducing
but reduce has no out knowledge of what dividing does
or what errors it causes
and
divide all doesn't really need to know how to combine
elements it just knows it needs to call reduce