61 election No.16 announcements
homework three is due on Thursday
you can also
earn back any lost composition points on your hog
project by revising your project this week
and turn in the revised version on Friday
you'll find instructions on exactly how to do that
on piazza
and the important point is that instead of writing ok
dash dash cement
you write ok dash dash revise
this is a lighter week in terms of assignments
but I really encourage you to
spend some time on lab
discussion and tutorials this week
in order to make sure
that you know what's going on in the course
maybe while you were working on the cats project
you fell behind
an lecture a little bit
now is a great time to catch up
here are all the important links
there are recordings of any
past events that you might have missed
like lab and discussion orientations and
exam prep sessions
from previous weeks
while this week is a little bit lighter
we are just a few weeks away from intern too
and there's another project coming out next week
so things will get busier
and you'll be in a great position to handle all that
as long as you're caught up by the end of this week
but if you're not cut up by the end of this week
it will be quite difficult to catch up later
so now is your chance
I hope you take advantage of it
mutable functions
are functions that have data associated with them
that changes
so here's a function with behavior
that varies over time
it's a model of a bank account
that starts out with a balance of $100 in it
and using a function called withdraw
or going to withdraw money from the bank account
so calling withdraw
of an amount 25
will return
the balance that remains in the bank account
we started with a hundred an hour down to 75
so the argument here is the amount to withdraw
the return value is the remaining balance
if I call withdraw again on 25
I'll have withdrawn from the remaining balance
and be left with 50
a second withdrawal of the same amount
leads to a different return value
and that's a function that changes over time
if I now try to withdraw 60 but only 50 remains
it will tell me that there are insufficient funds
so the question is where is this balance stored
and it's going to be within the function
so the way we do this is that we create a new function
using a higher order function called make withdraw
which takes the initial balance
and we would have to have done that
before we made all these calls to withdraw
now withdraw
is a function that has apparent frame
the make withdraw frame
and that is where the data will live
that records the balance of the bank account
that is modeled by the withdraw function
okay so I've
told you first
how to use this
without telling you how to implement it
and we're going to work up to the implementation
after we look at
the environment diagram that we want to create
so here's the goal
the goal is to have make withdraw
be something that creates
bank accounts that can be withdrawn from
which will be represented by functions
and by calling make withdraw
with some initial balance
I will have bound that balance in a frame
I'll create a withdraw function and I'll return it
and I'll bind that to the name withdraw
in the global frame
so now each time I call withdraw
I'm going to call it by introducing a new frame
where the parent frame is f one
because as the parent of the function
and therefore it will have access to the bounce
and it can do what withdrawing does which is
to reduce the balance by amount
and return the remaining balance
so the balance will be astold here
in the parent frame f one
of the withdraw function
and it's within this parent frame
that will contain the balance
are the local state of the withdraw function
and by local state
I mean the information associated with the function
that is particular to that function
but might change over time
every call to withdraw will introduce a new frame
but a new frame with the same parent
and it will discrease the balance by some amount
and the amount is the amount that's passed
into withdraw when it's called
and all the calls to the function have the same parent
so they share the same balance
and that's why the withdraw function
can represent a bank account
that changes over time
now how do we implement this
well we're going to need an assignment statement
in order to change the balance
but it will be a special kind
so first let's review
what happens when we use an assignment statement
inside of a function
what happens is that assignment binds names to values
in the first frame of the current environment
so normally when you have an assignment statement
inside of a deaf statement
that's going to bind the name difference
inside of a frame for % difference
so here we see that
% difference contains the name difference
which is computed as the absolute value of x minus y
in this case and then is bound
in the first frame of the current environment
because this is an assignment statement
and the execution rule for assignment statements is
to evaluate all the expressions on the right of equals
from left to right
then bind the names on the left to the resulting values
in the current frame
okay so
our assignment statement as it exists today
can only affect the current frame
it cannot affect the parent frame
we need a new kind of assignment statement to do that
it's called non local assignment
and it enables persistent local state
so here's the actual implementation of make withdraw
it takes an initial balance
it returns a withdraw function
that starts with this balance
and so in order to return that function
it defines withdraw which takes in some amount
to withdraw
it declares balance non local
now this statement
non local balance is a new kind of statement
what it says is that
changes to the name balance
will happen in the frame frame wake withdraw
instead of in the frame frame withdraw
now for the logic of withdraw
if amount is greater than balance then you're broke
return insufficient funds
otherwise
balance is rebound to balance minus amount
and then we return the balance
because that's what withdraw does
it returns the remaining balance
after a mount is deducted
and then from make withdraw
we need to return the withdraw function
so there's one new line
here that's different from before
it declares the name balance non local
and we tend to put non
local statements at the
top of the functions in which they appear
although that's not strictly required
and what it does is it tells you
about
all of the assignment statements that will happen
to balance from here on out within this scope
that they will change bindings of balance
somewhere in a non local frame
so what happens when we actually get
to the assignment line
is that it rebinds balance in the first
non local frame
in which it was bound previously
so let's say you call make withdraw and then you call
the function that comes out withdraw
balance will be bound in a make withdraw frame
because balance is a formal parameter
of the make withdraw function
here
inside the parentheses in the deaf statement header
so that's where it was bound originally
and the rebinding that happens when you say
balance equals balance minus amount
will happen in the first non local frame
in which it was bound previously
so let's take a look first at the environment diagram
and then add some coat
so here's the same implementation
that I just showed you
creating with a withdraw
function means calling make withdraw
which introduces a new frame or balances bounce 100
the body of make withdraw
defines a new function and returns it
and that new function is bound to the name withdraw
in the global frame
now I'm going to call withdraw
which introduces a new frame
balance is currently 100
we declare it to be non local
we check if amount is greater than balance
it's not so we don't execute this return statement
instead we execute this assignment statement
which reduces balance from 100 to 75
now without non local
this would be a statement
about balance in the current frame
but since there's a non local statement
this balance rebinds the balance in a non local frame
the one that's apparent
of the current frame f two
so which frame you go to
when you go up the chain of parents
from this parent to this parent etc
until you find the first instance of that name
you're rebinding
so balance gets changed to 75
and then 75 gets returned
okay so we make another call to withdraw
and balance gets changed to 50
right there from 75 to 50
so what's really new about this example
you could always refer to the current value of balance
from within the body of withdraw
because you could always look up names
in apparent frame
what you couldn't do before is change them
now you can change the values bound to names
in parent frames
but to do that you need a non local statement
so here's that same implementation one more time
if I create a
function called w
by calling make withdraw on 100
w is a function
that when I call it
it deducts 10 from the current bout
assuming the argument I pass in is 10
but I can pass in a different argument if I want
and now we're all the way down to 50
now 50 isn't a whole lot
if I try to withdraw enough to buy a new
car I will have insufficient funds
but I can still withdraw another 10 and get down to 40
let's talk about the details of non local assignment
a non local statement has the following effect
future assignments to the name
change its pre existing binding
in the first
non local frame of the current environment
in which that name is bound
and the python docks
this first non local frame is called an enclosing scope
it is possible to have multiple
names separated by commas in a non local statement
and there are restrictions on
exactly what names you can put there
these are
directly from the python three language reference
names listed in a non local statement must refer
to pre existing bindings in an enclosing scope
so these names have to have already been used
and the names listed in a non local statement must not
collide mean be the same as
pre existing bindings in the local scope
or the current frame as we call it in this course
so you can't declare something non local
if it's in the current frame already
but it must be in apparent frame
or the parent of the parent
somewhere between the global and the local frame
in the chain of frames
that makes up the current environment
if you want to read more yourself
you can find all of the python docks online
so you see x equals to somewhere in a program
based on the context of that program
it actually might do different things
so
here are the many meanings of an assignment statement
if there's no non local statement
an x is not bound locally already
then this creates a new binding from x to
in the first frame of the current environment
the current frame
if there's no non local statement
and x is already bound
then it rebinds x
the previous binding is lost
this all happens
in the first frame of the current environment
and these two conditions are old
but what if there is a non local x statement
before x equals two
then
it also must be the case that
x is bound in a non local frame
the effect is to rebind x to two
in the first non local frame
of the current environment in which it is found
the old binding is lost
if non local x is declared
but x is not bound in a non local frame
then you get a syntax error
and the error message will say no binding for non local
x found
if non local x statement occurs
x is bound in a non local frame
but it's also bound locally
which is not allowed
then you get a different syntax hitter
that says the name x is a parameter and non local
the exact text of these errors will
change over time with different implementations of
python but
they correspond
the two conditions that we saw on the last slide
x must already be bound
but it cannot be bound in the current frame
now these are general rules for binding non locally
and they occur in many languages
there's one feature that arises
it's particular to python
that you just have to be aware of
python actually tries to pre compute
which frame contains each name
before executing the body of a function
within the body of a function
all instances of a name must refer to the same frame
which means you're not allowed to have the same name
in the same function body
actually refer to two different frames
that just doesn't work
so let's say I'd tried to write the following program
which is the same as we saw before
but deleting the non local statement
the error would arise here
if an amount is greater than balance
what would happen is
by inspecting the body of withdraw
python would have concluded that
balance is a local name
because it has local assignment statement right here
remember we deleted the non local statement
so believing that balance is a local name
it will only look
in the frame for withdraw for that name balance
it will never find the one in the enclosing scope
and so you'll get an unbound local error
local variable balance referenced before assignment
so everything worked before
but now we're going to remove the non local statement
I'll just comment it out so you know where it was
but it's not going to do anything anymore
because now it's just a comment
I can still call make withdraw
because that just creates the function
but as soon as I call the function
I get this unbound local error
and it says it's online four which is here
now this is just such a weird thing
because we've always been able to refer to balance
even if it's an enclosing scope before
and that ability hasn't changed
except for that
local assignment to balance
and non local lookup of balance
cannot appear in the same function
because balance has to refer to one particular frame
and in this case it's trying to refer to two
now if we got rid of this line
we'd be back in a situation where we could
call this function
it just wouldn't do anything anymore
but it wouldn't cause an unbound local error
so this is a quirk of the python language
that just is part of how it's implemented
and something you need to be aware of
as you start using non local statements
now using non local statements is not the only way
to create a mutable function
instead I could use an existing multiple value
so here's an alternate implementation of mank withdraw
it takes in a balance
puts balance in a list with only one element
remember that lists can be changed
and so what deaf withdraw amount can do
is check and see if the amount is greater
than the balance that's stored within the list b
if it is then we return in sufficient funds
otherwise we reassigned the element at index 0 2
whatever it was before
minus amount and return that value
here we see the name b is bound outside
of the definition of the withdraw function
which means
that all calls to withdraw can refer to that same b
and that b can change because it's a list
and we can change it using
element assignment which changes a list
so the environment diagram for this
version of make withdraw
looks a little bit different
let's take a close look
we create the make withdraw function
now call it the make withdraw list
we call it in this line with an initial balance of 100
but instead of referring to that balance
we're going to make reference instead to a list called
b which contains the balance
originally with 100 in it
each culta withdraw
in this case one with 25 as the amount
we'll update this mutable value of this list
to contain a new number
it
used to be 100 now at 75
now we don't have any non local statements
because we're never changing what b is bound to
or what balance is bound to
or what withdraw is bound to
from within the body of withdraw
so we don't need to make any non local assignment
instead
all we're doing is we're changing mutable values
so these are two different ways
of having persistent local state
inside of a mutable function
we really understand why
local state is called local state
when we look at what happens when there are multiple
mutable functions in the same program
so here's my implementation
let's first say that john has a bank account
represented by it with draw function
where john has $100
and it's friends steven
also has a bank account with $100,000
so
john can john is a function
steven is a different function
and they're not the same
and they're not equal
and why is that
while they're representing
different bang accounts with different amounts in them
so if john withdraws 10 and then draws another 10
stephen
has an entirely separate account with 100,000 in it
and he pulls out maybe 1000 at a time
but notice by doing that
he's not affecting john's total
so if john takes out another 10
it's just marching down the balance that john has
within its function
stephen has this separate balance with 1000 in it
and so it can take out
another thousand whenever he wants
but if john ever tries to take out 1000
well that's not gonna work out
because there's so little funds in there
that it's more reasonable to take out
just one at a time
or if a really important purchase comes up
then of course john could take out a whole 16
steven on the other hand
can be pulling out 10,000 at a time no problem
or another 80,000
or another 7950
now we've reached a point
where both stephen and john have the same balance
but they're still not equal
because they're different accounts
and they're still not the same
the only sense in which there is some equality
relationship there
is that if they both withdraw
the same amount at this point
then their balances will be equal
so just for this brief amount of time
john has a balance of 50
and stephen has a balance of 50
but john just withdrew a dollar
and so now they no longer have an equal balance
so we've reached a point in our
writing of programs where we've lost something
called referential transparency
perhaps this was something you didn't even know you had
let me tell you what it is
expressions are referentially transparent
if substituting an expression with its value
does not change the meaning of the program
so let's say I have just multiplication
in addition to call expressions
that are used in order to make some computation
this was from long ago in the course
in a referentially transparent program
if I replace mull four six by its value 24
I have a program with the same meaning
so it's an expression that still
evaluates to the same value
if I again
replace add to in 24 with its value 26
I still have the same program
it looks different of course
but it has the same meaning
everything evaluates to the same thing
now this is only true
when we have a referential transparency
mutation operations undermine that
because they do more than just return of value
they change the environment
so this expression
would be different from this expression
if adding somehow change the environment
in addition to adding together its arguments
now adding doesn't
these are referentially transparent expressions
but when we have mutation
which is the enemy of referential transparency
then you run into trouble
so let's take a look at an example
where referential transparency is lost
this example is also just a good practice for
understanding
non local assignment
so I would suggest you try to work
through it to yourself before you watch me
okay here's what's gonna happen
well define f
and then we'll call it on the argument one
so x is bound to one in a frame f one
immediately we rebind x to four
and then we define another function called g
which gets returned
that g function is returned and bound to a
in this assignment statement
and then we call a on two
so what's a well a is this function g
and g of y gets bound where y is equal to two
introducing a new frame the g frame
with y bound to two
which defines another function age and returns it
and that return function h will be bound to b
according to this assignment statement
so now we have amb
bound to gnh respectively
and what we're going to do is call b twice
in the first cult b
I'll pass in the argument three
for its formal parameter z
okay so we've made it call
where z is bound to three
an x is declared non local
and then
x is rebound to whatever x is currently plus one
we have to look through the current environment
which starts with f three
and then goes to f two
and then its parent is f one
and its parent is the global frame
and find the first occurrence
in this chain where x is bound
which is here
in the f one frame
so any change to the value of x
will be a rebinding in this frame
in this case we change it from four to five
then we return x y and z
well there's z it's three there's y it's two
there's x it's five
and the total is 10
so let's remember this for a long time
this thing evaluated to 10
we have to remember it
because we still have to evaluate this thing
so the total will be ten plus something else
okay what's this something else
well
it's what you get when you call the h function on four
which rebinds x two x plus one
which x well let's look
we first look an f four there's no x
then we look an f two there's no x
then we look at its parent f one
there's the x
that's the one we're gonna rebind
now it's six instead of five
and we return four plus two plus six is twelve
ten and twelve together gives us a total of 22
so
there's an interesting example of how non local works
but what about referential transparency
well this used to equal 22
and b3 evaluated a 10
but what if instead I replaced this function call
by its value
and then I visualize the execution
the difference now is that the effect of calling p
would never have happened
because I used it value instead
and so the total is 21
there was never a second call to the h function
because I just used the value 10
instead of calling beyond three
and therefore
x only got incremented once
instead of being incremented twice
from four to five to six
so this program has a different meaning
from the one where I won't be three
and the reason they're different
is that now I have functions
that cause mutations
referential transparency is lost
that's all for today's lecture
but I'm going to go back and recommend an
old exam problem
from spring 2008
as a good example of a review problem
that you should look at
around this time in the course
I picked problem four b
from spring 2018
midterm 2
which is a six point problem
implement combo
which takes two non negative integers a and b
it returns the smallest integer
that contains all of the digits of a in order
as well as all of the digits of b in order
to enter zin one comes out
I'm not going to walk through how to solve this problem
I'm just going to
point out some things that are good to notice
before you start solving this problem
1st what kind of problem is this what kind of
solution technique might apply
well if you have two integers
and you think about
building an integer that has
all the digits of both of them
there are many ways to do that
for example with this five three one and four three two
I could start with a four or I could start with a five
both would be reasonable
so I could do 4 5 3 1 2 or 4 5 3 2 1 or 4 3 2 5 3 1
there's many different ways
when you're choosing among many different options
and you're trying to count them all
or find the best one
or print them all out
that's a tree recursion problem
here we have a series of choices
which digit to put next in the result
and there are many different ways to choose among those
so tree recursion means looking for base cases
looking for recursive cases
and figuring out how to combine
the results of multiple recursive calls
and there are other cues like here's a recursive call
okay okay but
without even glancing at the starter code
you should try
to figure out what kind of problem this is
and 2nd you can start looking for base cases
and in this problem
one of the base cases is provided to you
remember a base case is an
input where you can immediately return the answer
so if you're trying to build an integer with
all the digits of zero
and all the digits of three to one
apparently the answer is three to one
what happened to the zero
oh there's an explanation
the No.0 has no digits so zero is not in the result
so that's a useful
dock test because it tells you what to do with zero
and also a useful dock test
because it seems like I could compute
this result from these inputs
really easily
it's a base case
I'll let you take it from there
if you want to learn more
about how to solve this problem
you could go to the resources page
of the course website
and find the walkthrough video
that describes how to approach and solve the problem
good luck