here's the 61a lecture 10
q a yeah the question is about what does
it mean to escape
a character so typically when you put
something in
in quotes for example every character is
processed or interpreted by python when
you put a backslash
the not the division one the other one
um
essentially what python does is it takes
the next character
and bundles it up with that backslash so
backslash
t as john is writing on the screen right
now is a tab
so it doesn't treat it as two characters
backslash t
it's one character so the escaping of a
character means
you're essentially creating a special
symbol uh there's a tab
there's a new line and there's a number
of other of these as well
so here's a good example that john is
showing you
the length of hello there oh by the way
when you print hello there notice that
you get that nice tab
it's replacing slash t that's escaped
out
and then the length of that list is the
length of hello which is five
the length of there that is five and
then one more
which is the tab this works really well
john when you're you're keeping up with
the highlighting nicely
and then the length of the tab which is
one character not two characters
so uh so a new line or a line break
is so if john writes a hello backslash
and there
then when you print that while the
length of that is still 11 of course
when you print it
you just have a new line um in the
in the print you know
so it's the same thing that backslash
and is one character and it's a new line
or a line break
and it counts as one character the next
question was
what is slicing for a string or a list
and this topic was lightly covered in
today's lecture but will be covered in
more depth on friday
yeah so this is called slicing
whereas this is called item selection
slicing is when you have a colon
somewhere within the square brackets
but both of these occur after another
expression and this expression has to
give you some kind of container
like a list or strings behaved in the
same way
and then this part tells you how to get
parts of this
item selection will give you an
individual element of whatever this is
and a slice will give you some
subsequence
we talk about this in like some amount
of detail in friday's lecture but uh
slipped it in here just to give you an
idea of how it works
um this says starting at index one
and going up to but not including index
three
counting upwards so that would go one
two
and then we're done because we hit three
get all the elements of s and put them
into a string so
uh element zero is h element one is e
element two is l so that's why you got
this e and that l in the result
if we make a list
well let's use different numbers
um selecting an element of a list
will give you just an individual number
in this case because this is a list full
of numbers it doesn't give you back a
list
full of six that's a different thing so
six
and six are different things and this
syntax this item selection which we've
used a lot in this lecture just gives
you one element
slicing actually gives you back a new
list with some of the elements but not
all
so if i go from 1 to 3 of t this is
element zero so we're going to skip that
get element one and element two and it
will put it into a new list
um it turns out that it's so common to
go from the beginning of the list
up to a point that if you leave out the
first index then it just starts at zero
and it's so common to go from somewhere
to the end
that if you leave out the second index
then it just goes to the end of the
string which would be equivalent to
saying
one to the length of t um
and in fact you could leave out both of
them though you would just kind of get
uh equivalent list back so there are
reasons to do that that we'll talk about
later in the course
but uh but so far like if you leave out
the first and the end then you don't get
a subsequence you just get the whole
thing
so you can think about that the slicing
is just you know we did the range
in for loops it's basically specifying a
range of values
and you are grabbing that range of
values from either
a string or a list
um and the the bug that will bite you
over and over again
is that that last element in the slice
range is
not inclusive you go from
the first element in the slice one up to
one minus not including the last one and
that will bite you over
and over and over again it still bites
me so just be warned
yeah so if you say i want the six seven
eight okay that starts at index one
and goes up to index three and you try
to go from one to three
you won't have the eight that is the
that's the bug you want to look at
by the way there's a good reason for
that um because indices
because indexing starts on zero when we
say
zero to the length of the list the
length of the list is the index of that
is one more than the last element so
that turns out to be pretty convenient
that i can just say zero to the length
of the list but when you're sort of
manually doing these things you got
by the way this is a classic problem in
computer science we call it the off by
one error
um often you're off in the in the
beginning or in the end by one it bites
everybody over and over again
uh uh somebody's asking in the chat does
t colin create a new list or
modify the original list um it
it i'm not exactly sure i understand the
question but i think what you're
asking is if i assign
something to t colon um what happens
uh yeah so let's just try it and then
we'll talk about what's going on
if i say u equals t and then i slice all
the way from the beginning to the end
what do i get it turns out you have two
lists that contain the same values five
six seven and eight
why does it matter that they're
different well as soon as we start
changing the contents of lists which
we'll do
uh next week i think this will matter
so far it doesn't really matter at all
to your life and in fact if you
do project two just using what we've
taught you so far
um this distinction won't matter at all
but it will start to matter quite a bit
when we get to project three and and
stuff starts changing
so um yeah so this is an important
distinction eventually
uh not quite yet the next question was
whether you could use negative numbers
in a slice and if so what do they mean
good excellent question uh the answer is
yes
do you want to do an example john yeah
so actually slicing is
very flexible but you don't need to know
every detail for this course like
we'll focus on just counting up but here
are some convenient things
is that for selecting an element
you can actually put in a negative
number and that will count from the
end instead of from the beginning
so negative 1 means the last element
and negative 2 means the second to last
element
and this fact about using negative
indices
also applies to slicing so if i wanted
to slice
from element 1 which is here
up to but not including the last element
i could write that and get the six seven
eight
um and this would be equivalent to
writing
that so
um yeah i i guess that's the story
with using indices that are negative
is that they count from the end there's
also a way to
count backwards um and
this like definitely won't show up
anywhere in the course except for it did
show up in the first lecture so
maybe we'll talk about it there um i i
did some demo of reversing strings
and it turns out that once you've
decided
where you're going to start and where
you're going to end you can decide
how to go from one element to the next
and normally you would go
by adding one but you could instead go
by
subtracting one and then you end up
working backwards
so like a less confusing version of this
would be if i want to go
from the beginning all the way to the
end
and include the last element but i want
every other element
then i could add a 2 there and it would
give me the 5 and the 7 and the 9.
this says i want to start at the last
element when i go up 2 but not including
element
1 which is 6 um to get
from nine to whatever's next i subtract
one instead of adding one
so yeah that's the full flexibility of
the slice notation
is that you're allowed to have negative
numbers here and there to describe
things counting from the end and you're
allowed to have either positive or
negative numbers here
to tell you how to advance through the
list
so you can think about the the list and
the string is not living on a line but
on a circle
yeah and so when you get to the end like
the next element is the first element so
if you just think about it on a circle
then the negative sort of makes a little
bit more sense i think it's a little
weird
indexing a negative one but it turns out
to actually be convenient
algorithmically sometimes
when you want to move through the list
good question so the question is for a
range
i said it wasn't a list so what is it if
it's not a list
and the answer is it's a range uh
so it's its own thing um you can tell
it's not a list because it certainly
doesn't look like a list
you could even ask python what is this
thing and we'll say oh it's a range
which is different than what you get
when you build a list
where the type of that is
a list
the reason it's different is mostly
because you can
represent a range very compactly just by
memorizing where it starts and where it
is
then whenever you wanted you could
compute stuff in the middle
which means that i could create a very
long list if
i mean a very long range if i wanted to
and you know python hasn't really done
any work yet it's just remembered that
here's the beginning and here's the end
and if i want to know how long
it is well that's obvious i just like
subtract the
beginning from the end and i know how
long it is now if i actually wanted to
compute some particular value
then python's going to do some like
clever tricks behind the seats if i want
the
thousands value then it will just add
the number 1000 to the number three
in order to find out that the result is
and it didn't kind of count up from
three to four to five to six to seven to
eight
it just performed addition on the other
hand if i ever try to take
all of the elements in this and put them
into a list
uh python will crash because lists are
represented explicitly like all the
values
are allocated in memory and uh you have
to have enough memory
for all however many there were elements
and
my computer apparently does not maybe i
should upgrade but the point is that the
list
is kind of less flexible in the sense
that it can't represent such a huge
range
but much more flexible and that list
could represent kind of any arbitrary
collection of values whereas ranges have
to be some sequential order
you can think of it as sort of a
symbolic representation the list is
explicit
right you've literally stuck all these
values in there and they are there in
memory somewhere
the range is sort of symbolic it's sort
of the promise
when you go to ask for the values i'll
be able to figure out what they are and
you can see why that's so much more
efficient
it's going to do everything on the fly
only as needed
yeah great question so the question was
about how do you concatenate lists with
plus
how do you repeat lists with the times
operator like what's going on there um
so maybe we'll just review those
examples and talk about them a little
bit
um so if i have three four five
and i have uh eight nine
ten
and i add those this doesn't do any
addition
instead in computer science this is
called overloading an
operator so that means it does multiple
things
and it does something special in the
case that this is a list and this is a
list which is to build a longer list
that has all the elements of s
followed by all the elements of t and
you can still use this operator
kind of like you would addition with
numbers like you could
take the result of this and add
something else to it
and then you get an even longer list and
here we see we've added in t
twice well actually we have all the
elements of s and all the elements of t
and then all the elements of t
again um
python designers decided like oh
if you could add t and t together that's
kind of like multiplying t by 2.
so it turns out that if you have a list
and you multiply it by an integer
you end up with the elements
of that list some number of times
and like do you need to know this well
um
i guess we taught it to you so now you
know it and you might as well know it
um it actually does show up on occasion
in um in real programs
and uh yeah
not often i find it sort of offensive
as somebody who's trained in applied
mathematics because when i see that
t or s i think of it as a vector and
when i see a two times up front that
should be a vector multiplications on
matlab for example
which is a numerical
programming environment two times a
vector or a list is
you literally do p point wise
multiplication so i think this is a
little weird
but let me just mention one thing that
john said is that the plus operator and
the time dot
is overloaded and you've now seen three
operations that can be done numeric
adding integers or floating point values
strings you can do string concatenation
using the addition operator
and now on lists as well this is one odd
thing
about python not being a strongly typed
language is that
you know if you just see a line of code
that says you know s plus t
you may not know what s and t are you
don't know if the plus is
numeric uh edition string concatenation
or list concatenation so that's sort of
a quirky little aspect of these
non-typed languages
or explicitly type languages so yeah
good question so
there are two parts to this question one
was about the structure of list
comprehensions and how they work
and one was about what is meant by a
literal and does something need to be a
literal to be part of a
list comprehension the term literal
is actually just describing um
cases in which you build
something by just writing out its
contents
in the code as opposed to building it
out
programmatically through iteration or
something like that so
a string literal is when you build a
string
just by writing quote and then the
contents of the string and then end
quote
and a list literal is when you build a
list
by just typing out its elements inside
of square brackets that's what the term
literal means and uh there are other
ways you could build this same string
like i could
build it out of uh h e and
llo and this was not constructed through
a string literal instead this was
constructed through a compound
expression that had two little string
literals in it
and an addition operator and likewise
you could do the same thing
um here so um a list comprehension
is a way of
building up a new list from the elements
of some other container
so i could build up a list of uh
x plus one where i need to come up with
what what are the values that i'm going
to add one to
and then x gives you a name for each
element
and the result is x plus one for every
in well something and here i could write
any expression
so it doesn't have to be a literal it
could be anything uh
but it does have to have elements so
i could write a list literal to do it
at which point i would have bound x to 3
computed x plus 1 is 4 and put that into
the result
or i could have used a name if i already
had 345 in a name i could have written
x plus 1 for x in t and t
actually isn't a literal it's a name
it's like a variable name referring to
some list that already exists
so in that sense there's no restrictions
on what expression you put here
there is a restriction on the value of
that expression which is that it has to
be something that you can iterate over
so if i just put
5 in here i'll get an error because it's
going to try to assign
x to every element in 5 but 5 isn't a
container it doesn't have any elements
and so that's what this means int object
is not iterable
the int object is referring to the 5 and
it's not something that you can
have as the value of this expression
um yeah that's that's really the only
uh restriction you can put any
expression you want here there's no
restriction on that
here you just put names so this is not a
place where you would put larger
expressions
but instead it's just saying here's the
name i'm going to use to refer to an
element in whatever's here and then here
you can put any expression you want
as long as it evaluates to something
that you can iterate over
and let me state the obvious here that i
mean this is just a shortcut
you could have written explicitly your
own for loop to do this
right you could have said four acts in
the list create a new list where every
element of that list is
one plus the element in the previous
list so just this is just shorthand
because it's sort of a common thing that
we do on lists but
it's you know you could have written out
the for loop all by all by yourself the
python creator side
this is such a common thing let's make
it a little bit easy to
do yeah that's exactly right it's also
wonderful for bug prevention because
there's no
like manipulating of some list that
might already exist or whatever you just
like say oh
here's something that exists and then
all in one go you just build something
new
yeah so the question is what's a
container what does that mean
and are there other containers as well
so we try to give you some examples
like a range is also a container it's
not a list
but it's got a bunch of elements in it
you can iterate over those elements
you can figure out whether some element
is in there so
um if i have r which is a range from
three to six
and then i have s which is three
four and five
for the rest of the code it actually
kind of doesn't matter
that this is a range and this is a list
i write the same thing either way i can
say 4 and r just like in say 4 and s
i can get the element at index 1.
come on the element at index one of r
just like i can get the element of index
one at s
so when we use the term container in
this course we're describing
things that can be manipulated
in this way using item selection using
this in operator to figure out whether
something's in there
and it doesn't actually matter whether
something's a list or a range
or pretty soon we'll talk about
something else called the tuple
we'll talk about something on wednesday
called the dictionary and all of these
are kind of just ways of containing
values so
i guess that's the short answer is that
a container isn't like
something that is
a particular type but instead it
describes
all the types that can be used in for
loops
used within use with element selection
and in python the technical term for
these
uh varies a little bit depending on
exactly which of these
operations you can use um but the most
common term
is that these are iterable values
meaning you can kind of uh
iterate through them using a four state
and you know i just want to sort of
re-emphasize
the power of abstraction here the fact
that these things are implemented behind
the scenes differently
from your perspective you don't really
care um and now you make here
computationally and for other reasons
but from the from the programmatic point
of view
you index you slice you do everything
exactly the same that's nice that's nice
that you don't have to have a different
syntax for everything that'd be sort of
a drag
oh there was a follow-up question of
this which is
uh is a string a container yeah strings
strings are a lot like lists they don't
behave exactly the same
but the best way to think about it is
that it's a container of the letters
that are in the string
the quirky thing about strings is that
when you have a string
and you get an element out of it you get
a string back
and you could get an element out of that
and you get an element out of that
and like lists typically don't work this
way so so strings are a little bit
different than everything else but yes
there's still a container
yeah i think i understand the question
so let me try to rephrase it
so you're asking i can compute n
factorial
as n times n minus one times n minus two
all the way down to one i can write that
expression out
or i can write it as 1 times 2 times 3
up to n and you're asking is there one
that is preferred over the other
um i'd have to think through all that i
don't see a reason why
first of all let's agree that the answer
is exactly the same the order in which
you do the multiplication
or if we were doing something else with
addition absolutely doesn't matter
so numerically mathematically there's no
difference computation i don't believe
there's a difference
um john do you see a difference between
the order in which you go
um for factorial it really kind of
doesn't matter
what order you go in yeah but
for other problems it can so and in
particular
this homework problem called ping pong
it's easy to figure out what the next
number is if you know where you are
it's hard to know like what the previous
number was
that's more complicated whereas with
factorial you know counting up is no
harder easier than counting down but let
me just show you what
factorial would look like if you were
counting up and using recursion
and then you know how to do it
so first of all the version where you
count down
has this um nice property which is that
you kind of know when you're done
just by this special value zero when
you're counting up
that's not really true you have to know
where you are
and you have to know whether you're done
so for this reason if you're computing a
factorial kind of working your way up
then you have to know where you are um
so you have to know that you're going
we're computing the factorial of n
and right now you're at k
and if it happens to be that n equals k
well then you've kind of hit the end
right so
in this case you could return in but
otherwise
you would want to return well
maybe we'll just do k you'd want to
return k times the result of calling
fact helper
on n and k plus 1.
so now we're kind of counting up with k
but this has the wrong signature this
says uh
compute the factorial of n starting at k
so what does this actually do this
computes
k times k plus 1
times k plus 2
all the way up to n okay i should have
called this n in the first case
it doesn't matter because k or n they're
the same so
um if that's what this does then the
definition of factorial
is actually not this anymore
but it's call return the result
of calling fact helper on n starting at
the number one
and then we can compute factorial 4 is 1
times 2 times 3 times 4.
so that's one way to do it there's
actually a third way
to count up and accumulate as you go
that i think we should talk about just
so you know the full flexibility of what
you could do
with recursion is you could say um
that this computes this result
by accumulating the result in
result well
it's too much where
we add in a third argument the result
and if we hit the end
meaning we've reached the end
then we need to put and
put this final k into the result but the
result has everything else multiplied
into it already
and what this will do
is call fact helper on n on k
plus 1 and multiply k into whatever the
result was so far
let me make sure this works and then i
will try to describe what just happened
oh good it does so what this says is
call factorial helper we're going to
compute the factorial of
n k is going to start at 1 and then
we're going to work our way up
and the result the whole factorial is
going to start at 1 because we haven't
multiplied anything into it yet
then if we kind of reach the end
then we need to multiply the k in but
then we're done
um otherwise
we're going to make the result bigger
and pass that bigger thing
into the recursive call so that k gets
multiplied in there
this is really just to keep track of
where we are and this is to
um know when when we're done and in fact
we can get the same result
if we really wanted to be fancy by
saying if k is bigger than
n then we've multiplied in everything
that's one more way to compute factorial
so um yeah i guess the the ping pong
example
from homework kind of pushes you to
explore some of these different ways
in which you can track the result it's
not always the case
that you want to compute the result of
the recursive call and then multiply
something into it
maybe you could just multiply in first
since multiplication is commutative
it doesn't really matter how you do it
you can get the same result either way
with factorial but in other problems
sometimes it's hard to do it one way and
it's easier to do another
and by the way this is a lot like
assignment statements like you said
n equal to four k equal to one
result equal to one uh you know it's
like
while k is less than or equal to n
we're going to uh not change in
but we are going to increment k and
we're going to say result equals k
times result so like this
version looks an awful lot like
uh setting k to one
setting result to one while uh k
less than or equal to n or maybe we'll
make it as explicit as possible well not
k greater than n which is the expression
that we wrote there
then we could uh reassign
k and result to k plus 1 and k times
result
and then eventually return the result
like
that's uh this recursive version
is basically this code just uh
avoiding assignment statements by using
uh function calls instead
i'll add one last thing although it's i
don't think it's particularly important
to this class is that the order of
operation can
matter numerically when for example
you're dealing with very very large
numbers or
very very small numbers the order in
which you do things can create numerical
instability so for example if you
multiply a whole bunch of small numbers
together at the very beginning you'll
get these nasty little rounding
artifacts
so sometimes you have to think about
that in these very complex numeric
things
for what we're doing here it won't
really matter
that's a good question so i think the
question is the difference between a
helper function and a mutual recurrence
so let's look at what john has on the
screen right here
so this is not an example of mutual
recursion this is just recursion
and the only thing that the helper
function is doing
is sort of hiding the fact that the
recursive
call needs three parameters whereas
the the sort of the signature of calling
factorial only requires one parameter
i mean for example we could have just
said look if you want to call recursive
factorial
you have to initialize it with a one and
a one for these other things but that's
that's not nice to the user
and so we want to sort of hide that
implementation detail
and so we create this sort of this this
facade a little bit
right call fact with n and then all
that's going to do is call another
function which itself is recursive
right so if you look at the recursive
call down here in fact helper
i'm using my mouse to point to the
screen by the way which doesn't work it
turns out
um thank you john then that is itself
recursive
yeah a mutually recursive was i forgot
the example i think it was the credit
card example where
one function calls another function
which and that function calls the
previous function so a fact helper for
some reason called fact
then that would be mutually recursive
this is just recursive
with a little bit of sugar coating on
top to hide the implementation details
now that's exactly right and and this is
unrelated but
also might be relevant because it's a
source of confusion
sometimes instead of defining a new
function
and writing fact helper and passing in
the
initial values which i think is fine
practice
sometimes what you'll see is that people
will provide default values
for this and then
call this thing fact
and get rid of this entirely uh now
this will still work will not work uh
because we
called this okay uh this will still work
and what's going on here is that these
numbers one and one
only matter when you call fact with one
argument
as soon as you make a recursive call
we're passing in two different arguments
which means
ignore the default values and use these
values instead
um and and therefore we've got a
function that kind of works
uh this is okay but the old version was
better
because the old version said you know
this is what you call
and you only have to pass in one
argument and you don't even have to
think about what k and result are those
are like
deep buried and some helper functions
that you should never call so i i kind
of like this version
oh sorry i i agree with god i like that
version too and also
the other version where there's the
default parameters
the user could mistakenly call fact four
was
you know two and three and now you're
off to the races
so you don't even you don't even open
the door to the to the ability
to miscall the core function of facts i
i do like this even though it does
require a little bit more code
the next question was what's a helper
function
a great question so this term helper
is used to describe a function that
isn't really useful on its own instead
it's part of the implementation of
another function
and whether something is a helper or not
is really kind of up to interpretation
so
in your hog project i think i would have
described
uh take turn as a helper function for
the play function
meaning it's something that helps you
implement the play function
uh by describing some piece of logic
within it
but then again take turn is kind of
useful on its own because we did some
various like analysis
of like which number of dice gives you
the highest turn score
so in that sense it wasn't really just a
helper function it was useful
for other stuff too so that's the kind
of matter of interpretation part but in
general what it means
the reason i called this fact helper and
described it as a helper function
is that the only reason i wrote it was
to help implement fact
in fact was the main event and this was
just uh there to help it along
yeah that's how i would define it too
the way i think about these things is
there's sort of
an inward facing and an outward facing
functionality
right we create a library of
mathematical routines for computing sine
cosine factorial
tangent square root and all those things
and i want users to be able to call
those functions
in order for me to be able to implement
those i may need to do some gnarly
mathematical operations
the user doesn't need to know about
those so those i'm going to call
auxiliary or helper functions that are
sort of
hidden away they're for the internal
workings but the external
you know what are the functions that are
being called that's the fact
yeah yeah that's a great question so
like when would you use recursion
instead of iteration
if there's a straightforward iterative
approach then it's usually the right
thing to use
the only obvious advantage of recursion
is that if you're trying to track how
many times something happens
or um uh you want to
somehow set it up such that in every
iteration like some other
side effect happens like something gets
written to a log or something like that
then it can be convenient to do it
recursively because then you can just
decorate the function and every time it
gets called
like that information is uh captured
somewhere
so you know that's the main advantage of
doing something recursively that you
could do iteratively
but that's a pretty thin advantage so
most of the time you just want to write
things iteratively if you can
now the tree recursion examples that
we've talked about really
are quite a bit simpler if you write
them
recursively rather than iteratively if
you want to write them iteratively then
you kind of have to keep track
of where you are and the computation in
a way that the interpreter will do for
you if you just write
pre-recursion so this is like
competitions or the towers of hanoi
example
those are cases where i think the
recursive version is often
just preferred because it's so much
simpler
yeah the only thing i would add to that
is i've definitely stumbled upon a few
problems in my life where
just the iterative ones were just a bear
to implement and the recursive ones were
just so
sort of elegant and beautiful but for
the most part i think i think john's
right is that the iterative ones are
probably the way to go in terms of
efficiency and ease of implementation
the question was do you want to put the
helper function
inside the body of the main function
or afterwards yeah you could have done
it either way you could have made that a
local function
uh that um
uh that had scope only within the fact
yeah there were actually like there was
a related question in chats maybe i can
answer them both
the question is like uh
why is this its own function as opposed
to being defined within fact
and do you always need a helper function
when do you know whether you need a
helper function or not
um and recursion in particular the way
to know that you need a helper function
is that you want to track more things
than you have arguments for so if you
want to track
n and k and the result then you need n
and k
and result in the signature and if
they're not there
then you need to write a helper function
should this be
in here instead uh there is a tiny tiny
tiny little advantage
maybe not that tiny which is that we
don't need to track in
in this case so
our code got a little simpler when we
wrote it as an inner function
that would be one motivation to do it
this way um
because this end never changed and it
could always refer to that
you have to get rid of it you have to
get rid of that n2 right there yeah get
rid of that
um
the other advantage of this is that no
one could ever call
fact helper because it's not available
anymore so that's another reason that
sometimes people write inner functions
this is like extremely common in
javascript for some reason is that like
all functions are hidden within other
functions just
as a way of making sure that the wrong
person doesn't ever call them
um and it shows up every once in a while
in a python code base though i think uh
more rarely
yeah so yeah so that's basically the
story it's like if you're gonna share
names then it can be convenient but also
it hides
hides the helper function so that no one
calls the next note
that's what i would have done i would
have embedded in there maybe if i i
don't want anybody else calling it i
don't want it polluting the name space
and so i i would
i would have left it out but i mean they