61 election No.27 announcements
so today we're going to start a new unit in the course
and learn a new programming language
why are we learning a new programming language
well you know python already
you know about functions and data
you know about the object system
you even know advanced topics like
iterators and generators
there's of course
more you can learn about the programming language
but you don't really need to know anything else
in order to build all kinds of things
it turns out you don't just know python
you also know how programming languages work in general
and to demonstrate that
I'll show you that we can
learn a new programming language together
in just one lecture
today's lecture on scheme
so please watch this lecture
then try out what you've learned on the lab
and the homework
that are due Wednesday and Thursday of this week
lab is normally due Tuesday
but since we have an election in the us
I've delated to a Wednesday
and we've tried to make both the lab and the homework
fairly short since its election week
the only other thing to worry about is that midterm
two regrade requests
that should say regrade requests
are due on Monday
and if you need to try it out scheme
instead of installing something
the fastest way is to go to code dot csixtymana org
and load a new scheme interpreter
there it is start scheme interpreter
and then you can start evaluating scheme expressions
like 2+2 uh oh
scheme doesn't know how to add two and two together
well watch on to learn why
today's lecture is longer than most
in a normal semester
some of the examples from today's lecture
would just spill over
into wednesday's lecture
but I think that's worse for you
so instead I've front loaded the content a little bit
put more in this lecture so that you can see the
concepts and the examples together
and then wednesday's lecture will be short as a result
so far you've learned about functions and data
much the essence of programming
in fact you've mastered the fundamentals of the
python language
so it's time to move on to a new language scheme
and by learning scheme
we'll see that many of the ideas learned
about one programming language
easily transfer to another
and scheme is an older language
that was very influential in the creation of python
so we understand it for its history
its beauty and also
to see which ideas transfer from one language to
another naturally
and we'll find that that's many of them
scheme is a dialect of a language called a lisp
and lisp is one of the two oldest
programming languages that still use today
and it's certainly the oldest one
that's rapidly growing
because more and more people keep getting excited
about using lisp for new applications
what are people saying about lisp
alan kay the inventor of object oriented programming
said that it's the greatest single programming language
ever designed
my favorite sci fi author
said that it's the only
computer language that is beautiful
and brian harvey once told me
its god's programming language
even xkcd seems to love it
lisb is over half a century old
and it still has perfect
timeless air about it
I wonder if the cycles will continue forever
a few coders from each new generation
rediscovering the lisp arts
these are your father's parentheses
elegant weapons for a more civilized age
so hopefully
that gets you excited
about learning a new programming language
the beauty of lisp is its simplicity
the entire language can be learned in a day
and yet it can be used
in order to build
programs as complex as the ones we've seen
throughout this course
or much more complex than that
here are the fundamentals
scheme programs consist of expressions
which can be primitive such as two or 3.3
or two or plus
is a primitive expression or quotient
which does division etc
and there are combinations
so a combination looks like an open parenthesis
and then some other expressions
and then a close parenthesis
and in this way we can express
the quotient of ten and two
which is 10 divided by two is five
or we can express through combination
that not true is false etc
so numbers are self evaluating
but symbols are bound to values
call expressions look like combinations
and they start with an operator
followed by zero or more operands all in parentheses
so this is a little different than the syntax of python
normally we'd put the operator outside
but here we're putting it inside
so let's look at some examples
if at the scheme prompt I type open prentices
quotient ten five
sorry ten two close prentices then I get five
quotient names the built in injured division procedure
in python we called things functions
and scheme they're called procedures
but they're fundamentally the same thing
you can nest call expressions
I could say what's the quotient
of the result of adding together eight and seven
while that's 15
divided by five is three
and if I want to
I can spread these call expressions across
multiple lines in any way that I see fit
here's a typical way
to use indentation just to make the
expression clearer
so this says I'm going to add two things
the result of this sub expression
and the result of this sub expression
and that's why they're indented at the same level
now the scheme interpreter doesn't care
about indentation at all
these are here in order to make the program as
readable as possible
for people
so combinations can span multiple lines
spacing doesn't matter
going to new lines doesn't matter
all that matters is that you close
the parentheses that you open
the way to read
this is to say that we're adding together
two things the first is a product of two things
the first of that is three
and then we need to add together
what you get when you multiply two and four is eight
and you add three and five that's eight again
so something that together is 16 times three is 48
okay what about down here
while I subtract seven from 10 to get three
and I add that to six
so I've got nine
nine plus forty eight is 57
so this whole expression would evaluate the 57
let's do some more demonstrations
here's a scheme prompt
I can evaluate two
I can evaluate the sum of one two three and four is 10
what happens if I add together
nothing at all do you think
zero
I can multiply one two three and four to get 24
or I could multiply together nothing at all
one
okay
so I can multiply together two and two and two and two
and three and three and three
oops
to get 864 and I can nest this
so if I then want to let's say
subtract one
I would do it by surrounding the whole
thing in parentheses
placing a new operator at the front
and I cannot only subtract but I can also divide
add or
multiply again
anything I want to do
and the result will be computed
using the normal call expression procedure
where I first try evaluate the operator and operands
and then I apply the procedure to the arguments
so it's the same story as evaluating python
but this time
we put the parentha season slightly different places
in addition to these arithmetic
procedures that are built in
such as plus
there are also
various other procedures built in
I can ask whether something's a No.3 is a number
plus is not a number
I can ask whether some number is zero
two is not zero which is why we get false
but zero is zero which is why we get true
so if I actually subtracted two from two
I would end up with zero which is true
and we can also
evaluate whether something is an integer
2.2 is not but two is
now these question marks are just part of the name
the name is integer question mark
and the reason the question
mark is there is that
it's supposed to
help you figure out what the procedure does
so just like in any programming language
we'd like to use names
that help remind us of what things are going to do
and this integer question mark name
is a good reminder that
this is something that returns false or true
based on what its arguments are
we haven't learned all of this game language yet
we only know about college expressions so far
but there are other types of expressions
so they're called special forms
a special foreman scheme is any combination
that's not a call expression
for instance
there's an if expression
which has a particular syntax
so it looks just like a combination again
except for it has this special keyword if
as the first sub expression
and then it has a predicate
a consequent and an alternative
that are all expressions
in order to evaluate this
we first evaluate the predicate expression
and then we pick based on whether it's true or false
whether to evaluate either the consequence
or the alternative
so this is the consequence is like the suite
of the if statement
and
alternative would be the suite of the else clause
in a conditional statement in python
and an or
are also special forms
because while they have
a bunch of different
expressions that were going to combine logically
they might not all get evaluated
because you can
figure out whether the end of a bunch of things
is true or false
without evaluating some of them
you can look at the details of that
when you do your project
which will involve building a scheme interpreter
an important special form is how we bind
new values to symbols
and that's with define
so we define some symbol
to be the value of some expression
in order to do that
we evaluate the expression and then
bind it to the symbol
so if I defined pie to be three point one and four
then I can use pi the symbol in future expressions
so the symbol pies bound to 3.14 in the global frame
yes ski muses
the same model
of environments that we've been using in python
you can also define a new procedure
with a defined
expression that has a slightly different syntax
so you know you're defining a procedure when
after defining
there are parentheses
and this combination is not a call expression
instead it gives the name of the new procedure
and then it's formal parameters
and then after that we need the body
so how does this look
well an example is that we can define the abs
value procedure
which takes in some argument we will call x
and every time abs is called
it evaluates this body expression
which says
it affects less than zero
then we return negative x otherwise we return x
so this is the predicate consequent and alternative
of this if expression
and if I think the absolute value of three I'll get -3
I'll get three
okay so this creates a procedure
and binds the symbol abs to that procedure
in the first frame of the current environment
and since we're in the global environment
that's where it gets bout
okay let's define some procedures ourselves
so we can define what it means to square something
is multiply it by itself
and then we can square 16 to get to 56
we can define what it means to average x and y
remember it's okay to go to another line
it's totally up to us how we indent or space things out
so let's say that this involves adding together
x and y and then dividing the result by two
so you do have to be careful to close your prentices
in ski because we want to make well formed combinations
so that one closes the define
at which point I can average
five oh let's do three and seven and we'll get five
now in scheme
we already know
how to evaluate call expressions
and call expressions can contain other
call expressions
and it's okay to define recursive functions in scheme
in fact they are everywhere
let's build one
let's define how to take the square root of x
oh how do we do that again
well we have a bunch of updates
so let's define an update function
it takes a guess
and then gives us a better guess if we need it
and what will that better guess be well
if it's the case that the square of the guess
is already equal
to the number
that we're trying to compute the square root of
and we really don't need a better guess at all
we better stop the recursion at that point
so this is a base case
and we'll just return
that guess as the value of the update
because we're done
otherwise we need a better guess
and how do we get a better guess well
well update something that's even more useful than
what we had before
using the babylonian method
that was invented many thousands of years ago
where you can have a better update
through the square root of x
by averaging
your current guess
and what you get when you define x
by your current guess
okay so we'll close the divide
we'll close the average we'll close the update
we'll close the if
we'll close the define
and in order to actually take a square root
we'll start with a guess of one
and update that
and update will update it again until
the square of gas is in fact x
close the define
and now we can take the square route of two fifty six
and get back 16
so we've used a lot of features of the language already
we have a
square root defined here
within there we have to find update
and scheme like pipe found is lexically scoped
so within the body of this interfunction we can refer
to the name x
which is a formal parameter of the outer function
so how am I executing all of this scheme code anyway
did I download something
well you certainly can download an interpreter
or find an online one embedded into a web page
we'll give you pointers to both
but in this case I haven't been using either of those
instead I've just been using the implementation from
project four of this course
so in project four you'll build a python program
that implements a scheme interpreter
once you run it you're able to evaluate scheme
and you'll do that by actually writing the code
that it executes
the different procedures that are required
in order to execute scheme procedures
and this is called an evaluator
so one of the purposes of
learning this new language
is to learn a language that we can then
understand how to build an interpreter for
lambda expressions
create new procedures in scheme
so lambda expressions evaluate to anonymous procedures
they have the following special form syntax
as I lamb the
then I write down the formal parameters in parentheses
and then I give the body of the procedure
lambda is very important to nski
so here are two different equivalent expressions
that define a plus four procedure
combined to the name plus four
I could just use the define
procedure syntax that we saw before or
I could just define that the symbol plus four
is bound to the procedure
that takes x and gives us back
x plus four
this combine however we want
scheme is totally flexible
so in a call expression I can have an operator
that's a combination itself
for instance I could write
the procedure that adds x y and c squared
should be applied to one two and three
to get one plus two plus nine is 12
let's look at an example of a scheme program
that draws sir pinsky's triangle
using lots of the features of scheme that we've seen
so far when you start scheme
you can immediately start adding numbers together
but there's also some built in drawing facilities
in the version of scheme that we distribute
with the homework assignments for this course
so for example you can say move forward 100
and this forward procedure
tells a little turtle to walk forward 100 units
let's rearrange a bit
so that we can move the turtle some more
other commands include turning right by 90 degrees
going forward again
or in fact you could also go backward
and the turtle cannot only turn right
but also turn left
now all of this interacts with
the scheme language that we've already defined
so I could build a procedure to draw a line
that moves forward 50
and then I can draw a line and another line
and take a right turn
I could also define a procedure
that does something twice
by doing it once and doing it again
so if I twice draw a line
and it'll draw two lines
and all of this could also be stored in a file
now typically
what you store in the file
are the procedure definitions
so there's what a line is
there's what twice is
perhaps not just twice
we'd want to repeat something many times
repeat k times some procedure
means calling that procedure
we're going to do it at least once
and if it's the case that k is greater than one
then we have to keep going
so we'll repeat k minus one times
using that same procedure
I could load all those
by naming the file
then I'll take a right turn to point ourselves down
and we can repeat three times drawing a line
or twice more
we could draw a line
or we could repeat five times
some custom procedure
that we define using alamda expression
repeat takes a procedure of zero arguments
so I say lambda takes zero arguments
and each time it's called
I'd like to go forward 50
and then take a right turn of 144 degrees
cool let's quit and start over so we get a fresh canvas
now that I can repeat I can draw for example a triangle
but I don't want a triangle
that's just a boring old triangle
that always has a line as its edge
I want an arbitrary edge
so I'll use a function to define
what it means to draw the edge of the triangle
but the triangle always involves repeating three times
a procedure that first draws the edge
and then takes a turn of 120 degrees
so if I load this file
and draw a triangle with lines as the edge
I'll get a regular triangle
but I'd like to draw sir pinsky's triangle
let me tell you about sir pinsky's triangle
sir pinsky triangle has some recursive depth d
and also some side length k
it's a triangle
but drawing the edge of this triangle
involves making a choice
if d is one then we just draw a line of length k
otherwise we draw a leg of sir pinsky's triangle
with d greater than one
which is going to be mutually recursive
with this procedure
sir pinsky that I've just defined
the leg also takes in d and k
but it does the drawing work
and here's what it looks like
you draw sir pinsky's triangle
but half the size and with a depth of one less
then without drawing a line
you move to the end of where this leg should go
which means you have to pick your pen up
go forward k and then put your pen back down
so you can draw some more of sir pinsky's triangle
so I'll quit so I can start fresh
start with a 90 degree right turn
set to the speed of the turtle to zero
which is as fast as it goes
and then I can draw sir pinsky's triangle
of depth five with side length 200
which will work much better if I actually
load the file defining what it is
and then it will start to draw
so each little triangle you see is the base case
if d equals one
then it just draws a triangle using a line
otherwise
it builds a triangle out of sir pinsky triangles
a surpinski triangle is made up of three
surpinski triangles each of which is made up of three
regular triangles
we finally hit the base case
and of course if I went back 200
then I could draw an even bigger one
but it's going to take a while
you're welcome to skip to the next video
if you don't want to watch it draw
but some people like watching it draw
and so you're welcome to do that as well
yes right now it's redrawing sir pinsky's triangle
where I drew it before
the turtle doesn't keep track of what it's drawn before
and so it doesn't know that it's doing redundant work
but now finally it's completing the job
you'll notice
after it finishes drawing the last little triangle
it's going to work its way back to where it started
by completing all the pen up forward pen downs
of all the different recursive calls along the way
to creating this image
now I'll talk about three other special forms
these are going to be covered in lab and discussion
and they'll show up in homeworks in the next project
so you'll get exposure to them eventually
but I'll give you a preview now
just so that you know what's coming
first we'll talk about khand and then begin
the cond special form or cond is short for condition
is like having lf closets
or a big if lflflf else statement in python
so in python you can have one statement
with multiple different clauses
and you can have as many lfs as you want
as long as you start with a niff
and then there's this optional else at the end
and you could achieve this same result
just using if in scheme
by having that last consequent expression
have another if in it
and its consequent have another if in it
so you don't really need anything new
but
if you have a lot of ellipse then this nested if idea
is kind of annoying
which is why there's cond
so here's a scheme example that does the same thing
cond has as the rest of its expression a bunch of pairs
where the pairs are the condition
and then what to do if that condition is true
so this says effects is greater than 10 than print big
otherwise effects is greater than five print medium
otherwise print small
much like in python the else case is optional
but there can be only one and it has to be at the end
both of these have the same property
that only one thing will be printed
no matter the value of x
so if x is 12
it's both bigger than 10 and bigger than five
but only big will be printed because
x greater than five is the condition of an lf
that comes after the x greater than 10
that gets triggered first
and the same is true over here
now a conde expression does have a value
so if instead of printing
I just said
that I want an expression whose value is either big
medium or small
depending on the value of x
then I would write it like this
and I could do something with that value
for example I could print it
now these two expressions are equivalent
they'll either print big medium or small
but this one I think is shorter because it has
only one print instead of three
so that's cond
you can still use if
and usually what happens in practice
is that if you're just choosing among two alternatives
then you use if
and if it's more than two then you use cond
the begin special form
combines multiple expressions into one expression
the value of a begin
special form is just the value of its last
sub expression
and the reason it began is used
is so that you can do things
for example printing for a while
or defining some
symbols as particular values
before you compute the result that you want
so here's a python case where within the suite
for an if claws of printed twice
and likewise for the l's claws
how do you do that in scheme
well you need to begin
you say here are some conditions
the first of which is that if x is greater than 10
I want to both print big and print guy
but there's only
space in scheme for one expression here
and so the began expression
allows you to put as many things as you want
as sub expressions and they'll all get evaluated
and by the way
since there are only two alternatives here
it would be a little bit more natural to
just do it with an if
and you can indent however you want
or go to new lines however you want
so here's an equivalent expression
that just says if x is greater than 10
then print big and print guy
otherwise print small and print fry
and finally we'll talk about let
let is kind of like define
but it's different
in that it only bind symbols to values temporarily
just for one expression
and then those bindings are gone
there isn't really an equivalent in python
but we can talk about the difference just by showing a
python example
and its scheme equivalent
using a lead expression and how they behave differently
let's say you wanted to compute the hypotenuse
length of a right triangle
that has legs three and two plus two is four
so this would be a 3 4 5 triangle
where this expression c
should give us five
maybe in this program
all I really cared
about was making sure that c was bound to five
but if I write this python code
a and b are still bound down here as well
that could be a good thing
if you're going to use them again
that could kind of be a bad thing
if a was already being used before
and now you've overwritten it
or you want to just have as few names as possible
here's how to achieve the same thing in scheme
but the difference will be that after we've defined c
a and b are not bound down here
they are only bound temporarily
in order to compute the value of c
and then those bindings are gone
here's how it works
we define see as the result of a whole let expression
where the value of the let expression
is what comes at the end
in this case the square root of a squid plus b squirt
but before that
you get a chance to make temporary bindings
there's really just two parts to lead expression
the bindings
so here's where they began and here's where they end
and then
the value expression
which is here
and the bindings themselves are pairs
where the first thing needs to be a symbol
and the second can be any expression
that will get evaluated
in order to bind that symbol to a value
so it's like having a bunch of little defines here
except for
the bindings for a and b
go away
as soon as you finish computing the value for c
and in steam code of any
like interesting size and complexity
let gets used a lot
usually in scheme
define is used for things that are really permanent
like you want to define a new
procedure so that you can call it many times
or you want to define some constant like pi
otherwise
most scheme code doesn't make a lot of definitions
instead if you need to keep
track of some temporary information
you could use let to do that
and this is mostly a stylistic convention
but it's one that has some nice justification
which is that you don't have to worry
about defining anything that you don't need later
you can kind of just say I want c to persist
but a and
b were just temporarily there in order to compute c
and now we don't need them anymore
python has many types of built in data structures
lists tuples dictionaries sets and more
scheme has lists
and lists in scheme are like
the linked list class that we created in python
every scheme list is a linked list
lisp was created in the late 19 fifties
and back then it seems computer scientists
really liked confusing names and acronyms
so they invented a procedure called khans
which is a two argument procedure
that creates a linked list
creating a linked
list is only useful if you can access the first
element and the rest of the list
and there are procedures for that as well
car is the procedure
that returns the first element of a list
in scheme and kudur
is the procedure that returns the rest of the list
there is also a built in symbol nil
which evaluates to the empty list
so to create a length list of length one
containing the value 2
you would write khan's 2 knill
which would build r khan's with 2
and the rest of it being nil
oftentimes that's drawn in this way
where the slash just means
that the rest of this list is empty
now scheme lists are displayed as parentheses
with elements separated by spaces
there is this underlying link list structure
but the standard way of displaying a link list
doesn't show that structure
instead it just shows the elements
so if I cons to anil I build this cons
and if I cons one and cons to anil
then I build this cons
where the rest of the list is a list containing two
but evaluating this expression in scheme
doesn't show me this structure
instead it just shows a list containing one and two
if I define x to be a list containing one and two
I can look at x and see the whole list
the car of x is the No.1
the cutter of x is the list containing two
if I cons one cons two cons three cons four kneel
I'm building a structure that looks like this
but displaying it in scheme
looks like a list containing one
two three and four
so all scheme lists have a linkless structure
you acts as their elements using car and cooter
but you display them as a list of elements
let's take a look at some more demos
here I'm going to load a web based interpreter
that we use for the course
because it will
draw the linkless structure of any list that I create
so if I define s as khan's one khan's two nil
s is a list is displayed like this
but if I draw it
I'll see the linkless structure
and draw is not built into every version of scheme
but it is built into this one
so that we can see what's going on
what happens if I cons 3 on 2 s
I'm allowed to do this
when I call cons
the first argument can be anything
but the second argument either needs to be
another cons or nil
cons three s gives me a list 3 1 2
and cons four onto cons three onto s
gives me the list 4 3 1 2
which if I draw it
shows me that it has a linkless structure
so what if instead I
cons
four cons three kneel onto s
think about what this is going to display
I suggest you pause for a moment
until you have some idea of the answer
I'm going to show you the answer in 321
cons creates a list
where this is the first element
and this is the rest of the list
since s has length two
this cons has length three
and the three elements are a list containing four three
and then the No.1 and then the No.2
if I draw that structure
it will show me that it is a 1 2 3 element list
with a list as its first element
and then a number is its 2nd and a number as its 3rd
if I build this structure
and I look for its car
I will get the list for three
and it has a car
the No.4 hopefully you're getting the hang of it
let's try and even trick your one
remember that s is a list one two
what happens if I cons s cons s nil
think about it for a second
maybe pause the video
and I'll show you in 321
it's a list containing the list one two
and the list one two as elements
drawing this one
shows that they're in fact the same element twice
a list containing the list one two and the list one two
let's look at a few built in functions related to lists
so if s is one two
I can see whether that's a list or not
it is
and remember that sharp
t is scheme's way of saying true
is three a list no
is the car of s a list
no because the car of s is the No.1
is nil a list
yes it's the empty list
how can I tell the difference between the empty list
and a non empty list
I could use the no question mark predicant
and I can also build lists with the list procedure
list 1 2 3 4 builds a list with contents 1 2 3 4
now it's still a linked list structure underneath
I can for example get the cutter of the list 1 2 3 4
and that will show me the list 2 3 4
if I had this cutter and I caused zero under the front
then I'd have 0 2 3 4
lisp is well known for introducing the idea of
symbolic programming
manipulating
lists of symbols which represent things in the world
as structured objects
so with lisp
you could do more than just compute a number
you could manipulate whole equations
and for this reason
lisp was the standard language
for artificial intelligence
for many years
and was also this standard language
for any kind of automatic manipulation of mathematical
equations such as symbolic differentiation
or automatically verifying proofs
and there's just one feature in the language
that makes this all possible quotation
symbols normally refer to values
but sometimes you can refer to the symbol itself
if I define a is one
then a is the symbol and one is the value
if I define b is two then I have a second symbol
with another value
now I can use those symbols inside of an expression
but the value
that you get by evaluating this expression
has no as and bs in it
it's just a list containing one and two
so we've lost
all the notion of what
symbols were used to create this value
this value has no symbols in it
but
quotation allows the symbols themselves to be values
quotation is used to refer to symbols directly
if I make a list where I quote the a and I quote the b
always with a single quote
and never with one at the beginning and one at the end
but instead just one at the beginning of
whatever I'm quoting
then I build a list containing the symbols a and b
if I build a list with the symbol a
and the value to which b is bound
I get a list that contains a and the No.2
so as you can see
these quotes weren't necessarily paired
you can have just one quotation mark
inside of a larger expression
and it quotes whatever comes directly after it
the quote is actually short hand
for a special form called quote
and so this would be equivalent to writing list quote a
quote b
the special form
indicates that the expression that is quoted
is the value itself
as opposed to needing to evaluate that expression
quotation can also be applied to combinations
in order to form lists
so I can quote the list a bc
and that builds a list containing the symbols a b and c
the car of that is the symbol a
the cutter of that is the list containing the symbols b
and c
let's try some more demos
quoting a is the same as quoting a
I can use the value a in any way that I want
for example placing it inside of a list
and I could do that using either syntax
the nice thing about the single quote
is that it saves you a set of nested parentheses
when quoting a list
you get a list
but all the expressions within it are quoted as well
now another way to build that same list would be to say
give me a list of one and the symbol a
if I were to attempt to build a list of one and a
it would tell me that a is not a known symbol
because I've never defined it to be anything
I can't evaluate a until I've defined it
but I can refer to a even before I've defined it
because it's just a symbol
it could mean something in the future
it just hasn't been defined yet
it's possible to quote a nested expression
in order to build a list
that has as some of its elements other lists
so perhaps try to figure out
what is the car of the cutter
of the car of the cutter
of this quoted list
you're welcome to pause the video
I'll show you the answer in 123
it's the No.3
the cutter is a list containing as its first element
the list two three
the car of that is the list two three
the cutter of that is a list containing three
and the car of that is the No.3
and we could have told exactly the same story
if instead of numbers
these were all symbols themselves
programs are data
scheme programs consist of expressions
those expressions can either be primitivity expressions
just the number two three point three true
the symbol plus the symbol quotient
but everything else is a combination
and each combination is a scheme list
so here we have a list containing the symbol quotient
the No.10 and the No.2
here we have the symbol knot and the primitive true
the built in
scheme list data structure that we've discussed before
it's represented as a linked list for the karana kutter
but it can be used to represent
combinations in a scheme program
so if I evaluate the following expression
build a list of quotient and then 10 and then two
what I get is a little piece of a scheme program
a combination that says
take the quotient of ten and two
now notice evaluating this
doesn't actually divide 10 by two
instead it just built a list
but there's a built in procedure called eval
and eval takes any expression represented as a scheme
list or primitive
and gives you back its value
so eval question
ten two gives you the No.5
the lesson here is that if I want to write a program
that generates scheme code
I just build lists
if at any point I've
constructed code and I want to know
what happens when I evaluated
then I just call eval
python also has an eval function built in
that takes a string and tells you its value
what special about
scheme is that it has all this built in functionality
for working with scheme lists
and all the code is just lists
so it's easier to construct programs by writing
things like list quotient ten two
so
one of the beautiful things about the scheme language
and this is true of lisp in general
is that it's straightforward
to write a program that writes a program
let's do that now
so I'll start up scheme
and if I write an expression that evaluates to a value
that's pretty straightforward
if instead I list out
all of these things this is the procedure
that plus is the No.1 and the No.2
then I'll get a list of those pieces
but this is not scheme code
scheme code looks like that
so the reason I have quotation here
is to say that I don't yet want to evaluate the plus
instead I want to leave it as a symbol
and that symbol will be evaluated
just as soon
as I ask scheme to evaluate the whole combination
because this is in the operator position
so it gets evaluated to the procedure that adds
and then we apply that to one and two
now if I were to list out
plus and then have some more complicated expression
here 2+3
I'd end up with an expression
where this part had been evaluated already
because it's just part of scheme
and scheme evaluates the operator and its operands
and gives me back an expression
that's already computed the five
but hasn't computed the six yet
okay now let's load this small program on the right
fact is a procedure
that if n is zero just returns one
otherwise
it returns end times the factorial of n minus one
so that's a straightforward recursive definition of
factorial
if I take
fact of three then I get three times two times one
or fact of five
is five times four times three times two times one
this is just a scheme program that returns a number
but I could also write a scheme procedure
that returns an expression
that computes the factorial of n
so this variant called effect xp
doesn't have the job of returning a number
instead it has the job of returning an expression
one is an expression
a perfectly good way of representing the No.1
if I want to build an expression out of smaller
expressions I need a list
a list containing multiply
the number that I'm multiplying
and then the
expression for how to compute the rest of the factorial
so now when I compute the factorial of five
I still get 120
but if I ask for an expression
that would compute the factorial of five
I now see how the factorial five is computed
one times two times three times four times five
so here's a procedure that returns an expression
if I take that expression and I evaluate it
then I get 120
let's do one more example following the same pattern
first I'll define fibonacci number in
if it's the case that n is zero or one any number
less than equal to one
then fib n is just n
otherwise I have to add together the two previous
fibonacci numbers
fib n minus two
and fib n minus one
so fibonacci No.2 is one fibonacci No.6 is eight
how did it compute eight while using tree recursion
I could also have written a big nested expression
so here we're going to change fib to fib exp everywhere
in order to say that
the goal of this procedure is to write down
an expression
that computes fibonacci number n
and that expression is constructed
by writing down a list of what
operation I'm going to perform
and then applying that to the result of two
smaller expressions that compute
fib and minus two and fib and minus one
so fib six is still eight
but the expression that computes fib six
is that I add together fib four and fib five
or fib four is an expression that looks like that
and here is the expression for fib five
now if I ever go through and evaluate
this nested addition of zeros and ones
I get the result fib six
but
this is a procedure that gives me back an expression
this is a procedure that gives me back a number
so why ski do people actually use this language
well they do or variance
and why are people drawn to these
programming languages based on lisp
well because
the code
looks like just a bunch of symbols and parentheses
you could actually write a program that
generates programs
before we do that
I'm going to teach you one more feature called
quasi quotation
which is a lot like the quotation you already know
but there's an important difference
which is that you can unquote
parts of a quoted expression
so there are two ways to quote an expression
you can use quote which we saw before
or you could quasi quote
which is represented using the bactic symbol
which is in the upper left corner of your keyboard
and in many situations it does the same thing as quote
but here's the difference
parts of a quasi quoted expression can be unquoted
using the comma symbol
which is the unquote symbol
so this is quote this is quasi quote this is unquote
let's say I've already defined b to be four
if I quote a b I'll get a b
doesn't matter that I've defined it
if I quote a
followed by the result of unquoting b plus one
well this whole thing is quoted
so we're not going to use the value for b
we're just going to write out exactly what's here
a followed by the value of unquoting b plus one
so here we have a list within a list within a list
but writing the same expression
started with a quasi quote
will give me something that I think is more useful
a list a five
where five is the value of evaluating the expression
b plus one
why did this expression get evaluated whereas a did not
because of the unquote
so the way to read this quasi quote
a list a followed by unquote plus b one
is that we're going to build a list
that's what we've said here
it's going to start with a symbol a
because that's all quoted
but now this unquoted expression
is going to be replaced by its value
so by using all the same rules
of evaluation that we have already for scheme
we evaluate b plus one
which can depend on the current environment
b is four so b plus one is five
and then we get a list of a and five
mixing together
stuff that was quoted and stuff that was evaluated
quasi quotation is particularly convenient
for generating
scheme expressions
if I want to define a procedure that
makes a new procedure
taking in some n
and building a lambda expression that says lamda d
plus dn for whatever n is
and then I call make add procedure on two
what I get back is a list
a list whose first element is the symbol lambda
2nd element is a list containing just one element d
and the third
who's a list containing the symbol plus the symbol d
and the No.2
and quasi quotation makes it convenient
to write new code on the fly
instead of having it be lambda d plus d n
for two different variables dnn
here we have
an expression that evaluates to a procedure
that takes only one argument
and the n has now been filled in with two
so here's a procedure that writes code
and it writes code with particular parts filled in
okay let's do a longer example
wild statements
well in scheme there are no wild statements
but while the statements are awfully convenient
like let's say you wanted to know
what's the sum of the squares of even numbers
less than 10
starting with two
so two squared plus four squared plus six squared
plus state squared
what would you do in python
you'd said x equal to two total equal to zero
while x is less than 10
increase the total increase x
and at the end total gives you
the answer to this question
which is 120
how do you do this in scheme
well you want to iterate
but you're not allowed to use a wild statement
so you have to use recursion
you have to write a new procedure
that takes in x and total
this is the kind of current value of x
as you're going through a while
and the current value of total
if it's the case that you're still iterating
if x is less than 10
then you make a recursive call
updating x to be x plus two
updating total to be total plus x squared
if on the other hand this is false
that means you're done
well then you should just return total
but after defining this recursive procedure
I need to call it with the right initial values
total starts at zero x starts at two
and now I've written two expressions instead of one
if I wanted to fit it all into one expression
I would need to use begin
okay so it can be done in python
it can be done in scheme
I find the python easier to read
there's nothing inherently recursive about
this expression
it just
happens to be that the way you express it in scheme is
through recursion
and you could do more of these
what's the
some of the numbers whose squares are less than 50
starting with one
so one plus two plus four plus five plus six plus seven
is still seven squares still less than 50
but not eight
well it's basically the same code
except we changed the initial value
we changed the wild condition
we changed how we updated total
we changed how we updated x
and so likewise
those things need to change in the scheme code
but what if there were a bunch of these
and you know someone told you you have to write
scheme expressions for all of them
wouldn't it be nice
if you could just get scheme
to write this whole thing for you
well that's exactly what you could do
so I'm going to start us off with that example that you
just saw
of something numbers whose square is less than 50
starting with one
but I want to be able to define a procedure
that creates one of these some while expressions
out of
an initial value for x
a condition for the wild statement
what to add to total
and how to update x
and how would I call this
well I want to call it on an initial value for x
a wild condition
like I want to keep going as long as x squared
is less than 50
in this case I'm just adding x to total
and how am I updating x while using the expression
x plus one
I think it should be the case that this call
generates this expression
but now we're going to do something interesting
we're going to make this generic
we want to return an expression
that starts with begin
and that expression should always say
define f as x in total
if something
not always this but whatever condition
is passed in
the reason I unquote this is that I don't want the
symbol condition in the result
I want
whatever is passed in this expression in the result
likewise I want this expression
as what we update x with
so I'll unquote and write update x
I always want to add something to total
but what it is
depends on what I want to add to the total
which in this example I think should be x
the fact that I return total
when I've reached the end of the wild condition
stays the same
the fact that I call f
starting with total equal zero stays the same
but I do want this to have some other value
so I unquote and put the initial x here
so now I have a quasi quoted began expression
which means that the result of evaluating this
quasi quotation
will be a began expression
but I still need to close the parenthesis
for the procedure that I'm defining
okay I've rearranged a bit
so that I can load this file and make this call
and look what it did
it built for me something
let's give this thing a name
result
of evaluating this expression
this result
is a list
it begins with
begin
but it's also code
and when I evaluate that result
I get 28 which is the result of adding one and two
and three and four and five and six and seven together
if instead I wanted that other thing
thus some of the squares for even numbers
up to but not including 10
then I would evaluate something else
the result of starting it two
having a wild condition that says x is less than 10
what I add to total in this case is not x but x squared
and I update x to go to the next even number
this should give me two squared plus four squared
plus six squared plus eight
squared is 120
and the way that it did it
was to actually produce the code
that results in 120
including defining a new recursive function
and calling that
and then eval
actually defined
that function and called it and got the number
so this is an additional kind of expressive
power in a programming language
to be able to write procedures
that write the code for other procedures
and that's one of those things that get people excited
about lisp and ski