61 election No.24 announcements
answers du Friday
earn an early submission bonus point for submitting by
Thursday I'm happy to report that the office hours q
is pretty short
so if you need help
pop on there and we'll help you through it
homework five is due Monday
and you can finish it during the time
that you would normally spend
finishing the lab
because the only required part of lab
nine is to finish the homework
there are some optional questions on lab nine
and so there will still be a lab orientation
so that you can
learn how to solve those problems
and they will be helpful practice for them in term
but lab nine will be released with solutions
so it's just to kind of a study aid
as opposed to something you have to work on
midterm two is coming
there's some options for prep
you can of course just go back and watch lecture
one of the best things to do
is work through some of the
optional problems on past labs
but here are some events
we have our usual exam prep section on Friday
the student group
called cs mentors is running two review sessions on
Saturday one at noon one at six
another student group
hkn is running a review session on Sunday
at 4:00 both of these will be recorded
and the staff is organized a practice exam
starting at 11:00am Monday
but it will be available for you to take at any time
and what they've done is taken spring 20 20 midterm two
and just put it into the format of our exam
so if you've already read spring 20 20 midterm two
there won't be any new questions
and the practice exam will be pretty easy
but if you haven't looked at that yet
you might want to save it
and instead take the practice exam so that you can
feel what it's like to solve these problems
under exam like conditions
and I really recommend taking the practice exam
either at 11 or on your own time
just to make sure that you're familiar
with the exam software
it's the same as midterm one
but it's always good to refresh your memory
I made a piazza post
about some past exam problems that we've discussed in
lecture q amp a
over the last few weeks
so if you take a look at that you'll see links
two of those YouTube videos at the right time
to listen to how
professor fried and I would go
about solving some past exam problems
there's the midterm two study guide
which I recommend you read
and the staff have also put together
a document on how to prepare
I talked about this in some earlier
announcements videos
but just wanted to remind you that it's here
I don't have anything new to tell you about midterm two
this was
all the same announcements that I made last lecture
remember that we will be proctoring via video
where you need to include your head
and your screen in the video
if you want to request an exemption from this policy
then please fill out this form by Sunday
the exam starts at 7pm next Wednesday the 28th
if you would like to take it at an alternate time
please fill out the alternate time request form
and here are the various rules of the exam
okay today's lecture is not going to be terribly long
it's just got some example problems in it
that I think might help you refresh your memory
about some details
of the course material so far
and help get you ready to solve those midterm problems
finally
I wanted to alert you to some scheduling changes
for the course
I read your feedback about how the course is going
and it sounds like a non trivial number of students
are really quite overwhelmed with the
remote learning environment
and all that's going on in the world
I totally understand
we tried to anticipate this
by adding some optional content in
so we covered binary
numbers and circuits earlier in the semester
but decided not to require those for the exam
just so that we could
create some space in the schedule
give you something interesting to listen to
but not give you more stuff that you had to learn
and we're going to do some more of that
so
efficiency already happened that's optional
next week we're gonna have
two optional lectures on Monday and Friday
so really the only thing
that you have to worry about
is finishing homework five and taking the midterm
and once you're done with the midterm
we won't introduce new material
we'll make this homework really short
and I think we'll release it on Monday
okay there I moved it some of that Monday
and then let's see
so later in the course
we've picked some topics to make optional
we'll still have lectures about them
but we won't require them on exams
so that would be the macros and tail calls lecture
and also the databases lecture
you're certainly welcome to learn about this stuff
but it won't be on the final exam or on any assignments
so stick with it
make it through ants
make it through this week
make it through next week
take that midterm
there's still more stuff to come
but not quite as much
so hopefully
that will make this semester more manageable
let's look at an example of using the object system
here's something to remember
when you look up an attribute by name on an instance
you find instance attributes before you find
class attributes
and if you don't find the attribute on the instance
you look in the class
if you don't find it in the class
you look in the bass class
and in this way class attributes are inherited
here's an example
let's say we have a class of worker
the worker greets others as sir
has a constructor
that sets an attribute elf to the class
worker
has a method work
which returns the greeting
of the object passed in itself
plus I work and finally
has a special method repper
and this repper method is used to display
what a worker instance
looks like when you're running an interactive session
now this repper string is very weird
instead of doing anything with self at all
it takes bergeois v and returns its greeting
the bourgeoisie are the landowners
the ones who own the means of production
and so instead of working themselves
they gather wealth by employing their peons
to work they say
I gather wealth
jack is a worker
john is a bourgeoisie
and here we've assigned the greeting attribute of jack
to be ma'am
if you want to work through this problem yourself
from fall 2014 midterm two
here are some of the prompts
let's go through
exactly what happens when we execute all of this coat
so the first thing is that when we
have a class statement
its body gets executed immediately
and so it creates a new class called worker
where there's a class attribute greeting
which is valued at sir
this isn't an environment diagram
this is just a sketch of what's going on
the bourgeoisie class
inherits from worker and has its own greeting peon
in this case
you don't change the greeting of the worker
it's just that if we looked up the greeting
for a bourgeoisie instance
it would find this before it found that
then these two lines
create a worker instance and a bourgeoisie instance
the worker instance is created
and then passed immediately into the constructor
where it gains an attribute elf
which is bound to whatever the name worker is bound to
and worker is the name of the worker class
so elf value is this whole thing
the worker class
john gets created
because bourgeoisie does not have an in it method
it inherits the in it method from worker
so we look up is there an in it in bourgeoisie
no there's not
so we look at the base class and we apply this one
which has the same effect
so both jack and john have the same elf
finally we have the line jack greeting equals man
if we just looked up jack
greeting we'd look here and find there was no greeting
so we would look on the class
and the answer would be sir
however attribute assignment
has the rule that it
always assigns immediately to the
object to the left of the dot
so the effect of jack dot greeting
is that now
jack will have its own instance attribute greeting
bound to man
jack greets people as ma'am
any other worker greets people as sir
now let's go through these examples
worker
with parentheses after it creates a new worker instance
here we invoke its work method
which gets the
self greeting for the newly created worker
the worker doesn't have a greeting instance attribute
so we look at the class and we find sir
adding sir to I work return sir I work
okay jack
is a worker
when I just write
jack and then evaluate that expression
it evaluates to this worker instance
but
we want to be able to display that as a line of text
that's how interactive sessions work
and the way they work is by computing the repper string
for the object
that's the value of the expression
so what's the repper string of jack
well jack
is a class worker
worker has this special method name repper
which is exactly what gets invoked
every time you want to display
an object
so what does it return will
it returns bourgeoisie greeting
here's the bourgeoisie class
it's greeting as peon
and so what we'll see here for jack is peon
what about jack dot work
jack is a worker
the work method returns self dot greeting plus I work
or self is bound to jack
jack's self greeting is specialized
it's man so what we get here
is that self dot greeting evaluates to mam
add that to I work and you get mam I work
what about john network
well we look up the work method in john
the instance doesn't have one
but the bourgeoisie class does have a work method
and what it does is it prints the result of
calling the work method of worker
on self self is john
okay the work method on worker is this work
and so we're going to print out john's greeting
plus I work now what is john's greeting
well john doesn't have a greeting instance attribute
but its class does
and that class has the
greeting attribute pian
so we print out pian I work
after that's finished and printed out
this returns I gather wealth
so what we see is pni work I gather wealth
now this one
has quotes around it because it's a return value
and so we're trying to write down a repper expression
that evaluates to the same string that was returned
pian I work
does not have quotes around it because it was printed
printing a string does not print the
quotes around the string
it just prints the contents of the string
finally we have john
work john what's going on there
well we look at john's elf attribute
which is the worker class
the worker class has a function work
so this is the one we're calling
and we're calling it on john
so we have to look up john's greeting which is pian
we looked at that already
add that to I work and we get pian I work as a string
when you return a string
you see it with quotes around it
that's the representation of a string
that evaluates to that string
let's look at
some examples of manipulating iterables and iterators
and let's just focus on
using built in functions
and list comprehensions and dictionary comprehensions
in order to perform some like
moderately complicated data manipulations
these are things can be done in a line or two
if you use the tools correctly
and manipulations like these
often show up as the core part
of some larger problem
so I'm just going to lay a bunch out there
and then I would recommend that you pause
and just try them out on your own
and then we'll walk through them one by one together
so here's an example
what are the indices of all elements in a list s
that have the smallest absolute value
so if I have a list s
the elements with the smallest absolute value are
negative two and two
but we want their indices
indices in a list started 0 0 1 2 3 4 5
so here are the smallest elements in absolute value
and their indices are two and four
so how would we take this list as input
and have this list be the output
or if this list is the input
the smallest element by absolute value is the
element at index one
we're trying to list all of the indices
corresponding to the smallest elements
by absolute value
so we get a list containing zero
there's first exercise
I'm just going to go through them all
what's the largest sum of
two adjacent elements in a list
assuming that the length of the list
is greater than one
so here's a list
if I some these two elements I get -5
that's not very big
some these two I get one
well if I some these two I get six
so the answer here is
six is the largest sum of two adjacent elements
here's a similar list
but I've fittled with the negative signs
and in this case we don't get six
we get -2 with the end
that's not what we want
we can get a positive No.1
by summing together three and -2
so that's the biggest thing we can get
adding together two adjacent elements in that list
all right another one
create a dictionary mapping each digit d
to the list of elements in s that end with d
or d is an individual digit
so if I have this list of integers
I'm supposed to create a dictionary
that says here is all the elements ending in one
here's the elements ending in three
here's the elements ending in four
here's the elements ending in five
notice there are two of them five and fifty five
there's only one for eight and one for nine
and finally
does every element equal some other element in s
so given a list
is it the case that every element equals
something else
well -4 only shows up one so that's false
but here four is there twice and three is there twice
and two is there twice
so every element equals at least one other element
so this would give us true
so if you want to pause the video
and work through some of these
I recommend that
now we're going to go through and solve them
okay for the first one
what are the indices of the elements
in list s that have the smallest absolute value
we're going to start with this example
try to work it out
so here's smallest absolute value
is not the men of s
but it's actually not
the men of s using key equals abs either
that would give me
the element in
this that has the smallest absolute value
it wouldn't give me the smallest absolute value
so if my goal is to actually
get the smallest absolute value
I would need to first call abs on each element
and then take them in
which I can do by mapping abs over s
so now I have the min abslew value
what can I do with that
well I can find all the indices
where the absolute value of the elemented at index
is equal to this min abs value is equal to two
this is different than finding all the elements with
that absolute value
which I could do with a list comprehension
if I wanted to know all the elements x for x and s
if the absolute value of x is equal to main abs
that would give me both the two and the -2
but that's not my goal
my goal is to find the indices
and for that I need to go through
for I in not s
but a range of len s
which gives me all the index values for s
and we adjust this expression accordingly
we actually want just the index values
and we have to
adjust this expression accordingly as well
we want to know if the absolute value of
si is equal to min apps
that will give me the numbers two and four
so there's a two line solution to this problem
whenever I use a list comprehension
I could also use the map and filter built in functions
so I could have rewritten this
by first defining a filter function
that takes in some index
and tells me whether it's one of the indices
that I want to keep
then if I take this same range of in disease
and I filter it using f
I almost get what I want but this is a filter object
if what I really wanted was a list
then I would call a list on it
and I'd get this same correct result
so I could have replaced this expression
with this expression and gotten the same thing
okay let's go on to the next problem
what's the largest sum of two
adjacent elements in a list s
and here we're using the same s that we had before
were meant to get six
there are two reasonable ways to do it
one is to think about indices
range len s will give me all of the indices
but range len s minus one will give me
almost all the indices
here it is as a range
if I go through almost all the in disease
just leaving out the last one
and I compute s I plus s I plus one
then I'm summing together to adjacent elements
for every pair of adjacent elements
and I'm leaving out the last one
because there's no I plus one
for the last element
so that's why I use this shortened range
okay this just gives me what all the sum
of adjacent elements are
if I want to know the biggest one
then I should just call max on that
so there's another use of an aggregation function
in order to do the work
okay so we're done with this
you can copy it in there and call it a day
another way to solve the same problem though is with
zip so if I zip together s with s I get a zip object
and what are the elements of this zip iterator
well let's list them out
they're giving me
an element from s along with an element from s
these are not adjacent elements
they're just the same element
but if instead I had zipped
all but the last element of s
with all but the first element of s
now I have five elements here and five elements here
and when I zip them together
I see all the pairs of adjacent elements
so I had built two sequences
negative four negative three negative two three two
and negative three negative two three two four
zipping them together gives me a list of pairs
what happens if instead of listing out the contents
I add together the elements in each pair
a plus v for a kma b in zip
I get those same sums of which the max is six
so there's another way to solve the same problem
okay let's try another one
map each digit d to the lists of elements in s
that end with d
the result is a dictionary
so we're going to use a dictionary comprehension
this one's going to get a little bit long
so I made some space
it's a dictionary
where the key is a digit and the value is a list
the list contains all elements of s
that n in that digit
so we look at x
figure out its last digit and see if it's equal to d
that's a key value pair in the dictionary
we want one of these for every digit
for d in range 10 would give me all the digits
but notice in this result that there's no two
because there's no element in here
that ends in the digit two
so I need to filter out some of the ds
we want to keep a d
if any of the elements in s ends in d
we can use the built in any function
any of the elements in s ends in d
is expressed as
any
element ends in d
for all the elements in s
so this is the filter claws
here's what we're iterating over
the digit 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
and for each digit that has this property
here's what we're building
now to figure out whether this actually works
we need to set s to be this value
and then evaluate our big expression
and look that's what we get
so one implementation for this would be just to return
that
and while we've solved this problem
this looks like a pretty long expression
so maybe we should be breaking it up in some way
one way to kind of break up
this whole process into steps
is to get the list of last digits in advance
so what are the last digits
of all the numbers in s
well that would just be x percent ten for x in s
then we can rewrite this
as is this digit in last digits
and we get the same result
it's only a little bit shorter
but at least it only has one big
gnarly expression instead of two
okay next question
does every element equal some other element in s
and here's an example s
one way to solve this problem
is to focus on some particular index
so let's say the index one
s I is three there it is
we could figure out if three appears anywhere else
by building a list containing everything
except for this
s up to I gives me everything through four
but not including the three
s I plus one on
gives me everything after the three
so if I were to add those together
I'd end up with everything in the list
except for that three
we haven't gotten rid of all the threes
we've just gotten rid of the element at index I
and I could ask whether s I is in
this new list that doesn't have element I in it
and it is that means that three appears somewhere else
so now that we
have an expression to check whether
the elemented index eye appears
anywhere else within the list
we could just check that for all the eyes
is it the case that all of the following are true
this expression s I is in the rest of s not including I
for every eye
in range len s
let me just write that all on one line correctly
without forgetting the last parenthesis
so you can see what's going on
so that's one way to solve this problem
but there are other ways to reason about the same thing
like let's say we didn't want to do it about indices
we just wanted to look at the values themselves
well one useful expression would be
y for y in s if y equals three
tells me how many threes there are
I could get how many threes there I
by taking the length of this
or as an alternative
I could collect ones instead of threes and get the sum
in order to figure out how many
threes there are that way
but we don't care about how many threes there are
we care about how many there are
of any particular value
so we could write this same expression as
part of a list
comprehension
I think this one might get long
where instead of the three we want every x
for x in s one of these twos mean
this means
that there were two fours
that there were two threes that there were two twos
and then this is kind of redone
there are two threes
there are two twos there are two fours
if we want to make sure that each of these is above two
then one
way is to say that these are all greater than one
another way
would be to compute them all
find the minimum value in there
and make sure that that minimum
value is greater than one
now you know that they're all greater than one
so just two ways of writing the kind of equivalent idea
and all we're doing here is just
counting the number of times
that x appears in s
and in fact it turns out that that's built in
I could just say s dot count
how many threes there are and it will tell me
so I could simplify this a bit by saying
I want to know s dot
count
x for every x in s
and it will tell me that the smallest count there is
two and since those are all greater than one
we know
that every element equals some other element in s
so maybe that's the simplest way to solve this one
okay and if we did this right
then all of our dock pests should pass and they do
so it appears that we've solved all four
of these problems
let's do some linked list processing
I'll just show you a few exercises
you can try to solve them on your own
and then we'll work on them together
how do we write a function
that tells us whether a link list
s is ordered from least to greatest
the elements of this are
the elements of this aren't
how would you tell if a linked list is ordered
from least to greatest
by absolute value
so these are 1 3 4 are the absolute values
whereas these are not
and why just apps blue value
we could have any
key function that tells us whether they're ordered
after you call the key function on each element
here's a classic exercise
create a sorted
link containing all the elements of both sorted links
s and t
so if I have sorted s and sorted t
how do I create sorted s and t
and this builds a new link list out of these two
but what if we wanted to do the same thing
but never call link
instead we could take the original s and t
and mutate them in order to create
this link list structure
how would we do it
well instead of having the rest of s b five
the rest of s would be 1 4 5
you can pause here
and try to work these out on your own
now we're gonna go solve them together
so here's our link list class down here
takes a first and a rest
the rest is empty by default
and how do we check whether something's ordered
1 3 4 is ordered one and four three is not
well there we're going to use recrusion
check if the first two elements are ordered
and check to make sure that everything after that
is ordered as well
if it's the case that s is
linked up empty or s rest is linked up empty
then this thing is definitely ordered
because it's only got zero or one elements
there's not enough there to be out of order
if it's the case that s dot first
is greater than s dot rest
that's the elemented index
zero is greater than the elemented index one
then they're not ordered
if you don't know that it's ordered
and you don't know that it's not ordered
but you do know
that the first two elements are ordered
then you have to just check everything else
return ordered
s rest
now this gets a little bit more interesting if you
allow for a key function to tell you
what values you really want to think about ordering
so are we ordering the values that are there
or are we checking the order of the result of calling
abs on these
so abs one is one abs -3 is three
abs four abs 4 1 3 4 are ordered
so this would be true using a key function apps
we're using this in much the same way that key is used
for sorted or min or max
we'd have to add in a second argument
by default it just has the identity function
but if you pass in abs
then that's the condition we should check
is it the case that abs s dot first is greater than
abs s rest first
well that would handle the absolute value case
but we want this to be generic enough to handle
any possible key function
so we just replace abs with key
that means by default it will take
the identity function
but if you want
it could take the abs function instead and apply that
all right let's look at the next one
merge return a sordid list
with the elements of sordid s and t
so when I merge together a and b one five and one four
then I get 1 1 4 5
if s is link empty
then the merged result should just be everything
that's in t
if
t is Lincoln mt but s is not then I think the reserve
the merged result should be everything that's in s
now we know that there are elements in both s and t
so we can compare
s dot first and t dot first
if they're equal
it doesn't really matter what order you put them in
so we'll just put less than equal
but we'd be equally correct if we put less than
and here we're going to create a new linked list
that starts with the smallest element as start first
and is followed by
the merged version
of everything else in s and everything in t
this result has everything in s
there's the first and there's the rest
and it has everything in t
otherwise if t dot first is the smallest element
then that's what should be
the first element of the result
we still need all the elements in s
and we need the rest of t as well
and what about merge in place
the idea here was that we started with a and b
we called merge in place and we got
all of the elements in a and b in sorted order
but we never call link
well in fact
the implementation is almost the same as this
the base cases are the same
but instead of calling link
what we need to do is change s
so that s dot first is not the same
but s dot rest is
what would that look like
well instead of returning a new link
we're just going to return s
but we're going to change s rest to have
everything in s rest and everything in t as part of it
and likewise if t has the smallest element
then that's the one we're going to return
but we're going to change its
rest to make sure that it contains
everything in this
and everything in t's rest
let's see how we did
our doctor has passed
and so
we've played around a little bit with linked lists