welcome to the lecture nine q a
here we go the question was about what's
going on with inverse cascade and would
looking at it in python tutor help us
understand it i'm guessing not
i mean you could try and uh but
most recursion problems are best
understood by just understanding what
the pieces do
and how they fit together rather than
trying to trace through it
because as soon as you make the argument
just a little bit bigger then tracing
through it becomes
yet more complicated and so
the goal here this was like a exercise
within one of the videos
was to create this pattern
um it should be the case when your goal
is to print a bunch of stuff
that the code corresponds to printing
parts of it
so this call to grow when n
is one two three four corresponds to all
of that
and this call to string
corresponds to printing all of that and
what do we leave out oh well we need a
print watcher before oh and we have a
line to do it
so um that kind of explains this
implementation
except for that we don't know what grow
and shrink do and they're
defined in this kind of complicated way
but this complicated way isn't actually
that complicated if we try to unpack it
so it says grow
involves taking in a number which at the
beginning would be one two three four i
think it's helpful to think about
examples
and then calls one function and then
calls
another function f then g checks to see
if n
is not zero and if so it calls f and
then g
and then we see what the f and the g are
well they're grow
and their print and the n that we pass
in is not one two three four but instead
one
two three so uh if i had like rewritten
grow
without this higher order function
business it would have just looked like
grow and divided by 10 print
and divided by 10. that's what do f and
then do
means except that these are both uh
checking that if it's the case that n
divided by 10
and this in python just means if this is
not equal to zero that would be a good
one to write either one
in fact a quirk of python is that the
sort of standard style guide says you
should leave this part out
i think it's fine to leave it in as well
uh because it makes it more explicit but
in any case this is the grow function
that you construct
by taking in a number n then
calling f and g which checks to see
if n divided by 10 is not 0 and if so
calls f which is grow and then g which
is print
in order to do the work
so in this alternate definition still
works
so i guess that's how i would suggest
understanding this example
is that you're using the power of higher
order functions in order to write grow
and shrink
in a way that
is a little bit more succinct by
having a function that does the thing
that they have in common which is
basically like check for a base case
call one function on and then call some
other function on end but grow
involves calling grow first and then
printing whereas what would phrase look
like
well if we look at the definition it
says first print dimension
that works and then we can get rid of
all this stuff it's not doing anything
anymore because these are being
redefined
so let me add a couple things to this uh
so
i want to re-emphasize that
um often when you code and i i still do
this to this day
i start with sort of maybe a little
clunky a little long
but very explicit concrete
implementation
i make sure it works i make sure i
understand it so for example if i was
doing this i would start with the ladder
of these functions where i explicitly
define the functions it's a little bit
clearer
it's a little clunky you can see you
need a lot more code and then once
you've got that
then i can start tightening it up and
writing efficient code and doing the
lambda expressions and the reverse works
when you're trying to understand
something
you know that a lambda function is just
a shortcut for
a defined function so rewrite it as the
defined function it's often clear
because now you're dealing with these
sort of dual complexities you've got the
lambda expressions the anonymous
functions
and you've got this new concept of
recursion so removing
um complexity by just very just
unpacking that lambda is a good way to
do it
i'm also going to re-emphasize that i
don't think for a lot of the recursion
examples the environment diagrams are
the best way to do it i think the better
way to do it as john was saying is
to look at the code think about the tree
diagram of the recursive calls you can
sketch these things out
i call this i call this i call this i
think that's a little bit
more compact than trying to track these
huge environment diagrams of all the
variables
and there was one question in the check
a chat about how come this is just if n
whereas this has a not
zero and you could remove this zero is a
false
value in python meaning that if you say
if and then a number if that number is
zero
then it will not execute the suite of
the if statement
if it's anything other than zero so this
would do the same
in python you can actually just put in
it doesn't have to be an equality or
inequality check
you can just put in a value and so
they're now asking so there's no
base case um great question
so where would the base case be you
think about that yeah
yeah so there's sort of a base case here
it's just not explicit
yeah so you kind of say nothing to do
i think that's the base case is that you
just kind of return
it would be a fine way to write it but
if you wanted to kind of break it out
into
a base case and recursive case
the only action happens in the recursive
case and the base case
you don't do anything yeah so the base
case just says
stop so if you have a conditional in
there or the results of the conditional
i think
we've broken it somehow i think you got
it backwards it should be if not
yeah yeah there it is
so if there's no conditional
you're probably going to have trouble
right so that means it's going to keep
recursing recursing recursion you got to
have something that says
only do this under certain conditions
and if that certain condition is not
met well then there's nothing to do so
you're done now in this case in some of
the other base cases like fibonacci
we had to do something we had to return
zero or one
but here there's just nothing to do
we're done we just stopped working yeah
so there is an
implicit base case um and i think this
came up in the lecture too is
i probably would have written it like
this with the explicit base case
just so i can see it it was per april's
question is i just want to see
that it's there so i don't have to infer
it yeah
yeah i mean the point of this example is
not to say this is the right way to
define this function
because i think it would be much better
written like this
but the point of this example was to
show that it is certainly possible
to have sort of implicit base cases
where you only define what to do
in the recursive case where you could
use higher order functions
where the base cases like inside this
higher order function and it's not here
all of the things that we've learned so
far in the class can
be mixed in with recursion doesn't mean
it's a good idea
but it's worth knowing that that's
possible
sure good question so the question was
about count partitions which was an
example
from lecture and what's with the with
them and without them
and these recursive calls with every
pre-recursion problem like this one
where you're taking a
problem and you're
solving it with kind of smaller
instances of the same problem
i do think it's very important that you
understand
what you're trying to get done before
you start reading the code
like reading the code just isn't very
helpful unless you know
what you're trying to simulate and what
we're trying to simulate here
is uh if you're going to write the
number n
as a expression of adding up a bunch of
different numbers that are all m or
smaller
then it turns out there's
a way to split that whole group of
things that you're counting
into two smaller groups okay so
in in this case the two smaller groups
well let's just fill in the values
there um if we started with six
four they would now be two four
they would be 6 3.
now adding up to the number 2 using
positive numbers
up to size 4 well
you can't really have a 4 in there or
you're going to have a sum
that's bigger than 2. so this is
actually equivalent to just if we had
written 2
2 assuming we get our base cases right
so basically we're saying
if you want to write a sum of size up to
six what you should really do is figure
out how you
sum up to two and why is that relevant
well one way to get six is to use a four
and then have some other expression that
adds up to two
and in fact there's like two different
ways to do it you could write it that
way
or you could write it that way but this
part
is represented by this recursive call
where with m describes that what you're
really
counting is expressions that start with
the number m which in this case is four
if we're looking at this example
so definitely think about an example
when you're trying to analyze what one
of these does
and make sure that you know what you're
counting if you're counting or what
you're trying to find the maximum of if
you're trying to find the biggest thing
or whatever
and uh in this case we're counting up
expressions that look like this
and we're using ones that uh have a four
i think in the lecture description i
said that these need to be in
increasing order so let's just put the
fours at the end so it doesn't
make it even more complicated okay and
then what about without it
so this says count up all the ways of
summing to six
with parts up to size three well that's
because we're not adding a four
and so we have to get all the way to six
but we'll do it with
parts up to size three and we're not
adding four at the end right
um and uh so there might be one like
that
and one like that etc all of these down
here
are going to be counted by this
recursive call
if you count up all of these and you
count up all of those
and you add them together then they get
the count of all the ways of getting to
six
using parts up to size four where you
either used a part up to size four
or you did so let me add
two things here if i may so one is one
of the hallmarks of recursion
is that you you sort of break the
problem down into sub problems and those
sub problems tend to be simpler
yeah so in this case for example we are
looking for
all partitions of six with the maximum
number is
four and there's this really beautiful
graphic
in the lecture that john showed where he
showed you all the possible answers
yeah and what you saw is that there's a
set of those
answers that have a 4 in it yeah
so that's the with four recursive call
so
tell me how to get to six if i'm telling
you one of the numbers
if the maximum number is four yeah this
is it and then look at everything below
that
there's no four in it yeah so if you if
you look at the first two lines here
two plus four is six one plus one plus
four six those are the only two ways
that you can get to six where one of the
numbers is
four right you can see that of course
now everything below that
it's as if we had asked to solve a
completely different problem
well not a completely different problem
a different a smaller problem which is
how do i get to
6 where the maximum value is 3
and let's agree that since three is less
than four that is part of the solution
to the first problem so all we've done
with the with four and the without four
is we've split
the solution space here into two sets
one that include four one that don't
include four and then we do it again
so then below there's the solutions that
include three and don't include three
and then there's the ones that include
two and don't include two and notice
that we keep simplifying the problem
yeah so that's the elegance of recursion
is that you sort of you sort of peel off
a little bit of the problem that's easy
to solve
you know it's almost like almost like
the base case and then everything else
you just do
well recursively you just sort of jump
off the cliff say that you're going to
do it
and it happens so that's what those two
things are right there
if this takes a while to sync it like
that is very normal
um you know you might get up to this
point in the course and think like isn't
computer science really about just
learning all the rules
and then like applying them and maybe
looping through stuff but it turns out
that computer science is broader than
that it's really about
solving all kinds of problems using
computation
and this idea that you could use things
you
are building in order to build bigger
things comes up over and over and over
again and it's a different way of
thinking
and one of the trickiest parts
is that you need to relate the code to
what in the world
you're representing that's where how
most like interesting programs work
is that you're representing something
about the world using
your code whether it's numbers or we'll
learn about lists
on monday or whatever it is you can
represent all kinds of stuff in the
world using your program
but that means that like lines of code
have to correspond to stuff that you're
trying to represent
and it takes a little while to get used
to that but you'll get better at it
there's a question in the chat that asks
do we go all the way down to
six two uh sorry to six one or do we
stop
at six two and you can see here that to
get
that last line here we have to do six
one
so we go all the way down to 6 1 and you
can also see the base case
is that when n is equal to 0
and is less than 0 which means we've
gone sideways somewhere
and m is 0. so the base case
when you stop is either n has gone to
zero
or m has gone to zero in which case
there's nothing to do
and so that m equals one does in fact
get
um partitioned in the recursive call
yeah so you go you go from six six four
to two four
but you also go from six six or six four
to six three
and that goes to both uh
uh three three and five
and six two uh it's way too early for
this man
but the point is like there's all these
different options and they both happen
each time and so you go from six four to
six three to six two
to six one to five one to four one to
three one to two one to one one
to zero one and then you finally like
have built this
last example but it takes it takes a
bunch of recursive calls to even count
one of these
but you're making so many that you count
them all so there's another question
here which i like which is
could we have done so in your with m
example you said well we can't really do
2 4 this is basically 2 2. so could we
have done
n minus m n minus m
for the with m call
um yeah that would have worked for this
example but not for all examples one
thing you could do
is you could write i want the minimum of
m
and n minus m to say like look
if if this is getting so small that it's
bigger than m why don't we just use that
instead but sometimes it's not bigger in
6 4 it turned out it was if this was
15 4 then after using 1 4 you'd be at 11
4 but you don't want to make a recursive
call on 11 11
because then you're using parts that are
bigger than size 4 which is where you
wanted to start so
this would be a perfectly good
alternative version
so remember first of all so i think
you're asking about the return in the
else clause yeah
yeah right so we're asking about the
return on that size now remember
that that return has to be evaluated
every single time we call count
partitions
right there's not just one return here
there are multiple multiple multiple
returns
right so why so let's do the first call
to close count partitions
what do you do you call competition
that's the first line there with the
with m
there is a promise to come back yeah and
do the without and then the return
but you can't do that until you finish
the with
so you go off and you do a bunch of
bunch of recursive calls eventually it
will hit a base case in return
and then you'll do the without it'll do
a bunch of recursive calls eventually at
a base case in return and then you do a
return so there isn't just one return
there is the return of everything that
is being built up
yeah and that's why you get all the
outputs not just that last one with the
one on one
should we do something a little bit fun
we could use a decorator to see exactly
how it works
i was about to ask i think we should use
a decorator illustrate
what honey just described so uh
well let's call it trace so we'll trace
a function
by creating a new function that takes
n and m and it's actually going to
get the return value of calling
that uh f
on n m and then it's gonna print what
happened
so this is gonna print
uh f
that's just to get the name count
partitions
uh and then we had an m
and then we had uh
m and then
we had uh what a return
and what did it return
result okay i'm sure there's a better
way to write this but
we've done what we've done
uh return g
and uh we actually do need to move this
up here so that we can use it
and i really need to make it a little
wider so it doesn't look so weird get my
picture out of the way
and then we can trace this and then we
can try to look at what happens
when we call count partitions on six and
four
it crashes uh i think you've got
ah you have to convert yeah
well that was a miracle that that ran
quite a crash now you got another oh
result is an int
okay
so there are more compact ways to build
a big string but we haven't talked to
you about them yet so
yeah uh oh you've got a return
none somewhere oh yeah there it is
okay we finally made it okay so here's
what happened is that
competitions actually returned nine
when we called it on six and four
so this expression actually came up with
nine at the very end
why did it come up with nine well it
came up with two for this
which are these two and it came up with
seven for this
i didn't list them all out but you saw
them in a picture
and that seven came from calling
competitions on six and three
and where did the two come from well
long ago
we counted called competitions on two
and two and that's how we got the two
so it added you know that two
and that seven together to get this nine
how does it keep track of all this stuff
well that is the mechanics of
the programming language how call
expressions work is that they don't
return until they have all
of the values that they need to compute
and uh then can compute the return value
and then returns that so
this thing is doing a bunch of work in
order to find out that with m
is two making a bunch of recursive calls
after that to figure out that without
m is seven and then finally adding two
and seven together and returning
and these are all the different calls
that mix yeah go ahead whether we had
recursion or not
imagine that with them and without m
just called some other function not
recursively
it would be it would make total sense
right with them call some function you
get a two back without an m call some
function gets a seven back
and then we return the sum of those two
that's fine
right all that's happening here is that
in order to get that two and in order to
get that seven
we're calling ourselves but there's no
problem with that because what john just
said is that
the python interpreter has has state has
memory it knows
that it has to after the first call
return the sum of with them and without
them
when competition was called on six and
three and so it has to go do all the
work it needs to get with them recursive
non-recursive don't care it has to go
through all the work to do
to get without m recursive not recursive
don't care
and then it slams them together and then
the beauty here
is that okay to get the with them i had
to do
sort of the subversion of the problem so
then i had to solve exactly the same
thing
but there's no conflict with the
original call because that's in a
different environment
um if you will um and so it's doing its
own little thing in its own little
environment when it's done it finally
pops back out to the other one
the next question was how do you get the
competitions 0
0 when only one of n or m
is being decreased at any given
recursive call
ah but they're not right so the with m
is decreasing n and the without m is
decreasing
m right which means they're both getting
decreased
right because in the recursive call so
let's do the with
m yeah so with that is going to make a
call to
uh com partitions with a smaller n do we
agree on that
good that means that the pair of
recursive calls
for that call will both have a smaller n
right don't confuse this second end here
and without
m with the original n it's now the end
from the recursive call which is smaller
yeah and then with that makes another
recursive call decrementing and even
again
and then it goes down so that you have
to remember that those end variables are
with
with respect to the recursive call not
the original
call which in which case of course it
would always be the same but that's not
the case
i see yeah okay yeah that makes sense
now
good so just to finish this up i had a
little bit more trace
which says what happens when things get
called and
you know first we call it on six four
and that calls it on two two and that
calls it
on zero zero and then finally something
gets returned
so you can see that like in the
recursive call
n is now two and m is now two and so it
counts competitions on zero and zero
in the second time around and so we see
that call and that call is a base case
and so we find there's one way
to um
compute two using parts up to size two
where you actually use a two which is
just
two okay so if this example is extremely
confusing and it's understandable
because of the tree recursion so what i
would suggest is go back to
to one of the examples that doesn't have
tree recursion that just does a simple
like the the factorial yeah and make
sure that you really understand that how
every time you make the recursive call
you're reinstantiating the local
variables and the parameters
and once you've really got your handle
on that then the tree recurrence the
trigger pins are a little tricky because
you got to sort of
build out these trees by the way the
absolute right way to follow
these recursions is not the environment
diagram by drawing the tree
right so sit at the root make a call to
count partition with n
m before you do anything put the promise
for the three things for the two things
you have to do i have to make a call
here i have to make a call here
okay what does this one have to do i
have to do two calls two calls two calls
and you'll see the diagram and then you
should be able to trace the order
as john did in the lecture
yeah keep in mind that the environment
diagram is going to have as many frames
as we have
calls here so it's going to be just
absurdly large
right and that's why the tree diagram is
a little bit easier to see
it's just just you're not lugging around
all that extra stuff
and i would also say that this trace
while it's interesting
to kind of watch what's happening tends
not to be that useful
for writing the program or understanding
how the program works you really have to
think
abstractly about what's in here like
what are these going to do what are you
going to get back
and what happens when you add them
together
the next question was could you explain
why you added
min n minus n m
earlier on in this q a so
the question is about the min function
in the with m
you don't actually need that um the
reason we put that in there
is in this particular example with six
four
the first call um uh would be to f
uh four what was it uh
let me see if i can get this right uh a
two four
in which case there's there's there's
you don't need the second term to be
larger than the first term
and so i i'm pretty sure if you run like
this everything will run just fine it'll
just hit the base case
yeah um so we just put that min in there
because it sort of doubt with the with
the case when
m the second number is greater than the
first number which of course doesn't
make sense
because you can't get to two using a
four it doesn't do any harm
you just it's just sort of unnecessary
but this is something that's very
problem specific like it's
the the fact that you can't build up a
number using a sum
using parts that are bigger than that
sum is basically why that man is there
it's not something that's like a general
fact about recreating recursive
functions in general or something like
that
it was very probable specific
the next question was what would count
partitions 2-4 do
so let's think about a little bit and
we'll run it um 2 4 says
how do you make two out of sums and
there are two ways
you could have just two or you could
have one plus one so this should return
two
and fingers crossed
that's what it returns so it's finding
one way to do it with a two which is
just
two it's finding one way to do it
without a two which is one plus one
that's the recursive call uh two one
and then it counts both of those
so now the question is what would happen
if john changed compartitions to four to
two two
same answer right so what's going on
here well yes the second argument was
4 but you can't use a 4 to get to a 2.
so it ignores it
and i can't use a 3 to get to a 2. so i
ignore it um so
and the the last number can't be greater
than the first number
and that's what the min there was
therefore is just to sort of make that
explicit
but it doesn't harm to do it it just you
won't be able to get to it
all right any other questions i want to
re-emphasize
something that was said is don't don't
get frustrated at the recursion it takes
time it's it's it's one of these
it's a little weird it's not like the
the loops which are really
straightforward the conditionals and
all that it takes a little time you have
to sort of think a little bit different
by the way
back in the day we used to start by
teaching recursion the first day of
class john and i were just talking about
this the other day
if we don't teach you about iteration we
don't do anything we just teach you
recursion
in some ways that's excruciatingly
painful but it also
in some ways is easier because you don't
have this sort of iterative construct to
think about
i think we're doing it the right way
bringing it downstream a little bit but
it's okay these will take a little bit
of time to get your head around how
these things are working
well yeah a lot of people used to drop
after lecture two and this was a lecture
two example instead of a lecture nine
example but
still in this course we teach this much
earlier than most other universities
um i think it's a great way to get used
to the idea of functional abstraction
and to see the kind of problem-solving
power of just writing simple functions
and letting the computer do the work for
you
but it's not easy at all
all right we'll be back to answer your
questions at 2 10 p.m if you want to
join
for the unrecorded ask us anything
session then
see you soon i thought you were going to
say unhinged but okay unrecorded is fine
also might be on
thanks everybody see you this afternoon