61a lecture 25 q a
there were no questions about the
lecture but there were some questions
about
lab homework and past exam problems
one of my favorite things john about
that video was the use of the vhs tape
to play the videos during the talks
wasn't that great yeah yeah that brings
me back
so back in the day by the way when we
used to do presentations before we all
had laptops
we would um take pictures of our
physical slides
uh develop them as 35 millimeter slides
load them into a carousel tray get on an
airplane with that tray
show up at the conference hand some guy
that tray and they would literally put
that tray
on a carousel and like slip through it
and without fail
every single talk had like at least one
slide upside down and
the audience was all instead of doing
this trying to see the slide
that sounds excellent the good thing
about that by the way
was you know now when you go to
conferences and talks everybody's on
their laptop and device
so back then there was nothing to do you
just listen to the goddamn talk
now it's hard to get people's attention
yeah now at conferences everyone's
writing their talk that's going to
happen
i like sitting in the back so i could
see everybody else's talk being worked
on i'm like
what are we doing here if we're all
working on our topics exactly
i miss those days
yeah i took one class from a postdoc who
decided that
transparencies were better and i think
he was right
like he had this huge stack of printed
out
transparencies and he put each one on
the overhead projector and you know he'd
ride on it as he was lecturing and it
was very
nice but i did get a panicked email to
the whole department once saying
my four foot high stack of transparency
has gone missing it's like my life's
work
has anybody seen it i had the problem
where i used to go to talks
and every once in a while they were in a
box and i would drop the box and the
slides were like all over the place
let's see if there's a real my favorite
thing that i ever did
this is what i did when i introduced my
job at dartmouth
so we had this problem with transparency
it's called keystoning
so if the projector was very close to
the um
the uh uh screen the slides would be
really distorted because you were
projecting sort of
upwards yeah so i had three versions of
my slides that i printed with the
inverse distortion
oh so when i put the slides down they
were almost paralyzed people were just
complete
this by the way this is what what passed
for high tech 20 years
that will definitely get you a job
that's amazing yeah and it was just a ho
and then i had a slide
showing it's just a homography oh by the
way it's if you were
if you were present for the first
lecture where i talked about the license
plates
it's the same map that did the license
very nice yeah all right
okay so we're in lab nine question four
number of binary trees where you're
taking in
and it tells you how many different
binary trees
have exactly n leaves
and
it points out that there is a closed
form solution
i think unbalanced parenthesis which is
unacceptable but uh there it is so this
closed form solution
let's see what that looks like uh
oh it's just pointing to the wikipedia
page that says like there happens to be
a formula for this thing
all right well michonne's right that's
not really acceptable
um but the goal here is actually not to
just
write down that equation in code
but instead to think about this
recursively so
just to get you started if you
want to build a full binary tree
with three leaves well you got to have
some
number of leaves in the left branch and
some number of leaves in the right
branch
in this case there's two in the left
branch and one in the right branch
once you've decided how many are left
and how many are right
you can just use recursion to count up
all the ways of completing the left
branch
the ways of completing the left branch
is all the
full binary trees with two leaves
because we decided there are two over
there
and on the right branch that's the
number of full binder trees with one
leaf because there's a one there and so
either both of those can be counted with
a recursive call so the basic idea
is you decide okay i'm looking for three
leaves
okay so it could either be uh zero on
the right three on the left
one on the right two on the left so on
and so forth
and then once you've established that
for the top level well then everything
else is just recursive
and then i don't know how to do this
non-recursively by the way it's not
obvious to me
yeah i mean there's this formula but you
know yeah but
besides that that's uh that's all i mean
it looks like a recursion problem um
now i mean i guess what's interesting
here is that it's an unusual way of
combining the two recursive calls
so uh you know we can talk about this
for just a minute longer
you know okay so if n is one then
there's just one tree we saw that as
as a demonstration right but
otherwise let's forget the template for
a little while
we'd want to go through all the ways of
dividing up
and so uh for
we've got to have at least one on the
left
and then what's the most we could have
on the left well we could have up to n
minus one so we'd go to range n
how many left
is this
i think you need an i in there john or
something
and then how many on the right well the
rest of them
and then we um can figure out uh
like uh the number of trees
possible trees on left that's just a
recursive call
for the number of variables variable
names are getting a little long
okay well i'll trim it a little bit that
was that was absurd
[Laughter]
and how about on the right well that's
symmetric but then you do have to think
about what you're going to return
which is that if you have
eight different ways of building left
branches
and five different ways of building
right branches
how many different ways are there of
building a whole tree
well you can take any from the left and
any from the right so for any of the
eight on the left
you have five different options on the
right so for the first one you have five
for the second one you have five for the
third one you have five
fourth five four five so what's uh five
plus five plus five plus five plus five
plus five
that's eight times five uh so um
there's like a notion of a total which
you get by multiplying together at the
left
and the right but that's just for one
split
now you have to think about all the
different splits that you have
so uh really we should have a total that
starts at zero
and this is just describing if we picked
a particular number
of leaves on the left how many total
trees would there be
and we need to add that to the total and
return the total okay so now you can
think about how to get that all in one
line which you can do with uh
with some uh you know we're making a sum
of a bunch of different options and
maybe there's a list comprehension in
there somewhere
but i just tried to describe why there's
a product
uh like a multiplication in the middle
of this it's really because you're
saying like i can take any one of the
options from the left and any one of the
options from the right and pair them
together
and that's how you get a full binary
treat
there's a good lesson here too is when
you see these templates i always feel
like you know i've got like one hand
tied behind my back
but when you're thinking about the
problem you can break free of the
template
figure out how to think about the
algorithm and then go back and shove it
into the template
um that's how i usually think about
these problems
you know when we talk about clever
although i was teasing john a minute ago
about his variable name
there's a reason to do that it's not
just good programming style it's
particularly with recursion
it sort of helps you jump over the cliff
yeah
because you can see what this thing if
you believe that this is what it is
well then that's what it is a follow-up
question was why we're multiplying
let's say that um i give you
uh uh let's say a red let's see if this
analogy works here
i give you two things in my left hand
and
three things in my right hand yeah and i
ask you what are all the ways of
combining
them yep well okay so i can take one
thing from the left hand
and put three things from the wait no
that's not quite what i want is that
right john
yeah i think like if you have a b c in
one hand and you have one two in the
other hand
yeah what are all the different
combinations you could have you could
have a1 a2
you could have b1 b2 you could have c1
c2 that's six things
that's because it's three times two so
like if you ever think about how to pair
something from your right and something
from your left what are all the possible
ways of doing that you end up
multiplying yeah so it's it's we're
looking for
all we're not summing them up so it
wasn't like
oh here's the answer for the left here's
the answer for the right and it's the
sum of them we still have to combine
everything
and we can combine them by picking
all the different ones from the left
hand all the difference in the right
hand and doing all permutations of those
yeah okay
let's take a look at homework five
question six which is one of the
optional ones called yield paths define
a generator function path yielder
which takes a tree a value
and returns a generator which yields
each path from the root of t to a node
that has
that label called value
t is implemented with the tree class
and each path should be represented as a
list of the labels
along the path in the tree you may yield
the paths in any order
oh and they gave us some starter code
see what they did
so i guess we're gonna have to make this
one big we have an example tree here
um so one is at the root
two and five are its children three and
four
are children of two oh sorry three four
and five are children of two
and six is a child of four um and then
when we call pathfielder on six
it finds this one path to six
which is that you have to go from one to
two to four to six okay then there's the
list
but since there are two different fives
then we need two different paths the one
two
five path and also the one to five path
it says like uh iterate a little bit so
um
sometimes you find that the label of the
tree the root label of the tree that
you're on
is equal to the value you're looking for
if so
i think it's time to yield a list
containing just that label
or just that value equivalently so that
would handle the case if we were doing
path yielder
of one and we wanted that uh list
containing just one like a really short
path that's only got one element in it
the other thing is that this will allow
us to build up longer lists
because we've returned a list that's got
the right last
value in it and then we're going to have
to add stuff onto it to get the full
path that we want
okay so we're going to go through every
branch
for each branch it might contain
a bunch of paths to this label we're
looking for
and we need access to every one of those
paths in the branch
so that we can then yield paths in the
whole tree
here's an opportunity to use recursion
if i call path yielder on the branch and
the value i'm looking for
what i get back is a path through the
branch
but what i really want to yield is a
path through the tree
and so i just write that down i want to
yield a path through the tree which
is everything through the branch but it
also has the label
at the front
might be something like that nope
probably need a you know when the two is
not defined it's saying
yeah you know what a tree is okay
that works next we did the spring 2020
midterm
two question number one
so this question involves plunking the
leaves off a tree one by one
a tree with unique positive integers no
repeated labels
a plucking order for a tree is a
sequence of unique positive integers
that are all labels of t
and a valid plucking order if
uh
the plucking order has all the labels in
t and there's something special about
the order
the labels for each note of t appears
after the labels of its descendant nodes
so you have to pluck the leaves and then
you can pluck the appearance of the
leaves and then you can pluck the
parents of the parents of the leaves etc
okay uh i think we probably have to do a
in order to do b so let's just do the
whole thing implement order which takes
a number tree called
redwood it returns a valid plucking
order as a list of numbers
if there is more than one valid plucking
order your order function should return
any one of them oh how nice
uh so
we have something that's empty
uh it's called redwood for some reason
instead of t
but redwood.branches um
it seems like we can just get a plucking
order for the branch
and add that to our plucking order you
have to know which
method to apply if you have a list
already and you're trying to add a bunch
of elements
from some other list then the way to do
that is with the extend
method
okay all right here's the question you
actually asked about b
implement pluck which takes a number
tree called pine okay and returns a
function that is called repeatedly on
the elements of a plucking order
if that plucking order is valid the
final call returns success
otherwise if one of the repeated calls
is on a number that is not part
of a valid plucking order the error
string says hey
not valid
interesting so we take a tree
we then
get a function back we start calling it
on numbers
if they are a plucking order let's see
what happens i plucked the nine
then the eight then the seven and the
six
i can't plucked out one yet because it's
got
stuff still but i can pluck the five and
the four and the three and the two and
then one is bare i could pluck the one
at the end and then it would tell me
success
but if i ever try to pluck something out
of turn then it says hey not valid
okay cool what a beast
this is probably the longest problem
we've ever seen on a midterm let's read
it together
uh here's the function
that we're going to return and we return
it right away
so the only reason that we're returning
this function is because it has as its
context the tree itself so we can refer
to the tree that's good
we have this notion of pluck one leaf
which takes in something
return a copy of cyprus oh it takes in a
tree
without a leaf k and check that k is a
leaf label
not an interior node label okay so this
is the moment where we build a new tree
that's kind of like the old tree except
for we've plucked off one of the leaves
and then okay so however this does it
we'll figure that out later
we say non-local pine which is
interesting i think non-local pine is
gonna mean we're gonna change the tree
we're talking about to one that has its
leaf plucked off
if pine is a leaf then um
[Music]
it makes sure that it's the right label
and then tells us success otherwise
we need to change pine
to be the result of plucking a leaf
off of the current
tree if
is instance pine stir oh this says if
plucking a leaf caused a problem
that problem is a string that says
something like
wow you screwed up oh hey not valid and
so we'll return that
otherwise we return the same plucker
function that we had before because
we're just going to call it again
all right so uh it seems like pluck one
leaf has to not only
build a new leaf that uh has one less
um leaf
sorry build a new tree that has one less
leaf in it but it also has to sometimes
return a string that says we screwed up
all right so let's uh figure this out in
a second but this says if plucked
branches
equals okay so we're gonna go through
all the branches
and build new branches there's some
condition
under which we skip a leaf
and if we don't skip this leaf
then we pluck a leaf from the branch
um and this might be a string
and if it's a string then we're done
otherwise
we probably put this into our plucked
branches
append the plucked branch
so this is how you build a new treat as
you'd have a new list of branches
you'd go through all your old branches
and you'd put in the new branch
which is like a plucked version of the
old branch
um and then at the end we'll build a
tree
and that tree is just um
the old tree cypress
dot label with the plucked branches
i feel like we're getting close what
does it mean to skip the leaf well it
has to be a leaf
i think that's a method we'll check it
in a second
and it has to have the right label
what's it called oh not value okay
why k k is the next value we're supposed
to pluck
sounds about right so
this goes through checks all the
branches gets rid of the
one that we're supposed to pluck and um
if it's impossible to pluck it for some
reason
then it tells us so but we still don't
have this
case where we're supposed to return that
something has gone terribly
wrong when would that happen
i think that would happen if you
um
if you look at the root of cyprus and it
turns out that
that root is the k
as opposed to a leaf being a k
so here i'm assuming cyprus
is not a leaf itself
and if it's the case that cyprus
dot label
equals k that's bad
why am i assuming cyprus is not a leaf
well let's see where we call it
we call pluck one leaf
um here
where we've already checked that this is
a leaf and handled that case
so we know the initial call to pluck one
leaf is on something that's not a leaf
and then where do we make recursive
calls
well
if this thing's a leaf then we're gonna
skip it
so we must be calling it on a not leaf
here
miraculous that's the understatement
john
uh well it helps that i did once upon a
time write this question
apologies to all students whoever had
the ticket oh man you put this on an
exam
well it was an experimental exam
the experiment didn't go very well so
this is the first time that we gave
people an interpreter and i thought that
might help them a lot it turns out it
didn't help them very much
um that's a good homework problem though
and
yeah i mean you know the key to this
question is really understand
what you're trying to do it's not about
like memorizing some pattern you've seen
before
but instead just focusing on uh you know
like what exactly is the process that
i'm trying to describe with the code
but the reason this is you know it
turned out not to go well
uh is that there's all this like error
handling of strings
and that turns out to be hard to process
but but at least i ain't now giving you
a description of why it is the way that
it is
yeah good question so how would you
approach a question like this and
especially if you read some part and
you're like i don't know how this part
works
well i mean i hadn't looked at this
problem in quite a while
um so it did feel a little bit new to me
although uh
not entirely new because i wrote it but
um i wasn't
sure what was gonna happen in here when
i was reading the skeleton
so i kind of just skipped it as i was
going
and i had this idea in my mind
that that we'd like have a tree
and we'd like remove one of the leaves
and then we'd have another tree
and we'd remove a leaf from that like
and i was wondering
how's that gonna happen and like i have
a function to do it but
this has to be called many times and so
i ended up skipping ahead to here
to try to look for the mechanism that
involves
just like removing one leaf at a time
and doing it over and over again
and this part i think wasn't um wasn't
so confusing to me whereas this
you know upon skimming it it seemed like
quite a beast
because there was a bunch of blanks and
uh you know now it looks reasonable but
uh but it didn't at the beginning
um but this idea that we would kind of
keep track
of the tree that we were plucking from
and then pluck leaves from it
i guess that is one entirely separate
question
from how exactly you go through and get
rid of a leaf
so i think in a really big question like
this
um looking for ways in which you could
solve one part and solve another part
modularly might make it more manageable
okay so let's take a look at this this
is fall 2018
question seven a trictionary is a pair
of tree instances
k and v that have identical
structure each node in
k has a corresponding node in v
the labels in k are called keys each key
may be the label for multiple nodes in k
and the values for that key are all the
labels
of all the corresponding nodes in v
okay so k can have two labels that are
the same
and if you uh want to know all the
corresponding things for two
well you'd have to look up the
corresponding labels c and a
in the v treat and so that's why we see
here key
2 has two values
a lookup function returns one of the
values
values for a key
specifically a lookup function for a
node in k
is a function that takes v as an
argument and returns the label
for the corresponding node in v okay so
remember v
is a tree here
uh so a lookup function takes
the whole v tree and tells you which
label to get or like gets one of the
labels and returns it
implement the generator function lookups
which takes a tree instance k and some
key it yields all lookup functions for
nodes in k that have
key as their label the new lookup
function is part of the implementation
okay so
oh i said that other thing was really
big but this is big too
okay so i think we should learn how this
works
you call lookups on some k tree which is
this one that's given to us as an
example and some value
like two it gives us back
a generator over two functions
each of those functions takes this
entire tree in
but the function knows something about
like what path it's going to follow
and so it gives you the corresponding
value for some particular
position in k so calling f
the first f gave us c and calling the
second
f gave us a
so this question is all is kind of a
mixture of
traversing trees and also dealing with
generator functions
and higher order functions so it's
synthesizing a lot of topics in this
course
but i don't think you have to like
discover
how to do it so much it's like
lookups is going to go through and find
paths to the number two but it's going
to encode those as functions
and those functions are going to go find
the same path
through v and give you the the
corresponding label
okay so how will lookups actually work
if something yield a function that takes
in uh
[Music]
okay the whole tree and does something
with it
otherwise we go through all the branches
and we make a new lookup
um for everything in here interesting
um these lookup functions like f
they take a tree and they have to
somehow
get you all the way to a label that you
want
i think the simplest case is if what you
look up
is at the top so if
it's the case for
that
k which is a tree's label
is equal to the key that i'm looking for
then that means
the the corresponding value labels right
there
at the root so if i took in a
tree full of values
i would want to return the one
at the root
otherwise this key that i'm looking for
could be in the branches somewhere and
so i'm going to go through
all the branches but this doesn't go
through the branches it goes through
them by index for some reason
well we see the reason is that we use
the index here
um
and we've got a hint here that we need
like a lookup function already
and then we're going to build some new
lookup function that basically uh
uses this i somehow so i'm going to put
in a sketch of what i think might work
and then we'll take up
new lookup and see what it does
i think if you want to introduce this
name lookup
um really we're going to have to go
through all of the different
times that key appears in this branch
and get a lookup function for it that
sounds like uh use of recursion this is
i guess quite similar to the problem we
just did
where here we're not going to look it up
in k but we're going to look it up in
a branch of k
can't type well we're still looking for
the same key that we were looking for
before
and this says yield a new lookup so
let's think about what this function
would do
this function would look through a
branch
of v and find the corresponding values
that match the key
but we want to look through all of k and
find the corresponding value
so we build a new function here it is
that takes in the whole tree v
it has to uh
look up within one of its branches
i the label that we're looking for
where i'm assuming here
that
assuming f is a lookup
function for a branch of v
so what does new lookup do basically
like if you have a way of
looking from here and finding or sorry
let's do it over here
if we can look from here and find the a
what we're building is a function that
can look from here
and find the a that's what this does
and then how are we building all of the
functions
that find both the c and the a
well we're going through all the
different branches so here's this branch
this branch and this branch
and then we're going through all the
times that i found the key in this
branch
which is only here and here i'm taking
the function that knows how to look
through here and find the
corresponding c and the function that
looks through here and finds the
corresponding a
and building new functions that can look
from the top of b
oh that was a mess questions
yeah great question so the question is
you know when would you do this
and how does it relate to everything
else that you know
um this is quite abstract but
the following pattern shows up a lot
which is that if you want to build
something
that is you know four things long you
start with something that's three things
long
and you put something on the beginning
or sometimes the end
a linked list look like this you've seen
this pattern when just using regular
lists
here we're seeing it using functions
where a function could be representing
uh most of a path and then we're
building a new function that represents
an even longer path
basically just by like sticking
something on the front
now the way this function is implemented
is by
calling the function that represents the
rest of the path
and so if you call g you're kind of
calling the whole path now why would you
want to call a whole path
well calling a path is like doing
something with a tree in this case we're
extracting a particular label from the
tree
um so in that sense it does look
like the same concept you've seen before
but certainly in a different way this is
now
using kind of the mechanics of functions
to do what you could otherwise do
with a linked list and um
yeah and and knowing that you could
achieve the same thing in different ways
is part of computer science but it's
it's this is like really a new thing
that was presented to you on the exam as
like a new way of synthesizing
um existing ideas that you know you know
how to use functions you know how to use
linked lists you know how to use paths
but here you're asked to kind of put
them together in kind of a
new method okay so let's finish up by
explaining why
yield the new lookup i look up again
okay so
um let's focus on an example the example
will be
when we're looking for the number
three
we have not found it at the top
it never showed up here we did get
one lookup in this branch
and so if i call lookups on this branch
um then i get a lookup function
but i called lookups not
on the whole tree but just on the branch
and that means that the lookup function
i got is really only prepared
to process this branch of the
corresponding
v tree it knows how to take in
this branch and find the s
but it doesn't know how to take in this
whole tree
and find the s so we need to create
a new function that is based on the one
that knows how to find the s in this
branch
and can instead find the s in this whole
tree
that's why we call new lookup where i
is the index of this tree index one
and lookup is the function that can take
this branch
and find the s and then what we do