61 election No.34 announcements
homework gate is due today
the scheme project is due next Tuesday
but tomorrow there's a checkpoint
and you get an early submission
bonus point for completing it
by Monday
keep at it I know it's a long project
but you'll get through it if you work on it every day
homework nine is not do next week
it will be posted to morrow
but won't be too until the Thursday after thanksgiving
so you could just forget about it
until thanksgiving is over
and you'll be fine
lab 13 which is scheduled for next week is optional
everybody will get credit whether you do the lab or not
but do the lab
because it's a good way to learn and prepare to do
homework nine
the completely optional scheme recurs of art
contest entries are due Monday
after thanksgiving
we'll have an exam prep section tomorrow
and lecture q amp a as usual
just glancing at the schedule ahead
all of the lectures from here on out are optional
until the last two where we do some review
there won't be any
office hours or discussion or anything
like that over thanksgiving
we will have a lab orientation
for those who want to complete the lab on Monday
and we will have
lab and discussion the week after thanksgiving
as well as homework nine do after thanksgiving
so I hope you have a great weekend and a great
thanksgiving break
should be the case that once you finish up
homework gate and the scheme project
you're ready to take that break
and the stuff that's do
on the final week of the semester
should just help you get ready for the upcoming final
on the 17th
today's lecture shows you how you can connect
sequel and python together into one program
and also talks about how to manipulate
a sequel table by changing its contents
mutation for sequel here we go
a table can be given a name with create table
and that name can be forgotten using drop table
we've already seen create table statements
but there's an alternative
version that we haven't looked at yet
here from this sequelite documentation
is the complete syntax for a create table expression
you can write create table or create temp table
or create temporary table
you can optionally include if not exists
after that you can write down schema names
table names column definitions table constraints etc
some of these are in fact compound expressions
for example a column def
means writing down a column name
a type name and a column constraint
you can have multiple column constraints
and the type name is optional
a column constraint is one of many forms
you could give the constraint a name
say it's a primary key not null unique
check default colate foreign key clauses
there's really a lot to a create table expression
but we're not going to focus on all of it
that's for a database's course
instead
we'll just focus on the version we've already seen
where you say create table
give it a name and as select statement
or a version where you create an empty table
so we're going to ignore all of
these parts of the syntax and instead
just focus on what's left over
in black you can ride create table
if you want to make sure you're creating a table
that doesn't exist already
create table if not exists
creates a table
only if that name doesn't exist already
you give the table a name and then
you can either write as followed by a select statement
we've seen that before
or you can specify the columns directly
by enclosing in parentheses
a list of column definitions
a column definition involves naming the column
and applying zero or more column constraints
the only column constraints will worry
about for this course
are that you can say the values are unique
and then there an
error will be raised if you try to put the same value
twice in the column
and you can give a default value to a column
and this
default value is used when we insert new values
into a column
so here are some examples
you could create a table of numbers with a column in
and a note about each number in
I could alternatively create a table of
numbers where I specify
that n is unique
so I can only have one note per unique number n
if I want to make sure there's always a note
I might set a default value such as
no comment
now you might wonder what's the use of an empty table
well soon we'll see that you can add new rows
to an existing table
and so it won't be empty forever
drop table is simpler
that just removes the name that exists already
from a table
so you write drop table and then the table name
we won't worry about this detail of the syntax
and if you want to only run this if the table
already exists
then you can write drop table if exists
now if without this if exists claws
if you run drop table on a name that doesn't exist
you'll reach an error
creating an empty table
is only useful if we're able to modify it
and in fact any table can be modified by in surging
deleting or changing the rows
here from the sequel light documentation
you see that there are
many different variants of how you might
insert rose into a table
we're only going to focus on
certain paths
such as writing insert into the table name
specifying the column names
or you can skip specifying the column names
and then
you either write down a select statement that adds
all of the rows in that select statement to the table
or you specify values directly
by including those values in comma separated lists
each set of parentheses will create one new row
and what you separate by the commas
are the values for the columns in that row
for a table that has two columns
if you want to insert into just one of the columns
then you write insert into t
you say which column you want to insert into
then the keyword values
and then in parentheses
you'd put only the one value for that one column
a whole row will be inserted
and default values will be used for the other column
if you want to insert into both columns
then you can say insert into t
you don't specify which columns
so that means all of them
and then you give the values that you're inserting
into each of the columns
both of these insert
into statements would insert one row
if you want to insert more rows
then you just follow these parentheses by comma
and more parenthetical row descriptions
let's take a look at a demonstration
I'll start up sequel light
and create a table
that keeps track of positive integers
and whether or not they are prime
let's call it primes
and now I'll specify that there are two columns
n and whether or not it's prime
now I didn't apply any column constraints there
but I could have
one way to change what I've done
is to just drop the table and start over
now that table is gone
I cannot select star from primes
because primes doesn't exist
but if I create it again then it will exist
so let's make sure that each of these is unique
and that prime has a default value
now there are no boolean values in sequelite
so you can't have true and false
but it's conventional to use one for true
and zero for false
and let's assume things are prime
and let's prove it otherwise
so by default we'll have prime b one
meaning yes I think this number is prime
now I can select star from primes
I see no contents
but I don't see an error because the table does exist
now I can insert in two primes
the following values
two is prime and three is prime
and now if I look at what's in primes
I see two and three
both of them are prime
so that's why we have ones in the prime column
now prime is default one
that means if I insert
into just the prime's end column
then I'll get the default value for the other column
so if I insert the values four
five six and seven
now I have two three four five
six and seven in my table
this claims are all prime
that's not quite true
four and six are not
we're gonna clean that up later
what's a quick way to get even more integers
into my table
well I could insert into primes in
the result of selecting all the values in primes
so let's put m plus six
from primes into my table
and now I've got two through five six seven eight
nine ten eleven twelve and thirteen
now that primes is different
if I insert again I'll have an even different effect
so here's what we get when we
add 12 to each result that's in there now
and add all those rose as well
it's also possible
to update the contents of existing rows
you write update a table name
set
which column names are going to change
followed by an equal sign
and the expression that computes the new value
for what you're going to put in that column
now you may not want to update all rows in a table
but only a subset
and so you can include a wear claws in order to say
which rows you want to change
let's use update to fix the prime column
in the table we've already constructed
so far
we have a prime's table
with an end column and a prime column
we'd like these to be zero
for all composite numbers such as four and six
aside from two itself
all the multiples of two are not prime
so I could update
we're updating the prime's table
we're setting prime that's a column name 2 0
that's a value to place in the prime column
now I need to say
which rows I want to make this change for
I want to make it for
all the rows for n greater than two
where two evenly divides in
now if I run the same select statement
I see that the multiples of two aren't prime anymore
if I apply the same logic for multiples of three
and multiples of five
then I have correctly marked four
the values between two and twenty five
which ones are prime and which ones are not
so sometimes it's easier to build a table
not just all in one go
but by manipulating the values
after constructing it initially
and that's what we've done here
in order to list out
some numbers and whether they're not their prime
finally it's possible to delete rows
you say delete from and then what table to relate from
you don't have to delete all rows
instead you can provide a wear
expression in order to delete just some of the rows
but without a wear expression you will delete
all of the rows in the table
the table will still exist
so this is not equivalent to drop table
but that table will have no rows
only empty columns after you delete from it
so for example I could delete from primes
where prime equals zero
and then if I select star from primes
I see only the prime numbers remaining
python and sql can be used together
in particular
a python program
can construct and then execute sql statements
let's take a look
here's a python program
there's a built in module called sql light three
sql light three has a class called connection
to construct a connection
I pass in the name of a database file
it could be anything
how about n.db
and this connection object
can be used to execute sequel statements
so for example I can execute
select two union select three
which would give me a two row one column table
symicalin
now just constructing this table
won't allow me to do anything with it
if I want to give it a name within the database
then I write create table
these are numbers so I'll call it numbs
so here we see how python and sequel work together
is that within python I can construct a string
that is a sequel statement
and execute it on some database
now I haven't run the program yet so nothing's happened
but let's execute one more
let's execute an insert into statement
I could explicitly write out the values 4 5 6
or I could write a python expression
that computes the values 4 5 6
for example the range four through seven
not including seven
and then I can include in my sequel statement
some holes
that get filled in by the data passed in
as the second argument to execute
so in this way we can construct any sequence we want
using python
and then integrate that into a sequel statement
so here we've created a table
changed that table
we can also read from the table
by executing select star from gnomes
oh and I forgot a semicolon up here
I'll need those too
when I select star from gnomes
execute returns what's called a cursor object
and this cursor has a method called fetch all
which will fetch the contents of the resultic table
as a list of tuples
let's print those out so we can see what happened
and finally let's clean up the syntax
of our sequel statements
oh everything else looks okay
let's see what happens when we run it
all right here's what python print it out
five tuples each one has one element
and that element is the contents of the row
when you modify a table to ensure
that the file representing this database
stores all of the changes
there's one more method you need to use
which is call db commit
if committing is successful
then this file
contains all the contents of the database
just as you constructed it
by executing this series of sequel statements
every time I run this program
a file called n.db is constructed
let's run it again
there's n.tb
if I start sequel light
using n.tb as my database
then in fact all of the contents that python put
into that database are there
there's a table called nums and it has 23456
as its contents
so that's how you can write a python program
that interacts with a sql light database
and similarly
you can write
python programs to interact with
lots of different kinds of databases
it happens to be that this one is built into the
standard library
or as other ones you have to install the connections
when a python program
reads data from an external source
and then constructs
sql statements to store that data
or use it in some other way
it may be vulnerable to a sql injection attack
this security vulnerability is easy to prevent
but everyone who's writing a program that involves
python current instructing sequel statements
should know this attack exists and how to prevent it
this kind of exploit is so popular
that there's even an xkcd comic about it
hi this is your son school
we having some computer troubles
oh dear did he break something
in a way did you really name your son robert apostrophe
close parenthesis semicolent drop table students
semicolent dash dash question mark
oh yes little bobby tables we call him
well we've lost this year's student records
I hope you're happy
and I hope you've learned to sanitize your
database inputs
let's try to understand what's going on in this comic
if in a python program you have a string with this name
and then you attempt to construct a sequel statement
that looks like
I insert this name into the table of students
well this looks inocuous
you just take some name
and you put it inside of this command
but in fact
this particular name is going to cause problems
because the command you've constructed
is insert into students
values robert and then drop the table
students and then dash
dash is a way of starting a comment in sequel
so this part won't do anything
but it also won't cause a sequel error
so this will execute just fine and
robert will be inserted into the students table
but then all the students will be gone
in python execute which we saw before
only takes one statement at a time
but there is an execute script method
that takes a string
with as many statements as you like
and executes them all
so this code would run
and it would in fact drop the table of students
and that's bad
the problem here is that a string concatenation
was used in order to construct the sequel statement
instead the correct approach
that prevents equal injection attacks
is to call db
execute using a template
and then fill in
the values that are missing in that template
the question marks with python values in this way
this will execute a statement
that's different from the three statements down here
instead it will execute just one statement
that in fact inserts the long string
robert apostrophe
closed peren semicolon drop table students whatever
into the students table
so little bobby tables will retain his true name
and the students table will not be dropped
now what's the difference
between this statement
and this sequence of three statements
well the only difference is an extra apostrophe
that's how you insert an apostrophe into a string
in sequel but you don't need to remember that
all you need to remember
is that if you're inserting a string into a larger
sequel statement
you should do it
using the execute statements built in option
of passing in values
then they'll be escaped correctly
and you won't have to worry
about sql injection attacks
multiple programs can be connected to the same
database at the same time
they can all be inserting
values and reading values from the same tables
and one of the interesting things
about database management systems
is that they can handle the fact
that multiple different connections
are made to the same database
and that multiple different clients
are trying to change the same table
let's look at an example of this
by simulating a game of blackjack
in casino blackjack
the player is dealt two cards
and the dealer is dealt one card face up
and another card face down
so if I'm the player
I might get a seven
and then the dealer gets a jack and then I get a nine
and the dealer gets some face down
card that I don't get to see
the goal in blackjack is to have
more points than the dealer
but if you go over 21 points then you lose the game
you can request additional cards
in order to get more points
the suits of the cards don't matter
so I've just used spades everywhere
all that matters at the numbers
and the cards two through 10
just count for their point values
that are written on the card
all of the face cards
jack queen king count for tan and aces are special
you can choose whether to count them for one point
or 11 points
so if seven and nine make 16
I might worry
that the dealers gonna have more points than me
so I might request an additional card
oh I got a five
now my total is 21
that's very good because I haven't gone over 21
but I'm likely to have more points than the dealer
once the players finished requesting cards
then it's the dealers turn
in casino blackjack the dealer first flips over
the card that isn't shown
and then must continue to draw cards
until reaching a number
between seventeen and twenty one
so 13 is not between seventeen and twenty one
so it draws an additional card
this can either be worth one making 14 or 11 making 24
but 24 goes over 21
and that would cause the dealer to lose
so the natural choice is to count it as only one
so now the dealer has only 14 points
draws another card if it comes out as 10
now the dealer has 24 points and is over 21
that's called going bust
and that means that the dealer loses
this hand of blackjack
if instead of a 10 head had been a seven
the total would have been 21 and they would have tied
all right let's use python and sequel together
to play some blackject
this is a longer program but not too long
so I think we can read it together
first we store the points for each card in a dictionary
where aces are worth one or 11
we'll handle that fact later
jacks queens and kings are all worth 10
and then two through 10 are just worth that many points
so it two is worth two or three is worth three etc
points to add update
just takes a dictionary and adds more elements to it
from another dictionary
here we have a way of scoring a hand
a hand is a sequence of cards
we get the points for each card
using the points dictionary
and we sum them up
if it turns out that the total is less than or equal to
11 and I have an ace
then I should count that ace as
11 points instead of one point
which gives me an extra 10 points
so in this way if I have for example a jack and an ace
total will come out to 11
but the ace would let me get 21
instead which is a better score
alright so those are the rules of black jack
encoded as a python function
now we're gonna create a database cards that db
we're going to assign sql
to the function db that execute
just so I don't have to
type db that execute over and over again
every time you see this
think db that execute because they're the same thing
I'll drop table if it exists cards so I can start fresh
and then created table cards with two columns
the card which would be 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
or jack queen king ace
and then who has it the dealer or the player
or has it been discarded
to deal a card
we insert that card into the cards table
and then we commit the result
to make sure that it's reflected in cardstb
to compute the score of any player
we get all the cards for that player
select star from cards where
who equals either the player or the dealer
that's a python value that we pass in
and then we compute the hand score
for every card that we get
by fetching all the cards
you go bust when you have a score greater than 21
the two players are the player and the dealer
and here's what it means to play a hand of blackjack
you have to have a deck of cards
you pop off the first card and deal it to the player
the second card goes to the dealer
the third guard goes to the player
and then there's a hidden card
we're going to pop it off right away
but we're not going to deal it
because we haven't shown what it is yet
now we're going to use the built in input
function in python
to ask the user
what they want to do
if they say yes I want to hit
hit means get another card
at which point will deal another card
if that makes the player go bust
then the player loses and the hand is over
if at some point
the player decides not to hit but to stay
then it's time to flip over the dealer's hidden card
so we deal that to the dealer
and then
we keep dealing cards to the dealer until the score
is greater than or equal to 17
deal deal deal
if at any point the dealer goes bust by going over 21
then we say so and the hand is over otherwise
now there's a player score and a dealer score
and we compare them
and that's how we know who won the hand
a deck of cards has four copies of each card
one for each suit
we put them in a list
they are the keys of the dictionary called points
which we constructed earlier
while shuffle the deck
using the built in shuffle function
of the random module
and then we'll just start playing hands
so we'll deal play a hand
and then at the end of the hand
we'll move all of the cards that are in players hands
into the discard pile
and now we have a fully functional game of blackjack
we've dealt a hand
shall we hit or stay
well that really depends on what cards I have
how do I know what cards I have
I can make a second connection to the database
and take a look
I just need to know the name of the database file
cards db
I can connect to it with sql light
and then I can take a look
select star from the cards table
I see the player has a three and a four
and the dealer is showing a seven
well I only have seven points so I better hit
what did I get
oh I got a jack
now I have 17 points and the dealer has seven
I think I'll stay
the python simulator played out the hand
and the dealer ended up with 17 points
if we want to see exactly what happened
we can look and see that in the last game
the dealer had seven
and then the dealer also had a queen that was hidden
and when that queen was shown the game ended 17 to 17
all right we have dealt a new hand
the player has a jack and a six
that's 16 points
the dealer has a six
even though I have a low score
I'm nervous
about taking another card because I might go bust
so let's stay where we are and see what happens
oh I had 16 the dealer had 18 and so I lost the hand
it's dealt another hand so let's try again
at this point
it's hard to see what's going on
because there's so many discards
so let's simplify that by saying where
who does not equal discard
and now I see that as a player I have a four in an ace
that's either five or 15 points
either way I need more
now I have a nine and ace and a four
in total that's 14 points
I think I should take another one
oh I went bust
so I lost that hand too
and we've dealt another hand
let's see what I've got now
I've got a five and an ace
that's either six or 16
I think I'll take a hit and see where I am
now I have five ace and ace that's either seven or 17
I'm curious what will happen next
but I could actually predict what might happen
by looking at all the carts
what's gone by already
since I have access to all of the discarded cards
I can see that very few tens have been plaid
in fact if I really want to see what's going on
I should look at what card there is and its count
from the cards table where I group by the card
so I can see that there's been one ten played
three jacks one queen
but no kings so there's a lot of kings left
there's a lot of tens left
there's a queen left
there's a reasonable chance that I'll draw a 10
on the next hit
let's take another look at what I have
well I have 17 the dealer has six
there's a chance the dealer's gonna get
a couple of tens in a row and go bust
so I think I'm not gonna hit and see what happens
ah that dealer went bust just as I predicted
by accounting the cards
now in a casino
counting cards like we did by
remembering what was in the discard pile
is against the rules
but it can help you win
all right let's look at one more hand
we've got a four and a queen
14 is really not a good hand
because the dealer has a nine
that means
they could have 19 points with that hidden card
wouldn't it be nice if instead of a queen and a four
I had a queen
an ace well then I'd have 21 points
so something else
that's against the rules in casino blackjack
is to just change the cards
update cards set
card equal to ace
where who equals player
and card equals four
let's see what hand I have now
ah and ace and a queen
I don't think I need to hit after all
cause I already have 21 points and I've won the hand
so here's an example of
two programs connecting to the same database
manipulating it together
one of those programs is a python simulator
for blackjack
and one is the interactive sequel light
read eval print loop