sixty one a lecture number twenty five announcements
homework five is due on monday
it was released over a week ago and it's not terribly long
but i think it is a good review for the midterm on wednesday
so i hope you work through it
we have an unusual schedule this week
so i'll just go through it day by day
on monday we'll have instructor office hours as always
we will also have a lab orientation however
the only required part of lab nine is that you finish homework
five all of the lab problems are optional
and you do not need to submit
the lab in order to get credit for it
you just have to finish homework five
we will have homework parties
three to four and seven to eight you can read about them here
in case you want some help solving the homework
there will be no lab parties this week
since the lab questions are all optional
but if you have questions about them go to lab orientation
wednesday we will have instructor office hours and a midterm
announcements for the midterm began at seven pm pacific time
we will release the password on piazza at seven ten pm
and the exam will last one hundred and ten minutes until
nine pm
we will not have discussion tutorials or lecture on wednesday
just some instructor office hours and the midterm
there are no staff office hours wednesday thursday or friday
on friday we will not have instructor office hours because
the topic of the lecture
on the ethical use of data nai
is something that i think we should discuss in the afternoon
so professor fried and i will have instructor ask us anything
from two ten to three pm this will not be recorded
and i hope you come with some interesting questions
they don't have to be about the lecture
although they could be
they could be about anything at all
there will be no exam prep section this friday
since you will have already taken the exam
here are some tips for midterm to prep
there's a practice exam available monday
we're going to have a timed period from eleven to one
or we'll make sure that we're answering your questions on piazza
but we'll also have a version available all the time
in case you have something else to do from eleven to one
but you still want to work through the practice exam
the practice exam is just the questions from
last springs midterm two
but placed into the fall 2020 current semester format
here's a piazza post of lecture q amp a
exam problems that were discussed in the past
we discussed a couple more on friday that i added to the list
and i recommend reading through the midterm two study guide
so that you know what content will be on the exam
midterm to itself we'll start it on wednesday
i emailed you with important
information i hope you read it
here's a link to the piazza post about that
textbook content lecture content
we will have video proctoring where you should record yourself
using zoom or if zoom doesn't work for you
you could record yourself with your phone
you can use any number of pages as scratch paper
and as notes that you create yourself
but if you have electronic notes
then you have to put them in a google doc
and give edit access to csixtona epperc ledu
so that we can check your notes if needed
you can use anything on the course website
but you cannot use the rest of the internet
and you cannot communicate or collaborate with anyone else
even if you find a question that's hard
you still can't text your friend don't do it
what i hope you do do
is review a little bit
and then get a good night's sleep before the exam
if the weather's nice
take a walk and just try to stay relaxed
i know there's a lot of content in midterm too
but if you just read through the questions and answer them
the best you can methodically and diligently without getting
too worried as you go
that tends to be the best way to score well on the exam
but in order to do that you do need some sleep
and you need to try to stay relaxed
i know that's easier to say than to do but i hope it works out
okay here are the links and today we have a very special lecture
in the end of semester student survey
i often ask students what worked well for you in the course
and a lot of people do mention this particular lecture
which is always a video
it's never been a live lecture since i taught this course
and this lecture was part of the course even long before
i taught this course
the lecture is from the eighties
and it shows you a bunch of videos of stuff from the sixties
so it's really old
the main presenter alan kay
invented the first object oriented programming language
called small talk
he and his team at apple
invented many of the features of a modern
pc operating system
and the other folks that he sites invented
a good deal of other things
you know stuff like the window and the mouse
so this is not just a history lesson
this is supposed to inspire you
give you ideas
and give you a sense that what we've been learning about
in this course
programming languages
might have something deeply important to say
about the field of user interfaces
and human computer interaction
okay enjoy
welcome to the distinguished lecture series i'm karen
matthews of university video communications
our program is designed to enrich
graduate and upper division curriculum
with academic
presentations by top computer scientists from industry
its speakers and topics were nominated by computer science
faculty of more than fifty universities
this presentation
responsive by the higher education
marketing group at apple computer
dr allen k a pioneer in computer human interaction
received his
phd in computer science from the university of utah
in 1969
he joined the artificial intelligence project at stanford
and in 1970 became a founding principle
of the xerox parallel to research centre
where he remained for ten years
after xerox he was cheap scientist saratari
since nineteen eighty four
allen has been an apple throttle
with a charity to explore new ideas for apple's future
his track today
is doing with images make symbols communicating with computers
it's our pleasure to introduce dr allen k allen
thank you
this is a talk about the only computer most of us ever see
the one that's acted out on the stage of the screen
called the user interface design
user interface in many ways is a
second state development after
the operating system
because the operating system as we all know was a
layering of software that tried to turn a sometimes
poor disappointly designed machine
into one that was more foodful for the software environment
user interface tries to do the same play it tries to design
a special kind of machine it's very understandable
very efficient
for the person who uses it
without
removing any of the things that the machine could actually do
this talk is too short to include all of the people that
contributed the user interface over the years
i'm just going to pick out
a few that particularly struck me along the way
and illustrated by major examples
so in order to get
started let's go back twenty five years to the
what must be seen like the poison scene age for most
people in universities
today to the dawn of
some very important ideas and first
was the very first personal computer
which you see on the slide here
this is a machine called the link
it was designed at lincoln labs in nineteen sixty
two by wes clark
and is my vote for the first personal computer ever done
you see it has a
display and a keyboard
and has some plenty of little things that look
like that tapes were actually
originally designed for this
machine and one of the
design criteria for this machine was it was supposed to be
small enough on the desk
so that a person could see over it
so one of the ideas that this machine should not be intimidating
and about two thousand of these were built in the sixties
mostly for biomedical technicians who didn't
have a mainframe
to enter disposal
and didn't want to hire programmers to use it
they wanted something if they can build
setup experiments themselves through their own programming
and remarkably
a very large number of the original
two thousand are still in use
today twenty five years later
the reason is that among other things
nervous systems and animals
haven't sped up in those years and
so a computer that worked very well back
then for doing neurological experiments works very well today
somebody else was happening at lincoln labs in 1962
and that was the invention of computer graphics
ivan's local and sketch pad
probably the most significant single thesis ever done
remarkable program in many ways even today as we'll see
by looking at this tape
this tape is from the very first movie
from the very first movie
of sketchkad taken in the summer
of nineteen sixty two so this is twenty five years old
rubber bands you're familiar with but look at what he's doing
he's pointing at the edges and saying
i want them to be all mutually perpendicular
and sketchbad just figured out how to do that
sketchbad is the first system to ever have a window
he's actually drawing on a virtual sheet of paper
about a third of a mile on his side
again to get something he wants he simply sketches it in roughly
and then gives rules like be parallel
and perpendicular
and sketchbad figures out and solves the problems
here the rule is coloniarity
so that the dash is right directly over the guidelines below
skepta was able to solve very complicated problems in real time
involving both linear and non linear systems of constraints
so was the first non procedural programming system
and considerably more powerful in the spreadsheets of today
so it's made a hole in the flange
continuously zooms back
now he wants to make a rivet
and again we see why it's called sketch pad
he just draws a rough shape
uses the center of the crossbar there
as the center of the arc
and then points to the edges
and says i want these to be usually perpendicular again
solving that forces the crossbar to change
which forces the arc to change
which gives you a perfectly symmetrical rivet
and he shows that how no matter how you distort it
when he turns the problem solver on
it will come up with a symmetrical solution
and he could have made it more complicated
he could have constrained
the side lengths to be ratios of each other
or tied some other drawing in the
environment
another important idea seen here for practically the first time
is that of master drawings and instances
is working on a master drawing
and what he has here now is an instance of that
the instance can be rotated and scaled in position
so he's going to insert the river
in the whole by the way
the sketch dad was the first system in which it was
definitely
discovered that the light pen is a very bad input device
it's the blood runs out of your hand in about twenty seconds
and leaves at num
and in spite of that
it's been re embedded at least ninety times in the last
twenty five years
here's another instance of the rivet another one
the display is jumping around like that because this
they didn't even really have computer displays back
then the th two is putting up every
got by brute force
he didn't like the clasping so so he goes to the master drawing
makes them transparent
rolling behold received dynamically
that the rivets the instance rivets have felt that change
so sketchpad is also the first object oriented software system
i want to ask ivan sublim how could you possibly have
done the first
interactive graphics program
the first non procedural programming language
the first object oriented software system all in one year
he said well i didn't know it was hard
nothing like this before
and here is showing that every instance
that you make of something
every master can create instances
so he's making a bunch of copies of the hold
in the flange
i'd like to tell you where you could go to bias system
as good as stitch bed
but i don't know where
because there isn't anything like it even on the market today
twenty five years later
it was a one of a kind
thing it ran on a machine much larger
than the studio that i'm recording the talk on
that was the last computer large enough to have its own roof
in the united states
that mammoth machine had all four hundred and six decaded bites
and executed about four hundred
thousand instructions for second
was meant that this machine
a super computer of twenty five years ago
was about the size of a 520k macintosh
so what you saw
there on the screen
could be done on any of the desktop computers today
but nobody is doing it something we should think about just walk
now moving ahead just a couple of years we see another
pioneer douglas angle bart
the fellow invented the mouse the black on white display
and the first person to successfully
implement hypertext
something that everybody is talking about today
and he did something else that was almost obscene
even by today's sanders he actually went and studied his users
so he would poke around people's offices and see the way
people actually
worked in offices
and he discovered something funny that even after
sixteen years of schooling
that people wouldn't sit hunched over their desk
the way they'd been taught
think of it from tremendous failure and american education
sixteen years of
being taught to sit hunched over a desk
and people would still scoot around their office
chairs and put their feet up in their desk
and so forth and anglebart said well
why the heck
should we make people hunch over their desk and use
their personal computers
why not build something into the in this case
it's a lap board that's built into the arm of the chair
that says the person
moves around the room
and does all the things they're used to doing with their chair
he is able to also use his computer and navigation equipment
here's an example of
engelbart's system
as of about twenty years ago in a live demonstration
from san francisco
he is sitting in san francisco
in an auditorium with about three thousand people
and his group
and the machines
and the rest of the paraphernalia are in menlo park
about thirty five miles away
program luck
when you describe it it's quickly true prizeable by saying
if in your office
the us natural worker were supplied with a computer display
responsible
responsive
anthony response the daily action you have
how much value could you drive and lap
for this
basically paradise is what we've been pursuing for many years
in what we call you all about the pima collect research center
and senator research substitute
so look what else we can do here
i've got this fly out of structure
if i want to see what's in there
i can walk down
这是五百四百
死咗所有猪
我立即存在
capabilities just like my head start from work
and there's a real i seem to have to go
to the took a couple of materials
and that's like plenty of forgiveness
but if i don't know
i can say the library what am i supposed to pick up the air
after just point to laugh
the whole i see over new books
while there is a statement fairly
goodbye
all i do
is
such as i can show you
i can do things of my world just say as i definitely change
i will sit and pretend
they're all a couple of rappers i've tried to look
and they're changing the job
and so
they can fit it
they do it in all the sweet number
so weighs are studying over
making different views
moving around one of the specified points
and
modifying the structure
the same time i see the back of the repertoire location
knock off back here
replace the gel in the key
slime entertains of all
sorts that i can say i want to do operations on
this basic structure like move over
and study a bit of contractor
it's the essence of
the two you have a lot of materials and that's where the detail
the characters show me
the different views
of pines of which i can
add
with the singles folks
and each of those will be something to me
connect with larger protector patterns toss the gadget
for critical abbreviation for changing the engine
so i could say i am to go to produce
for the problems that you did and i say my grand charming and uh
let me up just apple
i see it oh i could say i'd like to see what my own
i can see so this
ways i move around the way i get feedback up here
with the way i
use both support me and tell them
to do what can i do what's
your middle sign
哦
i don't like the bill
and i don't question the homies right now so i have to
ask for somebody that i can do it part of it
i'd like to like the bill
and uh i don't want to go home so right now so i have to
pass for somebody to connect me to it hardly hardly
so bill will you come in feeders in the comment
hello diamond hi
i i used to know what turned on your own bill her day
is okay i might have him see my text
so the special certified like the third vehicle switching
which
over so this display you sees my texts are executed
sir off the dust
but what's that right round
while he took in my desk he liked something to say about it
so we put on a marker
of traffic spot that he
controls so he says that metal clock look into his text
the point to it
that we currently deserve for me to like to control
operate on this
some hybrids or power for the church
but we can have an
so alright so uh in case you haven't the most deal
setting up the collaboration here
so that we can go on integration a triple
we set up our audio company
and we're both
looking at the same display and that be very heavy to work
we can talk to each
other point
and maybe they like to add
you the chalk on the splat board like sex where you control it
from the status smoke out
you've had another feature that hybridizes
the kind of display we have
i'd like to see you by working on so
before i can do that
i'm happy to set up my display a surf white
set it up sort of i see a folder like that
the corner up there said
half the video automatic switching to the brain in the camera
picture camera modern office console
such as the camera out of my mind
five built
that's great now we're connected to the audio
i can see my water general analysis in your face on the top
so let's do some collaborating
so anglebard had a complete vision
of what this was going to be like years before
all of the rest of us
the vision included not just
some of the ideas about how people were going to react
and interact with the machine but also that
since people aren't natural born hermits in factor
all really communications junkies
inglebart realize it
any kind of user interface design must include
a person to person collaboration
through the medium of the machine
and so as the very first
set of ideas that they had it wasn't just
how you organized your information in
forms of interventional hypertext
but how you can share it
how you could do something much more than electronic mail
but be able to do direct uh
contact sharing the information be able to point
be able to talk to each other and be able to see each other
we might compare that with a very fragmentary
vision of the current day micro industry
which is just struggling over decades
to try and reach the vision that angle bart
had almost in a complete form
as early as nineteen sixty two
another thing that's interesting if we look at the
the set up here of the mouse in one hand
regular keyboard
in the center and a five finger keyboard on the left hand
we see something it was a very good idea
and we may have noticed something it was also a bad idea
the very good idea
anglebart realize that
you really didn't want to spend
most of your time going back
and forth between the regular keyboard and the mouse
you have to find the mouse
you have to find the keyboard and so forth instead
anglebart wanted to set it up
so that you would spend a relatively belong period of time
in either of those two ways of doing things
you know you'd be typing a paragraph of text
or you'd be doing lots of navigation and fixing
single character
errors and stuff
and so the fight
for your keyboard working with the three button mouse
is a way of
doing all the things that you could do with the keyboards
and you could stay for a very long time and never
touch the regular keyboard
and then the thing that they missed
and they want partially missed it
because of the inaccuracy of the analog
mouse was the
what we call boatless interaction
where you indicate the object first and then give the command
because the mouse was inaccurate what they would do in
the command
instead of just putting something like a word or a character
or a paragraph
and then saying something like move
or going to some drag icon they would have to go and say
move word
then wait for a mouse click to indicate which word
and by what you said to move like move word
move character
move paragraph the program would know how fine
to try and interpret the mouse coordinates have got
then after it had picked the object he
then had to do a command except
so in order to move something you had to do
four separate actions
which is quite inefficient
even though we'd already set up a more inefficient scheme
than we used today for action
using the tools
kind of interesting paradox that sort of the way
it does
now a few years later
nineteen sixty seven nine period
this is the first personal computer that i worked on
called the flex machine
did it with ed cheeto
and this is a picture of it on its own display
so by that time we'd realized that we can build a
desktop computer and of course
this was a desktop computer for only
very special kinds of debts like those made out of steel
it weighed well over a hundred pounds
and had two characteristics that were very noticeable
one of them was it was a tremendous talking war
now these little black dual inline packages that hold silicon
the macintosh has about fifty of them
or so that makes up a macintosh back
then you're lucky if you get eight or sixteen gates
in one of these
dip packages and
so this machine had about seven hundred of those
and generated enormous amount of heat
and had a fan that was likened to a seven forty seven
taking off
the other thing that was very noticeable about the machine
is that the user interface tended
to repel most of the people
that we tried about it
i was a designer of that interface and i was really
pressed fallen
that
people regarded it somewhat the way
you would if you lifted the lid on a garbage
can and saw something moistened pleasant
down inside
very puzzled is how could we put all this working machine we
had a very powerful interactive object oriented language
that i had derived from similar
graphic very high quality graphics
i could head one of the very first
gadgets called the flipping divider
done at the same time as ivan sutherland
in harvard and then later brought out to utah
had a very large virtual screen that you could map
onto the physical screen
had multiple windowing
not overlapping windowing because it was a calligraphic display
lots of good stuff and yet
it didn't fly with the people that we tried it with
and
one of the insights as to why this was and what to do
about it came from early contact at nineteen sixty eight
with seymour paparaz logo work at rip school in flexington nas
the whole idea of children being able
to program on a device that up to now
had been in what is called the glass house and industry
that big room with air conditioning
and raised floor and so forth
a whole idea
that this could be extended down to the world of a trial
just changed my whole conception
about what it was
i went from thinking of it
as did angerbart as some sort of super vehicle
something
akin to a car as compared to ibm's pennsylvania railroad
went from it making it as that to something much simpler
i thought of it now as media
because cars we would hold from children until we're eighteen
though i don't know why it's when they're most dangerous
but we still nonetheless think of
waiting until they're eighteen media we never think that way
paper and pencil we want children to start using
from the time they can grab the trade on
and so this work of patricks was critical
in our understanding of what was going on
nothing was going on
that lincoln labs was the first iconic program
was done at rand corporation
people who did the wonderful interactive programming language
josh was done
for economists and other
non computer specialists that rand who had to compute
and one of their complaints about
really their only complaint about jos was
he said hey
none of us can type can't you do something about that
so that led to the
invention of the first
data tablet is called grand tablet back then and this system
from about nineteen sixty eight
called braill for graphical input language
this list of processes takes us back to the top more slow
where we expect to head at the slow dog keyboard whatsoever
first we erase the flow arrow
then move the connector out of the way
so that we may draw our box in its place
recognize he wants one of the box and made one
cows recognizing his hand trimming
the box is slightly too lost change the size of the window
here's where macintosh window control came from literally
then draw a sluttle from the connecting to the box
attaching decision element to the box
and draw it flow from it to stay
most of every command is not just iconic but also analogic
but that i mean
that it looks like the thing that you want
so if you want to scrub something out
you scrub it out if you want to draw box
you just draw box
it recognizes you once one makes one the safe size
chop off the corner
you want characters you just make characters
and recognizes those there are no menus to reach through
you're always looking
directly at where you're working
notice it missed the end at the end of subscan there
he saw he hesitated
the world's first modeless system
so he's able to just go and change it without issuing any more
command
you see every command that's actually been issued
and they're all in the form of direct action
what a remarkable system
that was and when i saw that
i felt and used it for a half an hour in 1968
i felt like i was sticking my hands right through the display
and actually touching the information structures directly
this is the first system i'd ever use
and practically the only one sense that i'd call truly intimate
it was this degree of intimacy
it was so important in the user interface
i used to show this movie to my group at xerox park
every three months or so so
we wouldn't forget what we're trying to do
another thing that we saw
in nineteen sixty eight was tiny one inch square
first flat panel display done at the university of illinois
and we realized it was only gonna be a matter of years
until you could put all of the
electronics that we had in the flex machine
on the back of a flat panel display
you would have something like this
which i later came to call a dina book
back in nineteen sixty eight when i made this cardboard model
i just thought of it as the machine of the future
and started thinking about what would it be like
for millions of people
to have one of these machines
and so the metaphor
became the pencil
what would it be like to have something like this as
extent in the world as pencil and paper
could people actually use it
the answer in 1968 and the early nineteen seventies was no
so one of the ways
i started thinking about answering the question
is since we've failed at
designing for adults
i remembered a wonderful phrase of marginal cluelands he said
the
i don't know who discovered water but it wasn't a fish
the idea is if you're immersed in a context
you can't even see it
so we decided to follow a seymour patrick's lead
and instead of trying to
design for adults we would try and see what this
nine book of the future would be like for children
and then maybe hope
that some of it might go over into the adult world
so children were an absolutely critical factor here
and
the first stuff i did in my notebook
in nineteen seventy was called kitty top
and here's what it first looked like
it's going to be built out of a sony tummy chinatron
men xerox park came along with some wonderful
almost open charter funding
and a very interesting culture these are the being bags that
we're so famous
at park and whether reasons we use them we discovered
it was impossible to lead to your heat to denounce somebody
once you sat on the beanbag show
because you tended to sink
into it further and further
so i had a way of relaxing people and was very good for design
then we started experimenting so we built this machine
which was a very very high resolution
way of displaying video images
and first fruits of that was this font editor
first font editor done by ben laws
and all of a sudden you could get images like this
that it was quite possible to mimic
the high quality printing images on a bitmap display
we got very interested in that
trying some of these ideas out on children
discover they didn't always like their might zoom in on that
they didn't always like to have their
rough drafts look like
they've been printed by the new york times
so some of the children said well
what we really would like to have for rough drafts
is our own handwriting
so they used the sponsor and put in their own handwriting
and that was a way of
instantly telling when you looked at a document
just how finished it was intended to do
and the bit map display also allowed us to do
stitching and drawing as well as chris computer graphics
again one of the things that had not been possible before
is doing real design on a computer
before people always designed on the back of an envelope
then brought the back of the computer
as a way to render it
but here what we'd hoped for is
that people would actually stay with the computer
for the better part of the dead
and we put a lot of effort
to keep making this display
be somebody you would look at for six or seven hours without
ice train
next envisionment of this
was a little system called minicom
this was the summer of nineteen seventy one
and we went to a considerable
direction in
thinking about making this
and then
we also did some
dynamic animations we'll see in a minute space war had a very
important part
in the design of things because it was a conceptually simple
precursor of all the video games we know today
it should be something that a child could write for himself
we started working on small talk and object oriented language
based on
simula but also with a lot of look back to what sketch pad
then all of this led to the alto computer
built mostly by chuck backer at xerox park
the first workstation and
led through all of the subsequent workstations
and it also led directly to the
liza and the macintosh at apple
we used a improved version of inglebart's mouse
and in its early stages we call it the interim diner book
we brought lots of children into park to work on these machines
and then we took the machines down into the palo alto schools
working with several hundred children in all
here we are jordan junior high school
around nineteen seventy six
now let's take a look at
animated versions of some of the things that ran on
this machine and some of the things that the children did
so here's the famous dining book
model and back then we wanted it to be like the
health pack calculator except to be a real live computer
this is the inspiration for all that we are thinking about
is what it was going to be like
here's ben laws font editor
being used to make an a and lydian cursive
most of these are taken from
home movies we shot with sixteen millimeter bullocks
here's the painting program
this is something i
designed in the summer of nineteen seventy two
and steve percell
implemented it here you see some
hand character recognition and recognize the letter c
for as a command for drawing circles
that was put in by john shocked
we're experimenting with this at the time here's an l
for drawing lines
one of the nice things about hand character
recognition is that you don't have to move very far
to hit something here's a d for drawing
the idea of actually being able to fashion your brushes
right in the
the combination of canvas and pallet itself
was something that percell thought up i think
the idea of
having charcoal and airbrush effects of something it was also
added at the very beginning of this
and you get some charcoal effects
here's some experiments with very first
experiments with windows
dragging them around by one corner
opening their size of the other corner just like on the map
today
making another one by going up to the upper right hand corner
typing something in it
clicking the stuff that's inside
i think this is the very first
actual test of
course we knew windows are going to work
because there have been examples of windows before
this is the very first test of them on a bit napped
display and some experiments with the user interface
what the night you like to just manipulate them
here is one of the very first group of kids i can tell that
because there aren't even
display covers on the display
we had to put in old cardboard boxes to keep the kids from
getting electrocuted
this is a group of i think sixth graders
fifth or sixth graders this is a del dolberg
who later went on to head the group after i left part
and she was responsible for many of the ideas in
teaching the children
we first did logo like things in small talk
such as this program
we also experimented with animated windows
here's the very first test of an animated window
which we later abandoned
because the machine wasn't quite fast enough
but it's so good it's nice you're what i'm doing
where instead of getting a
just an open frame that moves you actually animate
all the text itself and have it equipped window
this is the alto screen in
early nineteen seventy three
not long after the alto had first started to work
the auto is actually a very powerful
computer
if you could get to its microcode directly you could
and the although is able to animate
about a hundred and twenty square
inches of graphics and multiple plains
so you can do very complex
two and a half b animatics and effects this is
something done by purcell hit
around the end of nineteen seventy three
that was really the machine
we thought we had
was a machine that you took animate everything
on it
tying all that stuff together with small tie
we got a number of interesting
things with the kids here is one of the
second level classes this was a
thirteen year old each and twelve year olds
marianne had done
one of the very first tours in small talk the year before
when she had learned it
and she was a very outgoing ebulliant
young lady and she wanted to teach a class
so we brought in
we had five machines at the time
so we just had five children and we videotaped
all of the one hundred hours of it
here's an example
this is from nineteen seventy five
of a program that looks very much like mac draw
it's an object oriented graphics illustrator
you can select by means of selection handles
you can change colors
you can change the size
so the menu is being used on the lower right hand
there and the
feedback is coming in the window in the center
the only thing that's
really interesting about this program is
besides that it was done in nineteen seventy five
which was before you can buy it into stores was to actually
conceived
designed and implemented by a twelve year old girl
after only a few months of programming in small talk
i took her about two weeks
to do this and the
size of the programming small talk
seventy two was about a page long
so
part of our aim
here was not just to get people to be able to access things
by means of the windows
but also be able to do the equivalent of writing
short essence and having them
take have great effect
one of the things that is disturbingly true
about most novices on computers is that
about two pages of program is the maximum that i can handle
i like to be able to spread it out
and use their visual field as an extension of their
shortcom member
here's another example
a fifteen year old boy
again after a few months of programming in small talk
seventy two
he was interested in ham radio
but really
had gotten bored
with the pdd m drawing radio diagram
so he decided to make himself a ham radio illustrator
it has some quite sophisticated features you see here a
pop up menu
with often use things like open and close dots
and it has a more extensive menu
of iconic shapes
for the circuits down below so you can pick up a
battered assembled and rotated and
but again this is also done in nineteen seventy five
and it's one of my favorite programs done by a child
because less than ten years before this
a phd had been awarded for a system that wasn't was good
this program is about eighty lines in code law
in the small top seven and two
next we have a
program done by adults
but for the most part
who had never programmed before
they were professional animators that came to park
in the summer of 74
and the thing that animators would like to do is to see what
their animated animations gonna work before
they have to go to film
so that summer they devised
a variety of systems
and this is what every animator would like to do
is draw the picture
reach over into the movie window grab the thing you just draw
and show it what to do
have it play back
now of course
it's not squishing when it hit
so it doesn't look like real
so he wants to go to the steps there in the iconic menu
and when it gets down to the bottom here what is going to do
is replace that
with a fresh drawing
that's going to come from
another transparent cell letting overlays
in the drawing windows on the
right hand side
so the
drawing windows can have several transparent cells overlaid
each other uses the old one for registration purposes
so he's now drawing on another
cell and that drawing will be inserted into the animation
as the animation goes
and now the animators will see
how much detail he has to put into that
squash drawing before
we see it as actually squash
and the obviously has to at least put in the
specular reflection
on the ball
there he goes now we see it as a declamation
even though it's a one twenty change
my program is about five pages long
which is longer than children can actually do
but here's a twelve year old girl
it was very interested in forces
and so you spend some time
getting the correct gate and animating a first
across the screen
then she wanted to feature that the adult animators had put in
and that was to be able to combine
two animations into a single one
so she has the force animation going over there
and here she has a jockey animation
and she wants to be able to pick it up
and in the active actually combining she wants to
vow to fuse into one drawing this is a feature
that she was able to put in herself
because even though
she wasn't capable of writing a five page program
like the adults
she was quite capable of reading it and making it changingly
and here's the the finishing animation
now what we've just seen
are some things that are familiar to us now in this
day of the micro computer
we've also seen some things that people aren't yet doing
people don't usually sit down and do
for themselves a complete tool
i can illustrate the go to the switch store
and spend several hundreds of dollars
and yet here we see
twelve year old children
coming up with the idea and being able to implement it
and not only being able to implement it
but being able to implement it is a very compact form
why is that and why is it such an important part
of computer literacy
i think literacy has three important parts to it
there's an access part
and in the print medium we call that reading
somebody else makes up the material that we have the skills
to penetrate that material and understand it
access literacy
second one is creative literacy
we don't think a person is literally if all i can do is read
we think they should be able to like
and the english language is powerful enough and it's metaphor
that we can do
very strong expressions of our own intent in just a pager today
and start a revolution with two pages at well attached
programming languages
just haven't been strong enough and easy enough to understand
but if we're ever to have computer literacy
it is going to have to have those two things
as
first order
attributes then the third thing
in computer literacy to set for anything
that we can be literated in
there is a literature
so when we read shakespeare
we have to read shakespeare
with a completely different approach
to the genre of the elizabethan
age than we do from reading the constellant
so throughout the many centuries in
which the legal language has existed there are
different genre that we have to be over adapted
that's the third form of literacy is genre
and then the third thing
in computer literacy is that for anything
that we can be literated in
there is a literature
so when we read shakespeare
we have to read shakespeare
with a completely different approach
to the genre of the elizabethan
age than we do from reading mickey splang
so throughout the many centuries in
which the english language has existed there are
different genre that we have to be able to adapt to
and that's the third form of literacy is genre literacy
i'm going to in this talk
i'm concentrating mostly on the first two
now i want to go and focus
on why this stuff works
and how we came to some of these design decisions of course
some of it was just half hazard and random some of it
we rationalized after the fact
but some of it
we actually thought it through
and were able to use stuff that had been done before
so give you an idea of how
difficult it is to
understand how the mind works let's take a look at
this slide and see if we can see what's wrong with it
if you look at it for a while
you'll see that the mouth is somehow upside down
and maybe the eyes something wrong with the eyes
maybe they're upside down too
if i were teaching in a school
and trying to teach you about what had been done with this slide
i would say in english sentence like the following i'd say well
here we've taken a slide of a young girl
extracted her eyes and mouth
and put them back in with an airbrush
and then turn the entire slide upside down
that's an english sense and now
that i said that you can understand everything about
what it looks like when i turn it right side up
i've given this
talk many times and i'm gonna have to move it back
because i've discovered nobody will listen to me when that
slide is on
and from many times
i've given the talk i know that there were gasps
in the classroom when you saw that picture
because you weren't prepared for it
even though i told you everything about what had been done to it
perceptual psychologists really love
when something like this happens
because it means that information going in through one channel
the auditory channel to your language crossing centers
elicited one kind of response to my sentence
and when you saw the actual picture through your visual channel
it elicited a completely different response
and this is actually understood
physiologically as well as psychologically
on the under right hand side of your brain
where you do face recognition
there are two pieces of brain tissue about an inch apart
one of them is an expert at faces
it's a thing that allows you to see faces and clouds
the thing that scares children and twilight
they see menacing shadows
and it's reporting right now i see an upside down face
like that
that about an inch away
is another piece of brain tissue
that's an expert in eisen mouth and eyes and mouth only
let's say well
that's a good looking mouth and those are okay eyes
there's very little dissonance
between the reports of these two separate pieces of brain tissue
now when i go to this
right side up version of the thing
the face recognition guy is saying well
that's a right side up face like thing
and the eyes and math guys
saying something is terribly wrong here
you can imagine why
nature might have arranged for you to be startled
seeing a face like this up
close might mean you're going to die in the next ten seconds
and a fact it is built into all mammals
something that we don't learn
but is in the mammalia nervous system
so if you try this on a dog
i suggest you pick a small one
so the basic idea here is that
we don't what we think of as the unitary i
the unitary highness of i myself and me
is really a multiple
set of different mentalities
that apparently came
about during different evolutionary periods
the mentalities fake differently
they don't communicate very well with each other
they're often in conflict and only a few of them talk
so we're only aware of a few of them in our
what we call our consciousness
most of what the other mentalities do we call our subconscious
but relegating everything to the subconscious is
almost akin to mysticism
and in fact there's a lot more to be learned about this area
and we got interested in three of these mentalities
first from the work of
john pajay
and pajay said that the
he thought children
and adults have a unitary
mentality that goes through stages as the child mature so
pha said first there is a doing stage
where the
hole is to dig it and an object is to grab it
thinking is action in that stage
child doesn't think ahead
doesn't imagine the consequences of his action he just does
later on is the image stage
child of five or six or seven
who
for instance
when given a squat glass poured into a tall thin glass
will say there's more water in the tall thin glass
i think everybody is familiar
with the with that experiment of phjs
it's because the child is being dominated by the visual image
the looks like there's more water there and so the visual logic
says that there is
and then around eleven or twelve
pja says that the child goes to a facts and logic stage
away from the immediacy of the visual environment
or at least in swiss french children
who eleven and twelve they are less
less evidence that american children
ever get into the facts and logic stage
now
when we looked at pha's theory
it was interesting
what it seemed to say is if the child is below the age of five
say you should only do muscular things and if the child is in
this age between say roughly five and eleven
that you should do mostly visual things and
than above that you should do sort of symbolic things
it just didn't come through with any ideas for us
but while reading about pha we had found the work of brunner
who was the american psychologist
who
was one of the persons to bring psj to the american
public's attention and burner had a more interesting theory
and it came about from experiments that he did to confirm
what psa was talking about so blinner
did the experiment
took the water in the squat class
and pointed into the tall thin one
the child said yes
there's more water in the tall thin glass
and then blinner did something that psa hadn't thought to do
brinner then covered up the glass
and the child said oh
but wait there must be the same amount of water
because where would it go
and then bruner revealed the tall thing glass
and the child said oh
wait no look there's more water
bruner covered it up again and the child said oh
there must be the same amount of water because where would it go
so if you have any nine year olds you'd like to torment
this is a good way to do it because what blenner was doing was
jumping the child
not from this mentality back to a previous stage
but he was showing as he did in many experiments
the existence of multiple mentalities
so the child was normally
visually dominant here but if you included the visual field
then this fledgling
symbolic mentality that was really going to be switched on
in a stronger way later on could actually work
and from this we got a lot of ideas
it suggested that there are ways of using some of these other
mentalities
and we got some confirmation from some interesting work
in the literature of creativity
one of them was by jacques hadamar
the famous french mathematician
who in the late stages of his life decided to pull his ninety
nine buddies the other
who made up together
the one
hundred great mathematicians and physicists on the earth
and he asked them how do you do your thing
and they're all personal friends of his
so they wrote back depositions and
only a few out of the hundred
claim to use mathematical symbology at all
there's quite a surprise all of them
said they did it mostly in
imagery or figurative terms
and an amazing thirty percent or so
including einstein were down here in the mud pies
einstein's definition
said i have sensations of a kinesthetic or muscular type
einstein could feel
the abstract spaces
he was dealing with in the muscles of his arms and his fingers
so one way of interpreting hadomard's diagram here
is the genius is the ability to recapture childhood it will
the sort of the pejetting and way of looking at it
but a stronger way is to look at it through bruner's eyes
and see that what is actually going on is that these
very creative people are somehow
able to be in contact
with other mentalities that are going on all the time
this is a better way of thinking about this than
simply splitting things
up into conscious
and subconscious
or right brain and left brain
this notion that there are each one of these things
evolved for a different reason
and can do different kinds of logics are very important
and we'll see why in a second now
i'm going to give you a the most graphic demonstration i know
of this principle in action of what it means to
actually be able to teach directly
to the mentality that's going to learn
rather than trying to teach through an inappropriate channel
you see the sad part of hatamari's diagram
is that every child in the united states
is taught math and physics through this channel
the channel that no almost no adult
creative mathematician and physicists
uses to do it
and that is really a shame they use this channel to communicate
but not to do their thing
and much of our education is
founded on those principles
that just because we can talk about something
there is a naive belief that we can teach through
talking and listening
this example i'm going to show is taken from a television show
in 1975 on harry reasoners
television show in
on abc and he had read a book that apparently upset him
called the inner game of tennis
which basically
said almost
anybody can learn to play a decent game of tennis in just a
single afternoon
if you don't try too hard
and that had made him wonder
because he'd been trying to play tennis for many years
and so he sent
an abc new squad out to california to expose the charlatan
and what they did was to round up
a number of people and get them to
sign legal affidavits
saying that they had
that they had never played tennis before
they took them all out in the court and picked the worst
one who happened to be a
fifty five year old lady forty pounds overweight
five foot two and a mumu
and she had the moo mo
because her deposition said that not only had she
never played tennis but she not even exercise in twenty years
so taking a while on the court
turning on the live tv cameras they set a clock
and said to tim galway
you have twenty minutes to teach her how to play tennis now
let's look at this
from the standpoint of user interface design
because in every way
tim galway is the user interface
of
this interactive teaching situation we have
and let's see what he actually does
i'm gonna have tim hit some ball sound
and as the ball
flies through the air i want you just to watch it
in a very instant the ball hit the court
i want you to say bout
and the very instant the ball hits the racket
i want you to say hit
just became bounce
hip all you need to do is watch the ball okay
bounce the key of all the exercises in the inner game
is to focus the mind's attention somewhere
where will not interfere
with the body's ability to hit the ball automatically
you stand here
and tim will throw you a
couple and you just continue doing the same thing
trying to hit it not at first at first just say bounce
when the ball bounces and hit when you would hit it
but don't hit then after
you feel like they didn't go ahead and hit it
now you might watch your right arm here
something's trying to hit that ball
even though she was told that she didn't have to
now she actually try she misses
he says bounce he's also out of the corner of his eye
watching me hit the ball
so even though he's not
trying to see how i hit it
the image of me hitting it is going right into his memory
enjoying yourself yeah really fact you like that okay here we go
the cardinal principle in any
book written on tennis about tennis is to watch the ball
no tennis play really sees the ball
and the reason is they get bored so i tried to
uh give him something to see in the ball that's interesting
so we watch the trajectory of the ball
they're the gracefulness of the line
made by the balls that fly through the air
the hallway is the same
put the mind somewhere where it can stay calm
and not get you up tight
but relax and interested then the body
does so beautifully so beautiful
i might start listening to the ball
molly listen to our sounds on your racket
hear that yes
hear that
one that sound like very dull it was like wood
a wood song
people listening and you'll hear the sound that you like
pretty soon
just listen good
okay now listen on this side
have a girl
okay now be aware that racket is part of your arm
and this just feel it
let's try so hard more than halfers
that's it it was comfortable molly
every time i did start to think things went wrong
they just stop thinking when the body seems to know what to do
can you feel with your left hand where it is
how to go just wait in the back there feel this
okay
now i'll tell you what molly
we're gonna do one other stroke now
and this one's called the surf
and the serve is just like a dance
you just like a dance we'll come back here and
i'll show you how to do a dance
call the serve
okay
and i've done this dance a little bit so i'll just do it
in fact you can start humming if you want
the rhythm like this
okay now what you do what's your stand there
shut your eyes
shut your eyes and imagine yourself doing that same dance
might start humming a little bit
as you're doing it yeah
okay now what i want to do is no thinking disco do it quick
no thinking disco serve yeah
sir
fine don't worry about missing keep serving keeps don't think
go do do do quick that's just
fine again don't worry about hitting that
out loud let's hear it out loud
there you go i get them to hum
the rhythm of my serve
so they're not thinking oh
this is what he's doing with the delbo
this is what he's doing his hands
out loud the river
there you go i get them the hum
the rhythm of my serve
so they're not thinking oh
this is what he's doing with his help oh
this is what he's doing with his hands
they're not trying to remember all that
they start humming and they see themselves doing very similar
things muscular movements to what i did
but they're not thinking about it
so it just comes out naturally and fluidly
that didn't take long
that's called serving
好好
don't mess
it
okay that's your first point in tenant
scored fifteen love fantastic
okay mom
no need for you to admit
all of a sudden everything became effortless
just i was just sort of like floating along you know and doing
what came naturally
you know and i said ah
playing tennis
it's really really beautiful
have a clear idea of what you want
then let it happen don't try too hard
i'm gonna try to make you miss molly
because it's going on too long
so i'll just
get a little bit harder
you just keep watching the ball
keep watching it
don't be distracted keep on that ball
well when i saw that
i said something akin to holy cow
so i just seen something that i wouldn't believe possible
and i realized that it applied very strongly
to use your interface design that something
really important
had been was going on here so i got tim galway's book
the intergame of tennis and i read it
and a number of things that he said really stuck in my mind
first one was almost a cliche
he said learning happens when attention is focused
but he was able to get something out of that
because if you don't have a good theory of learning
then you can still get it to happen
by just helping the person
focus one of the ways you can help a person focus
is by removing interference
and a lot of what you saw in that tape was a way of
holding focus of the mentality that
actually had to learn to play the tennis
and removing interference from the mentality that likes to talk
and make comments
another thing that tim said that
particularly stuck in my mind was
said the problem with most theories of teaching
is that the parts of the body you want to have learned
don't understand english
so the part of your
mentality that understands english doesn't play tennis
can't play tennis
can't do mathematics it can't do music
what it can do is talk and comment
and so in general for learning most things it is
good to find a way of short circuiting
that mentality that we think of is the eye
that always tries to take over
and finally kim made a very interesting observation
and that is that the problem with being a beginner
is that you get a lot of practice in staying a beginner
so a beginning tennis player
most of the time is does chase the ball
they get to be really good at chasing the ball
but all other forms of tennis involve hitting the ball
so it's very important for tim to find a way of
catapulting anybody learning tennis like molly there
out of the chaser ball
stage and instantly get into hitting the ball stage
so you had to find a way of getting a person
who would never pick up a tennis racket
before to be able to hit the ball
ninety eight percent of the time they swung at it
we realized that was an incredibly important principle
for user interface design
why spent two weeks trying to read an ms dos
manual to see how to copy a file
or open up in application why do any of those things
what do you get from it
much better to find a way of
designing the user interface
so that the person who uses it
acts like an intermediate from the first
first time that they sit down
and then they get into a process that is rewarding in itself
now these ideas
work beautifully for music
and they also apply in cognitive areas very strongly here's
an example of a programming problem and that is
let's take the logo
turtle and write a program to draw a circle
and we'll do it
with
three ages of people a five year old
a ten year old and a fifteen year old
as representatives from these three
mental mentality dominant areas the body
the visual
and the symbolic now the way you do a get a five year old to
to do a picture to do a circle
there's something that's more paporate learning long ago
and that is you tell the five year old close your eyes
and make a circle with your body
if they had gone part way around
you say well what were you doing
and the five year old says well
i was going a little and turning a little over and over again
if you type that into logo
you get a perfect circle
and that's because the five year old
knows differential equations
because the circle is particularly
simple thing in differential geometry
which is only discovered about a hundred and fifty years ago
by carl gauss
so a circle is that thing that has constant curvature
so the change in curvature is zero
and the trial's
body mentality
doing mentality
understands that kind of geometry
so the five year old comes up with a very simple program that
produces an elegant circle
the ten year old has a harder time
because a ten year old is visual
and really wants to look at things
he doesn't want to do things with his body
so much anymore
and so he wants to draw circles with a compass
and after a while
he'll see that
by drawing lots of circles
you'll see that the main thing
about drawing circles with the compass
is that the points on
the rim were always the same distance from the center
so his turtle program picks the pen up
starting in the center
jumps out to the rim goes one hundred there
puts the pen down makes a mark
picks the pen up backs to the center
turns one degree and does that over and over again
so it's chugga chugga chugga chugga
chugga chug and you get a perfect circle
much harder way of doing it but still a good circle
of course
i wouldn't be telling this story if the fifteen year old
were able to get a circle at all
because like most adults
he's in the facts and logic stage
and he knows the most horrible fact
thought up by the mind of man
which is x squared plus
y squared equals are squared
a very bad coordinate system
and even if it were a good coordinate system
it has very little operational significance
so here we see an example of
just concentrating on different mentalities in people's skulls
getting vastly different
results in doing the program and surprisingly
the age levels that are supposed to do less well
actually do better
this led to a slogan i made up
which is the point of view is worth adiq points
so in other words if you're in sixty bc and wrong
trying to multiply iq numbers together
you had to be a genius
to be able to remember
all the partial products that no roman numerals generated
during thirteen hundred ad wondering where mars is going to go
you had to be a genius to be able to figure out all of the
polymaic epicycles
so it's not logic
that is powerful
logic is actually
a weak method because it depends on fragile chains of inference
and people have used logic throughout history
but mostly inappropriate context
there was nothing illogical
about the way the alchemists or the babylonians did things
it was that they were in a context in which
their logic couldn't do much
so this notion that the context is powerful
and if you want to
be able to be good at solving problem and acting
much smarter than you are
then you have to find a context that is going to do most of the
thinking for you
most computer scientists know this
because it goes under another hitting of call
choose the appropriate
data structure before you start tinkering
around with the algorithm
do the right data structure
you will have most of the result
computed almost automatically as part of its inherent structure
all that reminds me of edward de bono's
famous comment about american business
i think it probably applies to american university is also
he said the problem with american business is
when it gets in trouble it redoubles
its efforts
and he liken this too
if you have a bunch of people digging for gold in a certain spot
they get down five feet and they don't find any goal one of
the ways
they could do to resolve their problem is to dig twice as hard
and of course if gold is twenty feet over to the side
then they can dig all the way to china without finding it out
the important idea is that problem solving
all of these things have more than one dimension
and a lot of the
important dimensions for doing thinking lie
along the lines of these different mentalities
and that led to another slogan
which said well
g we don't know how to choose between these brunarian
mentalities
the kinesthetic one is very valuable
knows where things are the image one is tremendously valuable
because it gives you a way of picking
things out of a conglomeration very easily
it's quite a bit more efficient to pick an image
from a bulletin board than to pick an item out of a linear list
of symbols and the symbolic one of course is very powerful
given the right context
because it can do inferencing that is not open to these other
mentalities so
we thought that the right slogan would be
well g why can't we find some way of tying these together
the way we did it was to say well
one way of involving the kinesthetic
mentality is to give you something to point with
so we have the mouse they are not just
because it's good to point to the screen occasionally
but because it involves a kinesthetic sense
and the kinesthetic sense is the one that knows where you are
it's the one that locates you in space
not your eyes
your eyes are an extension
of that sense the image one there is for recognition
here's a good experiment you can try some time
get a friend to manipulate cable
television movie channels
go to a random movie and see how many frames it takes before
you can say whether you've seen it before
think what that means you may not have seen this movie
for twelve or fifteen years
and yet after just a few seconds for most people
you can identify that you've seen this movie
and usually be able to remember what comes next
famous experiment by harmon some years ago took
twenty five or thirty people showed them ten thousand images
space ten seconds apart
so it took hours and hours to show them
all these random photographs of things
and even after thirty days
all of the
people in the experiment had better than ninety percent recall
on all of the images so
they could say whether
an image was one of the set with ninety percent
probably they could identify included portions in the image
an unbelievable feat
is performed by this
mentality tremendous for creativity and lots of different ways
and then this one
is the one that allows you to abstract what you've done
concretely there
so all those things should go together
and that was what we tried to do at park
so here's one of the first versions
of this interface and this is done by gan angles
who after i had invented small talk was the person
who did most of the
small talk implementation
and then became the major designer of small talk
and this was a crystallization of a lot of the ideas that
we had all had culminating around
late nineteen seventy five
around nineteen seventy six or so this is what the small talk
user interface
look like we see collapsed windows up here that
when you clicked on them would open back up again
clock multiple
applications and so forth
larry tesler whose now at apple
had this idea this is called galley editor
that documents should be able to have different paragraph types
so you might have a paragraph type of text
you might have a paragraph type that's a picture
and that when you put the mouse into the paragraph
it invoke the editor for what's there
and this is a metaphor that i think is going to overtake the
cut and taste
metaphor that people are used to today because
it's much better
in general to always work in the context of the results
you're trying to get we call the results mode interaction
here's a later version of this principle done by bob flagal
multiple views into the same structure
we're first done in at xerox park
by trigg
v reinscalga visiting professor from norway in our group
and he was particularly interested in scheduling so here is a
schedule versus a gant chart
for looking at the same thing
and you see you selected something here
and the selection shows up here
and it also shows up on this list and it also shows up
down here is a list of names of things
so this idea that
what you're actually looking at
are different views
seen through different filters is something
we originally got from engelbart
but redone in this new form
multiple window user interface
and here's the way the interface looks today in small talk
and
here is just a brief look at what that interface look like about
ten years ago
so what he's doing is actually entering into
sort of like a hyperspace window using a pop up menu there
to get a workspace window
scrolling is on the opposite
side from what you're used to on the macintosh
and you can see that the scroll
arrow is positioned sensitive the elevator
scrolls you through the text
and small talk anything that you type can also be executed
so if you just type three plus four in the
editing window or pick up something else
you can say do it and small talk will go off and do it
here's the state of the painting program as it was
almost ten years ago
there's a radio buttons that you could actually control your own
features
one of the wonderful things about
giving this talk
today is that we're almost at the point
where i never have to show this movie again
because most of the
things that
we have done at park in the system can now are now available on
powerful micros like the apple macintosh II
and the final thing i'll show here is
this is a browser
structure
invented by larry tesler
in which when you point to a category area
it retrieves a bunch of related things
so we're looking at all the different kinds of things that
we can do arithmetic on pick the integer there
looking at the arithmetic part of things
you can do to integers and
looking at the operation plus and here
is the code and small talk to do integer plus
and here is
an example of the debugger in the system
we'll type in some nonsense we'll try and add three
to a piece of text
piece of text
says this is a string so as we say do it to that
instead of crashing the system what we'll do get
as a notification
here that the string couldn't transform itself into an integer
here we can look and see what was going on at that time
so all of the
processing that was being done
and that thread of control was set aside
in small talk
in fact once
people looked on the disc and found seventeen
hundred suspended processes that were just left there
during the debugging of the system
now by expanding that
debugging window
we got a picture of things that were happening in that process
quite independently of the processes and small talk that are
operating the window system and the debugging system
so here's the code that was executing
here's the attempt of the string to make itself into an imager
that failed
couldn't do that because it couldn't find any
numeric characters to transform
and here are the parameters there's the argument
self is the thing that got the message so that's three
and so we get to see all of the
things we could single step it if we wished
we can restart it if we wished and so forth
so
the whole idea
of what we're trying to do here is
comes back to this question that i asked in the very beginning
and that is what would a computer be if it were like a pencil
can it be used by children well yes it can
can it be used by adults yes it can
how low can we go to childhood
can we go into much much much lower
than grade school
here's an answer to that question
it's a tape i got from
the woman who's my accountant
this is her daughter aged twenty two months
too much shy of her second birthday
and she's never lived in a world
that wasn't densely populated with macintoshes
because both your mother and father worked at home
and both of her mother and father had their own mac
and in fact
when i found that the little girl was interested in computers
i gave her an apple ii which she rejected
she wanted a macintosh just like her folks
and she literally learned to use it
by sitting on her mother's lap
while her mother was working
so for this child
the macintosh is not a piece of technology but simply
more material in the environment to manipulate
though i don't believe in user surveys the one
i did do with this
for a young user is
i discovered that she vastly preferred
macintoshes with installed hard disks
now given that she can use the mouse
and some people are surprised that she can without
having to look at it
but in fact that something that everybody can use
it's not too surprising that she can hit
visible menu commands in
mac paint
so when i saw this
i was in trigga i never seen a child this young interacting
with a computer before but
i wasn't too overwhelmed until i saw what she did next
she wants a fresh sheet of paper so she
hits the closed bar in the window she saves her
old drawing using the pop up and then she uses the pull down
to get herself a fresh sheet and she's off and running again
and in fact we discovered that she was about seventy percent
literate about seventy percent of the generic window commands
they were found in any macintosh application
she is able to use not just in a visual program like mac paint
so
the answer is is that
this stuff is for all of us and the reason it works
is not because the
goodness of computer science
in it all others some there the main reason it works is because
for some reason we decide to study human beings and involve
lots of human beings called children in our experiment
and try and stay closely coupled to them
for a number of years
and out of that came a bunch of ideas that
could not have sprung just from technology law
so if it weren't for the multiple mentality ideas of brunner
and the catalysis of tim galway's inner game of tennis
and a host of other
sources like suzuki's way of teaching children violin
and others to numerous dimension we never would have thought
of these ideas and implemented them the way we did
i think a good way of ending this talk is with a winsom
churchill joke which
you know all winston churchill jokes
he's at a party after a certain number of whiskeys
and no matter what happens
he's always in private command of the of the english language
this joke is rather early in the in the evening
and he's
over in the corner drinking his scotch
and the hostess of the party comes over to him
terribly distraught and says mr churchill
i'm really upset
i just saw the famous earl over here steal
one of my silver salt shakers
what am i to do
natural thought for a minute
and sucked a cigar in his mouth and went over to the earl
and on the way
he picked up a silver salt shaker
and put it in his pocket
when we got over to the earl
he took it out and said i think we've been noticed perhaps
we should put these back
the moral besides that being the reason we won world war ii
the moral of that story is if you want people
to go along with you
you have to involve them in the same conspiracy
and use your interface
design
is a conspiracy that i hope more of you will get interested in
thank you very much
i'm judah lemon
and our first question is from rensler polytechnic institute
alan what do you feel about
attempts to protect legally fundamental ideas graphics
especially apple's attempt to protect
the mac interface sutherlands
patentine of clipping out the ribbons
well i think that the
the basic idea of protecting inventions is something
that's been around for a long time and it
has done people who have taken the energy to invent
things fair amount of good
i would like to have a tenth of a cent for every
window that opens on a screen
for the next five years
but i think that even in patent law there is enormous confusion
between what's an idea and what's an invention
patent law doesn't allow you to patent an idea
even though nowadays ideas are important as
inventions that have been made concrete in some fashion also
there's a lot of confusion
still in what it means to copyright something
when i was at atari the earliest
statutes that they used
as precedent work
things that had to do a copywriting of player piano roles
back in the early nineteen hundreds
so it's a very complicated
issue i think that a
sort of a first principle in it
is if a company spends a lot of money
uh paying people to invent an idea
and uh then comes out with that idea
they should have some protection for it for a while isn't
i i don't see any
reason why uh
we should condone
having those things ripped off if
some companies paying millions of dollars
other companies shouldn't just get it for free
i think beyond that the situation is pretty much confused
this question allan comes from the university of utah
where will powerful micros take us first in five years
and then in ten years well
i think the simple answer is probably not far enough
the basic industry is very conservative
wall street
wants people to stay with the eighty
six and sixty eight thousand architectures
which i think is a big mistake
there are lots more interesting things on the horizon and the
amount of computer cycles we actually need to do
things particularly that involve interaction
is always grossly underestimated
so i think that
the one answer is that
the next five years
and especially the next ten years
could be incredibly interesting
certainly in the ten year horizon
is the possibility of doing real time
three d graphics at the flight simulator level on a desktop
i believe that could be done within five years
if companies took a great interest in it
so we're at a very interesting stage now
where the cost performance
as i think everybody realize it doesn't go in a steady
purr if it goes in jumps and fits
because the major cost and computer is in the packaging
and every time you can
get the number of transistors up by a factor of ten
you have an enormous change in
where you can put a thing on a board
or rather requires a rack or an entire case
okay from again from the university of utah
computers have not been a big success in
direct teaching for example
computerated instruction
why is this so and what can be done to approve it well i think
i think i'm pretty much after
the experience i've had with working with
both children and adults with computers
and at least dabbling in the areas of learning and education
i think that the
one of the best ways of thinking of a computer is very similar
to thinking of what a piano means
in teaching music
and the piano
can amplify musical impulse we can only sing
with one voice if we want to play a four part pug we have to use
something mechanical like a piano to do it
and it can be done very beautifully
but for most people
the piano has been the
biggest thing to turn millions of people
away from music for the rest of their lives
and i think the way to sum it up is just to say that
all musicians know that the music isn't in the piano if it were
we'd have to let it vote
and because of that that says in any situation
where education and learning is involved that
you first have to develop a curriculum based on ideas
not on media
the media can be amplifiers of those ideas
but you have to have the ideas first
and i think the reason computers have fail
is that almost everybody
no matter which way they try and use
computers have
wanted the computer to be some sort of magic ointment
over the super rating wound of bad concepts
and i think as soon as people get
what we saw is an amazing learning experience in the
king galway tennis experience
and that is something that can extend and be amplified by
machines and especially computers but first
you have to have the ideas
another university of utah question my old elm water
yes coming through
what new developments do you see coming for the disabled
well there
i think that's a particular interest of mine
because my father was a prosthetic
prostheticist
and suddenly i've been interested in for many years and
i just wish more people were working on it
the technology is there to do an enormous amount for
the ten million of physics is an example
there are
i think there are twenty million people in the united states
right now i've had strokes
ten million of them
uh suffer a fair amount of speech in pyramid
is quite possible to do technology that they can carry
around that allow them to
carry on normal conversations about things
just an enormous
set of areas and i think
for people who are interested in user interface
it is another area
that gets you out of the mclewan fish bowl
and into a context
where you have to go back to first principles and reexamine
things so i think it's
i think the future there is very bright
but we need more people working at it
ellen whatever happened to molly
molly yes
well it's a wonderful story because
after that
experience with tim dale
she came up this is a nineteen seventy five she came up to him
afterwards and said hey
does this stuff work for weight control
and tim said well gee i don't know
let's see if we can figure out something
so they figured out something and
molly over the next year took off
all of her weight and became a very good
intermediate
tennis player and for the last number of years has run
an inner game weight control
clinic in los angeles is a business she set up herself
to apply the principles that she'd used to take off all that way
so this whole experience completely transformed her life
part of it
she had never thought of herself as being a physical person
she never really thought of herself as having a body
and this experience got her in touch
with that whole body mentality
she'd never been in touch with before
and that's part of the secret of controlling your way
okay and the final question is two parts first of all
in terms of increasing human potential what do you see
is the most important challenges for students today
well i think the
i mean i see going where i felt like when i was in college
elementary school
all the way through except for graduate school
i always felt like a gorilla warrior
where the major
task i had was to retain any sense of
myself and my own ideas
while i was going through this incredible
mill
of different hurdles other people had set up
and
so i think that
i think that's number one number two i think is for
any students who are interested in going
into science in the engineering
they have to realize that
both of those are art forms
and that the
both of them are still exercises without an aesthetic feeling
and that the liberal arts
are the best place to develop your aesthetic feeling
so i'm pretty much even against
having strong concentrations in engineering
computer science
and those things at the undergraduate level i think
people should try and get a really solid liberal arts background
and i mean solid i mean of the kind
that they would call solid on the continent
not in the u s
and then use that as an endless well
for ideas and metaphors
that you can use when you're doing science and engineering
i think anybody who's ever read about famous scientists
knows that the strongest connection
they have with their work is not technical
but aesthetic
and so finding the aesthetic in yourself
and developing aesthetic in
yourself i think is the biggest challenge
and the last part of the question is what are you setting
as your next challenge
well i think for somebody in their forties
in a field that's only forty years old or so has
the challenge of
the basic challenge i think that we all have
but especially as we get olders the challenge of renewal
renewal i think is a very special word word and
i like to use it instead of education
education has strong connotations but i think renewal
is what it's all about renewal means
always being able to
sidle up to a new problem and
try and see it from a fresh point of view
i find as i get older it is harder and harder
to see things from a fresh point of view and so for me
the kinds of things i need to do are to
for instance be able to do more music
i used to be a professional
musician i'm still very interested in it
and i find the
now that
when i have a fair amount of contact with music during the week
that my ideas are fresher in the computer science domain
otherwise there's a tendency to just
keep on thinking old thoughts and old pathways
thank you very very much
and thank you for joining us today
we invite your comments and questions on this presentation
and we hope that you will make nominations
for future
speakers and topics if you're viewing this lecture on tape
we've installed some feedback
postcards under the label of the video cassette if you're not
viewing it on tape
our
address is at the end of this presentation thank you very much