61 a lecture No.10 announcements
midterm one regrade requests are due Monday
please make sure
that the links to your midterm one recordings
continue to work
through Monday
you will
be contacted if you need to keep them even longer
but if you don't hear from us you can just remove them
or not it's really up to you
but
if you want to free up some space on your google drive
or whatever you could remove them on Tuesday
homework two is due Thursday
the completely optional hog strategy contest
will end on Monday
and let's see how many people have submitted so far
a lot
we have 112 submissions
stanford's still there at the bottom
we have a four way tie for first place
that doesn't happen in many many years
but just because you're winning now
doesn't mean you'll win the whole contest
it's not unusual
that somebody will save their very best entry
until the last minute
so we'll see what happens this year
I'm delighted to see some many people participating
we will have a lab this week
lab is due on Tuesday
come to orientations on Monday
and just finish the lab on Monday
it's really only do on Tuesday
in case for some reason you can't finish it on Monday
we'll have discussion in tutorials on Wednesday
an exam prep section on Friday
and election q amp a with the instructors Monday
Wednesday and Fridays in the morning
today's lecture is not all about recursion
but there are some recursion examples sprinkled in
instead today we talk about how to give names to
multiple values
bundle together using a container
and we'll also talk a little bit about strings
because those are related
they're kind of like containers full of letters
okay here we go
lists are a built in data type in python
that are used everywhere
to create a list we write a list literal
to bind that list value to a name
we just use an assignment statement
so here are some odd numbers
I can get the
element at index zero or one or two or three
I can also get the number of elements
now notice that the
index of the last element is
one less than the length of the elements
so the right way to think about this index
is the offset from the beginning
offset of zero from the beginning is just the beginning
and then this is one after that and two after that
and three after that
now this is just a call expression
this is an element selection expression
where you have some expression that gets evaluated
that gives you a list
and then you have to evaluate the index
so it is possible to put arbitrary expressions in
either of these places
and also to combine the results in any way that I want
so I could say odds 3 odds two
and that gives me the No.2
I could then use that as an index into odds
so that means you can put an arbitrary expression here
which gets evaluated first
an arbitrary expression there
which gets evaluated
2nd and then once you have the value here
which is a list
and the value here which is an integer
you can look up the particular element in the list
so when working with lists we use list literals
we can also write expressions to describe
each element in the list
and in this case
digits would be bound to the lists that were equal
regardless of whether we wrote down the numbers
or expressions that evaluate to those numbers
to get the number of elements we ask for the len
of the list len is a built in function
if I want to find an element selected by its index
I can use element selection syntax or I can use the
get item function in the operator module
which has the same effect
in order to combine
two lists together or form repetitions of lists
I actually just add and multiply
so if I say the list to seven
plus the digits list times two
multiplying the digits
list times two just replicates its elements twice
and then adding those
to the end of lists to seven gives me one long list
with 10 elements
I could also use
the add and mull functions from the operator module
finally the elements of a list need not be integers
they could be anything including other lists
so here I have a list literal
with two other nested list literals
what I create is a list with two elements
each of which are lists with two elements
which are integers
and so asking for element No.1 of pairs gives me
this element which is a list with 30 and 40
so here you see that there is an combined expression
in this case an element selection expression
giving me a list
which I then select an element from
in order to get the No.30
lists contain other values
their values that represent collections of other values
and when you have one value that contains another
you might ask the question
does an element appear in a list
there are actually built in operators
for testing whether an element appears
in a compound value such as a container
so let's say I have digits
which is one eight two and eight
I can ask is one in digits
python will return true
so in is an operator
that evaluates
both one and digits
and then determines whether one appears in digits
eight is in digits
the fact that it's in there twice doesn't matter
it's in there
five is not in digits
so if I said five in digits I'd get false
but since I said five not in digits
this is another operator
that's equivalent to saying not five in digits
let's look at a few other examples
so here's digits
one in digits is true
five in digits is false
now it has to be the value since one doesn't equal one
if I say one in digits
the string one is not there only the integer
also we're looking for an individual element
if I say is the sequence one eight in digits
it says false
but there it is one and eight
that's not what the inn operator does
it doesn't look for subsequences
instead it looks for individual elements
if I had said is one two in
the nested list that contains one and two
that would be true
because there it is right there as an element
of this list
but if it's nested too deeply
then it's not there anymore
so this is a simple operator that doesn't search
through a structure
trying to find anything that matches
and said it just goes element by element
and sees whether it's equal
to the element that you're looking for
since sequences are fundamental to computing
people have developed new kinds of statements
that help us manipulate or iterate over sequences
and one of them is the four statement
so the four
statement is a way of iterating over sequences
I'll show you an example
and then I'll tell you exactly how it works
I'll write a function
that computes the count
of the number of times in a sequence s
that some value appears
count the number
of times that value occurs
in sequence s
and using a while statement
I might write something like total index equals zero
zero
while it's the case
that index is less than the length of the sequence
I'm going to look at the element
at
index
of s
so now
I've selected one particular element of the index
and if I start out with index zero
I'll pick the zero element
and if I change index later
then I'll get another element later on
so at some point down the line
I will rebind index to index plus one
and in this way I'll March through the
all of the elements of the list
and what do I do with this element
well I want to figure out if
element is equal to this value that I'm looking for
and if so then I'll change total to be total plus one
and at the end I can return total
so what have I done so far
I have to find a function called count
that takes in some sequence
and counts the number of times that say
one appears in that sequence
oh there it is three times 1 2 3
okay so that's a useful dock test
let's just paste that in right there
and then we'll talk about this implementation
well let's try to make it shorter
one thing we see here
is that total is rebound the total plus one
there's actually shorthand in python for doing that
I can just say total plus equals one
and this is a different assignment operator
that a science total to be whatever total was before
and then one more
and I can do the same thing here and simplify that
okay so we've made some progress
but I think we can do better
the meat of this implementation is here
and the rest of this is just doing the work
of iterating over
all the elements in a sequence
which is such a common thing
that we have a special statement for it
called the four statement
and a four statement allows us to just forget
about the index entirely
and instead of saying while index less than len s
I just say for every element in s
and that replaces both of these lines
and allows me to get rid of the index increment
at the bottom
so now if I read out what this implementation says
it says I'm going to keep
track of the total number of times
I've seen value in s
and for every element in s if element is that value
then I'll increase the total by one
if I run the dock test I'll see that it tried to count
one in this sequence
it was expecting three
and that's exactly what it got back
one test passed
okay so that was an example of sequence iteration
where we used a four statement
and how does it work
well what happens is that
the name element is bound
in the first frame of the current environment
not the new frame by the way
no new frames are introduced with a four statement
but the name element is bound
and then the suite of the four statement is executed
and then the name
element is bound of the next thing it is
and we execute this again
so when you have a four statement
it's going to execute the suite of the statement
a number of times
which is the number of elements in s
an element will be bound to the different
element of s each time
so here's the execution procedures belled out
the syntax of the statement looks like this
you need a name
you need an expression and you need a sweet
the first thing that happens as you evaluate the header
expression which must yield an iterable value
now I said we're doing iteration
and iterable values are related to that
but this is a term that I won't define precisely
for several weeks
but for now just think
this expression needs to evaluate to a sequence
later on we'll see that there are other
things that we can put in there besides sequences
and iterate over those as well
but for now just think
I need an expression that gives me a sequence
I need a name to give to each element in that sequence
and then for each element in the sequence
we'll bind that name to the element
in the current frame
and then execute the suite
one more cool feature
about four statements is that you can actually
do sequence unpacking
right inside the header of the four statement
so let's say I had a list of lists
I call it pairs here
and I want to count the number of pairs
that are just the same element twice
so I'm going to go through each pair
and I'm going to say is one the same as two no
is two the same as two yes
so same count will be one more than it was before
three or two are different
but four and four are the same
so we'll increment same count again
now what does the four statement look like
that can do that
this is something that only
works for a sequence of fixed
length sequences
such as a sequence of pairs
but in that case
then you can unpack each pair into separate names
so you can say for x comma y in pairs
pairs as a sequence of pairs
x and y
are actually now bound to the elements in each pair
as opposed to the pair itself
at which point you can check if x equals y
and if that's true then change same count to b
same count plus one
so you're giving a name for each
element in a fixed length sequence here
and that's called sequence unpacking
and this looks just like multiple assignment
when you say x kama y equals some pair
each name here x and y
is bound to some particular value in a pair
ranges are another sequence type
that means they're sequences but they're not lists
ranges are there to represent
sequences of consecutive integers
actually
they can represent all kinds of integer sequences
but we're just going to focus on the ones that
have consecutive integers
so counting upwards
imagine an infinite number line full of integers
here's a small slice
what arrange does is it picks out a
finite length within this long number line
by giving a starting value and an ending value
and selecting all of the integers in between
an increasing order
now the way that I've drawn this is important
both of these 0.2 just before the number indicated
in the number line
so that means that -2 is actually included in the range
from -2 to two
but the No.2 is outside of the range
so it's including this starting value
but excluding the ending value
now what a quirky thing
well it actually makes a lot of things simpler
to do it exactly
that way
you can compute the length of a range
just by subtracting the
starting value from the ending value
so two minus negative two is four
and there are four elements here
as you can see
element selection is also easy
you just take the starting value and add the index
index is started zero
so the elemented index zero is -2
and the elemented index 3
is negative 2 plus three is one
okay so it has length an element selection
so it must be a sequence
even though it's not a list
now how do you convert
to a list if you want to see the elements
well
you can use what's called the list constructor
which is a built in function
cost just called list
and when you call it on any other sequence
it gives you back a list
full of the elements of that sequence
so a range isn't a list itself
but calling list on it does give you a list
of all those elements
that's the list constructor
now one special feature of ranges is that if you
leave out one of the numbers
so you only specify one number
that's treated as the ending value
with an implicit starting value of zero
so listing the range four is 0 1 2 3
including zero but excluding four
okay
so if I create a range from five to eight let's say
it's not a list it's a range
if I wanted a list I'd have to call list on that value
at which point
I'd see exactly what elements are in there
now if I know what a range is
I already knew that it was five six and seven
but if I ever wanted a check
and make sure that it included the starting
value but did not include the ending value
I could call list and
find out that for sure
now a range up to four
is a range starting at zero and going up to four
and if I list out those values
I'll see that it's zero one two and three
so what might we do with the range
well there are lots of cases when
the sequence you want
is exactly a sequence of increasing integers
so if I wanted to some all the integers below
some number n
I could do that by keeping track of the total
grabbing each element I
in the range up to but not including n
and changing total to be total plus I
and then returning the total
at which point if I some below five
I'll be adding one and two and three and four and zero
and that will give me tab
now there are cases when you actually don't care
about the integers themselves
you just want to do something a fixed number of times
so if for instance I wanted to
say
go bears
three times a typical way to write that
is a four statement like this
or if I now cheer it will say go bears go bears
go bears now
range
three means that there are three elements in range
and we are giving a name to each element but
we don't actually care what that name is
because we're not using it anywhere
so one convention is that you use a single underscore
character or a blank
just just
let other programmers know that you're not actually
going to use this name anywhere
it's okay if I put x there instead
but I'd never use that x
so it really doesn't matter what I put there at all
this is an indication that you just don't care
and we're going to do a one more example
and I'm going to have you do a couple of drills
I'm going to have you write
both an iterative and recursive
so you can see
how to think about these two things simultaneously
all right here's the first one I wanted us to work on
I would like us to write a recursive function my sum
that takes us input a list of numbers
and sums them all up and gives me the sum
ok
here's a nice drill
if you want to do one just do this iteratively
almost everything
we do recursively will have an iterative component
and vice versa
they may be a little bit easier
they may be a little bit harder
or they may be the same
so if you want to take a break
go ahead and do that and write this interview
it's a good exercise
okay so the first thing first
and look
this is always true no matter when you're writing code
but more so when you're writing or cursor code
you got to really think about
what is it that you want to do
so think about the recursive definition
two parts base case and then the recursive case
so what's the base case here
I can think of two possible
one is
I give you a list with only a single element in it
what is the sum of all the elements of that list
just that one element
what's the other base case
yeah just like before if the list is empty
let's do that one
that way we'll just go ahead and deal
with the empty list
well now you got to ask the question is what is
my sum of the empty list
I think it's reasonable to return zero
we can say the some of all of those elements is zero
so let's just go ahead and write the base case
if the list is equal to the empty list so
score back it score back it
I could have also said
if the length of the list is equal to zero
that would have
tested for the empty list as well
return do not
do not do not forget that you are returning values
because recursively you are building up an expression
as we saw with both factorial and with string reversal
so be really really careful here alright
recursive what's the recursive definition
well what does it mean to sum up two four one and five
well one way to think about it is
I the sum of all of these elements is two plus
well whatever the some of the rest of the list is
so I can just peel off that first element
hold on to it and add it to my sum up for one five
yeah that sounds about right
and by the way that sounds a lot like factorial
right and factorial as end times
whatever the answer is for everything else
so here instead of decorating a value I'm just taking
one element off the list
and then summing everything else
and that's sort of like what we did with reversal
we took one element off the list
we put it to the end
and then we reversed everything else up front
same thing here
all right so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
peel off that first element
and then I'm going to add that
to the recursive call of everything else
okay that should be pretty straightforward
so if l does the empty list return zero else
grab the zero element
and added to everything else recursively
called with my psalm
so it began the one colon operator says
starting at
position one which is the second element of the list
up until the end
grab that list
call my sum recursively
and then this will eventually return
four plus five plus one which is 10
and it'll add that to two and I'll have my answer
and again that return there is important
you are building an expression
you have to return something to the previous
function call
whether it's recursive or whoever called you from the
outside
all right let's make sure we understand how this works
so let's
walk through an example with this list with four
elements my sum of 2 4 1 5
all right let's go into the code
list isn't empty
so peel off the first element
and add it to the recursive call of everything else
so that's two plus my sum of 4 1 5
okay am I done no
I want to add two things but that is a function call
so I eventually have to go call some function
and get an answer
and then I can return
all right what's my sum of 4 1 5
come into here that's not empty
peel off the first element
make a recursive call with the next two element
four plus my sum of one five
am I done yet nope I still need this
peel off the first element recursive call
aha you can see we're getting there by the way
now this little guy is done
why because it hits the base case
and notice the base case doesn't have to do any work
it hits the zero
so now five plus my some of the empty list says
please return zero to my some of the empty list
now I have an expression five
and now I have the answer to my sum of five
so I can pop that up to my sum of five
now I have an answer to my sum of one five it's six
now I have an answer to my sum of 4 1 5 it is 10
and now finally I have an answer which is 12
good
all right let's do a drill
I'm going to give you two back to back so
the first one is right and iterative function
that takes us input an integer end
just a number positive integer
and returns the sum of the first end integer
so some five for example
will return one plus two plus two plus four plus five
so this looks a lot like factorial
so do that please iteratively while loop four loop
I don't care how you do it
and then when you're done with that
please do exactly the same thing but do it recursively
okay so two drills back to back
go ahead and pause the video
take some time to do those two
I think the iterative
you should be able to do very quickly
and then again
think about the nature of the recursive call
base case recursive call
and then come back and we'll do both solutions to this
all right I hope you got the answer to both of those
so let me show you my solution
uh the iterative one
uh so some iter
I'm gonna just distinguish between the two types of uh
functions takes as input and
and again I'm not gonna check whether I'm
as a positive integra
we won't worry about that
I'm going to initialize a variable to be some
sorry
I'm gonna initialize a variable called some to be zero
and then I'm going to iterate
between the value zero and n
notice here this is an off by one
error that may have bit some of you
if I want to use a for loop
iterating between zero and n
I have to go from zero to n plus one
because this last value is non inclusive
so the value of I
inside the body of the for
loop will take on the value 0 1 2 3 4
up until n what do I want to do with those
I want to sum them up
so I'm going to say some is equal to the previous sum
plus I noticed by the way unlike factorial
where we initialize the effectorily the b one
because we are computing products
and one is the identity for product
in some of course we have to initialize it zero
okay so running some each iteration we add 0 1 2 3 4 5
and then eventually we return some
at the very end here
and relatively straightforward
now you may have done a little while loop
perfectly fine
I would argue the four loops probably cleaner
because if you're counting integers from
zero to some number
there's no reason for you to do with a wildlife
there's no reason for you to initialize a variable
do the condition and then increment the variable
let python do the hard work for you
so I would argue probably the four
version of this is a little tighter and a little meter
because it fits very nicely into what exactly range
designs for you
okay let's do now the recursive definition
base case is easy
if end is zero return zero
right so if I ask you to sum the the first zero numbers
I'm done there's nothing to do
okay good so that's easy
so what's the recursive definition
well let's see
the sum of n is
let's start from this side
five plus four plus two three one
so surely we can agree that that's five plus
the recursion of four
and four is four
the recursion call recursive call of three
it's exactly like factorial
it's just that we're summing instead of multiplying
okay good
so let's see what that recursive call looks like
so if n is not zero I'm going to take the number n
and I'm going to add it not multiply
to a recursive call of n minus one
and eventually
so I'll make a recursive call here
I'll keep building up the expression so it'll be n
plus n minus one
plus n minus two boot all the way down
until we hit the zero
the base case
okay good I hope you got that
by the way some of you may be getting errors in
python or jupiter notebook saying recursion
length exceeded
that's because it's sort of like an infinite loop
you keep going recursive recursive recursive calls
and it's not catching your base case
it's sort of the equivalent and iteration of that
you're not stopping the loop
and that just means something's wrong with your logic
or you have a little bit of bug in your code
so if you're seeing this
stack overflow or cube blown out or recursion limit
exceeded something is wrong
with the stopping condition on your code
all right now
at this point
we've seen a number of examples of recursive calls
and I'll be the first one to admit that they are
relatively straightforward
and there's no obvious benefit
to doing something recursively over iterative
and the last example I'm going to show you
I want to show you the power
the really the true power and beauty of recursion
and we are going to solve a
fairly complex problem recursively
and you're going to see how
truly elegant recursion can be when it's done very
very well
so we'll pick it up in a little bit when we come back
list comprehensions
are a powerful form
of combination in the python language
and a list comprehension
like the one that you see here
on this 2nd line
takes an existing list in this case a list of numbers
and computes a new list from it
according to some expression
so this one built a list out of the letter's eye
for every eye in 3468
where letters is the sequence of letters which gives me
demo oh time for a demo
let's start simple
I'll create a list called odds
with one three five seven and nine in it
now a list comprehension can state
I want to computer list that is x plus one
for every x in odds
and that will give me 2 4 6 8 10
where one became two and three became four etc
and this happened
by evaluating the x plus one
expression over and over again
with x bound to each of these in turn
there's a more complicated form
of a list comprehension
that includes not only an expression
of how to compute gentlemen
a name
and then the sequence that you want to compute over
but also
the word if followed by some condition
such as saying 25% x equals zero
which means I only want to keep an element x if
it's the case that x divides evenly
into the number 25
so 25 divided by x has a remainder of zero
using the remainder operator or modulo operator
so one goes into 25 25 times
five goes into twenty five five times
but three seven and nine don't evenly divide 25
so this
part of the list comprehension
lets me select
only part of the list that I want to keep around
and I can have interesting combinations of these
so I could say I want x plus one
for these elements that evenly defy 25
and then I won't get 1 in 5
but instead I'll get two and six
so those are list comprehensions
I can certainly put them inside of a function
so for example I might have
a function that computes the devices
of some number n
and how would it do it
well it would just return
one which divides everything
and then
x for x in the range from two all the way up to
but not including in
if it's the case
that
end divided by x equals zero
so what are the devices of one well just one
that's kind of a special case
how about four
well you have one and two
what about nine you have one and three
what about eight you have one two and four
twelve has even more
18 has several devices
and these are all the integers that
evenly divide some number n
strings are my favorite
strings are an abstraction
a representation of textual data
I call them an abstraction because we don't care
about the details of exactly how they're encoded
but they do represent information
they can represent numbers
and the way we write
numbers can all be represented with the string
here we have scientific notation
here we have some point
and all of these are just strings that somehow
tell us information
they can represent language
and as imagination
bodies forth the forms of things to unknown
and the poet's pen
turns them to shapes and gives to airy nothing
a local habitation and a name
I think when shakespeare wrote midsummer night's dream
he was talking about computer science and abstraction
you can also use strings to represent programs
so here's a string that defines the curry function
and python source files are just strings
so if I put this in a source file and executed it
then I would have defined the curry function
and by the way
if I start a python and create exactly that string
curry lamb the f
lamb the x lamb the y
f of x combo y
it's just a string
but if I execute that string
well then I've just defined curry
and if I curry the add function
using what was just a string before
I can in fact add numbers together
so some details about strings
that you may have discovered
already throughout the course
but I'll go through them now
there's three different ways to write down a string
I can use single quotes
I can use double quotes
and they're the same
except for that if you put an apostrophe
in the middle of a double quoted string
it works out fine
but if you do that in the middle of a
single quoted string
well then it would end the string
you don't have to
just put English characters in the string
nehal
is fine
single quoted and double quoted strings are equivalent
a triple quoted string
can span multiple lines
so I use those a lot for dock strings
because a lot of times
dock strings will extend the multiple lines
when you add dock tests
now when I evaluate this multiple line string
when it shows me at the end all fits on one line
and what's happened is
it's used a special symbol to encode
the end of one line at the beginning of another
this is called a line feed
so whenever you see a backslash inside of a line
that escapes the following character
and what that means is that the two characters together
the backslash and the following character
really are just one thing in the sequence of letters
that is the string
and this backslash n means line feed which means
start a new line
strings or sequences
the length and element selection
operations are similar to what you'd expect
so the length of the city of berkeley is eight
which means they're eight letters
each letter is called the character
now
actually element selection has the same indexing scheme
0 1 2 3
but the result is not quite what you might think
so what you get back is an
string even though what you selected from was a string
now list don't work like this
if you had a list of numbers
and you selected the element of the next three
you would get a number
not a list but for strings you get a string
but with only one element only one character in it
in and not in
are a little bit different for strings than they are
with other sequence types
so
instead of looking for only individual letters
inside this sequence of letters
you can look for whole words
so if I say is here in wears waddle though
it will tell me true
but if I said if 2 3 4 innocent here
even though two three and four next to each other
it would say false
and if I looked for the list in here
that would be false as well
so this you can only look for one element at a time
but in strings you can look for consecutive letters
that's because
most of the time when you're working with strings
you actually care about whole words
more than just individual letters
so strings are a special abstraction
which are like sequences in many ways
but they behave in a way
that's slightly different from other sequences
okay
let's pick it up where we left off
and we're going to talk a little bit more about
recursion and
you may remember that we wrote an
iterative algorithm for reversing a string
to reverse ward to draw or draw toward
so how did that work
we took the first letter in the last letter and we
swapped them
and then we incremented one decremented one
swap and kept going until we got to the midway point
and it was an iterative algorithm
we had either a while or a for loop
that would work its way from the first letter
to the midway point of the string
swapping swapping swapping swap
perfectly fine way to swap
and I just want to think about this
how we would do this recursively
so what does it mean to recursively reverse a string
well as you saw with the factorial
typically what it means is that you keep
simplifying the problem
until you get to a base case
so what does a base
case look like in reversing a string
what's the easiest possible thing
while a string with only one letter
is trivial to reverse it's that letter
or maybe the empty string
is a trivial base case
so that's always good to think about
when you think recursive is like
what's the simple case here
and then your job recursively
is to take a problem that is big
reverse a string with n letters in it
and figure out how to break that down
into a simple operation
with a slightly simpler version of it
say reversing and minus one characters
so let's just think about that
so what does it mean to reverse a string
so we had been thinking about this as I swap the w
and the d and the a and the r
but the other way to think about this is
I can just take that w
and put it all the way at the end
and then reverse the
rest of the string
yeah that sounds about right
so let's see if that makes sense
so can we agree that the reverse of the string ward
is
the reverse of everything but the first letter
string concatenated with the first letter
sure let's just do this in our heads
if I reverse this it's dra
and then I attach it w to it
and that's of course the reversal
so notice what I've done here
I've simplified the problem by one letter
and I've done that by
thinking about the nature of what reverses
by just saying
if I just take that first letter and put it at the end
and then I'll worry about the rest of the string later
that's a recursive definition
because notice I've defined
the
reversing of an entire string as
the reversing of a slightly smaller string
plus a simple operation
looks a lot like the factorial right end factorial
it was end times and minus one factorial
all right let's just do it again and make sure we see
how we reverse
now ard
it's the same game
take that I a
shove it to the end now not the end here of course
the end of this
and then reverse rd at the front of that
so the reversal of ard is the reversal of rd plus a
now eventually
so notice what's happening
this thing has to evaluate to this
this will eventually give me an answer
when I work my way down the recursion
I'll shove it in there it should be dra
I attach it w to it and then I'm done
okay
what's the reversal of our d
now we know what the game is
take that first letter
shove it to the end and then reverse a single letter
ah this looks like the base case I mentioned
if I have a single letter
reversalist trivial
there's no work to be done there's no computation
it's just the letter
so let's agree that the reversal of d is just d
base case no recursive call
this is like zero factorial is one
no work to be done
all right now what you have to do
notice what we've done if we
build up an expression
with a series of string concatenations
and now we've just got to work our way back up
this stack in order to create the final answer
so let's start at the bottom of course
what is reversive d
it is d and so reverse of r
d is just the string concatenation of d and r
okay that's easy I know how to do that
now there's no recursive call here
there's no work to be done
just do the string concatenation
so the reversal of r d is d r
and I'm going to concatenate that with a good
let's do that
so d r plus a
the reversal of ard is dra
so we pop that back up one
and now we have the reversal of ward is draw
and again we've done that
and notice
it's really a different algorithm in this case
right so instead of swapping swapping swapping
I am building up an expression of string concatenation
by one at a time
peeling off one letter
and that's what I meant when I said
at the beginning of the previous lecture
that recursion
you have to think really
quite differently about the nature of computation
and I think in a very elegant way
all right now let's do it in python
reverse is a function that takes as input a string s
base case if the length of the list is one
then return s
there's nothing to do right I sent you in the letter d
the reversal of d is d
go home you're done
otherwise
what am I going to do I want to peel off that first
letter and put it at the end
and string concatenate
the reversal of the rest of the list
so remember that string
rather remember that strings can be indexed like lists
here's where it's a very convenient
so s sub zero is the first element of the list
and you May not have seen this notation before
but this one colon operator
is short hand for everything from the first
character in
the first position of the string
so that's 2nd letter to the end of the list
so I could have also done one colon length of s
but this is a simpler notation
that python gives you that just says one colon
and then you leave a blank here
and that says give me
everything but the zero with element
yeah and that's perfect
because now I'm going to take
let's say what comes in is ward
I take the w that's subzero I take ard
and I take ard
and I shove it back into a recursive call
of reverse okay what does that do
that peels off the first letter and notice again
this is where it's really important to
understand these local variables
the first s coming in was ward
but when I make a recursive call the news is ard
and then the next time it's rd
and then the next time it's d
and then this expression the stinking cat nation
holds on
to the memory of all of those different instantiations
of the local variable
to the function reverse
all right last thing is
there's another base case
I just want to show you what it looks like
because it's equally fine
which is
you could have had the base case be the empty list
and it would have worked just fine
you would eventually hit the empty list
I don't think this is really necessary because
a character a list with a single character is in fact
the reversal is itself
the only reason you might want to do this
is if somebody passes you an empty list
it'd be nice not to choke on it
and so this is nice because it deals with an empty list
problem
that is the second recursive example that we've done
and I hope you now see that
not only is the code look different but
you have to think differently about the problem
and I really like that because it forces you to sort of
think about the nature of computation
in a really fundamental way
so we're going to do a couple more examples
when we come back
I'll see you in a few minutes