lecture 13 q a
yeah so the question here is what does
it mean when we say 64-bit
representation
32-bit representation 16-bit 8-bit etc
etc
so what it's referring to so typically
where you'll see this referred to is
when
they'll talk about things like the color
depth on your monitor
right this is a big graphics uh
terminology 64-bit
graphics yeah so what is that referring
to
it's only referring to the the number of
unique
integers you can represent with a single
number so for example if i have an 8-bit
number
i can represent 0-255 right 256 total
numbers
so when you have 8-bit graphics you only
had 256
distinct colors when i went to 16-bit i
now have 2 to the power
16 whatever that is 2 to the 32 2 to the
et cetera et cetera so when we say
64-bit representations it means how many
you you
distinct integer valued now
programmatically you can go beyond that
with these things called big numbers and
there's ways of numerically
representing big numbers the silliness
of a lot of this
is in the human visual system has
fundamental limitations on how many
distinct colors that it can represent by
the way
i have to make a disclosure my wife is a
neuroscientist and a vision scientist
and it always makes her crazy when i
talk about the human brain
and i think she's like lurking around
here somewhere coming to talk quietly
bring her around in you know her
otherwise ah crap she heard me
she's right there she looks pissed
so the brain you know can't i mean so at
some point the brain can't distinguish
all those distinct colors
and so that you know 64-bit hundreds it
doesn't matter at some point yeah
but to your question very specifically
um when we say 64-bit we're saying how
big
is a single integer and that tells me
how large of a number i can represent
and then what i can do with that number
like for example representing distinct
colors on the monitor
yeah and the other part of that question
was why are there billions of
transistors
could we only need 64 well you want to
represent lots of different numbers
and you also want to represent the
ability to
perform operations on many of those
numbers sometimes actually all at once
so
um the logic for performing some of the
stuff that we'll see on wednesday like
how you add two numbers together
is actually built into the chip it's not
like there's a program
running in software that adds two
numbers instead it's part of the
circuitry
of the hardware of your computer that's
adding those two numbers together
and whether that adder is built to
operate on 32-bit integers or 64-bit
integers is a decision
that the hardware designers have to make
and then the software has to all kind of
take advantage of that so modern
computers typically are built on 64-bit
integers as their kind of like basic
unit
and that's like a fact about
not how the memory is stored so much but
about how the
central processing unit manages all this
information so if you want to like store
a bunch of numbers
and operate on all a bunch of them at
the same time so that the computer could
for example
be adding these two numbers and these
two numbers because you know you need to
add them both so you might as well do
them at the same time
then all of a sudden you're getting a
lot of transistors yeah it's a really
good point and i i missed that part of
your question so i apologize but yeah so
what you're going to see is the
transistors represent can be used to
represent to store a number but
it's also going to be used to do
computation um
and they are the very building blocks of
both storing data
and computing on that data and you'll
see that i think in wednesday's lecture
the next question was how is the
arrangement of transistors determined
are half of them in series and have them
in parallel or something else
so these are as john was just saying
these are done
beforehand so what what happens is
i need to i need some special circuitry
to add two things together
and you don't know how to do that yet
but you will have to wednesday and so i
say okay
how many and gates do i need how many
objects do i need and i wire them in
and then that's it it's not like we're
on the fly
rewiring these transistors to do various
computations i think
there was a time when that was sort of
popular and i don't know if that still
is anymore there was this notion of sort
of dynamic
um reconfiguring but i don't know if we
but basically these things are hardwired
um you decide what you need what what
what computations do you want to be able
to perform on your computer
and you wire them in and then that's it
and then you get to use that circuitry
and then
the you know the operating system and
the controller says okay send this
information over here there's a circuit
to do that send this information over
here there's a circuit to do that
so once you decide what you want the
nature of your computation is
you figure out and you'll see what the
pipeline is we will actually
design circuitry i'll show you how to do
addition and a few other things
you and there's just a pipeline for
doing it it's really quite
straightforward actually in the simplest
case
and then you're like okay build give me
an and gate give me an or gate give me a
not gate give me this wire them up input
here output here
that's done that's a chip on your
computer or on your phone or on whatever
device it is
yeah exactly and the those basic
operations are there on the chip and if
that's all
that you wanted then you could have kind
of a smaller chip than we have today but
basically what's happened is that
common combinations like addition
or you know taking a logarithm or
whatever happens so often
that it makes more sense to build a
circuit that's
kind of especially for that in addition
to the basic ones that just run
and or not and those more complicated
circuits aren't anything more than just
like a bunch of and or knots all chained
together in the right way
but if you're going to do something over
and over and over again and you kind of
anticipate that it's going to happen
then you can make it happen faster if
you just like optimize it in the
hardware in the circuitry in addition to
having the full flexibility of just like
combining any and ors of knots in any
way that you want
yeah yeah that's exactly right so you
know no doubt
the biggest impact on computing has been
the miniaturization of transistors i
mean that's been just a huge
huge win uh for speed
and power and compactness but also what
happens is as computers are running as
we figure out what are users spending
more time doing we may decide we may
realize oh
users are spending a lot of time doing
this one computation let's build a
special circuitry let's put it in the
right place
and we can make computers uh five
percent more faster
great right so there's also a lot of
algorithmic optimization that goes on
not just hardware or
optimization i just got the stink eye
from my wife again by the way she just
walked by
[Laughter]
the next question was have people build
computers using base 10 instead of base
and would that offer some advantages
yeah that's actually an interesting
question
is there would would there have been a
benefit to base 10 like let's say we
we didn't have to worry about the
stability of a bit representation
um well let's let's start by agreeing
that there's nothing you can't
do in base two the base that we work in
is arbitrary
yeah i mean there's there's no
mathematics i can't do in base two
or based on so that's an arbitrary
decision based 10 is of course an
arbitrary too
well look uh simple things like
multiplying and dividing by 10 are
really easy in base 10.
um so that would be a lot faster but you
know i could say the same thing about
base two
uh multiplying and dividing by two is
really fast in base two
so i i don't know i don't know if like
would
somehow if i had a base 10 computer
would it be faster at certain things
would there be a benefit to certain
things
off the top of my head i can't think of
any can you john
yeah no i don't think that there's any
obvious advantage except that
the computer does do a fair amount of
converting like it needs to display
numbers to the users
and so at that point it needs to convert
them to base 10
but that's just such a vanishingly small
amount of the total computation that a
normal program does that it's okay
to have to do this conversion every time
you want to print out a number
and every time you want to interpret a
number so if i type in a number i type
it in in base 10
that has to be kind of then represented
as base 2 and then all the math happens
um but usually that math is just so much
more
work than either interpreting or
displaying the number that it's okay to
be switching bases
um and yeah if if you wanna
build circuits for base 10 they're just
more stuff to build
than in base two like in base two you
kind of just have to memorize that
zero plus zero is zero and zero plus one
is one and one plus one well that's the
special case where you carry uh
but you'd have to do this for every
possible combination of digits in base
ten you'd have to remember that like
three
plus four is seven and kind of build
that as a separate
pathway so um one consequence of
building a base ten computer i think
would be that
there would just be kind of more
hardware to do the same thing
and and so instead you could have more
hardware to do kind of other stuff
and that's the compromise that led
everybody to using base 2.
yeah that's a good point the rules would
get a lot more complicated one of the
nice things about base 2 is the core
rules
for base 2 arithmetic are trivial
whereas in base 10 they are a little bit
more involved so maybe that would end up
making the circuitry a little bit more
complicated by the way i don't know if
somebody has built a not i mean i'm sure
somebody has built a non-base two
computer
um and there's all there was there was a
time in the
i think it was like in the 90s and the
early 2000s where biological
computing was very popular people were
trying to do computing with dna
and molecules and the idea was to use
the power and the speed
of uh nature to do computation it never
there were these really influential
papers for a few years big splashy signs
and nature papers but they never
quite got anywhere today of course
quantum computing
is has been a buzz now for well actually
for quite a while
um i think there's something personally
i think there's something more real with
quantum computing
and here you're getting into a
fundamentally new representation you are
not representing with
an actual zero one it's these it's the
quantum state of a qubit
and there is some indication that things
that are
slow on a traditional computer
um could be very very fast on a quantum
computer
most interestingly is factoring large
numbers which is interesting because
that's the core of encryption so
organizations like the nsa
are very interested in this because if
you can build at scale of quantum
computing
you can break passwords um and that you
cannot do in a traditional computer so
these new
computing paradigms where you represent
information differently i've been around
for quite a while there's a whole field
of optical computing
where you represent information with
light and that light moves through
optical trains
nothing really i mean they're all sort
of interesting
and insightful but in my opinion really
it's quantum computing is the one thing
that has
has been slowly but surely trickling up
john you may know more about this
there's this canadian companies that
claims to
build the quantum computing but i i
think it's controversial and i think
many people have doubted whether it's a
true quantum computing
computer and so there's there's still
some uncertainty about the real nature
of what is feasible today with a
different paradigm
my understanding is that it was just
last year that
that someone claimed somewhat credibly
for the first time
that they had performed a computation
that otherwise wouldn't have been easy
to perform
but they got to kind of choose the
competition so instead of having this be
like something that's generally useful
at this point
it's it's still kind of in proof of
concept yeah and i thought there was
still some controversy around that or at
least i saw some controversy i don't
know if it ever got resolved but
i think there's something there and i
think you know when that breaks through
it's going to be a fundamental shift
in the way we do confrontation is my
guess
yes and i believe that the kind of uh a
national center for studying quantum
computing was just designated here at
berkeley so
uh i think that's right one of the big
we'll be hiring some new folks and uh it
all might happen right here
yeah i either by the way what's really
beautiful about quantum computing is the
combination of physics
mathematics computer science electrical
engineering this is incredible in
chemistry
incredibly complex from the physical to
the theoretical
and i think there's something really
cool there but
you know honey raised a great point
about talking about kind of different
ways of building computers
and sort of what's the history and we're
at a moment in time
where the way we build things now may be
very different from how we build things
several years from now but the pattern
that has emerged
so far in computing with quantum
computing be kind of an interesting
counter example but the pattern that's
emerged so far
is that if we can just come up with one
way of
build of building computers that's
really fast and really flexible
then we can simulate anything else that
we would want
through software and through kind of the
abstraction that you're learning about
here so um it's very common that there
will be
kind of different ways of expressing
programs
than as a bunch of bit manipulations
and yet instead of building a new piece
of hardware to achieve that
for the last several decades the answer
has always been build a piece of
software
in order to simulate a machine that
would have done that using kind of a
regular computer and actually that's
like
very close to the nature of programming
languages it's like
programming language is really a way of
expressing computation
a lot of what you see in a modern
programming language doesn't look
like uh manipulating bits very much
it kind of looks like uh you know
creating functions and calling them
and recursion and all of that you could
try to build a machine
specifically to do those things but
instead we kind of simulate that using
the
hardware that we have that happens to
run really fast
yeah that's a really good point john
that's a great point that that has not
changed and i don't see that changing
either
sure so i think this was from friday's
lecture
what's going on with the min function
and its
optional argument called key
sometimes what you want is to find the
smallest
number among a list
and min will do that for you but
sometimes what you want
is to find a particular number that's
extreme
in another way like it's not the
smallest
it's not the largest but it's the
closest to five or it's the
it's the thing that when you square it
is closest to 24.
or you know you could imagine any kind
of description
where there's like a some value
that would do this the best and
min allows you to find that element
for any possible condition and that's
the point of that key function
so the way you do it is that you
start out with your same set of values
of which
one is the one that you're looking for
and then you provide a function and this
function
is going to be called on every single
one of these values
and yeah let's use that example
of uh the square
is as close as possible to 24. i don't
know why you would want this but
maybe you would for some reason so
what's going to happen here
is that it's going to square and then
subtract 24 from each of these and then
take the absolute value in order to get
some measurement
of how close is the square of this x to
and it tells us 5 is among these numbers
the one that when you square it gets you
pretty close to 24.
in fact there's like an important
property about this computation that's
not shown which is that
5 squared minus 24 is 1 and there's no 1
in this output that's all hidden what is
happening
is that that 1 is computed along with
the result of
squaring 3 and subtracting 24 and
squaring 6 and subtracting 24. so it's
done it for all of them and then it has
found the one
for which the result of calling this
function is the smallest
that's why the smallest because it's min
so in this way you can use min in order
to find the kind of extreme value for
any notion of extreme that you want
but you always get one of these values
and if there's a tie
then you'll get an arbitrary one i think
you get the first one but i'm not
actually sure
so another way to think about it is take
that list
apply the transformation that you see in
the lambda expression square every value
subtract 24 and then just call min
right you could it's just a shortcut for
doing something in a clumsy in a more
clumsy way yeah
and the reason it's so useful is that
let's say you did this uh went through
and
computed f of x for every x in
this list you get all these numbers
but what you really want is the thing
that corresponds to this
so you really want like to remember the
x that goes with it
oh there's the smallest one so then if i
took the min
of this i'd get the pair that i want and
then i could
pluck out the value that got me there
and this would like do the same thing
but wow that's a mess so instead of
writing it this way
uh it's more common to write it that way
and there's a couple of questions in the
chat so let me go through them one at a
time does the key function always have
to be a lambda function i believe it
does
uh no any function could could do so
sorry yes it could be any
but it has to be a function sorry yes it
doesn't have to be a lambda but you can
call um
[Music]
um square root of x right guys well
let's see
yeah exactly so uh
right if we wanted like what's the min
from negative 5 and 4 and
negative 7 and 8. well the min
is negative 7 unless you say oh actually
i want to take the absolute value of all
of them first and then it would
find the 4. good and also what if you
wanted the key function to take
multiple parameters that i don't think
you can do
so i think it has to operate point wise
on the element on the elements of the
list
that's right so if if you
had some function of two arguments
that said return the absolute difference
between x squared
and y let's say
you wouldn't be able to use that as a
key
because it takes two arguments and the
whole idea is that we're going to call
this function on
each one of these individually now you
might do something like
create a one argument function that
calls
f on x and 24 and like fill in the y
that way and then that would work but uh
otherwise
you have to have a function here that's
of one argument
okay uh uh there's a question here when
you took the min of a list of lists what
determined what the minimum was
um so i think we're referring to this
line yeah so we had this thing yes and
to find the minimum you'd have to like
compare
that to that
and it's weird because this is smaller
than that
but this is smaller than that so which
one is it well this is
something that just happens to be
defined in python is that when you're
comparing two lists
you compare their first elements
and if one of them's smaller then it
uses that one
by the way i think that's ridiculous i
mean that's
i just got there's a lot of things that
the boolean operators that i've always
found slightly annoying about python but
that one always bugs me
yeah okay um
okay did we get your um i think tan
seems to have loaded yeah you go tan
yeah thank you ah uh at the end of the
min
has a square uh has square bracket one
mean the first element yes well it's the
what's in the position one so it's the
second element
yeah so in this monstrosity wait what
have i done
oh i changed f ah right oh my goodness
all right there was an old f uh
so in this monstrosity we evaluated
this expression to get a pair and like
a sensible thing would be to give this a
name and then
p1 is the 5 and p0
is the 1 and there's no p2 because it's