61 a lecture No.21
announcements
homework four is due today
ances do next Friday
but you have to do part of it
by next Tuesday to get the checkpoint
and you can get an early submission bonus point
for submitting the whole thing
by next Thursday
that's what I'd recommend
we will double the number of people working on
office hours next week
so there should be more appointments
and fester responses on the office hour q
we also have more people working on piazza
so hopefully we can
answer your questions in a timely manner
I know it's hard to get help in a remote course
but we will do our best
to be more responsive than we were in the last project
homework 5 will be posted to morrow
and it's due
not next week but the following Monday the 26th
we'll try to keep it short because
this Monday is right before the midterm
and completing homework
five is a great way to prepare for the midterm
so that's why we're having a do right before
to make sure that you get a little bit of practice
there is also a lab that week
but the only required part of lab nine
which is on ten twenty six
the due date for homework five
will be to finish homework five
there will be several optional problems
that I highly recommend that you do on the lab
as preparation for the midterm
but nothing will be required
so you'll just have one thing to do
early that week which is to complete homework five
and then take the midterm on Wednesday
the midterm is two weeks from yesterday
advising
office hours will be held on fridays from one to 230
on the office hours q
and right now
we have an anonymous survey
about how things are going in the course
that I encourage you to respond to
I see that several hundred people have responded
already so thanks for that
I didn't see any
consistent suggestions about how to change
the format of the midterm
so it will be fairly similar to how we ran midterm one
it will cover content up to an
including today's lecture
lectures next week are just optional or review
and one thing that was very clear
from the responses to the anonymous survey
is that you want more practice
working on tree processing problems
well today in lecture we'll talk about trees again
looking at them from an object oriented point of view
linked lists are a fundamental
data structure and computer science
they appear everywhere
and now we'll learn how to implement them
using python's object system
so a linked list is either
empty because it contains nothing
or it has the first value in some sequence
and then the rest of the values in the linked list
so here's how we're going to represent the sequence
3 4 5
we'll use an instance of a class called the link
I haven't defined that yet but I will soon
and that has two attributes
first which is three
and rest which is some object
now that object is holding the rest of the values
and it itself is also a linked list or a link instance
so every link list
has a smaller link list as the rest of the list
so this link instance has its first value as four
and the rest of its list is a link
instance whose first value is five
now
we've exhausted everything we're trying to represent
but we still need some rest attribute
in that case we use a special value called link empty
link empty is the exception to the rule
I just said that every linked list
has a rest of the list link
that empty doesn't have any first value
or any rest of the list
it just represents the fact that there's nothing left
so
the right way to think about a linked list is not this
particular class with these particular attribute names
but as a pair of values
it's a first element of some sequence
and then the rest of that sequence
in this case we're storing the first
actually the zero f element as an attribute value
I call it the zero
element because it will correspond to index zero
once we come up with a way of indexing into this list
the rest of the list is itself a linked list or link
empty and that's stored as another attribute
so you can have objects that are values of attributes
and here we're using the idea of composition
in order to construct an interesting structure
so a link list has a link list as its attribute value
finally there's some class attribute
that we use for any link list that's empty
and we call it link empty
now the way we construct this is not by writing three
come a four come a five
that would make a tuple
instead we have to write out the constructor
a link with three
and the rest of the list is a link with four
and the rest of that list is a link starting with five
and the rest of that list is link that empty
so each one of these calls to link
creates a new link instance
this call creates that instance
which must exist in order to make this call
which creates the lengthless starting with four
followed by five
now here the order in which
functions are evaluated in python is important
in order to evaluate link
for comma link five comma link mt
we have the first
evaluate this
operand sub expression
in order to create the link instance
that represents the sequence of starting a five
followed by nothing else
once that's created we can pass it in as an argument
to this link which starts with four
and is followed by all this other stuff
and then finally we can evaluate the whole expression
and build the whole linked list
now these structures are so common in computer science
that there are some conventions
about how they get drawn
typically
you do draw them as a sequence of pairs with arrows
like this
but instead of drawing an arrow to link that empty
it's very common to just put a slash there
this is not any sort of official notation
but you will see people do this out there in the world
so I thought I'd show you now
in our implementation
we're going to mirror this structure
by making link
empty the default value for the rest attribute
and that means you can leave it out
when you want to construct a link list
so we want this expression to actually
evaluate to a link instance
representing the sequence 3 4 5
and for that we need a class statement
in the link list class we just have an in it
method which takes in the first and the rest
so here's the class here's the in it method
as I mentioned before
we're going to have a default value for the rest
which is link empty
which I haven't yet to find
the first thing will do is make sure
that the linked list were constructing is well formed
it follows the property that I said
that the rest of the list either
has to be the empty list
link that empty
or it's an instance of the link class
meaning it's itself a linked list
so those
when the only two things were allowed to pass in
as the rest of the list
and then we store the first
element and the rest of the list as
attributes of the instant self
is instance is a built in function in python
that returns whether rest is a link
when past these two arguments
if you ask for the help from python on his instance
it will tell you that
it returns whether an object is an instance of a class
or of a subclass thereof
so it's a little bit different
than just getting the
type of rest and seeing if it's exactly
equal to link
this will also be true if rest
is an instance of a class that inherits from link
and this is a good idea
because now our system is extensible
if we want to build a special kind of link list
by inheriting from link
we can still use this same constructor
and this verification will still work out as we expect
so what is link that empty anyway
well here we have a choice in our implementation
I've chosen to represent it as the empty tuple
although I could have invented a special class
just for the empty linked list
instead I just picked some zero length sequence
because that's what it is it's a zero length sequence
okay let's see how it works
I can create a linked list
with three followed by four followed by five
if I call this s I can start inspecting its attributes
s dot first is three
s dot rest is four five
which means if I want to get the element four
what I need to write is s dot rest first
the first element of the rest of the list
I can access five by saying
the rest of the lists rests of the list's
first element that's five
and finally I can ask whether the rest
of the rest of the rest of the list
is link
empty and it should be because there's nothing there
so these are the ways
in which I'll manipulate a linked list
it is of course
possible to change the values within the list
I could set s rest 1st seven
then if I look at what s is
I find that it's three
he followed by seven followed by five
however
oftentimes
linkless are used in situations where you're not
mutating the values
that's where they're specially designed for
so you can create a list that's similar to another list
just by adding
a different value onto the front
so if I want to create a linked list that starts with
eight and then is followed by seven and five
I would do that just by writing
link eight followed by the rest of the list
writing this creates a new list
but it doesn't change the old one
recursion is very common in linked list processing
when constructing a new linked list
or taking an existing linked list
and doing something with it
let's look at some examples
ranges are built in
the map functions built in
and the filter functions built into python
but they don't operate on linked
lists because those are user defined
so if we want the same functionality
we'll have to implement our own notion of range
and map and filter
let's remember what these things do
if I have two functions like square
which takes an x and squares it
an odd which takes an x
and returns whether it's an odd number
then I could for example
write the following expression
using the built in map and filter in range
get the numbers one two three four and five
filter for only the odd ones
so now I have one three and five
and then map the square function over those
so one squared is one
three squared is nine and five squared is 25
those results will place in a list
the same kind of thing could be done with linked lists
using the class that we just defined
but the syntax will be slightly different
we'll have to come up with our map link function
which will implement momentarily
which takes the square
and square as all the elements of
the result of filtering a linked list
using the odd function
where we start with a
linked list representing the range 1 2 3 4 5
filter out the two and the four to just have one
three and five
the odd ones
square all of those and you get a linked list of one
nine and twenty five
so let's go through an implement range link
which has a starting integer and an ending integer
and returns a link containing consecutive integers
from start
including the start to end
not including the end
so the range link from three to six would be three
four and five
and will also write map link
which returns a new linked list
that contains ffx for every
x in the original linked list s
so if we square everything in the range three to six
then we get three squared
four squared and five squared
and will also write filter link
which returns a linked list that contains
only the elements
of link s for which
f called on that element returns a true value
so if we filter for only the odd elements of this range
that we get three and five
leaving out the four
actually
all of these are going to be recursive functions
so here's our link class
here's square and odd
and how do we build a range
well if it's the case
that starts as greater than you're equal to end
then there's nothing in the range
we return link
empty to represent an empty link list
otherwise there's at least one element in the range
and that is the start element
followed by some other stuff
return a link with start as the first element
and what's the rest of the range
while that is the range that starts at start plus one
and goes to the end
how do we take a function and map it over
all the elements in s
calling f on every single element
and building a linked list of the result
if it's the case that s is linked out empty
there's really no work to do
we could return s or return linked out empty
since those are just two
expressions for the same thing
it doesn't matter which one you write
otherwise you know there's at least one element
so let's call f on it
and we'll return a new linked list
with its first element being the result of calling f
on the first element of s
and then we need to call f on the rest of the elements
we do that with a recursive call to map link
where we're calling the same function f
on everything in s rest
and what about filtering
well if s is linked empty again
there's no elements to filter so will return s
otherwise I do think that we need to filter everything
in the rest of s
so let's get the filtered rest
which is the result of calling filter link
using that same f on the rest of s
but now we have to make a decision
is it the case that s dot first is in the result or not
well that depends on what you get
when you call f on s dot first
if that's a true value
then we need s dot first to be in the result
and what's everything else
while
that's the result of filtering the rest of the list
otherwise if this is a false value
then s dot first is not supposed to be in the result
so we can just return the filtered rest
let's check to see if our doctest saw work
oh they do so it should be the case
that if I start with a range
from one to six so that's one two three four and five
I filter it using odd
I map the square function over the result
then what I get is 1 9 16
and there it is
so since linked list several recursive structure
a natural way to process them is with recursion
like we've seen here in these examples
a linked list instance is an object
and all instances of a user defined class can be
changed or mutated
let's take a look at what happens
when you start changing the attributes
of a link instance
linkless can change
using attribute assignment statements
you can change
the first and rest attributes of a link instance
in fact an interesting consequence of this
is that the rest of a link list can contain the link
list as a sub list
so let's say I start with a link list
with three elements
one two and three
here's a sketch of what this might look like
the actual environment diagram is more complicated
but here's the essence of a link list
is that it's just two attributes the first and the rest
where the first is in this case in number
and the rest is another link instance
so here's the second one
if I assign estad first equals five
what I'm left with is 5 2 3
but it gets really interesting
when you come up with another name
for s tad rest
like t so that's the link list
two three and then we reassign the rest attribute
of a link instance
in this case we're assigning it to s
then s first first is five
and what's s rest rest rest rest rest first
we'll think about it
for a minute and see if you can figure it out
this is going to be the number two
one reasonable reaction is
how did we have so many dot rests
when we had a linked list that was only
three elements long
well back when we created it it had only three elements
but now it has a different structure
because we changed t dot rest
and t was part of s
what we've created is the following structure
we changed s dot first to five
we never changed s dot rest
we did give a name to it t
and we changed t dot rest
to refer to s
so when you evaluate
s dot rest dot rest dot rest dot rest dot rest first
you get the No.2
here's an example of linked list mutation
let's say we have an ordered list
with no repeated elements
and we want to maintain the fact
that s is an ordered list with no repeated elements
but write a function add
that places elements into the list
in the appropriate position
so that everything stays
ordered from least to greatest
so here's the function
add to a list s a value v
which modifies s to make sure that it contains v
and then returns that modified s
however if v is already in s
then we don't modify s
so that we don't have repeats in the list
but we still want to return s from the add function
now is a good time to pause the video
and try to write this function
I'm going to describe how it works in 321
when you add zero to s
we'll make sure that zero
is the element at the beginning
and that one comes after that
instead of rewriting all of the values in the list
we can do this
just by creating a new link instance
whose first element is one
changing s so that its first element is zero
and re routing
so that the
rest of s is the link instance whose rest is three
then five now we have a linked list
representing the sequence 0 1 3 5
instead of just 1 3 5
if we add three
we should
look through s until we find the place that three goes
and since we discover that three is already there
we're not going to modify s at all
we'll just return it
and what if we add four
well we look along here
until we figure out where four would go
between three and five
so that means we can change the five to a four
add a new link instance for the five
and now we have 0 1 3 4 5
and what if we add six
well that's actually a little bit different
we keep looking
until we find that we've reached the end
so instead of rest being linked empty
rest needs to be a new link instance
containing the six
that's how we add v into s
try to implement it
add v into s returning modified s
don't change s if v is already there
and make sure that s remains ordered
we assume that s is ordered at the beginning
and we have to place v
into s
so that the order remains from least to greatest
here are some examples
if s is 1 3 5 and we add zero then at 0 1 3 5
we add three and it doesn't change
we add four
and the four which shows up in the right place
and we add six it ends up at the end
and let's assume that s is not empty to begin with
how can we do it
well will assert s is not empty
and then if s dot versus is greater than v
we mutate s to by changing s dot first in s dot rest
if s dot versus less than v and s dot rest is empty
then we have to place a value at the end
if s dot rest is less than v we got to do something
and in the end we return s
why don't you pause and try to fill in the blanks
and we'll talk about it in 321
if s dot first is greater than v
then we place v as s dot first
and change s dot rest to contain the old s dot first
and the old s dot rest
that's building this link instance
or building this link instance
if esta first is less than v and the rest is empty
then we need to build this link instance by setting s
rest to a link
where v is the first element and the rest is empty
which is the default 2nd argument for link
otherwise
we keep looking for the place where we're going to put
v which is just a recursive call to add
we don't need to return
because we're going to return down here
we're always going to return s
the point of this call
is not to compute a value to return
but instead to perform the addition on the rest of s
another recursive computational data structure
is the tree
and we've already talked about trees in this class
but they're so
important that we should talk about them again
a tree is a lot like a linked list
a tree has a root label
and a list of branches that are trees
a linked list is a first element
and the rest of the list
so the main difference
is that a tree has multiple trees as branches
whereas a linked list has only one linked list
as the rest of the list
here's vocabulary that we've talked about before
but we'll do it again
there are two ways of describing trees
their recursive description
uses an analogy to wooden
trees growing out of the ground
except for that they grow down instead of up
a tree has a root label and a list of branches
here the root label is three
there's a branch and there's one other branch
each branch is a tree
a tree with zero branches is called a leaf
in this diagram there are five leaves
the leaves have labels as well
they just have no branches
a tree starts at the root
there's the root of the whole tree
there's the root of the left branch
there can be multiple branches or one or zero
and every single branch is another tree
meaning every single branch has another route
describing all of the different trees within a tree
often involves the term node
a node is a position or location within a tree
it's always another tree itself
but when using the term node
it's not so interesting to think about the sub trees
but instead just
their relative locations to other nodes
each node has a label
and each
node also has a configuration relative to other nodes
three is the parent of two
two is the child of three
the top node is the root node
and like I did just there
people often use labels to refer to locations
instead of saying
the node with label
two is the child of node with label three
it's often the case that people will just casually say
two is the child of three
but in fact it's the nodes that have
this family relationship
and their labels are just numbers
a path is a sequence of nodes
where each element is either the parent
or the child of the previous note
so they are connected in the tree diagram
and the most common paths are
paths from the route to a leaf
but you could have other kinds of paths as well
we were able to work with trees using data abstraction
but we can also use pythons object system
a tree has a label and a list of branches
each branch is also a tree
we can state this by defining a tree class
with a constructor that takes a label
and a list of branches which by default is empty
we set the label
we check that for every branch the branches a tree
and then we assign selftop branches
here we make a list of the branches
in order to retain a copy
and also to convert branches to a list
if it was something else
here was the definition using data abstraction
very similar but there are some important differences
now that we're using the object system
we define how to build a tree
but we don't have to explicitly define
how to get the different attributes out
of a constructed tree
in data abstraction
we wrote down the constructor and the selectors
here we write down the constructor
and the selectors are implicit
self dot label will give the label
and dot branches will give the branches
more importantly
when using data abstraction
we had to invent a way
of combining together the pieces
the label and the branches
in this case
we decided to put them all in one long list
but we could have done something else
put them in a pair put them in a dictionary
whatever we did
we had to come up with a method
for extracting those pieces back out
using the selector functions
when we use python's object system
we don't have to make any decisions
about how the pieces are combined
into a hole we always choose the same way
each part is an attribute
and an object has all of its attributes accessed
by their name
so the definition is a little bit simpler
using the object system
but using tree instances
is just like using the tree data abstraction
here's a definition
of a function that creates a fibonacci tree
and it's the same with flight differences
when I used the object system
I capitalized the word tree
and I access the label using dot notation
under data abstraction
I had a function called tree
and I accessed the label using a selector function
but our code doesn't change at all
so the coding style used an object oriented programming
is not
terribly different from the coding style used with
data abstraction
once I've defined the tree class
I can go ahead and use it
so a leaf I can create just by calling tree
if I want to add branches to that tree
I cannot do it just by passing in label values
I have to pass in a list of trees
this creates a tree which I'll call t
its repper string is an expression
that builds an equivalent tree
printing it out
gives a multi line output
where the route label comes first
and all of the other labels are indented
it's not a bad idea
to take a look at the code that
generates the repper string
and the stir string
to understand how it works
and we've added one more method is leaf
which returns whether there are no branches
and we've also defined the fib tree function
just like it was on the slides
fibtree four is a fairly large tree
fibtree five has fibonacci No.5 at the route
and fibtree six is looking quite large indeed
look at all those parentheseas and square brackets
but if I print this out
then it's easier to see the structure
eight at the route
two different branches
one has the route label three
the other has the route label five
and three plus five is eight
so what are the leaves of this tree
we have 0 1 1 0 1 1 0 1 etc
let's write down a function
that computes the leaves of a tree as a list
if t is a leaf then will return a list with one element
the label of the tree
otherwise we need to build up a list of all the leaves
let's start with an empty list
and for every bnt
branches we'll make a recursive call to leaves on b
and what do we do with that
well we're gonna add all of its elements to all leaves
which is one of the built in methods on a list
which one
while we want to extend the list of all leaves
with the new list of leaves that we get
by recursively calling leaves
on the branch v
then we can return all of these leaves
and if we call leaves on fib tree six
we get a list of leaves that's some to eight
which is fibonacci No.6
and what's the height of this tree
well the height of a leaf is zero
and the height of a tree in general
is the number of transitions in its longest path
we go from here
to one transition
two transitions three transitions
four transitions five
I think the height of fibtree six is five
how could we compute that
if t is a leaf
then the height is zero
otherwise the height is one more
than the maximum height of any branch
so let's compute height b
for b in tw branches and take the maximum value
there's fib tree six
and what's its height five
so everything we've learned about processing trees
is the same
whether I use data abstraction or I use the tree class
but we get some nice advantages using the tree class
like a nice way of displaying trees
using this simple recursive
stir function
here's a tree processing example
where we actually change the tree instance
removing some of the subtrees of a tree is called
pruning
either you remove some of the branches
or remove some branches of the branches etc
when possible it makes sense to
first prune the branches of the current tree
then recursively prune whichever branches are left over
you can prune a branch before you remove that branch
but since you're removing the whole branch
why not remove it first and only prune what's left
so here's an example tree
and let's say we want to prune
all of the sub trees whose root label is one
this zero goes because it's part of this subtree
here's a template
pause for a moment and try to fill it in
and I'll go over the solution in 321
the key here is to modify tw branches
by setting it equal to a new list
we could also change the old tw branches list
but we achieved the same effect
by building a new list with a list comprehension
for every branch in the tree
I'm going to keep it in t dot branches
if its label is something other than in
now t dop branches
might not have all the old branches in it
so this says iterate through the branches that remain
calling each one b
and prune that branch using n as the label
were looking to prune and that's it
we don't need to return
because the purpose of the prune function
is to remove subtrees
not to compute a new value