61 a election No.13
announcements
the cats project is due on Friday
but phase one
is do Tuesday if you want to earn the checkpoint
which is one point
and all you have to do to get that one point
is finish all the phase one problems by Tuesday
you can get an early submission bonus point
for submitting the whole project by
Thursday or earlier
today's lecture and wednesday's lecture
will not be covered on exams or assignments
but it's really interesting stuff that you should know
it's just that there's plenty of other
things that will test you on
and you will see these topics in future courses
but you should certainly have some exposure to them now
and hopefully
these two lectures will help increase your depth of
understanding
about how computers are actually
representing the programs that you're running
enjoy
welcome back
expend the better part of this semester talking about
python data structures algorithms classes
object oriented programming
and if you'll recall
one of the
themes in all of this is the power of abstraction
the power of compartmentalizing either data or code
so that the nitty gritty details of it
don't have to be
part of our work
in writing code around that
and there's a really powerful notion of abstraction
and in the last part of this course I want to talk
in some ways about the ultimate obstruction
which is a computer
we use these things routinely
whether they're handheld devices laptops or desktops
and they're remarkable they do incredible computations
do we know exactly how it works
well for the most part no
it's an abstraction
we know that when we turn on the computer
and save a file
something happens
we know when we turn on a computer
and ask
the computer to add two numbers or divide two numbers
just sort of works
but how how is that nature of that computation working
and because I think it's important to
understand this very
tool that we are using at a daily basis
we're going to spend the last part of this class
talking about that abstraction
which is how do modern day computers
now obviously
this can't go into every little biddy
nitty gritty detail of how a modern day computer works
but I'm going to
show you the building blocks of a modern day computer
and what is I think
really truly remarkable
about that is how incredibly simple they are
so let's go ahead and dive in first
and see how computers actually work
alright so
let me first start talking about the language
of modern day computers
which are binary numbers
but before I do that
let me talk about the numbers that we all know in love
which are base 10 numbers
and then we'll talk a little bit about binary numbers
so when I say the No.7 23
you and I have a common language
what do I mean by that
the language is that we know that this number
is in base 10
what does that mean
that means that the seven
corresponds to the 101th position
tend to the power to
the two corresponds to the 10th position
10 to the power one
and the three corresponds to the oneth position
10 to the power zero
and we don't I don't have to say seven twenty three
base 10 it's assumed
we all work in base 10 unlike languages
metric versus non metric
there are many
other conversions that we always have to worry about
so when I say a temperature
fair and height of southeas when I say a distance
kilometers or meters
and so but one of the nice things
about numbers is that we've agreed on a base 10 okay
and that's the language of numbers and it's implicit
but really there is
a rationale behind this number which is that this is
seven times a hundred
plus two times 10+3 times one
and I'm going to
because this is how we're going to be doing things
in base tenors
remind you that the one hundredths place
the 10th place and the one place
are just successive powers of power of ten
so 10 to the
0 1 10 to the 1 10 10 to the 2100 and obviously
10 to the 31,000 and so on and so forth
and that's what we mean by base 10
is that this base is being raised to an exponent
and that forms the base
and then we multiply by whatever number
is in that position
so for example
if I had the number
five thousand three hundred and forty nine
that would correspond to
five times 10 of the 3+3 times 10 of the two
four times 10 of the one and nine times 10 to zero
and again when I give you this number
I don't have to tell you base 10 it's agreed upon
we've sort of pre agreed on this
but we should agree that it's sort of arbitrary
why base 10
well you know some people think it's because of this
it's a pretty good fit actually
base 10 because this is how we count on our fingers
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
right but
there are if you look through history
other civilizations that have used different numbers
my favorite example this is my father
my father when he counts he does one
2 3 4 5 6 7 8 counting with the thumb
I don't know what he does when he gets to nine and ten
you can only count up to eight
base eight is a perfectly fine number right
so what does it mean
for two fifty seven to be represented in base eight
it means that the
base is now not 10
there it is right there and they're there
it's eight so it's this
two corresponds to two times eight to the power two
this five corresponds to the base eight to the power 1
and eight to about two
so notice that this number
this number and this number are exactly the same
except I simply replaced
in the previous example 10 with eight
and then of course the exponents work out
and so two fifty seven
base eight can be converted to base 10
by simply working through this arithmetic
and that's 175
so you could imagine a world
where some societies work in base eight
and some work in base 10
and we'd have to convert units the same way we convert
temperature distance weights between
metric and non metric
it'd be annoying but we could do it
and there's nothing fundamentally wrong with this base
and there's nothing
fundamentally right about this base
you can represent all the numbers
they just have a different meaning
now
base two is a perfectly valid base as well
notice by the way
that numbers in base two only have two numbers 0 1
so numbers in base 10 have 10 numbers 0 1 2 up to nine
numbers in base seven only have eight numbers zero
to seven and numbers in base two only have two numbers
zero and one okay
so if I give you the number zero one one zero
and I ask you what is that in say base 10
well then we play the same game
this leading zero is multiplied by
two to the power three
this one is multiplied
which of course is that one right there
times two to the two
two to the one two to the zero
work out that those powers of two so it's 8 4 2 1
those two are multiplied by zero so they go away
the one and the four are multiplied by one
four plus two is six so that's base 10
nothing right or wrong about base two
I can represent any number
that I can represent in base 10
which I can represent in base eight
or base four or base 16 for that matter
okay so the bases are arbitrary
that's the point here they are arbitrary
we can represent all the numbers
they just have a different representation
that's all and the reason of
doing this is because modern computers talk
in binary numbers
they have two numbers that they can represent 0 in 1
and I'm going to talk a little bit about why that is
and then we're going to see how we get from
that language of
modern day computers
to actual computations on binary numbers
but of course we have to understand the language
before we
understand what's actually being done on that language
all right so for example
because computers
have finite memory and finite precision
we always have to specify how many bits
we will be talking about in our binary number
so unlike base 10 I can just give you a number
five thousand three hundred and seventy one
twenty seven eight
I don't have to say this is a four bit or a five bit
or a one bit but in binary numbers
because everything
has to have the same length representation
we're going to always specify how many bits
are available to us
and simply by bits I mean how many
powers of two do I have so a two bit
finery number says that you can have a bit in the
first position two to the power zero
and you can have a bit in the second position
two to the power one
and that's it
now with a two bit binary numbers
you can walk through and figure out
how many possible
numbers can I represent if I only have two bits
well I can represent 0 0 0
I can represent one zero one
two one zero and three one one and that's it
there's no other bits
so now
when I restrict the number of bits
and by binary numbers
now I do have a restriction
I can only represent numbers between zero and three
that's true a base 10 ii I could have said
you have no more than two decimal places
or two positions
then you can only represent numbers between zero and
909 and there is no 100
so the same thing holds
sure I'm just going to now start fixing the bitch
and you'll see a little bit why that is
so let's just make sure we understand this
so why is this zero
because this number in base 10 is zero
times two to the z
plus zero times two to the 1 0
what's this No.1
times two to the zero that's 1 0 times two to the one
so that's zero so that's the one
okay zero there
and then the one times two that's that
and then of course I have 2+1 is three
and notice that with a two bit binary number
I will always
if they're always positive
we'll get to negative numbers in a little bit
I can always go from zero to two to the power 2-1
so in this case that's
four two to the 2-1 is three
okay so if I give you a three binary number
my maximum value is two to the power three that's eight
by the way if you're going to be a computer scientist
you have to get really good at powers of two
one two four eight sixteen thirty two sixty four
one twenty eight
two fifty six five twelve ten twenty four
you can stop there
ten twenty forty eight is after that that was easy to
okay so maximum power of two is maximum
sorry
largest number is two to the power three that's 8-1
probably
why the minus one because I'm starting to count zero
so notice I have three bit binary number
starting from the right
this is the two to the zero position
two to the one position two to the two position
and you should be able to convince yourself
that you can get every number here
by doing the conversion I just did
so let's let's do say five here
so how do I know that this is five
this is two to the zero what's that one
that's a zero so I don't care
this is two to the two that's four
four plus one is five
go through each one of these please
at least in your head and make convince yourself
that you get these numbers here
okay so that's a three bit binary number
I can count between zero
and four bit binary number
same game two to the four is 16
minus one is 15
that's the maximum number we have all fours there
minimum numbers all zeros of course
again two to the 0 2 to the one
two to the three two to the four
so let's look for example at
this number right here 11
why is that 11
well let's go from this side
so this is two to the four
which two to the four is 8+2 to the two
that is sorry two to the one that's two that's ten
and two to the zero is one that gives me 11
and again
pick a couple numbers here and convince yourself
that these are the decimal base 10 numbers
correspond to these four bit binary numbers
okay
now the question you want to add is why am I doing this
did fundamental to computers
or is it that there's a reason for it and it is not
fundamental to
but there's a really good reason for it
which is
that representing binary numbers in a computer
is incredibly reliable
and let me tell you what I have
so information of course on the computer is stored
but in terms of electrons
that's how computers are powered
and so
we have to be able to represent different numbers
so imagine I want to represent say
base 10
let's say I wanted my modern computer to be base 10
which means I have to represent the number zero
one two three four five six seven eight nine
and let's say that the way I'm going to rep it
let me do an analog to how the electrons work is
I have a little test tube
and I'm going to fill that test tube with water
to the level that corresponds to the number
and then that
test tube will correspond or represent that number
so here's a zero
it filled up to level zero here's a four
it fills the four
six and seven
okay nothing wrong with that perfectly fine
but what if that water level was a little unstable
what if it was shaking around
and it was moving around a little bit
and that means a zero
might accidentally look like
a one every once in a while
and a seven may accidentally look like a six
or an eight because of a little bit of instability
now obviously this is not water in a modern computer
but these are electrons
electrons have a little bit of instability
it's difficult to keep that
level at exactly the right level
and so to distinguish
between 10 distinct levels
is just not very reliable in a computer
and what is reliable
is distinguishing only between two things
so here's my test tube again with water in it
if it's empty it's a zero
if it's full it's a one
and now you can imagine if there's a little slop here
this goes down to eight and this goes up to one
and it slops around
I can still distinguish between those
so we want representations that are incredibly
distinct from each other
and when you have to do 10 levels
you have to have a much finer resolution if you will
and if you only have two levels
it's actually
easier to deal with fluctuations in the internal
physical representation
and that's in a nutshell while we use binary numbers
okay good
so what have we done at this point
we've said that
binary numbers are the language of modern computers
now it's not entirely clear what I mean by that
still what do I mean by language
right so when it comes to numbers
sure I'm going to use base two instead of base tent
but what about letters and street
strings and other things
we'll get to that in a little bit
so the language of modern computers is
we are going to talk in base two
the reason we're going to talk in base two
is because of the reliability
with only having to store two states 0 1
now at this point
I've shown you how to represent using an n
bit binary number
numbers between zero
and two to the n minus one
that's the maximum number you can represent
but obviously
there's other things I'd like to represent
what about negative numbers
what about floating point numbers what about strings
so what we're going to do when we pick it up
after the selection
is we're going to start talking about
how to do things like
negative numbers
and then we'll talk about fractions
and then once we get that and once we
understand the language of modern computers
binary numbers
we're going to talk about the nature of computation
how do computers actually compute
on these binary representations
all right that's it for not
we'll pick it up in a few minutes see you soon
welcome back we just talked about binary numbers
and how we can represent number
positive numbers
between zero and two to the n minus one
with an end bit binary number
now obviously
just the positive numbers is only
one aspect of what you need to do
in a modern computer
so you need to be able to do things like negative
numbers and fractions and other things
so let's talk about negative numbers first
so how do we encode negative numbers again
we don't get a minus sign right
this isn't like we're writing
algebra on a piece of paper
there are only
two things we can represent on a computer
zero and one that's it
everything has to be done with those two
bits of information
okay and so we can't just put a negative sign
in front of something that doesn't exist
so we have to somehow figure out how to use
series of zeros and ones to represent
both positive and negative numbers
and fractions and so on and so forth
well so here's one idea
we can just put a zero in front of an end
binary number and that represents a positive number
and a one represents a negative number
and I could have switched these
doesn't matter
just something we come up with some standard
some language that you and I are
the computer and I agree upon
okay so let's look at that
and let's see what that would look like
so let's say I give you now a three bit
signed binary number
and notice here I've been very careful
when I give you these binary numbers
to tell you what it corresponds to
because if I had just given you these
this could have been a three bit unsigned binary number
and this would have been the two to the two position
two to the one position two to the zero
but I'm telling you now this is a three bit
signed binary number
and so starting from the right
this is the two to the 0 2 to the one
but then this is the sign
zero is positive one is negative
and look by the way you notice here that
so all four of those are zero
and then the numbers go zero zero 11 011
all of these are one those are negative
same thing 0 0 0 1 1 0 1 1
so you see you get the negative numbers here
the positive numbers here
good
so if that's the sign as we agree
and then I have a two bit binary number
well we know what that is
this is 0 1 2 3
let's just make sure we understand that
this is three because it's two to the power zero
times 1+2
the power one times one so that's 2+1 is three
so same thing as we did in the previous lecture
okay so what about the four numbers below
well obviously these are negative numbers 1 1 1 1 1
so what is the negative number
well it's whatever is in the two bit position
so that's three
so this is -3
that's two that's -2 that's one that's -1
well this is a little odd
now I have a -0 which of course is the same as zero
so that's a little
bit of an odd thing
with this representation
we essentially have two zeros a positive in the -0
that's not great
there's actually other problems with using this type of
leading bit for the sign
which I'm going to show you in a little bit
and this in fact is not
what modern computers use they do not use this
it seems like a really easy thing to do
and frankly it's good for us as humans
because I can look at that first bit
and as long as I know what it is
I can immediately tell you whether it's positive
or negative
and then I'd have to interpret all the bits beyond that
but as it's going to turn out for computers
it's a pretty clumsy representation
and instead of doing
the assigned representation
we are going to do what's called the two's
complement representation
so let me describe what I mean by that
so we need again a mechanism
to represent positive and negative numbers
okay so I'm going to start with an unsigned
so that means that first bid
has nothing to do with the sign
right now
for bid binary number
where the left most bit is always zero
okay so this bit is going to be the sign
but not in the way that I showed you before
okay so this number must be a zero
for it to be a positive number
okay and then this of course is two to the two
two to the one two to the zero
so let's make sure we understand why that's six
this is two to the one that's two
two to the two that's four
four plus two is equal to six
okay good and so we start with an unsigned
four bit or five bit or six bit or whatever you want
where the left most bit is zero
and that zero of course is going to
correspond to positive numbers
but again not in the same ways above
and you're going to see in a minute why that is
now to make that number to get -6
here's what I'm going to do
so we know how to do all the positive numbers
right it's a zero in the fourth position
and then you just run through
all of the
two to the 3-1 possibilities for these three bets
good
how do I make -6 so here's what you do
take that representation of six and flip the bits
it's called complementing the bits
so zero goes to one one goes to 0 1 goes to zero
zero goes to one
that's the complement where every bit has been flipped
notice that by definition
that first position must be a one
why well because that is by definition to zero
and when I flip that it's going to be a one
so anything that has a one in that
significant position will be negative
but the interpretation is not the same
is what I showed you up top
because that obviously is not six right there
that's something else
okay so we have to figure out what that actually means
okay so complement your binary number and then add one
okay so here's my 6 0 in the most significant position
compliment it
all the zeros go to one
all the ones go to zero and then add one
so what does it mean to add one to here well 1+1 is two
that means I carry the one drop the zero
the one comes down right there and I've got 1 0 1 0
that is -6
now what's odd about this representation
is if I look at those just these three bits right here
that doesn't look like six
two to the 0 2 to the one that's a two
so we can't look at this and just say oh
the way we did with
either positive numbers or with the signed
the non Tuesday complement sign thing
it's a slightly different representation
and it seems like we've taken a step backwards
this doesn't seem better
it seems worse it seems more complicated
but it's going to turn out that this is not written
for you and me
it's written for the computer
and I'm going to show you in a minute why
this is a really nice representation
of negative numbers for computers
even if for us
it's a little bit harder to read
all right so let's look at this now
let's say I have a three bit
signed using two's complement binary number
all right so let's do the easy ones
so the positive zero through three is what
we must have a zero in the most significant place
so that means there's only four possible numbers
two to the 2-1
and that's the same as before
0 0 0 1 1 0 1 1 good
so that's obviously three
two plus one that's two that's one that's zero good
now I want the negatives of these
now there's this
thing with zero we're going to have to sort out
remember
in the previous one with the signed representation
we get this two different representations of zero
we'll come back to that in a minute
how do I get the negative number of a positive number
I complement the number flip the bits
I add one and that will give me
the negative representation
of that positive number
so let's just go ahead and do it for all of these
and we'll also see what happens to that
zero right there
okay so let's just start with one
and I'll come back to the zero in a minute
so please if you will complement 0 0 1 that's 1 1 0
add one to that
so you can do this in good old fashion
what you learned in grade school
you put a one under here you add those two
you add these two you add these two
remembering to carry in doing
one bit edition
binary edition rather
so that 0+1 is one and then there's nothing to carry
so 1 1 0 the complement of this plus one is this
that is -1 that's it that's the representation
let's do this one
let's flip the bit
0 1 0 gives me 1 0 1 0 goes to one one goes to zero
add one please
okay what's one plus one two
what's two in binary 1 0
so the one carries
into this position and the zero comes down
then 1+0 is one and then I got of one
so I've got 1 1 0 that is -2
okay and notice again that this position here
must always be a one
because when I flip the bits
I'm always going to have that zero flip into a one
let's do one more
flip three which is 0 1 1 it goes to 1 0 0
add one that of course is just 1 0 1
that is -3 okay
now let's see what happens with zero
you can sort of see what's going to happen by the way
so what happens when I complement zero zero
I get 1 1 1 and what happens when I add one to this
well okay so let's put the one here
I'm going to carry the one and drop the zero
that's two
again I'm going to carry the one drop the zero
again I'm going to carry the one and drop the zero
so I've got all zeros
and then there's this one which we call it overflow
it's the fourth bit
but I've only got a three bit number
that 4th bit it goes away we can't represent that
and so I end up with ah very nice zero
so this is one very nice thing about
two's complement is that the two's complement of zero
is zero
now one of the strange things about two's compliment is
these numbers are a little cryptic right
if I just give you this number
it's not immediately obvious that's negative to
-1 or -3
you have to sort of reverse the process to get back
but I'm going to show you that for a computer
this representation is fantastic
because it makes things like arithmetic very easy
and by the way we only have 1 0
which is just a nice thing to have
okay
so one odd thing here is we seem to have lost a number
why I've got 0 1 2 3
and I've got zero which is the same zero
and then I've got negative one negative two
negative three
so I only have seven numbers
but with three bits
if this was an unsigned binary numbers
how many numbers should I have with three bits
two to the 3-1
I should have eight number
seven numbers right from zero to seven
I've only got 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
where did that last number go
huh well something's missing yeah
so where is it let's see
well okay
I see that I have four numbers starting with a zero
but I see they only have
three numbers starting with a one
so which one is missing can you see it
good 1 0 0 it's not in here
okay now what is 1 0 0 correspond to
well it's the sort of weird tooth complement number
I don't know
but I do know this I know it's a negative number
so how do I figure out what the positive core it is
well I've got to run this process in reverse
so what do I do I have to subtract a one from here
complement again and then I get the positive number
and by the way why do I complement again
how is that the inverse
well if I go from zero to one by flipping
I can go from one to zero by flipping again
so if you complement a number twice you get back to it
so the inverse of complementing is just complementing
all right so let's figure out what this is
what is this number
I mean you sort of know it's probably negative for
but let's convince ourself of it
all right so let's do 1 0 0
we're gonna subtract one
we're gonna complement and let's see what we get
all right what's one zero zero minus one okay
so a couple of ways you can do those
here's one
you can just write out the binary numbers in order
there's 1 0 0
and you can subtract one by
seeing that the previous number
is just 0 1 1
okay good so
one zero zero minus one is 0 1 1
let's complement the bits
so that's going to give me 1 0 0
ah
so what is that 1 0 0
so this is now the positive number
notice by the way there's a one there
which looks weird
because there should be by definition is zero
but this is the negative number
we're simply reversing it
so this is two to the 0 2 to the one two to the two
that's four here which must mean that it's -4 over here
all right good
so
now what we have is an interesting a symmetry
if I had an end bit unsigned binary numbers
I would be able to go from zero
to two to the un minus one
so I'd have two to the end total numbers
but the max number would be two to the un minus one
with a
n bit signed using two's complement binary number
I go from minus two to the un minus one
to two to the un minus one
minus one that is there's one less positive number
than negative number
let's make sure this makes sense to us yeah
so in this case what do I have and is three
right so if I have n is three
then what is this representation
so it's two to the 3-1 which is two
two to the two is four so that's my -4 here
I've got 4-1 so that's three right there
so there's a slight asymmetry
and by the way why is there an asymmetry
just because there's only 1 0 now
right so you're going to have
one more on one side than the other
and it just turns out you have one more negative number
it turns out in practice this doesn't matter at all
but notice the slight asymmetry here
okay
so why I mean this just seems like an awful lot of work
and a lot awful lot of hassle to do this to complement
because now I can't read these two's complement numbers
truly
I've got to go to subtracting one and complementing it
so why am I doing this
well one reason is
you get the single zero representation
and that's nice
but here's the real reason
is that when you do arithmetic with two's complement
it works out beautifully
and let me show you how that works
alright so let's go back to unsign binary numbers
and let's just do some binary arithmetic
so let's say I want to add 2+2
that's my of course in base 10
let's write out the four
bit binary representation of two
two to the 0 2 to the one
two to the two two to the three
so two is just one times two to the one
and then zero everywhere else
so there's two there's two
alright how do I add
same way I add in base 10
so just column by columns 0+0 is zero
one plus one is two
two in binary is one
I carry the one and I drop the zero
so now I've got one plus zero plus zero that's one
and then I've got zero
so that is
the four bit some of these two
for bit numbers
and of course what is this well that's two to the
0 2 to the one two to the two
that's four and that's of course four
so in the same way that I can add in base 10
I can add in base two
you just add up but you just do everything in base two
so let's see how this works if we use the old fashioned
signed representation the non tubes complement
okay
so let's sum up two in -2 of course that should be zero
well in the old fashioned assigned representation
two is what 0 0 1 0
that zero tells me it's positive
and I get the three bits to represent every number
between zero and
two to the un minus one
which in this case of seven
now to make this negative I simply flip that bit to one
and everything stays the same
I love this representation
I find it really easy to read
I don't have to go through all this
sort of computation
to go from tooth compliment back to
the regular binary so I can figure it out
but let's see what happens when we try to add
these two things up
okay zero plus zero zero
one plus one is what two
watch two carry the one drop the zero
so now I've got one plus zero plus zero is one
and then I've got 0+1 is one
and that's what I get is that zero
absolutely not
so the simple
even the simple and by the way this makes sense
it shouldn't be zero because
these aren't
numbers in the same way they represent sign
so this makes no sense at all
and so doing that simple arithmetic with sign numbers
simply doesn't work
and by the way that's not an accident
take any two positive negative numbers
try to add them up and you won't get zero
so here's three here's -3
sum them up you get this mess here
which of course is not zero
but when you do this with two's complement
it's really nice how this works out so let's find out
alright so let's add two in -2
now here's the drawback
what is -2 and two's complement
well I got to do the calculation
okay fine let's do the calculation
so -2 is I complement this number and add one
so please complement from a 0 0 1 0 that's up here
those zeros turn into ones
the ones turns into zeros
and then I add one and I get that number right there
okay good
so that in two's complement is -2
let's drop that down
and now let's add the old fashioned way
all right 0+0 is zero
1+1 is two carry the one drop the zero
one plus one is two
carry the one drop the zero
carry the one last time drop the zero
that one by the way is an overflow
it's the fifth bit it's get flush don't care about it
and now I've got zero
so notice this very beautiful representation
allowed me to do simple bit edition
which by the way
is where all the magic is in computers
doing those types of computations
and it's incredibly simple
let's do another example to show you that's not a fluke
so in twos complement four bit twos complement
this is still a three
two to the 0 1 2 to the one that's two so 2+1 is three
so that's three
and then of course that number has to be a zero
for deposit of number
let's figure out what -3 is all right go back up here
complement
the zeros turns into ones the ones turn into zero
add one I go from 1 1 0 0 to 1 1 0 1
that right there is -3
drop it down
add up alright 1+1 is two carry the one drop the zero
one plus one plus zero is two
carry the one drop the zero
one plus zero plus one is two
carry the one drop the zero last one
one plus zero plus one is two carry the one
that's an overflow it's our 5th bit
drop the zero and you get zero
so when you add
two and bit two's complement binary numbers
simple binary arithmetic just works
and that is really beautiful and by the way
not at all obvious
when we set out to do this
it seemed like we were doing this weird thing
and this representation that's hard for us to read
but it turns out it's incredibly nice for the computers
because it allows computation
to happen very nicely
okay this is great
we now have positive numbers and negative numbers
we need a little bit more
and then we're going to start looking at the
nature of computation
on binary numbers
all right we'll see you in a few minutes
welcome back
so at this point we've now seen how to represent
positive
and negative numbers in a binary representation
and of course the binary representation
is the language of modern computers
I just want to do a little bit more
just to make sure we have a really firm
understanding of this language
and then we'll start talking about computation
let me remind you also again
that we have different types of binary numbers
we have unsigned
binary numbers where if you have an n bit binary number
you can represent from zero to two to the n minus one
posit vintage 0 1 2 3 etc
if you have a signed representation
you use the first bit to represent sign
zero as positive one as negative
but we saw that that leads to some problems
multiple zeros and
bit wise edition doesn't seem to work out
so in fact we're going to be using two's complement
for negative numbers
zero in the first place is still positive
one in the first place
is still negative
but the numbers have a different meaning
and we saw that this very nicely in the previous
lecture gave rise to being able to do addition
with two's complement binary number
and everything works out very nicely
so
just to make sure that we're all in the same page here
let's do a couple of exercises
and remember again
that whenever I give you a binary number like this
I have to
I have to tell you how it is being represented
I have to say for example this is a four bit
signed with two's complement binary number
because if I just said it's a four bit binary number
could be on sign 0 2 2 to the 4-1
if this was the plus or minus here
then these numbers mean something different
so I always always always have to tell you if I ask you
what is 0 1 1 1 in decimal
and that's all I ask you
you have to say
you have not given me enough information
I need information to be able to decode this
okay so if I tell you that this is a four bit
signed using two's complement binary number
what is that number in decimal
okay so let's think it through
what do we know about
that position that corresponds to the sign
if it's zero it's a positive number
and if it's one it's negative
and if it's one
not only is it a negative
but it's in that two's complement representation
which we have to undo
but if it's positive
I'm home I actually know what this number is what is it
it's just two to one times two to the 0+1
times two to the 1+1 times two to the two
so four plus two plus one okay
is equal to of course seven
good so if the end bit
sign two's complent binary number starts with a zero
it's a positive number
you simply decipher
all of the bits after that most significant bit
now on the other hand if it's 1 0 1 1
now we have to do a little bit of work
because it's not enough
to just take this number and try to convert it
because that's not
the positive number
all right so this one tells me it's negative
which means I have to undo
the twos compliment
alright how did I get twos compliment
I complement flip the bits add one
how do I undo
I subtract one and I complement it again
and that's of course because the complement
is its own inverse
because when I flip from zero to one
the way I go back is just flip from m one to a zero
all right so let's do that
let's subtract one from 1 0 1 1
all right well if I just put a one here and I subtract
that position goes to zero
so I get 1 0 1 0
let's flip the bits so the one becomes a zero
the zero becomes a one
and now I have this
so good there's a zero in that position
and if there's not you've done something wrong
because when I undo the two's complement
I better get a positive number
so that's not a zero
something's wrong go back and check your arithmetic
now what do I have
I have a positive number
that I can decipher in the same way that I just
did it earlier
two to the 0 2 to the one two to the two
all right two to the zero is one
two to the one two to the two is four
four plus one is five
so this number
it as encoded as a four bit
two's complement binary number is
sorry this number is five
so this number is of course -5
okay good so practice that make sure you can go between
binary numbers and decimal numbers
and make sure that you
understand how this two's complement
with the adding and the subtracting and the complement
works
okay so at this point now we have positive
and negative numbers okay
and we have a couple ways of representing the negative
and we're going to stick with the two's complement
from now on
that is the representation we will be using
so obviously if we are going to do computation
arithmetic edition subtraction division
we need to also be able to encode fractional numbers
and I can actually spend a fair amount
of time talking about that
but I'm not going to
and so I'm going to just mention very briefly how
fractional numbers are represented in binary
and the way they are represented
is with 1 2 3 4 5 parts
so there is a mentissa
which is plus or minus that's two parts
there is the base
and then there is an exponent
with also has a plus or minus
so two parts for the exponent
the actual exponent
and then whether it's positive or negative
and the mentissa
and whether it's positive negative and then a base
so for example what do I mean by this
if I want to represent
o I would have a mantissa of one
the bass would say b 10 and the exponent would be zero
if I want to do 0.1
then this exponent would be minus one and so on a sofa
so this is just good old fashioned scientific notation
and notice
why this is nice for representing fractional numbers
is because that's an integer
that's an integer and that's an integer
and I know how to do integers and binary numbers
and in fact I know how to do signed
integers and that's what that
so all I have to do is represent one signed integer
another signed integer the mantis in the exponent
and then whatever the base is
and once I've got that
I pack them all together
and I've got fractional numbers
okay good
so at this point now we have enough of a language
there's a little bit more we could talk about
but I'm going to stop here
because I want to get into the nature of computation
so at this point
we have the language of modern day computers
which is binary numbers
and we know how to represent positive
numbers and negative numbers
and fractional numbers
okay and now what we want to start asking ourselves is
how do I do computations how to build a calculator
right for example how do I do
in excel spreadsheet
add two numbers subtract two numbers
divide two numbers do modular
division and that's what we're going to see
nexus how do we go from this binary representation to
actual computation
and what's going to be really
magical here is how incredibly simple it is
there's really only going to be
three things we have to learn
and three things only
and we're going to be able to build
the basics of a modern computer
okay we'll pick it up in a few minutes see you soon
now we're ready to start talking about
the nature of computation
using binary numbers as representations
so let me start
with a very simple idea
that I'm going to have you think about
the binary No.1 as true
and the binary No.0 as false
and the reason I'm going to do this
is I'm going to introduce
blue and logic
which are all familiar with very simple concept
but to do that
it makes it a little bit easier to just think about
we're going to operate on true and false hood okay
where one is two and zero is false
okay so just simple translation in your head
okay so let me remind you what
the boolean operators are
there are three of them
logical and logical or and logical not
okay
and these have the plain text reading of those words
so if I tell you
it is sunny outside and it's warm outside
it means both are true
if I tell you that it is sunny outside
or it's warm outside
one or both are true
and if I tell you it is not sunny outside
well then it's not sunny outside
so it has that saint that logical plain text reading
but let me go ahead and define it formally
with so called truth tables
so my truth table here has four rows and three columns
the first two columns
denote the values of my two inputs
a and b so when I compute logical land
I ask for the end of two things sunny and warm
and then I output to you the logical end of them
there are four possibilities here which correspond to
all possible inputs
why well
there's two inputs
and they can each take on two values
so there's four permutations
0 0 0 1 1 0 1 1
the order I put in here doesn't really matter
okay what is the logical and
of two statements that are true
so if a is true and b is true
remember again here that I'm
substituting about these is true where it's one
and false word zero
if a is true and b is true
then the and is true good
in all other cases the logical land is false
so if this is true and this is false
then they're both not true
if this is false and this is true they're both not true
and if they're both false
you better believe that the end is also false
so for a logical and operator the only time
that the end of two things is true
is when they are both true
okay good simple calculation
and it's a computation by the way
it's got an input and it's got an output
it's pretty simple computation but it's a computation
all right let's do the logical or same truth table
this side stays exactly the same
two columns for the input one column for the output
and there are four
rows corresponding to exact same things 0 0 1 0 1 1
now remember that an or is true if
one or more of the statements are true
so here they're both true so the or is true
a is true so the or is true
b is true so the or is true
and here of course neither are true
so the or of them is false
okay so that's a logical or
now logical not has only one input
so the not of something you don't not two things
so now I only have two columns my input and my output
and I only have two rows
which are the values that a can take on
which is zero or one
true or false
and the nod is it's sort of like complementing a bit
so the not of true is false the not of false is true
so those are the three logical operators
okay now
I've already said this but let me emphasize it again
you can think about this as computation
I have an input a and b
and I do a computation
in this case is a look up in a truth table
and I have an output
and notice that the input is a boolean variable
0 1 true false
and the output is also a boolean variable true false
so everything is staying within that boolean construct
and of course I care about that
because we're going to be building a computer
with only the ability to represent zero or one
okay
so now here's the beautiful thing about logical and
logical or logical not
the ability to compute those three things
on two binary inputs or on a nod on one
is the building blocks of a modern day computer
they are completely built
I'm being able to do those three incredibly simple
and surprisingly simple calculations
so what I'm going to do is I'm going to take
this truth table and I just want to abstract it out
and render it or draw it or just depict it
as this thing right here
so this is called the gate
we're going to be talking about that
in a little bit more detail
and it simply
think of it as sort of a graphical representation
of this computation
two inputs come in a and b
those are my first two columns
some computation happens
that determines if both of them are true
we'll talk about that in a little bit
how we're going to build this for you
and then outcomes an output
so zeros or ones come in here
two columns here
zero or one comes out here
this and inside of here is a computation
we don't know how it works yet it's abstracted out
but we'll show you that in a little bit
so this is called a logical and gate
that's drawn as this big d
and we often draw a little dot in there
because sometimes our drawings get sloppy
and that helps us know that it's an and gate
now an orgate again simply implementing the or table
here the truth table has same thing
two inputs corresponding to the two columns
one output corresponding to the logical ore
this time it's drawn as this sort of curly
d here and it has a plus on the inside
which is a way of representing ore
computation there is a computation going in here
we don't know what the computation is yet
again we'll see that in a few minutes
but two binary numbers come in
one binary comes out
it's a computation
it tells me whether one or more of these variables
is true or not
and lastly logical knot is represented as a gate
with only one input
one column one output one column
and now it's a triangle with a little circle at the end
so 0 1 comes in 01 comes out
there's a computation going on in there that says
how do I flip from a one to a 0
to a one
okay so now if I can
build these things
this logical and logical or logical nod
from actual physical things
I have the building blocks for computing and or not
and then I've got to show you that I can actually
build a modern computer
with only those three operations
and that's sort of the magic of a modern computer
is you don't need anything more
for the basic computation
obviously you have the display in the mouse
and the keyboard and all those other nice peripherals
but in terms of the core computation
we're going to show how you can build
modern computation
from three simple logical operators
okay so I'm going to pick it up there
I'm going to show you how we're going to
build logical land
logical or logical knot from transistors
and then we're going to start
talking about the nature of computation
and how you actually
pull all these gates together
in order to do real computation
so we'll pick it up in a few minutes
in the last lecture
I promised you that we are going to be able to do
computation using only logical land
logical lore logical nott
now what I have to do first
is show you how I can physically build those gates
to compute
and or not essentially implement those truth tables
two inputs one output for anden or one input
one output for logical knot
and I'm going to build those and then
in the next lecture
we're actually going to use those gates to actually
do computation
all right
so let's start by building a couple of gates and or not
I think building blocks of a modern
computer are transistors
and you've almost certainly heard of that word
I'm going to show you one version
there's many versions of transistors
I'm going to show you one
that's particularly simplified
slightly dated
this is not what modern transistors look like
but I like this because I think it's particularly easy
to explain so here's the transistor
it's got a very simple construction
there is power that comes down
and the transistor can control this little door here
so when the door is open
nothing goes through and then when the door closes
everything goes through
so what do I mean by that so these are the two states
you can think about these as zero and one by the way
obviously you can think about this if you want
is water coming down a hose
and here the hose is pinched so nothing comes down
and if I took a reading down here
I would say there's no water
coming out here
I've unpinched the water
so it comes straight down and I've got water
and I've got power
I've got a signal here
so obviously
this is not going to be water's going to be electricity
I can stop the electricity from flowing
in which case I have zero
there it is
and I can allow electricity go through and I have one
there is my binary representation
these transistors represent in one of two states
a zero or a one
and now what I have to show you
is how do I combine these transistors
which are physical realizations
of the language of computers
zero or one in order to compute and or or not
and then I have to show you
how do I go from and or or not
to
actual computations like addition and multiplication
all right so let's start with logical and
so what do we know about logical and 2 in 1 out
two inputs a and b
which can either be zero or one
and now we know that this transition can represent one
a and this transistor can represent b
so here's a representation where I've open these doors
so that I have a zero here and I have a zero here
and I have power here
so what did I do I put these transistors in series
so I have power coming down
transistor one which is a
that's the input a and the output of that
goes into the next transistor
so why is this okay
well because this is 0 1
what's this 0 1 so it's all fine it's all the input
the output of one can be the input to the other
it's just power coming down
okay so
let's think about
the various state that these two transistors can be in
so here's the state zero zero
so if powers coming down here and this is a zero
and this is a zero
then what's the reading down
here in the little gauge that I had
of course it's zero
nothing comes down it's being stopped twice in fact
so let's
set one of these bits to be one
so power comes down
what's the reading coming out of this transistor zero
so if zero is coming into here
it is allowed to flow through
but there's nothing coming into there
so of course the reading here has to be zero
so input zero
input one output zero
okay let's flip those
let's say
we allow the power to go through the first transistor
but not the second one
what's the reading here
so we've got power down to here but then it stops
so the reading there are zero again
so one more right one one
so now I have a clear shot through
power comes down
goes through the first transistor
goes through the second transistor
and now I have a reading of one
and so the output is one
okay so let's think about
let's look at all
four of these together and see what that looks like
so with two input zero zero I get an output of 0 0 1
I get an output of 0 1 0 I get an output of 0 1 1
I get an output of one
what is this it's an angate
it's an and operator
so think of these
left to right here as the columns of the truth table
four rows 0 0 0 1 1 0 1 1
and think of this
as the last column which is the computation
so I've built an angate
I've built something that where I can set two inputs
that's my input I get to decide what those values are
and by simply putting these transistors in series
I have computed a logical and
great okay I can do computation now of a logical land
now I just have to be able to do or and not
so let's do or
okay just to remind you that's an end gate
so let's do an orgate
now I know I need two transistors
because I have two inputs right
so there are my inputs
I just set them to be zero and one for now
let's think about the nature of an o'er
now that we've thought about through
what happens when you put those
two transistors in series
so the reason why that's an and
git is the only way to get the power
from the very top to the very bottom
is both are one
right that's only time that an and is true
but within ore I want something to come out
if one is one
if the other one is one or they're both one
so I don't want
I can't put them in series because
one has the vito power
but I don't want anybody to have vito power
so what if instead of putting them in
series top to bottom
I put them in parallel like this what happens
so let's think about the power coming down
I split the power along the top
I bring them down into both transistors
so this one stops the flow but this one allows it
and outcomes and there's my one
so as long as one of these is open
I'm going to get a one here
now I noticed
by the way if I switch these
if this was a one and that was a zero
I would still have a one here
the order of these doesn't matter
all right what happens if they're both one
no problem at all
I still get power out the other end
good and what happens if they're both zero
power comes down stops here stops here
so I have a zero here
what did I just do
I built an orgate
if this is 1 0 or 0 1
power comes through because they're in parallel
if they're both one
power comes through and I have a one
and if and only if
both of these are zero
then no power comes through and I get a zero
that is the definition of an orgate
2 in 1 out of course
by the way the power is just
provided to you by
virtue of your battery or plugging in
so you don't have to worry about where that power
comes from
all right we have an end in an orgate
both of them are built by putting two transistors
which simply represent one of two states
binary in parallel for an ann gate
sorry in series for an ann gate
and in parallel for an orgate
now we have to build a knock gate
okay so a knot gate only has one input and one output
so let me orient you here
this is a little bit of a different picture here
power comes down
this is the output right here
I'll describe this resistor to you in a second
so power comes down
and this is where our output has been
and now it's junk
we're simply going to ignore it
so I'm going to wire up the input here
I can control that transistor door
this is going to be my output
and of course this is still the power
and this is a resistor
so what does a resistor do
the resistor said look
power can come through here
but I don't like going through there
I prefer not to go there
and so if there's no other route to go
you can come out this way
so what's going to happen is
power's going to come down here
and it wants to go here
but this is totally shut off
and so the power will actually go through the resistor
but
if this allows the power to go through this way
is seamless frictionless
and so the power goes straight down
and it doesn't go out through the resistor
and then that's a zero
ah this looks about like what we want
on the previous slide I had an input of zero
which would not allow the power through
so the power has to go out through the resistor
and I get a one there
zero to one now the power can come through
gets pushed out to junk don't care
but there's no coming power out here
because it didn't want to go through the resistor
I have a knock gate
now for the knock gate
of course I only need one transistor
and that little resistor right there
all of which of course are physically realizable
all right so what have we done
we've taken this very very simple little thing
this little tiny transistor
by the way these are the
this is a magic
of squeezing all that computation
onto the phone in your pocket
is because those transistors every year
get smaller and smaller and smaller and smaller
and I can pack
millions and billions of those
into a square centimeter
and do phenomenal computing power
because they are
the backbone of all modern computation
and we can build logical land
logical or logical not from two transistors in series
for an and two transistors in parallel fern or
and a transistor install little resistor for a not
so now what I have to convince you of
is that that's enough to do modern computation
which seems like a real stretch by the way
you probably believe that I could build these gates
super simple calculations
but how do I go from those gates to actual computation
that's what we're going to see next
so see you in a little bit