61a lecture number 23 q
a so here we've got fall 2019 midterm
two question four
and i think we'll just go through it
implement stable
which takes a list of numbers as a
positive integer k and a non-negative
number and it returns whether all pairs
of values in
s with indices that differ by
at most k have an absolute difference in
value of
atmos and okay so
numbers near each other in the list need
to be near each other in quantity
the functions that aggregate iterable
arguments on the metric to study guide
have the following behavior when empty
list is zero
okay is this saying john like it's sort
of
sorted uh yeah kind of it's kind of
sorted
kinda sorted right you go up and down a
little bit but yeah you go yeah i have
two numbers that are very different next
to each other
right right cute
okay so let's see what we have
uh a bunch of numbers that are all near
each other
all the adjacent values differ by at
most two there's the two
there's the adjacent and so we get true
and then we have an example that says uh
same numbers but a different
k this says even numbers that are two
apart
like three and six or five and two
are supposed to be only two away from
each other in quantity
and that's not true so we get false
and this last example um
has ones and fives next to each other
and that's bad
all right so what are we going to do
well um
go through all the numbers this is what
this says
well actually this goes through all the
indices so we get all the positions
within s
we're going to get a range of other
positions and it's called near
which i think is an indication that
these are the numbers that are kind of
just before it
why just before it well it goes up to
but not including i
and then we have an if statement
and some big gnarly expression that we
need to fill in
and then we return false so this general
structure which says
for a bunch of examples if we find
something is true
then we return false otherwise after
we've gone through all the examples if
we never found something that proves it
false
then we return true is kind of a typical
structure for checking some condition
about every position in a list or
something like that
so you go through all the positions in
the list you look and see if the
condition is violated if so you're done
and if you never find such a problem
then you have
decided well it's stable so what is this
condition we're going to look for
we're going to look for two numbers and
where the difference is to be
so the way i would think about this is
to say
let's pick an i we're gonna go through
all the i's
so let's pick uh i equals
0 1 2 3. and this is an example so if i
is 3 then we need to be able to detect
that 5 and 2
are too different from each other so
what are we going to check
for all the other values j we're gonna
have to check
one and two check
compare s1 to s3 and compare s2 to s3
so that helps me figure out what my
range is if this is three
then i need to go from one to three
which i think is
i minus uh
what's that is it k or n n
magnitude and k is how far you go
now um we kind of don't want to go off
the beginning
so it might be worth saying i don't want
this to ever be
smaller than zero and john can you
explain why you're not
going in the other direction like why
are you only looking backwards not
forward
oh good question yeah so this would only
look backwards
um and if you check each number and
everything before it
since this is kind of a symmetrical
check that's the same as checking each
number and everything after it so you
kind of don't have to do both
even though the condition is described
as pairs of elements
it's it's fine to get all the pairs of
elements by taking each one
and then the ones before it we could
have also changed the range
not to start at zero we could have
started at a k
because there's no reason because the
first then we wouldn't have to worry
about that max but i think it's fine the
way it is too
uh yeah i'm sure there's other ways to
write that
okay so now we need to figure out how to
check for this condition well let's see
what we have we're building a list
comprehension
that says yes something greater than n
for j in near
so j and i are both gonna be bound
in this expression right here i was
bound up here
to three j is bound down here
to one and we're trying to figure out
whether
that pair of indices causes a problem
and that problem would be if the
absolute value
of the difference between s i
and s j is greater than it
so this expression is going to give you
true if there's a problem
and it's going to check each index in
turn for
all the different js one and two in this
case
if any of those is a problem then
there's a problem with the whole
sequence so that's why we will aggregate
with the
any function which takes in a list of
true false values and tells you whether
any of them is true
if any of these differences is bigger
than n
then the whole sequence
is not stable then someone asked if i
could explain the near part again
yeah so near is supposed to i is already
set for us
and so it's gonna go through from zero
to one to two to three to 4 for these
examples
and for each of those ending values
we're going to consider other numbers
that are nearby
and we need to come up with a range of
indices
for those other numbers and we do that
by computing how far back do we have to
go from i
if we went back to zero that would be
too far
the condition is only about stuff that's
nearby and then i think it's worth just
thinking about examples
so if i is three
when i is three then what we really want
is a range from one to three
so we can get i'm doing this example
this center one so that we can get
2 and the 3 and compare that to the 5.
if i is 1 then we really just care about
the 0th position so that would be a
range from 0 to 1.
if i is 4 then we care about a range
from
okay so i is four we care about
comparing that to the three and the five
that's index number two and number three
so we really wanna go to two and three
and so
like you can just think about each of
these examples and figure out what's a
general expression that describes
the first number in all of these and the
second number is always just i
the next question was whether there were
any good resources
for learning how to think logically
because solving these problems
isn't just about knowing the mechanics
of the programming language
you also have to think logically about
how to solve the particular problem
yeah let me before i i don't know about
a lot of resources but let me point out
a few things when you're solving these
problems
i think there's a tendency because of
the way the educational system tends to
work
is to favor and reward memorization
right like i've seen this problem i see
the problem again
i know the answer done and a lot of
mathematics frankly is taught that way
and it's pretty bad
and so the thing to take away from these
problems is not
you know this is how you solve this
problem but it's the logic for example
that john just gave
us that said there's a really nice
construct here
where you check something if anything
returns false
then you are done otherwise you return
true so what you're going to see in a
lot of these problems it's not about
solving stable
it's about the constructs that we use
it's how we put together
the constructs and the conditionals and
the variable assignments and all of that
so part of the part of the goal here is
to really um um
separate yourself a little bit from the
actual details of the problem
and think about the overall structure of
how we're putting these pieces together
and then what you'll see is that those
are what generalize across problems
you'll see
themes over and over again right so you
know there's a finite set of problems we
can we can
specify but what you'll see is that the
underlying structure is pretty similar
well you'll see patterns across that is
what i should say
maybe john has suggestions for other
resources
yeah i thought that was a good
explanation i don't uh
know of any resources about logical
thinking that are like really great
um most people learn it kind of by
working through a lot of problems in
this course and it's not uncommon at all
that it is
not something that just comes easily but
practice does seem to help a lot and
there are relationships between problems
just as honey said
i think that's uh that's
true that as you kind of work through
more of these problems
you just recognize like oh this is
pretty similar to something i've seen
before
and if it's something you haven't seen
before well sometimes you can just kind
of work it out on the fly
and sometimes you can't and so that's
why uh practicing a little bit
beforehand
just to have seen some similar problems
is a good way to prepare
okay so we're gonna look at uh spring
midterm two question two part
b and try to focus on the question of
you know when you make a recursive leap
of faith
um does it work
i guess and what can go wrong so
uh we've already let's say solve this
power which takes positive integer
and returns whether s is a power of the
base
okay and now we're gonna do
implement powers a generator function
which takes positive integers n and k
it yields all integers m that are both
powers of k and whose digits appear
in order in n
oh fantastic
so what does this mean you look at the
digits that you're given one two three
four five
and you can take subsets of those digits
like just the two and the five
and if that's the power of five then
that should be part of the result
doesn't sound easy but we can take a
look
so we are filtering basically like when
i see filter
i assume this is about find all of the
ways
in which you can build up numbers
just by taking digits of n and then
we're gonna filter them to have only the
ones that are a power
of k so this will worry about the power
of k
and this will find all the numbers that
exist within it
so let's just worry about the numbers
that exist within n and talk about
kind of building that up recursively
so there's this notion of a seed and
this seed
is i think the digits that we still get
to work with
if there are no digits then there are no
then we can still build one number which
is just zero
otherwise we're going to go through
something
and uh do something with it
i guess now we have to find some
recursive structure
and i think the recursive structure is
that
if you take a number like this you could
find
all the numbers within it by finding all
the numbers in one two three
four and then for each one of those
either stick a five on the end or don't
so that will give you all the different
possibilities
is that if you find all the numbers
within n divided by 10
all of those are also oh sorry not n
build
or seed in c divided by 10 then all
those numbers are
also in seed
but there's another number within seed
which is what you get
when you put the last digit of seed
on the end of whatever x is
by the way this is i'm going to come
back to steve's question in a second
we've seen this many many times exactly
this construct where john is peeling off
a number with the integer division
and then creating the base so that
that's another pattern that we've seen
over and over again
for this type of manipulation
yeah exactly and the recursive leap of
faith happened
right here where
we're kind of trying to list out every
possibility
so we assumed we had a way for listing
out all the possibilities
if i just had a smaller number one two
three four
and assuming that works then i can
start putting uh
different variants of that so if i find
12 in there
then i want to yield both 12 and 125.
and notice here too that john did
something very clever at the beginning
where he went all the way to the bottom
said ah there's a filter
so what must be happening is i'm going
to generate all possible solutions
and then narrow them down into the ones
that satisfy the
constraint um so that that makes it a
little bit easier up top and now we now
he has to do some hard work
yeah okay so now let's look at the
filter now build has given me
everything 12 13 14
134 and in there somewhere is the 1 and
the 5 and the 25 and 125.
these are all powers of 5. so i need
something that's only true if uh
i call it on a power of 5. well that's
exactly what the
is power is that what it's called
is power function that i implemented in
part a does
but is power takes two arguments and by
currying it i get to fill in one
argument
and then wait until the other argument
is available so the first argument i'll
fill in
is k and then what filter is going to do
is it's going to call basically it's
going to call is power
k on every element
of build n leaving us only with the ones
that are
powers of k yeah life is so much better
if you
fix fixate on an example so if c
is this then c divided by 10 is that and
then the hard part which is
what happens when you build one two
three four
well you get one and two and three and
four but also twelve and thirteen and
fourteen and also 123 and 124 and also
one two three four
and also zero and also 23 i don't know
if i said that already
but that's the thing that's the leap of
faith is to say build is gonna give me
all those possibilities
and then all i have to do is like stick
a five on the end or not
yeah good question so it's about lecture
and about
um using
sets and why they're fast i guess
um the built-in
set
has like two useful properties one
it gets rid of repeats but the more
useful property
is about its efficiency which is that
figuring out whether something is an
element of a set
happens in what's called constant time
so if you watch the efficiency lecture
this means that it doesn't scale with
the number of elements that are in the
set
so if you have 50 elements in the set
and figuring out where something's in
there
takes about as long as if you have 5
million elements in the set
and this is achieved through a technique
called hashing
which you get to learn about in 61b got
to leave something for 61b so that's
like one of the topics that we don't
cover
in this course but you could read about
it if you want and
um it's a wonderful technique so
basically anytime you're trying to
figure out whether some
thing is in a group or in a set um you
want to use this particularly efficient
technique which is called hashing
and um and it's built in to the set
but we haven't really talked about how
to re-implement it you'll do that in 61b
um yeah so we have an implementation
in this project which comes up with
the um
number of elements between here
and here is that what this does
oh yeah there are five and six and seven
so
if instead of writing this code and
using sorted lists
we instead had two sets that one
and that one
then uh i could there's a built-in
functionality for taking the
intersection between two sets i can get
the length of that
and now i have a fast overlap
that didn't take a lot of code
okay so here's an optional question from
lab
write a function reverse other that
mutates a tree
said 3 is input and we're going to
change it
such that labels on every other odd
depth are reversed so if we start with 1
4 3 then we reverse the order
of the 2 4 branch and the 3 branch
and so uh oh actually we don't
reverse the order of the branches we
just reverse the order of the labels
themselves
so the branches are still the same
structure except for we've uh
changed the two and the three to be
three and two
oh it says notice that the nodes
themselves are not reversed only the
labels are okay
and here's an example okay
sorry i gotta get all these zoom things
out of the way
um so how might we do this well um
well okay so when you're doing something
that's like every other depth you really
have two choices
one is track what depth you're on this
is a good good way to go
and another is to only process
even depths and then you assume that the
level below is an odd depth so we could
do it both ways
i don't know if if you all have a
preference but let's
try this this notion of
process only the even depths so we
assume that t
is either the whole tree or it's a
branch of a branch
meaning another even depth that would be
depth two or it's a branch of a branch
of a branch of a branch that would be
like depth four that's one way to do
that
okay so um one way to solve this
recursively would be just to focus on
the first odd
layer that would be um the
labels of the branches and then make
recursive calls to handle
all the other odd layers
so the
labels of branches
would be
b dot label for b in t dot branches
if uh t is a leaf then there are no such
things so i guess we can just return at
that point
um otherwise we want to get the
reversed labels of branches
so there's various ways to do it there's
a built-in reversed function
i think maybe the uh
well this is a fine way to do it we can
practice some of the stuff that we've
learned in earlier lectures so
reversed is something i can call on
labels of branches
and then
i kind of get them in the other order
now the tricky part is that i have to
take each branch
and i have to find the appropriate label
for it
so in this example now i have
which example should we do let's do this
example
we've got two and six and eight
now we have an iterator over eight and
six and 2 and that's what we're supposed
to slot in
as these labels so we have to go through
in parallel
the branches so we can update their
labels and the new label values
and we did in fact learn about a
built-in function that does this
called zip so this would go through
every branch and every new label
that we get by zipping together tdot
branches
and the reverse labels
and now we will set b
dot label to be its new label
what about the recursion well
we don't actually want to call reverse
other on the branch
because then we'd have an odd branch as
t
so instead what we want to do is go
through all the
uh grandchildren
and call reverse other on that
this would be grandchild sorry
[Music]
i'll probably do the trick let's try it
oh it doesn't fit now it fits
nope
uh probably we need to know what a tree
is
yeah it works
um
you are supposed to know what zip is but
it's kind of an esoteric
topic and you should know what reversed
is but we could actually try to solve
this without reversed and without zip
just fine we could instead go over
indices and that would be a fine thing
to do
so if we did something like for i in
range of the len of
b dot t dot branches
we would then find the appropriate
branch
and change its label to be
the label
in the like reverse position
one way you could write this is negative
i
or if you wanted to be more explicit you
could write len of branches minus
i uh oh
but it doesn't work yeah so
oh is it yeah something seems wrong but
i don't know what it is
uh let's see if we can fix it real quick
oh name error b is not defined oh it's a
boring
problem so this needs to be t dot
branches oh
see we were in the wrong line of code
nope
no what's wrong uh
it didn't reverse oh
no you're going this is just the wrong
index yeah
we're going to fix it so this is
n minus i or while you don't have n
so if this is zero this needs to be
negative one
yeah it's uh oh i see yeah yeah and this
is one
this needs to be negative two yeah so
it's
oh it's really negative i minus one yeah
classic off by one error the next
question was what does
super do when you have a class that
inherits from two different classes
well good question so if you
use super on a class that inherits from
two different classes
what have you built you built something
very strange but basically what you've
built is it's the same object except for
it's going to not look up things in its
class it's going to look at
them up in one of the base classes
and which one well it looks at them in
the order that you inherit
so if you have a class that inherits
from both b
and c it's going to look in b first and
then it's going to look at c
to find the corresponding attribute that
you're looking at
all 18 midterm two
number six
implement replace which takes two
non-empty linked lists s and t
as well as positive integers i and j
with i less than j
it mutates s by removing elements with
indices from i
to j
and replacing them all with some other
list t
afterwards s contains all the objects in
t
so a change to t would reflect reflected
in s
as well t may change as a result of
calling
replace okay so it's okay to change
t
and we assume s has at least j elements
so what's going on here if we had
printed this out it would say three four
five six seven
and then we replace elements from two to
four
so that's the five six
elements that's element two and element
three but not including element four
so now we have three four something
something seven
and what's that something something well
it's the
elements in t the zero one two
so we're left with three four zero one
two seven instead of three four five six
seven
and this is supposed to demonstrate that
if you change t
t dot rest of first equals eight
that's changing the zero one two to a
zero eight two
this is also changing s so now we have
three four zero eight two
seven whew
uh well i think this is not gonna be
that quick but let's take a look
if i is greater than one
then we're kind of not where we need to
be to make the change
i think is the story there because with
the linked list
you can kind of only change the first
thing and the rest
but um things later on
you'd usually handle with recursion
so oh i can use pdf annotation that
would work much better
can you not see my screen anymore uh we
see your screen but no annotation yet
john
now we have it so if
i is greater than one then i think we
need to just kind of move on
it's the same thing as replacing the
rest of
s with t with a smaller i
and a smaller j
so how did i get that well basically
like replacing two to four with an s
is the same thing as replacing one to
three within s.rest
that was the idea there okay so we've
kind of moved forward into s until we
find the place where we're gonna
make this edit we've found this place
where uh i
equals one is i ever zero no positive
integers i
okay so now we basically know that i is
one
and that means we're going to make some
edits
this says k times
or sorry j minus i times so
uh kind of the length of the part that
we're removing which would be like four
minus two okay so we need to remove two
elements
we need to remove the next element
and we saw this in lab as well you can
remove the next element
by
changing s dot rest to be
start rest.rest
so what did this do this just
remove element at index one
uh okay so um just like in lab that's
how you get rid of the elemented index
one
we're doing it a bunch of times j minus
i times in order to kind of get rid of
all the elements that we want to get rid
of
okay now we have an interesting
expression n equals t
while something n equals and rest
i think what we're doing is we're
finding the last element in t
yeah how would we find the last element
in t
well we'd start at the beginning and
then
if we haven't reached the last element
then we move forward in t
by calling end equals n dot rest how do
we know that we've reached the last
element
if end dot rest
does not equal link dot empty
so it might be that t only has one
element and we've already reached the
end
in which case we need to make no updates
but if not
then we need to continually go through
end
until it really is the end until there's
nothing after it meaning
the rest of it is empty now we found the
last
thing in t by the way when you see that
end equals n dot rest that's basically i
equals i plus one you're incrementing
through a list that's a classic
how do you make your way through a list
yeah exactly great great point and and
so now i think
uh we found the end of t we know where
we
are supposed to be splicing in this t
which is right at
the position one within s
because i is one remember so we're going
to change
s dot rest to just be t
but what about everything after like
what about the old s dot rest
that's supposed to appear after t which
means we can change
the end of t to be
everything that used to be in
s dot rest i don't want to sign this one
i don't know it's it's you can consider
it artwork john i think you should sign
it when you're done
there we go so
um you know
let's think about this example what we
did is we had three four five six seven
we kind of worked our way past the three
until we just had four five six seven
and
i was one then we got rid of the five
so we had four six seven we got rid of
the six we had four
seven and that was called s in our
recursive call
s was the link for seven
now we found end n started out
being 0 1 2 then we went to the rest so
it was just 1
2 and then we went to the rest and we
found that the end was this
link 2. and then we made the following
updates after four
comes
t which was zero one two and after two
comes whatever used to be after four
which was seven
and then we ended up with three four
zero one two seven
think about it uh imagine you have a
train that's connected uh
you know all the cars we essentially
deleted a bunch of cars and now you have
two pieces and you have to splice
something in so that requires two
splices
at the front and at the end yeah so
that's basically what's happening here
that's why i have to keep track of