sixty one eight lecture No.33
announcements
homework eight is dum Thursday
the scheme project is due next Tuesday
we'll have a project party today
in the evening from 79:00pm
check 0.1 is due today
check 0.2 is due Friday
and you get an early submission
bonus point for completing it by Monday
scheme project is big
please get started
the completely optional scheme recursive art contest
entries are doomed the Monday after thanksgiving
feel free to enter just by drawing some scheme art
with your scheme interpreter
I also wanted to mention that the
eaks department updated its lnscs declaration policy
you can read about it here
regarding 61 a
the policy says that a letter
grade will be computed for all students
regardless of what grading option you elect
we will share that grade with you
just by sending you an email after your final is graded
and that grade will also
be shared with the department and
used for the purpose
of assessing whether you can declare computer science
which currently has a gpa threshold of 3.3
in this way you get some control over your transcript
you can decide whether to pnp the course or not
but if you're trying to declare
computer science then your grade in this course
contributes to that
this might not seem like much of an accommodation
but in this course
we've tried to give you accommodations
by reducing the amount of required
content to just focus on the really important parts
so that's why we have several optional topics
that would normally be part of the final exam
but aren't
and the projects have been trimmed down a little bit
we've tried to do this carefully
to only leave out topics that
really are just nice to know
as opposed to something
you have to know in order to continue on
and computer science and be effective
so I hope you're not too stressed out
hang in there
or in the home stretch
I know that it's been a tough semester
but it turns out that today
is the last day of required a lecture content
for the whole course
and the lecture is not very long
I do encourage you to watch the rest of the
lectures in the course
in particular fridays lecture
tells you how to link together a python program
and sequel lights database
so that you can have some application logic in python
and some of it in the sequel queries
and the example that we do
about playing blackjack is kind of fun
here are all the
important links for the rest of the week
and in particular we'll have exam prep on Friday
and conceptual office hours on Thursday
so if you have questions about concepts in the course
and you don't come to the lecture q amp
a you could instead come to the ta
lead conceptual office hours
and ask your questions there
in the sql language
you can perform aggregation over multiple rows
using aggregate functions
so so far all as
ql expressions have referred to the values in a single
row at a time
what do I mean by that
well if we look at the structure of a select statement
we see that there are expressions
in the column descriptions
also in the wear claws and the order by claws
each one of these expressions can refer
to column names in this table
but what they actually are referring to
is the value in a particular row
for that column
so when you use an expression here
in order to filter the rows of the table
using an expression such as
the latitude of some city is greater than 38
what you're evaluating is whether the value
of the latitude column for a particular row
is above some No.38
and if so you keep that row
otherwise you get rid of that row
but the expression itself is evaluated per row
everything we've seen has looked like that so far
but now we're going to look at what's called an
aggregate function
which can appear in left
expressions in the column descriptions
and it computes a value from a group of rows
for instance by summing together
all of the different values
for a particular column
so we're going to
introduce a new data set
in order to study this problem
here's a table of animals
a dog is a kind of animal with four legs
and weighs about 20 pounds
a cat has four legs and weighs about 10 pounds
a ferret has four legs and ways about 10 pounds
that's a pretty big for a ferret actually
but let's just go with it
a parrot has two legs because it's a bird
then it weighs about six pounds
a larger bird would be a penguin which has two legs
and weighs 10 pounds
and then I was trying to think
what's something with two legs in weighs a lot
you might think an ostrich but I chose a t
rex which weighs about six tons
so here's my table of animals
and now I can write select statements that refer
to the animals table
here is a select statement that contains an
aggregate function
in its column description
select max legs from animals
legs refers to a particular column in this table
and max legs is a computation over multiple rows
so we haven't included a wear claws
so we haven't included any filtering
and yet instead of having a six row output
from this six row input
we get only one output row
which takes the maximum value
over every value that appears
in the legs column
so this thing is called an aggregate function max
and you can also take them in
and the sum and some others
so let's try it out
first
I'm going to load the same table that you saw before
now I can select the max number of legs
from animals and I'll get four
I could also select the sum
of the weight of every kind of animals
and I'll get 12,056
which is what you get when you sum up
all of these weight numbers
the argument that I pass to max
can be an arbitrary combination
I can ask
what is the maximum value of the legs minus the weight
then I could add five for that
and take all these and animals and I'll get one
now where did this one come from
well I computed what's the legs 2 the weight six is -4
which is the biggest value I can get from any row
plus five gives me one
okay it's also possible to combine
multiple different aggregations
I could select the maximum legs and the min weight
from animals
which would be four and six
now there's no animal that has four legs and six weight
so these are computed independently of each other
I can even combine them
I can take the maximum legs
and subtract out the minimum weight
and I'll get -2
now all of this can be combined with a ware claw
so I could say select the min legs
and the maximum weight from animals
but perhaps I don't want to include the big guy the t
rex so I could say I'm only interested in rose
where the name does not equal t rex
sorry where the kind does not equal t
rex
and then I'll get the maximum weight is actually 20
which came from the dog
now in addition to min and max and some
you can also compute the average value
so the average
number of legs from animals
takes an aggregation overall six rows
and comes with up with three point o
you can also count the number of legs
now what does count do
well it just tells you
how many different rows there are
so there are six rows and animals
it doesn't matter whether I count the legs
or I count the kind
or I count the weight
I'll get the same thing
which is why a more typical syntax
uses this special form
count star
and count star just counts the rose
now there is a reason why you would put a
particular column name inside count
and that reason is that
there's a special keyword called distinct
which you can place before a column name
and then it will count the number of different distinct
legs so there's four legs or there's two legs
what about the distinct values for weight
well there's four of them there's 30,612,000
this distinct keyword can also be applied to the sum
so this sums up 12 1016 and 20
leaving out the repeats
now it's possible to
come up with the column descriptions that mix
aggregate functions and
single values that don't include aggregate functions
what you get
is the number of rows that you would get from
aggregating so an aggregate function also
selects a particular row in the table
along with
aggregating the value that you ask it to aggregate
and that row may be meaningful
so what do I mean by may be meaningful
well if you ask what's the max weight
as one column
and then the kind as another column from animals
you end up getting one row
and the row you get has a maximum weight of 12,000
and what kind you get
well you get the kind t rex
how does that work
well what happens is that when you maximize the weight
it selects this weight
but it also selects this whole row
so that referring to kind or legs at this point
will tell you about the maximal value
who is the animal
that weighs 12,000 pounds
well that will be the t rex
now what if you ask what's min kind
come a kind from animals
well min kind
will compute the minimum in alphabetical order
that would be cat
and it will select this whole row
so if you pick out the kind from that
you'll get cat again
now you don't always get something so sensible
if I say select max legs
come a kind from animals what should I get
well there's actually
four different animals that I'll have maximal legs
so you'll get something arbitrary
or if you say select average weight
come a kind from animals
then there's all these different weights
which one should you pick which one is the average
well none of them are the average
so we can try this out
and you'll see sometimes you get a meaningful value
sometimes you don't
so what we'll do is we'll select the maximum
weight
from animals we get 12,000
if we ask for the kind as well
we'll find out it's the t
rex
the minimum weight and the kind is six
and it's the parrot
if we ask for the minimum kind
then that will check
lexographic order or alphabetical order
and pick cat and then it picks out that whole row
so a cat is a cat
and it has how many legs and how much weight
will for in 10
now when you select out the average weight
from animals that gives you something meaningful
2009 but if you also try to select what kind is that
it tells you it's the t rex
and what does that mean
t rex is not average in any way
so you have to be careful about selecting
single values in conjunction with
aggregations
some aggregations give you a meaningful value
like min and max
others don't like average
and that last example we talked about
what's the maximum legs
well that's four
if I ask for what kind is that
there's no clear answer
because there are three different
things that have that many legs
and it gives us cat
but cat isn't really the right answer
I mean
cat or dog or ferret I'll have four legs
an aggregate function
takes all values of some expression
such as a column name
from all the rows in a group
and does something with them
takes the max or the sum
now by default
all rows that are used to compute the final table
meaning the ones that passed
the filter in the wear claws
are all in the same group one big group
and so the result when you apply an aggregate function
only has one row
but it's actually possible to divine a select statement
with multiple groups
so rose in a table can be grouped together
an aggregation is actually performed on each group
individually
so here's another form of a select statement
it says select
still has column descriptions
remember
these expressions can contain aggregate functions
from some table
where I group by some expression
and I keep the groups having some property
group bi and having are both new
let's focus on group bi
the number of groups is the number
of uk new nique values
of some expression
which you place here
so here's our animals table
and here's a select statement
let's select the number of legs and the maximum weight
from animals group by legs
what group by does
is it partitions all of the rows from the animals table
by the unique values of
what value is in the legs column
so we have four here we have two here
those form two different groups
the legs equals four group
and the legs equals two group
each of those is going to result in a different row
in the table that we get by selecting legs
comma max weight
now legs here because it matches the group by
will give us the value
of the legs for that group
it's really giving us
the legs value for some arbitrary row
but they're all the same so we get four
and then it computes the maximal weight
by maximizing over all the rows in this group
so the maximum weight for a four legged animal is 20
and the maximum rate for a two legged animal is 12 000
this notion of grouping together rows and then
aggregating those groups is actually
quite powerful
so let's look at some more examples
I can select the number of legs in each group
from animals where I group by the number of legs
that will give me four and two
which are the unique values
of the expression legs
now I can also compute the count
of the number of rows that have those many legs
okay
so there are three different animals with two legs
than three different animals with four legs
and like I said
I could also compute the maximum weight
in each of those categories
12,000 pounds for a two legged beast
20 pounds for a four legged beast
it is possible to group by more than one
call them at a time
so I could get the legs and the weight
from animals
or I group by both the legs and the weight
so here's all the unique combinations of a value for
legs and a value for weight
notice there are only five
whereas we had six rows in the beginning
because ferret and cat have both the same attributes
I can actually group by any expression I want
so I could get the maximum kind
along with the value of dividing weight by legs
from animals
where I group
by the value that I get dividing weight by legs
now sql performs integer division when it divides
two integers by default
so what I'm dividing is 20 by four to get five
or 10 by four to get two
or six by two to get three or 10 by two to get five
and I see that there's various values that I get
and here it's picking the alphabetically last
kind of an animal
for each
ratio of weight to legs that I can possibly get
within the animal's table
so here we've seen
grouping by a particular column value
multiple column values or an arbitrary expression
now sometimes when you group rows together
you want to keep
some of those groups around and get rid of others
a having claws filters the set of groups
that we keep for aggregation
now we also have a wear claws to filter individual rows
but a having claws can even include aggregation itself
so here is a select statement where we've said
we want to keep
the result of weight divided by legs
and the count of the number of rows
that have that weight to leg ratio
from the animals table
where I group by this arbitrary expression
weight divided by legs
but I only keep the groups that have account
greater than one
so how does this work
well it computes weight divided by legs for each row
weight divided by
legs can be five or two or three or five or 6000
we group by this value
so the unique values are five or two or three or 6000
and then we apply the having
claws to filter any group
that doesn't have a true value for this expression
so the count has to be one
which means that we need
weight divided by legs to be five
which has a count of two
or weight divided by legs is two
but both of these groups are discarded