61a lecture number 22 q a
the question is about creating
attributes inside of a function
which uh i did in an example
from this lecture it turns out
that if you have a function
that function itself can have attributes
now right now it doesn't have an
attribute if i call f on 10
i get nothing because it has no
attribute y
but i could give it one
and now when i call f on 10 i get 15.
you know functions can have data
associated with them that's been true
for
a long time since we talked about higher
order functions in
in in lecture four i think
and here we have another example of a
function with data associated with it
i um basically what's going on here is
that functions
are values they're objects objects can
have attributes
it turns out in python that any user
defined function can have arbitrary
attributes
and so this is one way of just
associating data with the function
by storing it as an attribute in the
function and the nice thing here is that
it is mutable
so you can kind of change it later um
there's no control over who can change
it so that it makes it a little bit
too flexible in some cases but this is
an alternative to for example using
non-local assignment or a higher order
function is that you could just store
the data
right there as an attribute in the
function
yeah great question the question is
about
space complexity and whether
recursion uses up a lot of space
because every time you make a recursive
call you're allocating
more space to hold the frame that
represents the kind of first frame in
the environment for that recursive call
and so if you make 50 recursive calls
then you're creating 50 frames
um yeah that's exactly right
there is one answer to this that exists
in other programming languages but not
in python
um which is that there there's like a
special case where it turns out you
don't need to create a new frame you
could just kind of reuse the old one
uh called tail recursion we'll talk
about that it's an optional topic in a
few weeks
but this is just like one particular
esoteric point
i guess the main point is that yes
when you make a bunch of function calls
then you introduce a bunch of frames
and this incurs some space overhead so
if you could avoid it that's not a bad
idea at all
so typically when you'd write a um
when you have just some iterative
process you want to like go through all
the elements in something
then in python and most other
programming languages the best way to do
it is just with a while or for loop
and not to write it recursively
recursion isn't really for that it can
be used for that but what it's really
for
is for tree recursion and processing
trees or other hierarchical data
structures
that's where it's quite helpful and if
you think about those cases
actually the space use tends not to be
that
large so in a typical tree recursion
you're going to have a massive amount of
computation if you don't memorize
because you're like building out this
whole tree of many many different
recursive calls
but the space that you need is only the
length of the longest path through that
tree and you could have many more nodes
in the tree
than you could have the height of the
tree and so
for that reason the space usually isn't
the kind of
important limiting factor for a tree
recursion problem
it's usually time making all those calls
um rather than the amount of space it
takes to capture all the active ones at
any particular moment
usually you know depends on the problem
yeah and 20 years ago space was a real
concern
these days it's a little bit less of a
concern memory is cheap
everybody's got a terabyte of memory so
we worry a little bit less about memory
but you're absolutely right michonne is
there
are certain recursive functions we have
all written that you would never really
do recursively
there's no reason not to do them
iteratively it's just more of the
exercise
of learning recursion and if you think
about a tree recursion problem like
count partitions
where you're kind of uh making branching
calls
there's a way to do this without
recursion but it does use the same
amount of space if you do it without
recursion you basically just have to
track all the frames explicitly in a
list instead of having the interpreter
do it for you so it's not like avoiding
recursion tends to help you much
there and then some problems
um so if you watch the the lecture on
the towers of hanoi
they just the solutions are just so much
easier recursively like they have to
think through the iterative solution can
be really gnarly
so every once in a while you know
there's a very clean and elegant
recursive solution
those are the ones i particularly like
and i guess the final case to talk about
is when you're doing something with a
tree that's a common case for
uh recursion and in that case like the
tree is already there
you've already like used that much
memory so having an extra frame for each
node in the tree
you know it's more but it's not like a
lot more um so it tends not to be
a big issue that was a long answer to a
simple question but uh
but i guess it wasn't that simple
[Laughter]
no it's a great question michonne it's
absolutely the right question
and so if if the kind of essence of the
question is
should we not use recursion for stuff
where we could just use a while loop
basically that's a good piece of advice
yeah
okay so the question was about the exam
prep
sections uh worksheet number six
which covered object drawing and
programming
and had the following question on it
fill in each of the blanks and the code
such that the expressions and outputs in
the table below are consistent
okay so it gives you a bunch of examples
and uh
i assume that effects from previous
subpart persist to future subparts i
think that's like as we go
down here changes are going to
accumulate
so we have a party class which has a
guest's linked list
as its class attribute
some minute that will have to work out
some notion of attending
and then we have a costume party
which is a subclass of party that's got
its own in it
it's going to do something to party's
class attribute called guests and it's
going to do something to its own
instance attribute
um and it's got its own notion of attend
and it's got its own rapper method which
i guess is going to be pretty
interesting here
so um
let's take a look at what's going on um
when you create a linked list
you create it with two arguments the
first element and the rest of the list
if you left this link that empty out and
just passed in one argument you get the
same thing
because link that empty is the default
value for the rest of the list
and link has a wrapper method which
generates uh an expression that would
create an equivalent linked list
okay um so that's what we see here and
here
what we see here is that when you create
a party
with one as its
time
and you look up the guests you end up
with a linked list that's got
2 in it we don't really have a story for
why that would be except that here
we have an assignment line that we could
use to change
partygut yes to be something else
um or we could change the instance
attribute for guess to be something else
and the tricky thing about this problem
is that we don't actually know which one
it is yet like you can't tell from this
expression
whether guess is an instance attribute
or a class attribute
but since the class attribute is there
already hopefully it's that
okay when we
call party3 and then dot attend
now we have well an interesting pattern
is emerging
which is that uh this is one more than
that
and this is one more than that and
um then something a little bit crazy
happened here this is not a linked
list but instead well it is a linked
list but it doesn't have three elements
instead it's got two elements where the
first one is four
and the other one is its own list so if
we were writing this
in a python list this would look like
four with two as the second element
that's what this link
four link link two structure is
equivalent to
um and how we got here i guess we don't
know yet but we can take a look at what
attend does
so attend uh
does something and then
it returns
self.guest is party.guest okay
so that must be true
because otherwise we wouldn't we'd just
be getting false and that's not what
we're getting we're getting a linked
list
and so it's returning party.guest so
this
is an interesting hint self.guest is
party.guest means that there really is
no
instance attribute on a party instance
instead it must be a class attribute for
these two things to be the same thing
so it must be that we're manipulating
class attributes here
and uh we can look at how that happened
we um
added something to the linked list and
then somehow we like got this nested
structure which i guess we're going to
have to understand
it's plausible that the elements were
added here
and that the nested structure was
created here
maybe this is more of a puzzle than i
would expect
um but uh i think we're making some
progress so
uh let's see if we can
fill some of this in and then i'll stop
and ask
take questions so it seems like this has
to be
that party dot
guests is being changed and how's it
being changed
well as far as i can tell we're taking
time
adding one to and putting that in
as a new element in this linked list how
do you take
a existing linked list and put something
new on the front
well you call link with the new element
on the front
and then keep the rest of the list in
there
so the original list becomes the rest of
the list you would write that as
party.guests
so this just makes like a linked list of
numbers
every time you call party then you get
like a
another element now why is it that
guests and time are somehow related i
have no idea
but i didn't write this problem so um
here we are
now we have to think about this nested
structure how could it be
that um
after calling party one and party three
we had
uh guess as like a nice linked list that
looked like link four link two
and somehow we got an extra link in here
we're to need an assignment
statement in order to do that i think in
order to get from here
to here let's see if i can line these up
a little bit better
we have to change the rest of this
linked list
in order to be a linked list that
contains whatever was there before
this is a valid thing to do um maybe
we'll do a python list version of it
in a minute but let's talk about what it
would look like so this would be like
party.guest.rest equals
link of
oh i typed it wrong party dot
guests
this particular assignment statement
would get us from here
to here because all we did was
replace what was in this position with a
linked list containing what was in that
position
then if you evaluate this you'll find
that self.guess is parted i guess so
that's true
and and uh expression will always return
the second thing if the first one is
true and so the second thing is
party.guests which means we're returning
this whole
linked list and that's what we see so
this is now the value of party.guests
nothing in the chat yet people want to
ask questions you could just chime in
otherwise i'll keep going
here's a question john why is it not
party.gus.red
for what's in the link parentheses oh
yeah i probably shouldn't
i think that's right if you go down to
the yeah
i think that's right otherwise the the
party 7 wouldn't have worked i think
yeah otherwise we would have had a four
in here and we don't want a four
in here we just want the rest of that
all right thanks that's right
thank you raymond
okay um
what's going on with this costume party
well let's take a look
so when you call a costume you're
passing a bow and a tie
which is gonna update party i guess that
rests somehow
and it's going to update this instance
attribute
and then we're going to attend which
calls this
it doesn't necessarily call the party
function at all what it does
is it prints a wrapper string for
self dot ie
[Music]
and
what came out was
[Music]
nice
link costume these both have to have
appeared
as a result of this print call because a
10 doesn't return anything
so none of this is due to a 10's return
value
this all has to be from the print
so when you call repper
on selfie
you are invoking the rapper method for
the class
of uh
of selfie so um
this is not immediately going to invoke
the repper method
for this value itself
because instead it's just going to
invoke
oh come on invoke the
wrapper method for whatever this link is
that we've created
now if this link happens to contain
uh the costume party instance
then we'll get a call to this repper man
this is a convoluted one
so um
we need to construct this value such
that
we get print nice
right here
i'm gonna make a hypothesis then we'll
trace it through and see if we got it
right or not
i think the trick is to print nice here
to return
costume here
and to oh
create here a linked list with only one
element and that element is
self
let's see what we've done
i'm gonna ignore this line for a while
just work with what we have
if it's the case that we create a
costume
with five and six so far we're ignoring
the five and the six
and we're creating an instance attribute
which is a linked list
containing just this costume instance
now when we call when we invoke a tend
we're calling this method which prints
the result of calling
wrapper on selfie which is a linked list
containing the costume
when you create a linked list
uh when you create the wrapper string
for a linked list
what it does is it gets the
um the string that represents each
element
and puts those into a larger expression
so let's take a look at it
this is true of all kinds of lists we
happen to write it explicitly
when you want a wrapper string here's an
example
the way you do it is that you
recursively get the repper string for
the rest
but you also get the wrapper string for
the first and then you put those
together into an expression
it's like link of whatever the first
looks like
and whatever the rest looks like so
to get a wrapper string for this linked
list you need to figure out how to write
down the number one
and you need to figure out how to write
down the rest of the list and then you
put them together into one expression
that's what's happening here
here we are trying to draw this as a
string
which means we have to call repper on
self
when we call wrapper on self that
invokes this wrapper method which prints
out nice
returns the string costume that's the
string
that's representing this costume
instance
and then it is the wrapper method of the
link
class that puts the word link
and the parentheses around whatever i
returned
right here and that's not even the end
of the question
apparently there's a there's a part
there's a whole other part to it
this is a good i have to say this is a
killer question
yeah if the exam prep is difficult then
maybe the exam will seem more reasonable
or maybe not we'll see so um this is
changing what party.10
does
in some arbitrary way i think
the easiest way to get this behavior
would be to just kind of ignore
everything
and say oh from now on party.attend
just returns uh
this text
[Laughter]
that's really bizarre that's one way to
hack it to do what we want
that you would be right there totally
could be another way
that involves getting party.guest.rest
to be oh there's no way there's no way
you're converting the
what's the current party for yeah no
that's got to be the way to do it right
john
well no there's this opportunity to like
reset party.guest.rest to whatever we
want so
ah it was this but we could rewrite it
to have uh an eight and a four and a
five in it there
yeah okay and then we could like
print that out but in any case i think
this solves the question
party seven just does whatever it does
who cares
uh because now whenever you invoke a
tend you just get this
probably not the answer that was
intended but
okay a really great exercise
i would say is uh
trying to figure out how some nested
structure
would be represented as a linked list
if you have this thing what's the linked
list equivalent so
you know let's call this s what's the t
well it's a linked list that starts with
one
the next element is actually another
list
and what's the last element
just a number
oh it's never a good sign
so s looks like that t looks like some
monstrosity
but there is a stir method on
linked list that does something kind of
reasonable
basically this was designed let's look
at that
this stair method which you get when you
print something out oh look
this example looks very familiar um
this method was designed so that it
behaves in basically the same way
as the built-in lists wrapper
so that you can kind of look at the
correspondence between the two
now it's still the case that in order to
access stuff in here
you know accessing something in here
like getting the 2 would look like that
but getting the 2 in here means you have
to treat it like a linked list
you have to get the rest and then you
have to get the first and then that
turns out to be a linked list and so you
have to get a number out of that
so still the operations are different
because it's a different kind of data
structure
but it can represent the same sort of
nested stuff that you could