this is the lecture 11 q a
and the first question was what is an
abstraction barrier
they turned out to be like one of the
more important concepts
in this course so
i get emails once in a while from
students
who say like oh i just took the
operating systems
course 162 and i never would have
survived that huge project except that i
remembered about
abstraction barriers and so i was able
to build it so
this is a concept that's very important
for building large programs
which is quite different than what we've
done in this course i mean actually your
projects are pretty large but
but eventually you want to build really
large applications
and the only way to make those
manageable is to use abstraction
barriers because then you can change
parts without having to change other
parts
you can think about one thing at a time
you don't have to kind of
understand everything and how it
interacts all at once in order to make
progress
so the idea behind an abstraction
barrier is that
you choose how you're going to describe
some computation
using some particular set of names
or functions in this case because uh all
of our names refer to either values
or functions and functions actually do
stuff
so the story would be that when you're
like doing
something like performing some big
computation
you only use uh these operations here
in order to do it that you want to add
rationals together figure out whether
rationals are equal
if you're working with rational numbers
without ever
like doing anything with the
representation of rational numbers
like uh inspecting their components
the reason you do this is so that all
that code you wrote in order to perform
a big computation of like uh
you know the weather system or the air
quality forecast or whatever
doesn't need to change at all if later
you decide to change the way in which
you're representing numbers
and this is true not just of
representing numbers but representing
anything if you want to like
build a system that crawls the web
looking for like interesting web pages
you want to build that in terms of a set
of functions that describes how to get
the parts of a web page that doesn't
assume that you know
the internal data representation of that
web page which might change over time
so uh you know that's basically the
story is that
when you write part of your program you
say in advance
oh i'm going to write it in terms of
these basic operations
and then use those basic operations and
and those basic operations then need to
be implemented somehow and that is the
next
layer below the abstraction barrier is
that you describe
how to add rationals or multiply
rationals or whatever
so you're basically parts of the program
that implement
the things that you're using in the
higher layer also
need to be built out of a fixed set of
components in this case
functions that get the numerator and the
denominator because you can't
add things unless you know how to get
their parts so
um yeah i hope that wasn't too
long-winded but the story is
break apart your large program into
pieces
that don't depend on how the other parts
are implemented
let me let me add a couple things i i
like that last bit i think that was
exactly right so let me add a few things
so first of all
abstraction barriers are somewhat
abstract and
it's it's going to be hard to know
exactly where to draw those lines until
you start writing code and then you
realize
oh i made a change over here that
trickled down
and i had to go through ten thousand
lines of code to make some changes which
means you violated
an abstraction barrier and that's you
sort of learn by making these mistakes
that's number one
number two is abstraction barriers are
built on the concept that code is not
static it's constantly changing there's
no notion of
you write something and then you go home
and that thing runs for the next 10
years and
code is constantly changing and because
of that
you want to isolate the impact of change
yeah so imagine an automobile think
about all the complexity of an
automobile the wheels
the chassis the engine and imagine a
world where
you decide you're going to make a change
to the windshield wipers and now you
gotta change you gotta make a change in
the carburetor
because of that so you wanna isolate
where
change impacts and that's this notion of
abstraction barriers that
if i make a change in one of these rows
here there's no
ripple effect down to the rest of the
code
and that makes it easier to make changes
and to of course debug
and now the question you want to ask is
well how do i know where to draw those
lines
and that's where it takes a little bit
of time and experience and you'll see
where we draw those abstraction barriers
to make sure we hide things
from other parts of the code a follow-up
question was
if you make a change to one layer in
this picture
does that affect all the layers above or
all the layers below
it depends how you make that change
there are many changes that happen
in within a layer that
won't affect any other layer
above or below if you don't change the
names of the rational operations
and you don't change how they're being
like
the basic components all you do for
example
is now store the numerator and
denominator
in terms of uh like terms by
like applying a gcd uh every time you
uh perform addition that change could
actually be isolated at just one
particular layer
and not have not require you to make any
changes to the code that implements all
this stuff
and not require any changes to the code
down here so
that's the ideal sometimes a change will
require
you to edit something above or below if
you've sort of changed the name of add
rational then you're going to have to
change everything that calls that
rational to
use the new name but
but many changes will be limited in
their scope to just
one uh layer meaning it won't
cross either abstraction barrier above
or below
so there's a couple questions in the
chat so let me just read them and then
we'll see if we can answer them so as
you go down the chart the function
should be simpler
not necessarily you can have incredible
complexity
in the implementation of a list hide
that from me
and i can use a list and i don't care so
the
the hierarchy here isn't really about
complexity it's just about
layers of abstraction and how you're
doing things
exactly like we talked about
dictionaries in this class
the implementation of dictionaries
actually changed quite recently
in python but no python code had to
change as a result because all the
python code that you write
is above the abstraction layer that
separates
the language from its interpreter the
interpreter did change like the way in
which
you know what is a dictionary is it a
list of key value pairs is it something
else well you'll learn all about it
in 61b but actually i'm not sure that
even in 61b you'll learn all the details
of what goes into a modern python
dictionary i mean it's quite a
complicated data structure
but it was edited and changed without
really affecting any python programs
because there was something complicated
but sometimes the program you write that
uses a dictionary can be very simple
okay next question in the chat and we'll
i'm sorry we'll get back to the i think
we have plenty of time we'll get back to
the hands raising a second but these are
good questions um how do constructors
and selectors come into play
so what constructors and selectors
they're just a level of abstraction so
let's talk about a selector
the selector says give me the numerator
and then you don't have to worry about
that it's represented as a pair as a
list and get the zeroth element so the
selectors
are a way of abstracting out the
underlying data implementation by saying
look here's a function call
this function call hands you back this
part of the data it's none of your
goddamn business
how i implemented it just ask me for
what you want and i will give it to you
and that's that's what the
selector does and it's also what a
constructor does you give the
constructor numbers and it builds the
data type without you knowing
necessarily
that it's implemented as a pair or a
tuple or a list or whatever
so that's sort of the goal of those
functions is the function
themselves abstract out the underlying
data type
yeah in this picture the group of names
that's over here on the right in the
using column
kind of describes the barrier just below
and we'll see here there's an example of
just selectors and constructors being
the names
that are describing this barrier so
that's just one way to create an
abstraction barrier is to use
data abstraction constructors and
selectors and together
they describe how you're going to
separate
creating some values and operating on
them
from how you represent those values
using something else
but it's not the only way to create an
abstraction barrier you could also do it
by just like any collection of functions
that you describe
uh even if we change the implementation
of a function should the arguments
always stay the same as this function
would be called another layer this is a
really good question so
ideally yes that's sort of what you want
um now every once in a while
you know things just something really
complicated happens and you
you have to make a change to the
parameters being called and then you've
got to ripple
you know trickle that up or down
the extraction barriers but ideally yes
when you make a change in one of these
rows nothing should change but you know
we're also aware that sometimes
you add a huge amount of complexity or
something really radical changes in
which case you're going to have to deal
with that
sometimes you will have to break through
those barriers
yeah exactly and your barrier stable in
a way
if your function signatures stay the
same so that's the name
plus the set of arguments that they take
that's the whole signature of a function
basically the whole def line uh and if
that stays the same then you're you can
make change below without
affecting anything above uh this is just
a very specific question about
dictionaries
for dictionaries do all the keys have to
be one data type and all the values be
one data type
um so the i'm not sure about the latest
uh dictionaries in python i don't
believe they do right certainly
the values can be any data type you want
and the keys also well they can't be
lists of course but they can be
integers or strings yeah yeah you can
have a mix of different
uh types so it's very flexible in that
way
yeah and by the way lists are the same
way obviously the the key
in in a list is just the integer 0 1 2 3
but the values in a list can be
arbitrary right you can have a list of
a mixture of strings and integers and
lists and lists of lists and objects and
blah blah blah
so the dictionaries are just even a
little bit more general because you can
index on anything
another follow-up question was does data
abstraction only apply to rational
numbers or is this something more
general
that's just one example we're going to
be doing a lot of examples of data
abstraction that was just a particularly
nice example of how you can hide certain
implementation details from the user
yeah good question so um
the question is how would you convert a
rational that you've created using
this data abstraction to a
float value so that you could perform
whatever mathematics you want
using the float um
and where do you have to be careful
about violating abstraction barriers
i think a good way to handle this case
would be that once you have your
rational implementation that we talked
about
from lecture which does whatever it does
you would write another function which
is part of the description of how to
manipulate rational numbers which
converts it into a float that would be a
fine way to do it so
if this is
our abstraction
uh we could write a rational to float
function
which returns the numerator of r
divided by the denominator of r
and you know where is this
in the like uh layers that we developed
well i think this is actually
part of the like manipulation
of rational numbers the same place where
ad rational
is where in order to
uh
in order to convert this into a float
you have to have access to its numerator
and its denominator you can't just
create
think of it as a whole object you have
to think of it as parts
but you don't have to know how those
parts are bundled together
you just have to know that those parts
exist and then
that they give you back numbers and
those numbers can be divided
so um yeah if there's like three parts
of the program you have your
uh data abstraction you have your
operations on that data and then you
have your
you know weather simulation or whatever
is down here
um that is based on rational numbers
i think that converting to a float would
be in here somewhere as yet another
operation that you might apply to
rational numbers
yeah i think that's exactly right notice
a couple of things notice that the
function
rational to float does not access r
using r sub zero and r sub one it uses
the selector
functions because it's across a barrier
right so even though it sort of knows
what it's doing that's a no no because
if we change the
representation up at the very top here
we don't want it to trickle down that's
number one
and number two to uh the question is
if you want to create functionality for
rationals do it
add that functionality i can add
rationals i can multiply rationals
i can now convert it to return to a
float and build it
into your think of it as a library
you're building a library for
manipulating in this case rational
numbers
i need something to represent them i
need something to manipulate them and
don't let the user do it
i mean the user may want to eventually
do something but your job is the coder
to say all right what is the user going
to need
give them the functionality to do that
and a follow-up question is should we be
assuming that this r that gets
passed in was created by this function
and that is exactly the assumption that
you make for everything in here
assume all r's uh
are the return value of calling rational
yeah those are think of them as those
are functions that
operate on rational numbers defined
using what you see above right that's
what they operate on that's the data
type that they operate on
exactly so we are making assumptions
um wouldn't it be nice if we could like
assert that somehow
um well um you
you could try to set that up we haven't
really talked about how to do it but
it's not terribly complicated
um you could just uh
add an is rational check
in here which does something and that is
what you would assert
and you might want to set it up so that
not every pair every list
is this maybe you want to set it up so
that the way you really build these
is that you talk about it as a rational
number
and then you could have this be like uh
return
len r equals three and r zero
is this special string rational or
something like that
so then basically not every list that
has two numbers in it
is a rational number instead they all
have this kind of special keyword this
is the kind of thing that was done
quite broadly before um object-oriented
programming
and it is the same idea that we'll see
in object-oriented programming except
for that will then be
kind of built into the language and
happen for you automatically
so this is an old idea of tagging data
types
and then kind of checking to make sure
that you have the right thing and i
think it's a good one because it helps
reinforce these assumptions right by the
way notice something super cool in what
john just did
he just made a huge change in the
underlying data representation of
rational numbers
it's now a triple with a string in the
first position and the numerator in the
denominator second
and third position what did he have to
do to change the code to make
everything work he had to change two
functions right
numer and denom and everything below
stays exactly the same there is no
impact on the rest of the code that
right there what john just did
is sort of epitomizes the abstraction
barrier right he made a change up top
and there's absolutely no impact down
below
the next question was how do you figure
out in a tree recursion problem
how to break down the problem into two
recursive cases
so this is a question of how to think
about recursion and i think you're right
there is something a little
sort of twisted in the way you have to
think about it so
here's how i think about it and i don't
know if this will be helpful either let
me tell you how i think about it
as i'm writing the function i tell
myself
this function works and i can call this
function
to do the thing i want it to do it's
really sort of the ultimate in
abstraction
i say i'm writing a function that
computes fibonacci
assume i have it and when i have it
assume i can call it and then just do it
just call the function and that's sort
of that's that leap of faith that we
were talking about earlier you're going
to jump off the cliff and hope that the
parachute is
is going to get configured as your fault
plummeting to the earth
yeah um so i think it is really thinking
about
the functionality first of all it's
thinking about how the function is
defined
how the the problem is defined
recursively and then just calling your
function and
one of the things that helps here is to
use really sensible
function names and variable names if
you're using them so that when you say
you know the fibonacci of n is the
fibonacci of n minus one plus
fibonacci of n minus two it sort of
makes sense that you're just calling
this thing in some ways you can think
about
it is calling somebody else's function
that does the thing that you want the
fact that a recursive is
not really actually that important it
turns out john may have
another suggestion i thought that was
great i i think the other
one last piece to keep in mind is that
many tree recursion
problems involve making a choice
like am i gonna you know you're trying
to find the
longest sequence within a list
that um that all increases or something
like that
the choice there might be am i going to
keep the current element in the answer
or am i going to throw it away
and figuring out what that choice is
where if you stack many of these choices
on top of each other make one after the
other
then you could get to any possible
solution and this choice splits like
all the possible solutions into two
groups one that
where this choice is true and one where
this choice is false
finding that choice is often the key to
the implementation this was true for
competitions it would be true for
example in the account change problem on
your homework
um and it's not something that's
obvious in the description of the
problem instead it's part of the
implementation that you have to figure
out it's like how could i make one
choice here
and by making similar choices many many
times over i'll eventually get to the
answer that i want and i don't think
it's
uh trivial at all to come up with that
choice
but you can think about options like oh
am i going to use this first thing or
not
is is often the choice and um
or like how many of the first few things
am i going to use one or two or three or
four or whatever
and then coming up with the recursive
calls
usually is kind of mechanical once
you've figured out what the choice is
so in count partitions it was about
like am i going to use the biggest part
or not
and um when i use it then i get one
recursive call and when i forget about
it then i
get another recursive call and and so
like you can often reconstruct what the
recursive calls are
just by thinking about like what happens
if i follow this choice
path a or path b and then just like
connie said in order to
figure out whether you made progress or
not you do have to assume that the
function works
and think about that recursive call as
something that's got behavior it's going
to do the right thing without worrying
about how it does it
yeah and then the less good answer here
to this is it will come with experience
like you just you got to do more
examples you'll start to see patterns
emerge
there's a relatively small number of
patterns emerge that
in doing recursive functions and the
more you do the more comfortable you'll
get with it
um almost so the question is about this
concept of getters and setters
in java and is that the same thing as
constructors and selectors
in data abstraction
and there isn't quite a one-to-one
mapping there instead what i would say
is that constructors are like
instructors in java and that
selectors are like getters and we
haven't really talked about setters at
all because we haven't talked about
changing a value at all yet but we will
get there so if you really wanted to
replicate that behavior from java then
you'd need another set
of setter functions in addition to the
selector functions
and the constructor but conceptually yes
it is it's it's those the setters and
the getters probably
like my the the hairs on the back of my
neck
cringe when i hear that because i'm not
a big fan of the java programming
language
but conceptually that what they are
about is data abstraction they are
hiding details
from the rest of the code and so
conceptually that is the same idea and
you'll see that get formalized a little
bit more
in python too there is a not there is a
notion of classes and objects in python
and we'll see that
well great question so the question is
like what exactly is a constructor and a
selector we've done one example and how
does this generalize to other examples
and like what counts as constructors and
selectors and what doesn't
the the core concept here is about data
representation
there's like something in the world and
you want to write a program about it
but your program is just full of like
numbers and lists and strings
how do you represent something else in
the world that's um
more complicated and rational numbers in
some sense is a bad example because it's
just more numbers but what we really
should be thinking about is
like how do you represent a whole um
house and because you're building like a
real estate site
well a house like has all kinds of
attributes it's got a
location oh so how we're going to
represent locations
uh it's got a layout oh so how are we
going to represent the layout
well all of these are actually like
different data abstractions that you
could include you could have
a location is represented as its
longitude and latitude but that might
not actually be right
instead it should be represented as like
it's a
street address which has a number and a
street name and the zip code and stuff
like that
so basically everything interesting in
the world has multiple different
attributes multiple different parts
and some of those have parts and some of
those have parts
and data abstraction gives you a tool
for managing all of this
where you can say like oh a house is
built out of its location and its layout
and a location is built out of its uh
street address and its longitude and
latitude and the street address is built
out of a bubble ball
so the whole use of constructors and
selectors
in a larger program would be to define
these things that you're trying to
describe
in your larger program so they would say
like oh i'm going to give function names
that associate
to each one of these attributes of some
concept that i'm trying to represent
like a house and i'm going to say like
every time i build a house i need these
three things
and every time i have a house already
and i have a name for that i can access
those attributes
here's another example let's say you
want to build b courses
yeah so what do you need you need a
course what's a course
well it has a title it has an instructor
it has a date and time
it has a well it used to have locations
where they were being taught
you have students students have ids they
have scores they have the year
of their enrollment and then you want to
be able to construct a student
that's a constructor you want to be able
to ask something about
a student what's their student id number
um
what is their grade on this exam or on
this homework
and so john said it exactly right that
the rationals is a really simple example
right you just have these two little
numbers in the list and you're like
why am i doing all this fussiness for
that but as you build bigger programs
the amount of data you have can get very
complex and again you want to hide that
implementation detail from the user
and we'll see examples of that you'll
see where we start to build more complex
data
types and where you need to be able to
use these things
a follow-up question was is there a
difference between constructors and
selectors or are they basically the same
thing
there there is a difference between
constructors and selectors so let's go
let's do the rational example
the constructor creates a rational
number
yeah it takes two numbers takes takes a
list and hands that back to you
the selector says give me one part of
the data the numerator
or the denominator in my example of b
courses a constructor
would create a record for a student it
would populate everything
that was passed to it and then the
selector would say okay give me these
little pieces of information
associated with a student that has been
constructed
yeah the next question was is data
abstraction
similar to object oriented programming
are they basically the same thing
they are they are absolutely i mean
they're object-oriented programming is
designed
around this notion of data abstraction
that you build these
classes slash objects you abstract out
the underlying data with constructors
and selectors you create functionality
within the class
and then you combine those classes to
create larger programs
and object when did object-oriented
start john maybe
20 years ago something like that
certainly became popular like 20-30
years ago i think yeah
it's back to small talk so it's uh its
invention was older than that but um
but it's certainly become like the
dominant paradigm for building
applications more recently
right but but you're absolutely right
audrey that this is
this is this is the this is the lead up
to
classes objects and object-oriented
programming
yeah and i think object-oriented
programming has multiple ideas
all kind of lumped into one in this
course we try to isolate them a little
bit to give you some exposure before we
kind of throw you into everything at
once so this is the biggest one
thing that objects allow you
to do data abstraction but it's built
into the language instead of you having
to decide the representation every time
that kind of happens automatically
the second is about
changing state which we'll talk about
next in the course like very soon
and the third is about like
relationships between types which is
something that
actually is used less i'd say in modern
programming
than these other two features but it's
also an important characteristic of
object-oriented programming
which we'll teach as we teach you about
object-oriented programming and so
that's coming up as kind of the next
unit
in the course uh after we finish talking
about data abstraction
and uh what we call mutation which is
basically like objects that are changing
then we'll put that together and you can
see how it's built into the language
using objects
and by the way since somebody mentioned
java earlier let me just mention a few
things
if you've done any java programming if
you haven't just ignored what i'm about
to say but if you've done notice that in
java
everything's an object you can't really
can't do anything without objects and
one of the great things about python is
there is you will see that there is an
infrastructure for doing object
programming but you don't have to use it
it gives you that sort of flexibility
um and that's actually by the way
pedagogically one of the reasons why i
like python as
a first language is it it doesn't get
into all of this stuff on day one you
can actually
well extract it out and not worry about
it until you have to worry about it
the next question was for the slide that
lit on fire
what exactly was wrong with the code
that was written there how did it
violate data abstraction principles
oh yeah first of all can we just applaud
john for how awesome that slide was
um i really i was i was i
i got a great kick out of that and by
the way it violated the data abstraction
in so many different ways i don't even
think john enumerated all of them
yeah i mean it's hard it's hard to think
about a large program in the context of
a lecture where the program is actually
tiny
right so um so what's wrong with this
code
it looks sort of fine right but it is
violating these general programming
principles
which are really important if we were
writing a larger program
and so what we would expect here
is that ad rational would only take as
arguments
the return value of calls to the
rational constructor
so when earlier in this discussion
oh i guess i deleted it yeah you changed
the representation of rationals to like
include a third element a string
this line of code would break as a
result because it doesn't call rational
on one and two
instead it just builds a list of one and
two which means that if you ever changed
the behavior of rational
you'd have to go change this line of
code which we don't want to do
so the idea is that every call to add
rational
should not be affected by changing the
implementation of rational
or its selectors numero and dino so that
was what was wrong with this line
is that we passed in the wrong kinds of
arguments to add rational
even though it ran it wouldn't run in
the future
if we had changed the implementation of
the constructor and the selectors
what a mess right is that like the code
is wrong because
one day it might be wrong but right now
it's right well that's exactly the kind
of thing you
do have to think about if you're
building large programs
is that it's not good enough that this
thing runs today
and uh doesn't crash and passes all the
dock tests or whatever
it really has to be built with an eye
toward the future
where decisions that you made about your
implementation
when you're first getting started are
certainly going to change because you're
going to think of something new
later like you want to be able to assert
that something's rational so you need to
change the representation
well look like uh if you have to go back
and edit all your code then you're never
going to want to make changes
and that means your code base will never
improve and you'll end up with kind of a
program that's stuck with all the
problems that you ever inserted
whereas if you write code that's sort of
future proof
in this way by using these abstraction
barriers to isolate
parts of the program then uh
then you can be comfortable making
changes and
uh you won't have to worry about
breaking anything that was already there
so that was basically the story and and
what you see here is true down here as
well
divide rational was supposed to be part
of the program
that assumes it's getting rational
numbers and
only manipulates them using the
constructor and the selector
so it should have returned a call to
rational
that got the numerator and the
denominators
using calls to numer and dnom and that's
not what we did
and therefore this would have to be
entirely rewritten if
we changed the implementation of the
data abstraction
this is this is a really important
concept and it's
it's understandable if it's not entirely
crystal clear in your head
don't worry as we do bigger examples and
more examples you'll start to see that
abstraction but it is something that
um johnson did exactly right um is
at least for me when i really learned
this is when i had to either change my
code or change somebody else's code
and i realized that you know something i
would do up here in some function had
this weird effect down below
and you're just going to learn by
writing crappy code
and you're going to realize oh this when
i want to make some change to something
which
always happens um and it's and sometimes
it's
you start writing code and then you
realize you you forgot something
you've already got 10 000 lines of code
you got to make some big change back
early on
and you're like oh crap this is going to
trickle all the way down
and so that's when you start really sort
of thinking you know really hard
about these abstractions and how you
write code in a way that can
build sort of a really solid
infrastructure
so it takes a little bit of time and
experience so hang tight
this is maybe the first topic in the
course where having learned it
you can't do anything no
at this point some chaos ensued because
of the phone call i received
and i've edited that part out
um well who knows what i was saying but
i'm sure it was very you're saying
you're saying that this is one of the
concepts where you learn it it's not
immediately obvious how to apply it just
yet
right you can't like write some program
that you couldn't write before
but you know also a topic that students
tell me is one of the more important
things that they learned
while they were in 61a because it
applies so much to
kind of later parts yeah this is the one
concept that will carry you
just about every class you take when
you're writing code this is probably one
of the most important concepts that
you'll take away from you and it's also
one of the most abstract
so that's okay that just means it takes