61 a lecture No.15
announcements
the cats project is due Friday
you get a bonus point for submitting the whole project
by Thursday that's today
homework three will be posted on Friday
is do next Thursday
we have some advising off
sour appointments Friday Saturday and Monday
those are just for advising
not for homework or project help
I know that there have been some
long weights on the office hour q
this week
we are definitely trying to improve that situation
and I'm sorry if you're having trouble getting your
questions answered
remember that
you're welcome to post private post sam piazza
which will not be answered immediately
but we'll be answered eventually
and you're also welcome to discuss these problems
with the other students that you know in the course
for example from your tutorial group
and if they've finished a question already
then it's okay for them to take a look at your code
and give you some advice
you can't share
your code with someone who hasn't finished a question
because otherwise they might just copy it
and you need to write code yourself
but if you want to work with
another student that's in the class
you're welcome to discuss any ideas
and you're welcome to help people
who aren't quite as far along as you are
by taking a look at what they've done so far
and giving them some advice
I know that your time is valuable
and I don't want you all waiting around
we are trying to deal with this
it is an unusual semester
where we've had much higher question volume on piazza
much more demand
for 1 on 1 office hours than we're used to
and we will try very hard to meet that demand
but please bear with us
okay back to the course content
today is a very important day
where you learn about mutation
which is when a value actually changes
and this is not something
that's happened in the course before
but it is very common
and it's a core
element of what we're going to be studying
very soon in this course
which is what's called object oriented programming
the current
dominant paradigm for designing large programs
and a wonderful bundle of ideas that includes
as one of them
this notion of mutation
okay here we go
objects are an important concept
in software engineering
an object is a value that behaves
like what it's supposed to represent
let me show you an example
there's a module called date time
which represents things like dates and times
and from that we can import date
now date is what's called a class
and when I create an instance of a date
I do that by calling the class
so if I created date
two thousand fifteen february twentieth
that's a date
another date is the date of your freedom
which in this course and this semester is on may the 12
when you take your final exam
now an object is supposed to behave
like the value that it represents
so it should be the case that if I combine
today and freedom
for instance by computing how long it is
between freedom and today
I should get a reasonable representation
something that
tells me these things are dates
that I'm subtracting from one or another
there are 81 days left until you're free of this course
the primary mechanism by which objects have behavior
is through their attributes
and you access the attribute of an object
through a dot expression
so you can get the year of today
or the month of today
by asking for its year
or its month attribute using a dot expression
we'll talk exactly
about how dot expressions get evaluated
when we do a
deeper introduction of the object system in python
but for now you should realize
what one of these expressions means
this is a name
it could be any expression that evaluates to an object
and then you have a dot
and then
the name of the attribute that you want to look up
in addition to attributes that are bound to values
you can have attributes that are bound to functions
those are called methods
so a method is anything that you access
using adot expression
and then called like a function
the stirf time method of a date
is a way of formatting that date as a string
why is it called stirf time
well that's a historical accident
somebody named this stirf time long ago
and so we still use that name today
what surf time does
is it takes in a string that describes how
I want to display this date
today is what's being displayed
and so this method is invoked on today
in order to give me a string representation
that says Friday February 20
where the % a correspondent of Friday
% b correspondent of February percent d
corresponded to 20
now notice that up here
I never said that this was a Friday
I never even said that the way you say February is febr
uari
it's just part of what it means to be a date
to be able to generate things
like the name of the weekday
or the name of the month
and so that's what I mean when I talk about
objects behaving like the things they represent
so objects represent information
they consist of data and behavior bundled together
to create abstractions
objects can represent things
but also properties of things
or interactions or processes
they're an extremely general concept
anything that has attributes
can be represented as an object
a type of object is called a class
classes are first class values in python
they can be passed in as arguments to functions
and objects are the heart of object oriented
programming which is an approached programming
that allows us to organize large programs
using a central metaphor
that a large program is just one big thing
it's a bunch of individual objects
communicating with each other
by sending messages back and forth
now in order to convincingly use
this metaphor throughout the large program
we have a special syntax
and the dot expression is part of that special syntax
that helps us improve the readability
or composition of our programs
in python every value is an object
every value has attributes
including numbers and strings
a lot of data manipulation actually happens through
object methods
and we're going to look at several of those today
functions are meant to do one thing
so the well design function has a single purpose
you pass in some arguments you get some return value
objects are different
they represent something that may
have lots of different behavior
bundle together
dates don't just do one thing
they're used in many different ways
so objects do many related things
and they can have multiple methods
each one of which is like a function
strings are objects
and so strings have attributes
the string hello
has a method called upper
which makes it upper case
that's part of the behavior of being a string
you can lower case it
you can even swap case it
now none of these things have changed
s s is still hello
each of these method
invocations has returned a new string
based on the old string
but it does something very string like
so these aren't general functions
these are things that are just particular to strings
and that's why they're methods
as opposed to functions
that are built into the language
now strings are an abstraction
that allows us to represent text
but there is an encoding of those strings as numbers
and actually this encoding is not specific to python
it's shared among many programming languages
so I'll just tell you a little bit about it for fun
an original encoding
not the first one ever invented
but one of the first
standards to take hold and computing
was called asci
the american standard code for information interchange
this was a table that laid out
which numbers corresponded
to which letters and symbols
there are eight rows
and eight is important because
that's how many different rows you can represent using
three bits three ones and zeros
and there are 16 columns
which you can represent using four bits
the layout was chosen to support
sorting by character code
so if you've ever used a computer and found that its
sorts capital letters
before lowercase letters
and puts things with an exclamation mark at the top
and things with a tilda at the end
that's because of the order in the ascii co chart
it was also designed so that if you didn't have
enough bits to represent the entire table
there would be a useful
subset right there in the middle
it meant you had to type in all caps
but that's better than nothing
the control characters at the top here in red
were
designed for transmission or information interchange
but they have original meanings
most of which aren't used today
but some of them still are
so the line feed called lf
was supposed to tell the printer on the other end
to go to the next line
and if you wanted to get somebody's attention
after some information interchange
you might ring the bell on their printer
and these things still exist today
so if I say a is the capital letter a
I can
figure out what number corresponds to that a
it's No.65 which in hexadecimal format is 41
41 tells me the row and column of the capital letter a
and my ascii table
oh there it is
row four column one
if I print the line feed character many times
I'll get multiple lines
and if I print the bell character many times
I should get a sound coming out of my computer
now there are more characters than just these
the ascii standard was English pacific
but the unicode standard
was designed in order to have one character set
that would be used for all different languages
so it's the case that for every character
in every language and every script
that's being used anywhere in the world
there's meant to be a unicode code point for it
or a number ascribe to it
that lets us refer to that character as a number
and use that for any kind of information interchange
among computers among different programming languages
etc
there are currently 109,000 characters
at least last time I checked
in 93 different scripts
and they're organized by script
so it's more than just enumerating
all of the different symbols that people use
in language
they're also marked with what's capitalized
what's not capitalized what language they're used in
etc
and it even supports by directional display order
English is written left right
but arabic is written right to left
and every character has a name
the letter x is called latin capital letter x
now there are a lot of different characters
109,000 of them
including a smiling face and a frowning face
which are just letters in some alphabet
and most programming languages support unicode
and so you can access these characters directly
so I'll add type from unicode data
import name and look up
name gives the name of a unicode character
that's latin capital letter a
and that's a latin small letter a
look up does the opposite
I start with the name and it gives me the character
so if I look up
the smiling face
there's that smiling face
we can make it even bigger so you can see
just how smiling it is
and there are many more characters that
are a little bit quirky
there's a snowman
there's a
sucker ball
there's even a baby
hello baby
now depending on the font on your computer
these will be displayed in different ways
so I think only on the mac
do you see a baby that looks in this particular way
with this haircut
but it could exist on other operating systems as well
the point is there is a character representing baby
how exactly if displayed
might vary from machine to machine
but the idea that there is a baby out there
with a particular encoding
is universal to lots of different programming languages
and you can look at that encoding
by encoding it in bites
and you see
these are the four bites that it takes to represent
a baby
whereas the letter a is encoded just as the letter a
the big no idea for today
is that an object can actually
change its value over time
so in particular we'll look at lists
lists can change their contents
the same list can contain different things
as time goes on
so I'm going to demonstrate how that works
by telling you a story
a story of the history of suits in playing cards
so we think that playing cards were invented in asia
and they began with three
the coin the string and the myriad
and these were representing
different nominations of money
because what are cards good for
well of course gambling
okay so those are our suits
and we're gonna try to keep track of these
original suits
by using this assignment statement
and then we're going to tell a story
about how those suits changed over time
so playing cards migrated over to europe
through Egypt we think
and in the process this myriad suit was lost
and it was also the case that the string suit was lost
leaving only the coin
by the time playing cards reached Spain
there was a need for some new suits
so
in the Spanish deck you have the suit of cups
you also have the suits of
swords
and
clubs
so I coined the cup the sword
and the club I believe existing Spanish decks today
and we've seen so far
you can pop off one element
you can remove an element
that might be anywhere in the list
pop always removes and returns the last
element in the list
you can append a single element
or you can extend the list by
adding multiple elements in a sequence
the italians adapted playing cards of course
and in Italy the way you say sword
which is element No.2
as you say spada
so we have the spade
and then the fringe decided to change some of the suits
and so the coin and the cup went away
and they were replaced by the heart and the diamond
so here are the suits that appear
in a modern american deck
hard diamond spade and club
I believe they're also used in France
okay way up at the beginning
we bound original suits to suits
let's see what original suits is now
it's the same as suits
and that's interesting because we bounded way up here
and then we made a bunch of changes
but it turns out these were just two different names
for the same object
and so changes to one were reflected in the other
this is the first
example in this course of an object changing state
so something big just happened right now
the same object can change in value
throughout the course of computation
if I bind the name same person to some baby
by the way this is a unicode character called baby
then if that baby grows up
same person is still bound to the same person
but
changes appear in that object
if I bind two different names to the same object
and that object changes
while those changes will be reflected
regardless of which change I use
okay so
all names that refer to an object are affected by a
mutation now
becoming an older woman
isn't necessarily called a mutation
out there in the real world
but in computer science
mutation is a word that's used
whenever there's a change to an object
only
objects of mutable types can change in their values
and lists and
dictionaries are examples of that that we've seen
so far
so let's look at how to change
the contents of a dictionary
if I create a dictionary called the numerals
with I bound to one and b bound to five and x
bound to 10
I can look at the contents of the whole dictionary
or I can look at a value bound to a particular key
I can also change the value bound to a key
at which point if I look it up again
I'll get a different answer
and the numerals dictionary has changed
notice that the binding between x and 10 is just gone
completely and it's been replaced by x paired with 11
now I can also make new entries to a dictionary
just using this element assignment statement
so now numerals has more in it than it used to
and I can look up what l is bound to
I can also get rid of a binding by using the pop method
which takes a key
and removes the key value pair for that
so now if I try to get the
value for the key x there's nothing there
because numerals has changed
by the way mutation can happen within a function call
so a function can change the value of any object
that's in its scope
that's a mutable value
so if I say four is 1 2 3 4
and the length of four is four
some mystery function could be called on four
at which point the length of four would be only two
what sort of mystery function might do that
here's one
so this one takes in an argument
will call s and then pops it twice
so invoking the method pop removes the last element
so we define the function
we create the list we call mystery
mystery introduces a new frame in which
s is bound to the same object that four is bound to
so that when I pop that
I'm actually removing the last element
which forever changes the value to which four is bound
now four isn't bound to anything
different than it was before
it's just that this list is different
it has different contents
popping again means that it will be even shorter
here's a different function
that would do the same thing
remove every element after index two
and that would mean removing the three and the four
and replacing that slice of the list
with just no elements at all
now what happens when we create four
and then we call a mystery function
that doesn't take any arguments
does it still have access to four
can it change it sure
how does it do that
well it just refers to the four list
which is within its scope
it's in the global frame
anything can refer to something in the global frame
and so it just starts popping stuff off of four
tuples are sequences
but they are immutable sequences
meaning that they cannot be changed
now before I go on
I will mention that some people call these tuples
and some people call these tuples
and while there is no
established convention
for the pronunciation of this word
the two groups can at least agree
that the other group must be wrong
I'll let you decide how you want to pronounce this word
but I'll say tuple most of the time
though occasionally you'll probably catch me saying
tubal
so doubles or sequence values
3 4 5 6 is a double
see how we've not used square brackets
but instead parentheses
though in fact
you don't need those parentheses at all
in order to have a tup of literal
anything separated by thomas is evaluated as a tuple
a lot of people always put the parentheses around them
just to be clear about what's going on
you can make an empty temple
you can call temple on nothing to make an empty temple
or you could call temple on a list
or any sequence for that matter
and it will give you a temple back
with the same contents as that list
now what if you wanted to have a tupel with only
one element well it is possible to do that
and the syntax is just terrible
you have to put a comma at the end
and you can put that in parentheses as well if you want
so that's different from the No.2
and that this is a tubble containing two
and this is just the No.2
now you can add together
tuples in order to get bigger tuples
you can use the
membership operator to figure out whether
an element is in a tuple
and you can slice tuples as well
now tuples are immutable values
which means it is possible to use them
as the keys in a dictionary
remember that it was not allowed to use a list as a key
in a dictionary
because you get this error unhashable type list
now even though you can use a tuple
you can't have a tuple with a list in it somewhere
that will cause an error as well
so tuples are immutable sequences
and immutable values actually have some benefits
one is that they're protected in a way from mutation
if I have a turtle which is a sequence 1 2 3
and then I call some function called ooze
the turtle is going to still be 1 2 3
because this sequence cannot be changed
numbers are immutable values as well
so are strings
the only mutable values
the ones that can change are lists
so if I have this list turtle 1 2 3 and I call ooze
just like we saw before
we might have anything in turtle at this point
now
it's not strictly true that ooze cannot affect turtle
it can't change this value
but in lex
lecture we'll see that a function could change
what the name turtle is bound to
so you get some protection
but not full protection in the language
from having functions make changes
to your current environment
the value of an expression can change
because of changes the names
or objects so a name change we've seen for a long time
if I have the same expression twice x x and XXX
we might get different values
because the name x has been used for something else
so if I said x equals two then this would be four
but if I said
x equals three then x plus x would be six
so those are name changes
and we've seen them throughout the course
object mutation is different
but it can also have the same effect of
changing what an expression evaluates to
so if x used to be the list one two
then x would be 1 2 1 2
but if I append three to the end
then I'll get one to 3 1 2 3 for x x
so these are two different ways
in which the same
expression can have a different value
and with immutable objects this one doesn't apply
but this one always apply
so you can always change the names of things
an immutable sequence may still change
if it contains a mutable value as an element
so let's say I have a tuple that contains a list
then I can't change the tuple
that's what I mean by immutable
but I could change the list within the temple
so the temple still contains the same stuff
but the list within it is different than it was before
because this one was changed to a four
so as you can see that's not that
so mutation
let's talk about
what it means for something to be the same
and what it means for something to change
once upon a time we never modified objects
and at those times
a compound object was just the totality of its pieces
there was nothing more to being a rational number
than just what was your numerator
what's your denominator
but this view
that the hole is nothing but the some of its parts
is no longer valid in the presence of change
a compound data object such as a list
has an identity
in addition
to the pieces of which it is composed of its elements
so a list might
still be the same list even if we change its contents
so if I have a to bound to 10
and b then bound to that same list a
so what happens here
a gets evaluated to the list containing 10
and then b is bound to that list
a is equal to b
if I aid out of pen 20
a is still equal to b
because a is ten twenty and b is ten twenty
b and a were bound to the same list
even though we changed its contents
however we could have
two lists that happened to have the same contents
but are different in their identity
they are not the same
they just might be equal
so if I say a is the list 10 and b is another list 10
a equals b is true
so far not too different
but if I append 20 to b
a is now 10 b is 10 coma 20
and these two are no longer equal
they were equal before
we never reassigned a or b to anything
so there's no a equals this or b equals that statements
but it's just that these
happened to have the same contents before
so they were equal
but they were never the same
and so when one changed the other didn't
now
how do you figure out whether two things are the same
well there's something called an identity operator
which looks like the word is
and the opposite of is is called is not
so one expression is another expression if
both of those expressions evaluate the same object
equality
is true if both expressions evaluate to equal values
so any list
containing 10 is equal to any other list containing 10
but they may or may not be the same list
identical objects are always equal values
but not the other way around
so it will always be the 10 is 10
and if a is 10
and b is a list containing 10
then amb will be equal
but they won't be the same list
when two things aren't the same
changes to one
don't affect the other
but c being bound to b means that c really is b
they're just two different names for the same thing
so if I pop something off of c
I've also popped it off of b
but nothing has changed about a
now one less something to look out for
is that multiple default arguments are very dangerous
so as soon as you learn about mutation
you have to learn about its risks
a default argument value when you define a function
is part of that function value
not generated anew every time you call the function
so let's say I define a function f
which takes some sequence s
and by default it takes the empty sequence
and what it does is it appends five to that
and then returns the length
of the sequence s after that five has been appended
so you call f
it uses the default argument value
which is an empty list
depends five to it
and returns the length of that list
which contains five
and you get one
if you call it again you get two
if you call it again you get three
and that's because
every time you call it
s will be bound to the same value
that's how defeld arguments work
and if that default argument value is mutable
and you mutate it in the middle of your function
then that change
will still be around
the next time you call the function
and you get that same default argument value
so something that looks pretty simple
will actually have strange behavior
where it's different every time you call the function
and that's definitely something to look out for
in the first call s is bound to an empty list
and that list is then mutated to contain three
the next time I call f
s is bound to that same list
which is mutated again to add another three
and the third time you get the third three
there it is
and that's why we get different return values each time
one than two than three
let's review list mutation and environment diagrams
names can refer to lists
and assignments statements can change
which names refer to which lists
in addition the contents of a list can change
the length of a list can grow or shrink
even
if the names that refer to those lists don't change
an environment diagrams help keep track of all this
change as it's happening
throughout the course of execution of a program
so let's work with an example
where s is bound to the list two three
t is bound to the list five six
and we perform various mutation operations
have some example calls and show the result
and we'll start with the append operation
which adds one element to the end of a list
so if I append t to the list s
here's what happens
I start out with a global frame
with s bound to the list two three
and t bound to the list five six
s dot a pen
t adds one element to the end of s that refers
to this list containing five and six
it's important that this arrow doesn't point to
the name t
it has to contain a value
it's the value that you get when you evaluate the name
t which is the list containing five and six
now when I assign the name t to something else
like zero that means t is bound to zero
it's no longer bound to the list five six
but that does not affect s
s is now two three and a list five six
that's a three element list containing two
numbers in a list
and t is bound to zero
okay let's start over and take a look at extend
extend adds all elements in one list to another list
so s dot extend t
will add to the end of s the elements five and six
now if I assign t one equal to zero
I will change this element to zero
but that won't affect what's in s
because s just contains a bunch of numbers
let's start over once more
and take a look at addition and slicing
addition of two lists creates a new list
and slicing creates a new list
these lists contain the elements
of the lists that were added or sliced
and here we'll do a longer example
we're going to assign a to s plus a list containing t
we're going to assign b to a slice of a
and then we'll make some changes to a and b
and see what happens to s and t
starting at the top
if I added s and t together I'd get a list to 3 5 6
but this is different
this says build a one element list containing t
so let's go ahead and do that
even though we're not going to give it a name
instead we're going to add this list and this list
building a new list containing the elements two
three and the list five six
so the result of this expression s plus list t
builds a three element list with two three and a list
and we give this the name a
now before we move on
we should probably figure out what to do
with this floating
one element list that has no name
you could leave it there
you could also erase it because it can't be reached
it was created during evaluation but never given a name
okay under the second line
b is a slice of a
starting at element one and going to the end
that creates a new list containing three
and the list five six
now we can make some changes
a's element one is nine
here's a here's element one
that changes to nine
b's element one's element one is zero
here's b here's b's element one
here's b's element one's element one
and we change that to zero
that actually affects t
so the result now is that s is a list two three
t is a list 5 0
a is a list two nine containing 5 0
and b is a list three containing 5 0
the fact that this addition and this slice
all contained t
means that a change to t
affects all three of them
and therefore we see three different zeros
all referring to the same element of a list
okay let's start over
the list function creates a new list
containing existing elements
so if I say t equals list s
I get a new list containing two and three
that replaces what t used to refer to
if i set s element one equal to zero
then i'm changing s but i'm not changing t
because we copied it
so the result is that s is two in zero
and t is two in three
what about slice assignment here are as an example
if s is two and three t is five and six
and I assign to the list s from zero to zero equals t
I'm saying that right in here
I should have all the elements of t
since this slice had length zero
and this list had length two
I had to shift everything else over
slice assignment from three onwards
means that this value is going to change
but since I'm replacing a slice of length one with a
list of length two
I put the elements five and six in place
now t one equal zero changes this value
but it does not change this value because
the last element of s is just a number
so those are ways of extending or changing a list
it's also possible to shrink a list
I'm not going to draw environment diagrams for these
because I think they're pretty straightforward
but let's go through the operations
pop removes and returns the last element
so if I start with s is two three and t is five six
and then assign t to s
pop that removes the three
and changes t to refer to that three
so the result is that s is a list containing only two
because I've popped off the three
and the three is now the value of the name t
we've lost track of the list five six
starting over with ss two three and t is five six
what if I remove will remove
removes the first element equal to the argument
so if I write t dot extend t
that means t is now 5 6 5 6
and if I remove five then I'm left with just 6 5 6
s has not changed at all
and finally
let's do another example of slice assignment
that's the same as the thing
we looked at in the last slide
we can remove elements from a list by assigning
empty list to a slice
so the slice from zero to one is empty
means that all those elements in the slice zero to one
are removed leaving only three in s
and in fact if I remove all the elements from zero
to two of t then I'm left with no elements at all
so let's put them together
into a couple of more complicated examples
let's say I assign t to the list 1 2 3
and then I perform slice assignment
where the slice from one to three
that includes elements one and two
is assigned to a list containing t
so let's build that list containing t
and then we'll replace two and three with
the contents of this list
which is just a reference to the whole list 1 2 3
so we replace that with a reference to this list
now we have a list that contains itself
that doesn't make python explode
and so we can keep going
t dot extend t says put all the elements of t in t
and all the elements are one and then a reference to t
and if you print this out
you'd get something that looks like this
okay let's do one more
t is 1 2 3 4
a list with two elements which are both lists
if I look at t zero that's this list
and I append to it a slice of t
a slice of t from one to two
is a list containing just three four
and that's what I append
so I build that slice and I append it
and I've constructed the result
which looks like this
I think it's very challenging to move straight from
code to the eventual result
without drawing a box and pointer diagram
showing what's going on
and so I'd recommend
that you get comfortable with this notation
so that you can solve these kinds of problems