61 a lecture No.14
announcements
project two is due on Friday
but please get the checkpoint
by submitting phase one by today
and the bonus point by submitting the whole project by
Thursday
today's lecture
along with monday's lecture
will not be covered on exams or assignments
but they're pretty interesting
so definitely watch them and come ask
questions if you're curious
we have some advising office hour
appointments coming up
this Friday Saturday and Monday
those office hour appointments
whose location is marked as advising
are just for receiving advising
not homework or project help
so if you want to ask
about study strategies or future classes
or clubs or research or internships or
what it's like to live in berkeley or whatever
then grab one of these 1 on 1 appointments
but if you need help with your homework
grab an appointment that has a different location than
advising
okay here we go
continuing mondays lecture
with a description of how the circuitry in a computer
actually implements
basic operations on numbers
welcome back so let's see where we left off
so at this point
we know that you can use binary numbers only
zeros and ones
to represent numbers positive and negative
and floating point numbers
and we know that we have three basic
boolean or logical operators
logical and logical or and logical not
and I showed you using transistors
two in series for an and gate
two in parallel for nate and for an orgate
and a single transistor and a resistor for a not gate
how I can physically
build these logical boolean operators and or not
and now what I need to show you is
how I can go from these three
incredibly simple operations computations
two full blown computation on a modern computer
that's what we're going to start talking about today
so let's go ahead and just dig in
so let me start by defining a circuit
a circuit is a collection of logical gates
you know what a gate is
that's simply an instantiation
of and or not using the transistors
but you know this again is the power of abstraction
so at this point
I'm going to just start calling them gates
I don't have to worry anymore
that they're built from multiple
in series in parallel
resistors transistors doesn't matter
they're just gates
they are operations that do and or not
okay so a circuit is a collection of logical gates that
transforms a set of binary inputs into a set of
binary outputs
it's just a function
so a bunch of things come in that are binary
because that's the language of modern computer
and a bunch one or more things can come out
which are also a binary
such as definition of a circuit
and all it's made up is a collection of gates
so all you get to do is and or and not
okay so let's look at a really simple example
so this is not a meaningful computation
I'm not computing anything that's meaningful
I just want to show you
an example of a circuit
and then of course
we'll get into meaningful computation
in a little bit and then how we build these circuits
I just want you to see what a circuit would look like
so typically in a circuit
the input is on the left
I have two inputs here and b
this can be a zero or one this can be a zero or one
I have two outputs
c and d of course these have to be zero or ones
because they are the output of
pushing binary inputs through a series of gates
and here are my gates
so here's an ore gate
remember the shape of the ore gate
it's got that sort of funny rounded back
and a plus sign in the middle
just to remember it
an ore here's an end gate with little dot
and I have a knot gate right there
and a knot gate right here
so let's see what's happening here
so let's see this output is the result of what
a is coming into this oregate
b is coming in
and notice that little white dot right there
that tells me I'm going to take this input
and I'm going to bifurcated
I'm going to bring it up here into this orgate
but I'm also going to carry it through into this knot
and eventually into this
and so that little dot tells me that the same
signal goes in
two different directions
so whatever b is
it comes up here and out of here comes what arb
so the output c is simply the result of arb
not meaningful
it doesn't mean anything right now
but let's not worry about it
I'm just trying to show you what a circuit looks like
so that is the output
and of course
since a can be zero or one true or false
b can be 0 1 true or false
c of course is zero or one true or false
so let's see what d is
okay so let's see
so the output of this oar is coming into the and gate
so first of all is that allowed sure
this is just a 0 1
and the result of oaring these two bits
so this is just another binary number it's coming in
so this is the end of and or b
and what else well let's see
b comes in here
it goes through a knot gate
which I'll have to note is b
with a hashtag
sometimes you'll see a b with a b with an apostrophe
sometimes you'll see b with a line over the top of it
so that's also coming into the and gate
so I'm ending a or b
the output of this
and not b going through here
and then I'm going to knot the whole thing to get
d at the end so the expression d
is equal to a or b
coming in from up here
and not be and then the whole thing is nodded
there's the a little apostrophe there
okay so it's a circuit
what is a circuit it's a collection of gates
or not and that's all I can do
that takes a series of binary inputs one or more
and outputs a series one or more of binary outputs
that's a circuit
now again this isn't a particularly meaningful
in fact it's not at all meaningful
and now what we want to ask ourselves as well
okay
now that I have a mechanism for creating a circuit
that is a computation right
we're going to take a bunch of binary inputs
and create a bunch of binary outputs
so imagine my binary inputs are two
binary numbers I want to add
and the output is the summation
or my input is two things
I want to compare if they're equal
and my output is true or false
and so the nature of computation is going to happen
by pushing inputs a and b c and d
whatever that is on the left hand side
through a series of gates and or a not
to get a series of outputs which
hopefully are going to be meaningfully computations
okay so we're going to do nexus
we're going to show
how do you actually build meaningful computation
now that we know
what a circuit is and how we build a circuit
from gates so
that's the end for now
and we'll pick it up in a few minutes
okay so
the nature of computation
using boolean operations and or a knot
is we're going to build a circuit
a collection of gates that transforms
binary input to a binary output
that's what we just saw in the previous lecture
and now
what I'm going to take you through is a four step
process for going from what you want to compute
to a circuit
okay so I'm going to go through the four steps
and then we're going to see a bunch of examples
on really meaningful computations that you might see
for example on a modern computer
so the first thing we're going to do
is we have to ask ourselves
what is the input and what is the output
okay so let me do an example
where I have two in and two out
I could have one in and three out
I could have three in and four out
that's irrelevant right now
but we're going to start with just this simple example
so four steps we're going to follow
and the first step is to build the truth table for all
possible input output values
okay so if I have two inputs a and b
my truth table must have
two to the two four possible rows
so I have to enumerate every possible pair of inputs
so if I have three inputs I need
eight rows if I have four inputs I need 16 rows
I need two to the end rows
because I have to enumerate every possible input
nothing can be left out
so if I have two inputs a and b
I know what all the possibilities are
there are 0 0 1 0 1 1
by the way notice
this is the easiest way to build your truth table
just count in binary
0 1 2 3 4 rows from zero to two to the end minus one
two to the end total rows
okay so that's the easy part
so no matter what circuit I'm building
with two inputs
those four rows are gonna be exactly the same
that is the four possible inputs into the circuit
and now I have to decide
what do I want the output to be
okay so for now I'm going to pick something arbitrary
because this isn't
again not a meaningful calculation
like the previous circuit we did in the previous
lecture eventually
I'm going to do something more meaningful here
but I want to take you through the four steps
and then we're going to start doing
meaningful computation
so what is my output I'm determining
I'm just telling you this is your job
this is the nature of the computation
is that c should be a one when a a 01
and sorry when a is one and b is 0
or when a is one and b is 0
and it should be zero otherwise
and d should be one only when a is one and b is one
it's computation
it doesn't really mean anything right now
but again we'll see what
meaningful computation is in a little bit
so now I have a truth table
I predetermine the rows
that's super easy
just enumerate all the possible instead of inputs
and then you tell me what the computation is you want
if you want to add two things
your output has to have something to do with summation
for example
and we'll see examples of that in a few minutes
so these are again are just arbitrary for now
step two build sub expressions
with and and not
for each output column I have two output columns here
this is really important
you're gonna build a sub expression
I'm gonna show you how to do it in a second
and the only things you can use are and and not
you can't use the oars yet
and I'm gonna explain it a little bit why that is
okay so how do you build those sub expressions
all right so here's what we're gonna do
let's do d because this is a little bit easier
and then we'll go back and do c
so for each output column
we are going to go down and find where there's a one
ah there's a one right there
okay and then so d is going to be equal to
now obviously d must have something to do with a and b
because it's the output
input rather is determining the output
okay and so what we're going to do is
we're going to say that
d is equal to
again I can only use and a knot so there's no knots yet
is equal to a and b
and the reason I'm doing that is because a has a one
here and b has a one here
okay so just logically
what you're going to do is
you're going to find the one
you're going to go back into here
and wherever you see a one
you're going to use that variable
when you have a zero you're going to nod it
I'll show you an example of that in a minute
and you're going to add the two together
now let's ask ourselves why this makes sense
alright let's see
well first of all can we agree
that column d is in fact the end of an b sure
because what's the and
the and is that when a and b are one
the output is one and it's zero everywhere else
okay so look what I'm doing here
I'm saying that when a is one there it is right there
and when b is one
the output is one
and notice that sort of for free
I get all the other rows of that output
because for all other
instances of this
when aa zero or b a zero or their bow zero
I get a zero so this little expression here that's it
this little and
embodies that entire output for those two inputs
okay
so let's see another example that's a little bit like
we'll do c
and we'll see exactly where this is coming from it now
all right so see we're gonna play the same game
we're gonna roll down
we're gonna see where do you see a one
okay there it is right there
and now I'm gonna build a sub expression
and I can only use ants or not ands and knots
okay so I'm gonna roll over to the input
and what do I have
I have a zero here so I'm going to knot that
and then I have a one here
so I'm going to just carry that over
and this c is equal to not a and b
so let's make sure we understand that
alright so when a is zero what is the nod of a one
when b is one
b is one so the knot of zero and one is one
sure that's that one right there
now unlike this one here
this little expression doesn't capture everything
why the only time
the only time when this expression is one is when
when a is 0 and b is one
I've captured that
one row right here with this little sub expression
but notice I have another one I have to capture
I also care when a is one and b is 0
my output should be one
well so if I put a
one into here that goes to a zero
b goes to a zero that's not one
so this little sub expression doesn't help me here
it sort of helps me here
we'll get back to that in a minute
and sort of helps me here
but it doesn't help me here
I need another sub expression for there
so now again we're going to go down c
we've already captured that one sub expression
let's capture the sub expression
so now we go back to the input
a is one so we just bring over a
b is zero so we nod it again
let's make sure we understand that
when a is one and b is zero I get one and one
so I get c is equal to one
and notice again it's the nature of and
and is going to be one if and only if
a is one b is zero and this sub expression
and in this sub expression a is zero and b is one
and notice that's exactly what I want
that's exactly what I want
I want c to be one when a is zero b is one or
a is one and b is zero
so these two sub expressions capture those two rows
of course I'm going to have to combine them
I think you can sort of see what the
how that's going to happen
but we'll do in a minute
but notice also that we're sort of getting this row
and this row for free
because for all other values of a
so
when a is 0 and b is 0 what is the sub expression zero
what is the sub expression zero
because that's a zero and that's a zero
when a is one and b is one what's the sub expression
well that goes to zero
so the whole thing goes to zero
and that goes to zero so the whole thing goes to zero
so these two sub expressions sort of for free
and because of the nature of the
and give me those two
zeros for the first row in the fourth row
okay all right good
so we've now in step two we've built sub expressions
for each output column
the d only needed one because there was only one here
and the c needed two of them
because there are two ones here
now we're going to combine two at a time
all the sub expressions with an ore
I mean
you knew the ores that were going to come into place
so this is now step three
step one is build the truth table
step two is for each outpa column
build the sub expression using
and not only and step three says
start to combine these things with an ore
okay so what is c
let's go back to this one
well we have one sub expression here
which was not a and b
we had another sub expression here
which was a and not b
and what is c
I want c to be one when what is true
when this is one or there it is right there
this is one so I simply or those two sub expressions
and now
this expression right here this full expression of the
sub expressions
and the ore of them captures that entire row for sea
because we've just convinced ourselves
at the only time this is one
is row two the only time this is one is row three
and all other times at zero
so if I order those two together
I get a one in these two cases
and I got a zero elsewhere
so now I now have a sub expression
I have an expression rather
that embodies the output c
for all possible inputs a and b
okay so what does the combination for d look like
while there was only one sub expression
so there's no orring to do
this little sub expression
now let me just call it an expression
embodies the entire column for how I get d
from a and b and notice it's just an end right
because that's exactly what that column is
okay step three
now step four
draw a circuit
well what does that mean
well what do I have at this point
I have a truth table
I have boolean expressions and or a knot
that tell me how to transform my input to my output
using what logical or logical not
well if I can do things with and or not
I can draw a circuit
because that's exactly what a circuit is
all right so let's draw the circuit
this is now the fun part this is the easy part
you're done so typically
not always but typically we'll put the inputs on
on the left sometimes we put them at the bottom
running upwards when the circuits get to complicated
and output is on the right
so there's gonna be two inputs a and b
those are the four rows that you saw on the truth table
there's gonna be two outputs
c is gonna come out up here of course
and d is down here
so let me do d first because that's the easy one
so what is d it's the and of a and b
so I take a I shove it into an angate
don't forget the dot there
to remind yourself that's an angate
if your drawing is not very good
I take the b and I shove it in here
and I like to write the expressions here because
in the early days of this cause
it will remind me what I'm doing
and then I drive that output to there and I get d
so that's a really simple circuit with only one and
gate
all right so how do we do the c
well the c is the result of oaring two things
that little sub expression right there
and that little sub expression right there not a and b
a and not b and there's my c are gonna or there
all right so here's my and gate
and I'm going to shove in
I have to bring in not a there's my not gate
I have to bring in not b
there's my not gate
and then of course
a will come into here and b will come into here
so we just got to feed them in from the inputs here
so let me go ahead and do that now
all right let's follow the line
so notice that whenever I buy
for kate or split off the signal
I'm going to draw a solid dot
to tell myself that the signal a
is going into this and gate down here
and it's going to go into this knot gate
and into this and gate
okay so there's the a going in
let's see where do I get the b from
here it is right here
okay so here's b
I'm going to bifurcate
and now notice I have an open circle here
that's to tell me that
two wires are just crossing on top of each other
so I'm not taking the input here
I'm just going to cross the wire
I'm going to bring it up
I'm going to bring it up I'm going to bring it over
and now I have not a and b
alright same thing for the next one
a's gonna come in
we're gonna split the signal
I'm crossing there's an open circle
and I go into the and gate
and then of course there's the b again
I'm gonna peel off the signal
I'm gonna shove it into a knot gate
I'm gonna shove it into the and gate
and then it's gonna go
those two are gonna go into the ore and there's my c
so nothing complicated
you can see that
the wires can sometimes get a little complicated
and you've got to think
how you want to lay these circuits out
so usually I sometimes like to start at the back
then work my way this way
because I know that there's going to be an orgate here
and then I feed everything in moving backwards
okay good
so there are the four steps for designing a circuit
again we haven't done anything meaningful
in terms of actual computation
that's going to come next
but let's go ahead and just review the four steps
step one
first of all figure out where your input outputs are
that's probably step zero
tell me what you want to do
input output so
build a truth table for all
possible input output values
what does that mean
if I have n inputs
I have two to the n rows that enumerate every
single possible set of inputs
so the easiest way to do that is just start
counting in binary from zero
so if it's three inputs I do 0 0 0 0 1 0 1 0 0 1 1 etc
so you count and you should always have two to the end
basically from zero to two the end minus one
if you convert everything into
base 10 that's step one
tell me what the output is
what is the nature of your computation
we'll see a bunch of examples of that in
the next set of lectures
two for each
and notice that each output is separate from each other
in that previous example
d and c don't care about each other
they're just separate
they're completely separate in the true table
so for each column
build a sub expression using only and a knot
no oars right now
so how do you do that
find the ones
go back to the input and everything together
and if it's a zero
it's a value of one you and it together
and if it's value of zero you nod it
and when you do that
you get something that gives you a one
for only that set of inputs
and then in step three by ordering all of those
expressions together
I then get the entire column wherever there is a one
and by design there is a zero everywhere else
now I have an expression for each output column
how do I transform my input to my output
through a series of and or or not
and now I simply draw the diagram
and there you have to get a little bit of
practice to figure out where to draw things
but we'll do a bunch of examples of that
to see what that looks like
good four simple steps for doing basic circuit design
and now the only piece that's missing is
what does meaningful computation look like
and that's what we're going to do next
so we'll see you in a few minutes
we're not ready to do our first meaningful computation
we have now all the infrastructure
we know what gates are we know what circuits are
we know how to go from a tooth table
input output sub expressions expressions draw circuit
okay so now let's actually build
small but at least meaningful computation
so we're going to build what's called a one
bit compare for equality
a ce circuit so what do I mean first of all by one bid
I mean I have my inputs r
a and b which are each a single bit either zero or one
a four bid compare for equality
which we'll do in a little bit
would be that I have a is
0 1 1 0 and b for examples 1 1 0 0
and all I want to do is ask
are these two one bit values a and b
equal or not
and so here's my little pseudo code for the computation
if a and b are equal then return one
otherwise return zero
notice everything's binary
a and b can either be zero or one
because everything's in binary representation
and my oppot is either a one or 0
depending on if those two bits are equal or not
so pretty straightforward
so now let's start turning the crank
let's figure out how to design a circuit that does this
so step one is what
build a truth table
what are the first two columns of the two table
they are my inputs
I have two one bit inputs a and b
and I have a single output c
which is going to be equal to
one when the two bits are equal
and zero otherwise
okay so the first part of this is easy
simply enumerate all possible set of inputs
0 0 1 1 0 1 1
and you should do it in this order by the way
because it makes sure that you don't miss anything
and it's just a good discipline
and it's the way everybody else does it
so the inputs are trivial
just count in binary
from zero to two to the un minus one
now you gotta tell me what the output is
so this is the work
tell me what you want to compute
what do I want to compute
let's go back to the previous slide
I said
I want this to be a one when these two bits are equal
and zero otherwise
all right so here they're equal not equal not equal
not equal so now I know what my output is
it's a one in the first row
zero zero it's a one in the last row
one one and it's a zero otherwise
so this is now a meaningful computation
it's talent simple but meaningful
it's telling me if these two bits are equal or not
okay good
we've done step one of our four step circuit design
let's do step two
what a step two say to do is to build
for each output column there's only one output now
a sub expression
okay so let me remind you how we do that
we isolate where there's ones
we go figure out what is the combination of and and not
that gives rise to that one
and then we move on to step three and then step four
so let's just do the sub expressions for now
all right so there's a one here and a one here
so this is the only place I have a sub expression
so what do I do I go back to the input
that's a zero so I not a
there it is right there
that's a zero so I not b
I am those two together and again
remember that why this works
because when a is 0 not a is one
when be a zero not be as one
so when I and one and one I get one
and that is the only place I get one
there is no other
possible values of a and b that will give rise to one
so this is this
very surgical strike this little sub expression
it's going to evaluate one here and only here
this is somebody else's problem down here
and this is nobody's problem
because the default is going to be that everything
evaluates to zero
if it's not this or not this
all right let's build that sub expression again
go back to a and b
that's a one so we bring the a over
that's a one we bring the b over and again
this sub expression is one if and only if
a is one and b is one and it is zero everywhere else
so again notice these why we like the ans here because
for any value that is not zero zero
and any value that is not one one
these expressions are going to value to zero
so here for all other values of a and b
this evaluates to zero
here all other values of a and b of value to zero
so I get these two for free
by simply these being so surgical
and evaluating to one if and only if we're here
or we're here
good so step two is done
I now have the sub expressions
so let's do step three
combine the sub expressions with ours
for each output column
of course we only have one output column so c
my output is going to be equal to not a and not b
there it is right there
or a and b and again
you have to convince yourself
that this is exactly what you want
okay so again this can be one and only one situation
this row right here
this can be one in only one situation
so this entire expression will be one in this case
in this case
and again notice it's zero everywhere else
we sort of came for free
because of the nature of the ann
so there it is I've got a little boolean expression
that is what one bit compare for equality
so at this point you're sort of done
drawing the circuit is just the fun part
it's just to sort of
prove the point
that you can actually implement this thing
but I've now got a computation
one bit compare for equality
using logical land logical ore and not
let's go ahead and just draw the circuit
okay again input on the left
output on the right
there's two in this is a two
a one bit compare for equality
I'm only comparing two binary numbers
and here's my output
and I've brought over my expression here
so we can carry it over
okay
so we know there's gonna be an ore somewhere over here
there's gonna be two ends here
and I need a couple of knot gates for the a and the b
okay so
let's go ahead and just
start pulling these pieces together
all right so let's see
I'm going to take
a and b and I'm going to shove them into this
and gate that's the sub expression right here
okay that's the easy part
I don't need any knots
and now I'm going to peel off a and b again
filled circle when I peel the signal off
open circle when I cross the wires
you have to do this so you can follow the input
so when you follow this line
you know to keep going here you can ignore that
and then it goes into a knock gate
and it goes into an ann gate
same thing with b
I'm going to peel it over
drive it into a knot gate
shove that into an end gate
don't forget the dot on the and gate
so we can see what you're doing
and this of course is not a and not b
this is amb I again like drawing these
the actual expressions here
because it sort of reminds me that
you know what I'm doing
and I can go back and check my work nicely
now these two of course so this
sub expression corresponds to this
this sub expression corresponds to this
and what do I want to do with those two
I want to shove them into an orgate
and then I have my output
all right good shovement to an orgate
that's now the full expression and I have my output
and now we have our first meaningful computation
it's incredibly simple
it is simply a one bit compare for equality
but it's meaningful it actually does something
okay and notice here in some ways there's something
I always think magical about these
designing these circuits because notice that
you're not really computing one bit
compare for equality
what do I mean by that
what I mean by that is
you've sort of memorized one bit compare for equality
that truth table and step one
gave the computer the answer
what did you say
you said look here are all possible sets of inputs
0 0 1 1 0 1 1
and here's all the outputs associated with that
so when you see zero zero
output one when you see one one output one
and at all the other times output zero
you gave it the answer
and now what it's doing is simply
I mean it is computing it
because it's pushing it through the circuitry
but you're the one who did all the hard work
you're the one who told it what the answer is
and now it's simply doing that for all possible inputs
using these operations
so in some ways this is sort of the magic of circuitry
is you're actually doing a lot of the hard work
and the designing of that true table
building the sub expressions building the expressions
eventually we'll see how to simplify
those things to make them more efficient
and then this is just sort of turning the crank
it's just simply implementing the machinery
that you actually designed
you gave it the answer
okay all right good
so this is the first and simplest now
where we've actually done a meaningful computation
using our four steps
input output build the truth table
sub expressions
combine the expressions draw the circuitry
and what we're going to do now for a little while
is we're going to just do a lot of examples
we're going to see
how you get more and more complex computations
and then near the end I'm going to show you
because I'm sure
some of you are already thinking about this
is there's going to be
at some point there's going to be a lot of these gates
and how can I make them simpler
is this really the best way to design circuits
and the answer is absolutely not
this is not the best way to design
service circuit design is incredibly complex
and you really want to optimize it
so that you get the most amount of bang
for your buck on a circuit
we're going through the simplest
possible circuit design
I'll show you a couple of optimization techniques
near the end of the class here
but until then
we're going to do a bunch of examples to make sure we
understand this four step process
all right that's it for now
and we'll pick it up in a few minutes see you soon
in the last lecture we
built our first meaningful computation
starting from a truth table
through building sub expressions
expressions in
a circuit for one bit compare for equality
so we ask if we have two one bit numbers a and b
can we build a circuit that tells me if they're equal
they're both zero or they're both one
incredibly simple maybe not very useful
so let's see a few more examples of this
and the next example is going to be
a four bit compare for equality
so what do I mean by that so remember that when
when we specify binary numbers
we specify how many bits
and whether they're signed or unsigned
so for now let's just do unsigned
forbid binary numbers
I have two four bit binary numbers and I want to return
true one if those two numbers are the same
and zero otherwise
okay so let's just start turning the crank
so the first thing
and this is really where all the hard work is
is figuring out what does the truth table
what does the truth table look like
how many input columns
what is the output
and then populating that truth table
so let's of course start there
well okay so first of all
what does a four bit binary number look like
so here it is
let me label them
a18283 significant
so that's my first
binary No.4 bits
let's call that a
but notice that there's actually four numbers there
and then of course I have b which has b three
b two b one b
0 and I want to know are these two equal
well what does it mean for those two numbers to b equal
well it means that a three is equal to b three
a two is equal to b two and someone and so forth
okay so notice that even though I only have two numbers
they're each represented in terms of four bits
so I actually have eight input columns
a 3 to a 0 b three do b 0
so don't get confused by numbers and bits
because we are living in binary world
we have to always think
about the underlying bit representations
okay so I have let's see four here four here
that's my input
and I of course have one output which is c
it's one when they're equal and zero everywhere else
okay if I have eight input how many rows do I have
remember the relationship
two to the power
the number of input
so in this case it's two to the power eight
which of course is
two fifty six
that's a lot of rows you have to populate
so you have to go through every single of the 256
temple inputs
right out of row
tell me what the output value is and you can do that
be a little tedious but you can do it
but let's think about
whether we really need to go to all
this trouble or not
because
when we think about it in this two bit
and this two four bit numbers
there's really
I'm sort of doing
a very simple computation over and over again
so what is that
well I sort of said it
I said that this forbit number a
and this forbit number b are equal if
a three is equal to b three
and a two is equal to b two
and a one is equal to b one and a 0 is equal to b zero
so really if I could just figure
if I could solve this one big problem
and then this one bit problem
and this one big problem and this one big problem
well then I could just
logically combine them using an and operator
so maybe we can simplify this calculation a little bit
and not have to populate that full 2006
row table so let's
remind you what the one
bit compare for a quality looks like
I take two single bits so
careful with the switch and notation here this
you can think of this as a 0 and b 0
and this is telling me whether those two bits are equal
so these are just two one bit
and remember that the way this circuit works
it says if they're both one
so if they're both one then this end will respond one
if they are both zero
they go into knock gates they flips to ones here
this will respond to one
so if this is a one or this is a one
then I get a one out here otherwise I get a zero
so this is the one bit
compared for equality that we did before
let me
draw this with a little bit of abstraction
because this is a lot
I don't want to have to keep drawing this over and over
again so I'm going to represent the one big
compare for equality
with this little box here with a one ce
one big compare for equality
and done
now there's two levels abstraction right
because here there are two transistors
here there are two transistors
but I don't draw that every single time
I just draw this little abstraction
for what a gate looks like in terms of transistors
and now I can draw another abstraction
for the entire circuitry
and underneath it is this
and underneath that is a bunch of transistor
so again that power of abstraction
and now let's think about
how do we combine
those little one bit compare for equalities
to get a four bit compare for equality
well again I want to compare a three and b three
and I want to compare a two and b two and so on and so
and of course I still want to have a single output
which is if these are equal
and these are equal
and these are equal and these are equal
then I want to say yes
otherwise I want to say no
all right so let's start pushing the bits
through the compare for equality
so a three and b three go through a one
bit compare for equality and outcomes
what a one or a zero
if it's one if those two are
zero zero or one one and it's a zero otherwise
and similarly I can push a two and b two
a one and b one and a zero b zero
so each of the bid positions
each through their own one big compare for equality
notice the power of the abstract here
I don't have to write an entire circuitry
I can just write that little box
and I know what it is from the previous slide
now what do I want to do is I have four outputs here
and what do I want to do
well let's think about what the rule is
the rule is that this should be a one
the output to the entire circuit
if this is a one
and this is a one and this is a one and this is a one
I know how to do ans
I just need an ann gate now
so this should be pretty easy
notice by the way the ann gates only take two inputs
so I can't shove all four of those into an angate
so I have to do them two at a time
and it doesn't matter what the order is of course
so these two go into an angate
and now this will tell me if they're both one
and then I'll take the output of that
and I'll shove it into the
and gate an angate where it's
the bit down here
and then I'll do that one more time
so let's just think through the logic here
let's say that these are
let's say they're all ones just to make it simple
so out of here will come a one because they're equal
a one goes in the antigate out of here will come a one
it will go into here
so this is a one coming out
the first two bits are equal
this is a one coming out here because they're equal
out of here comes a one
this will be a one here and eventually one
and notice if any one of these are not equal
so let's say these are not equal
well then a zero comes into this angate
and that means a zero comes out of here
and if a zero comes out of here
a zero comes out of here and a zero comes out of here
so once one of these angates flips any of them
because one of the bits is not zero
we get zero on the output
and the only way
we get a one on the output here is if these are equal
and these are equal
and these are equal and these are equal
and so now look at the power of this circuitry
I've got a really simple circuitry here
here and here I've got three and gates
so instead of having to build a true table 256 entries
build all those sub expressions
build the expression
then draw a fairly complex circuitry
with eight inputs and one output
with the power of a little bit of abstraction
I was able to do something a little bit nicer
so I use this example because
one of the things we'll be talking about is
yes we'll want to turn that crank on the circuitry
true tables sub expressions expressions
but sometimes it's really inconvenient
sometimes we have to be a little bit more clever
okay so that's it for now
when we come back
we're gonna design a couple more circuits
and we're gonna keep sort of
seeing how these things are built
and how to build more and more meaningful computation
so see you in your few few minutes
all right so we're gonna build
an adder we're gonna
go from these relatively simple circuits to something
that you can really imagine a computer needing to do
which is to add a bunch of members together
so we're going to do this in two steps
I'm going to build a one bit adder
and then I'm going to show you how it generalizes to a
four bit adder
so in the same way we went from a one bit
compared for equality to a four bit
compared for equality
we're going to build this up a little bit slow
so here's the task
please build for me a circuit that adds two
one bit number
so again remember we have to think in terms of bits
so I have two numbers each of them are one bit
so either it's a zero or a one
and I'm going to add that either to a zero or a one
all right so we know what we have to do
let's first start making sure that we
let's start by understanding that we
let's start by making sure that we understand
how the one bit addition work
so here my two bits I'm going to add bit one bit two
let's call that a and b
and let's just do the addition so 0+0 of course is zero
zero plus one is one and one plus zero is one it's
that's easy all right what's 1+1 well let's see
so this is one and one in base ten one plus one is two
what is two in binary it is 1 0
so now we have already had a little bit of a problem
because here I only have one output right
there was no carry
but here I have some two outputs I have the sum
which is zero but then there's like that carry
or I have two bits out
it's 1 0 so maybe I have to
think about this a little bit different
so
carry and
here's a good place to think
about what's going to come next
so eventually we're going to want to build a four bit
an eight bit and a 16 bit adder
and to do that we're
definitely going to want to be able to carry digits
because when we stack
two binary numbers on top of each other
we need to carry
information to the left as we sum
so let's see
so initially I was thinking I would just have
two inputs a and b and one output c
but maybe I should rethink that
maybe the input should be two digits a and b
and then possibly a carry
and again this is all about
thinking down the line a little bit
when I go from a one bit to a two bit to a
or bit I'm going to stack these down
and think about how you just add normal arithmetic
you add the digits in the column
but you potentially bring something over
from the previous column
so let's think about the binary edition
in terms of now having three inputs
ab and a possible carry
and again that's going to allow us to generalize
the circuit down the line
okay now
of course the output has to have more than just this
it has to have an output which puts down
below the horizontal line but also goods carried out
so now even this
one bit addition has already gotten a little
complicated we have two in plus a carry that's three in
and then the output is what is the sum
and then what is the carry over here
so we're gonna have two outputs
all right
let's make sure we see what's all happening here
so let's imagine I want to some
I have a
three bit representation and I want to sum them up
so let's first of all make sure this makes sense
a 1 0 1 remember this is two to the 0 2 to the one
two to the two
so this is 4+1 which is five
this is two to the zero which of course is just one
and that vipers one is six
so I'm gonna add these two numbers up
and I better get six
so let's start adding them up
and I want you to keep track of the these three in
and two out okay
all right so here I have clearly two digits
what's the carry from the previous column
there is none
it's zero it's implicitly there's a zero up there
because there's nothing there
all right what's one plus one two
what is two it is 1 0 so there it is
I have two in plus an implicit carry of zero
and my output is what do I carry to the next column
that's one and what do I bring down
that's zero okay good
now you can see my three inputs
I'm going to sum that carry from the previous column
plus 0+0 what is that that's one
so I bring the zero down
and implicitly I'm bringing the
zero over to the next one
so and then I've got zero plus one plus zero
and of course that is one
and of course if
I do the calculation here that is two to the two
two to the one two to the zero
so it's 4+2 which is six
okay so too bit addition
if we are eventually going to
generalize this to 3 4 5 6 7 8 fit edition
we now have three ends
what are the two digits you're summing
plus a possible carry
and we have two outs
what comes down and what carries over to the
next column three and two outs
good so look at how much work
by the way we had to do just to
establish what the input output is
but this is sort of the hard part
now we've established what the problem is
we've established how to define it
and now we just have to start
billion true table sub expressions expression circuitry
okay so I have three ins
I should have been called this a carry in
and a carry out
yeah so it's what's coming in and then what's going out
okay 3 in 2 out
all right good
let's build a true table
all right true table has three columns
if it has three columns that has how many rows
two to the power three
which is eight
and the way you populated is simply by
counting in binary from zero
to eight minus one seven
so 0 0 0 0 1 0 1 0 etc etc
so here are my eight
rows associated with the three input columns
those have to again enumerate every
single possible pair of inputs
and now I have to tell you what is going to be the
sum that comes down
and the carry that goes over
so again these are the two digits
were summing plus a possible carry
that's the carry in
this is the sum and the carry out
okay so now just got rhythmetic
we're going to tell the computer what the answer is
in the same way we did for the compare
for equality I'm going to do
the addition for you
and then the
circuitry is simply going to implement those rules
all right let's start going through it
all right zero plus zero plus zero is zero
and there's zero caring
okay that one's easy
what is zero plus zero plus one it's one
so the one comes here what's the carry out zero
there's nothing to carry there's no overflow
okay that's easy
let's look at this one
so what's zero plus one plus zero well it's still one
it's actually the same as this
right I don't care what the order of these bits are
so no reason to do extra work here
once I know there's only one one here
I know what the answer is
it's going to be 1 0
so that one's easy now
ah this one let's think about this
so this is zero plus one plus one that's two
so what is two in binary
carry the one drop the zero
so that's going to be a zero here
that's what comes down
and the one is what carries over to the next column
this one's easy
there's only one one so we know what the answer is 1 0
this one's easy there's two ones here the answer is two
it's the same as that zero comes down
carry as one this one's easy
right work smart
we've already done the work
no reason to do the calculation
now let's do the last one
one plus one plus one is of course three
what is three in binary it's one
one drop the one carry the one
so now c is d is one and e is one
good now really truly all the hard work is done
now we gotta just start turning the crank on
sub expressions
expressions and circuitry
so I have three ins two out
I've established what the value of the sum
and the carry out is
for all possible inputs
and now let's start building up the sub expressions
okay remember how the sub expressions work
you treat each output column separately
the d and the e
output column are completely independent of each other
we're going to identify wherever there's a one
and then here here here and here
we're going to build a sub expression using only
and and not
and then we're going to combine those sub expressions
using the or operator
and then once we have the final expression
of course we're going to draw some circuitry
so let's get started
all right let's start with d
I've isolated 1 2 3 four ones here
so what is the sub expression associated with this
remember you go back to the input variables
if it's a one you nod
if it's a zero you nodded
if it's a one you carry it over
so this sub expression should be not a
and not b and c
easy to do but again remember what you're doing
you're looking for an expression that is 1 in 1
and only one situation
when a is 0 b a 0
and c is one so if I not these two they turn to one
that one's a one
the only time that little sub expression
which I'll draw right here is one
is in that little row right there
so not a not b and c
all right let's do the next one
what is it
not a b
not c good
there it is right there
and then let's just do the last two
so this one is a
not b and not c
and last one is easy
a b and c good
so there are my
four sub expressions
corresponding to wherever there's a
one on the output channel
I won't go through these again
I think we not window what the rule is
so this one for example is not a b and c
and these three you can
derive from this right here
so I have four sub expressions for d
I have four sub expressions for e
and now I'm ready to put them together in
an expression
and then we can draw the circuit
alright so what's the expression
this sub expression is one on this row only
the sub expression is one on this row only
and so on and so forth
I want my output d to be a one if this is true
or this is true or this is true or this is true
so I simply or all the sub expressions together
okay there's the expression right there super easy
this same thing
it's a one on this this this this
I want the ore of them
so I'm going to combine them with three oregates
so now I have full on expressions for d
and e and now I'm ready to build my one bit add
okay so here is the one bit adder
now in the past
what we have done is
we've brought in the input from the far left
and the output is on the right
I've done things a little bit differently
you can see down here
the inputs are coming from the bottom up
and then the outputs are here
so again a and b are the two inputs c is the carry in
d is the sum and e is the carry out
okay so
the reason I've done it this way
is I'm going to take these three inputs here
and I'm going to drive them all the way to the top
and then notice the three knot gates here
I'm peeling off the signal to the knotgate
I'm going to drive those all the way up
and then I just feed the signal
and the not of the signal
into the angates
into the angates down here and then into the oregates
and the color coding here of course is
the red corresponds to the d output
and the blue corresponds to the e output
the angates here
of course from the original sub expression
and then the ores
those three ores are summing them up
to get the final output
and notice here that
there's a fair amount of circuitry here
even for this really simple one bid adder
you need a fair amount of circuitry
and so what we're going to talk about next
is you know what can we do to reduce that circuitry
and what happens as these things
start to get more complicated
and also what happens when I try to build
for example a four bit adder
and suddenly I have to draw
lots of these different gates
and things get complicated very fast
we're gonna see how we can think about these larger
more complex circuits
so we'll pick it up in a little bit see you soon
as promise we're now going to build
circuitry for doing four bit edition
so we're going to take two four bit numbers
and we are going to add them
in the same way that we did in the previous lecture
we just stack them on top of each other
we sum
we carry we sum we carry we sum and we keep going
and we do binary
arithmetic or edition
and obviously we're going to use the one bit
adder that we just built because we know that
end bit addition is just a series of these
one bit addition
so we're going to build this in a smart way
all right so please build for me a circuit that adds
two four bit numbers
and again I want to emphasize
pay attention to the bits
because the inputs is not two
it's now well at least eight
but we know we have all those carries two right
so we always
have to be thinking in terms of bit representations
because everything we do operates on bits
all right well we know how to do one bit addition
so notice here I've done something
very similar to what I did
with the one bit compare for equality
I've taken that
full circuitry that I showed you in the previous
lecture I've got
I have the carry in
that's what's coming in from the previous column
and I have two outputs
the sum what drops down below
and the carry out what carries over
okay so 3 in 2 out
and now I've simply drawn a little box
and I've written one add
which is a one bit edition
and that is that full circuitry
and again this is the power of abstraction
once I know what's in here
the same way that I know what's inside of a gate
I simply can draw it in this abstract way
and I don't have to worry about it anymore
I built it I've tested it I know it works
and now I can simply use it
and so now what we want to do is
wire up a bunch of these things
in order to do forbid edition
and of course we could do six eight
et cetera et cetera
we'll stop it for except I think you'll get the point
so let's start thinking about how we want that to work
and you just got to think about what happens and work
I take these two things
and then I'm going to
shove that next carry to the next one
which should be the input to the next one
bid adder
and we keep repeating that over and over again
so let's see how that works
all right so first of all
here are my four bits for a and my four bits for b
so that's what I want to sum up
at those carries that we got to bring in
that's fine we'll do that in a minute
here's my one bit addition right here
here are my two outputs
there's a carry and then there's the
digit the sum
notice by the way
that this is the thing that's coming out
this carry is for internal purposes
I don't report that to the summation
I just need that to propagate the bits down
so the output outside the circuitry is here
now okay so here's a zero here's b zero
those are the two ends but I also need a carry in
so what's the carry in for the right most bit
well it's zero
okay good so we just shove a zero in there that's fine
that's easy to do
so now I've got three in
I'm going to get a carry which
again internal purposes is going to be used for the
next bit a one and b one
and the output is really just d zero
that's the only thing I care about
that will actually come out
all right so how do we add the next one
while I want to take a one and b one
and what is the carry in
it was the carry out from the previous bit
so that's simply going to go into the one bit adder
good so I've got a one here again
cross wires open circle
here comes b one right here
the carry came in from above this adder
the output is the same d one
and now I've got the next carry
good now we see the pattern
all right started with a carry of zero
and we keep dropping it down
shoving it into the adder
associated with the column that is to our left
all right good
a two here it is
crosswire crosswire into the adder
here is b2 into the adder
carry in carry out
my next sum is right there
and now we're almost home
we got the last one right here and we got the last
sum what do I do with the carry out
well I can only have four outputs
that's how I've designed it
so I have four in and four out
so if these two things sum up to something
that is bigger than four bits
I'm gonna have what's called an overflow
and for now I'm going to ignore it
there's other ways of dealing with this
which we won't get into
5th output and summed and said
I have 4 in 24 bit numbers
and please allow me to have
an overflow but I'm going to ignore that
so that carry just goes into junk and gets ignored
so notice again the power of abstraction
notice how much
easier this was to do
once we understood we had this building block here
it's a lot like functions
once you build these
simple functions that have functionality
you can use them over and over again to build
more and more and more complex things
okay and of course I can take
two four bit adders now and make an eight
bit adder and then I can take two eight bit adders
make a 16 bit adder in each time
I can keep it distracting out the complexity of what
underneath it
alright so
this again is the circuitry for a one bit adder
and if you remember in the last doctor
I said that's a lot of
gates to do something as simple as a one bit adder
I just want to sort of run through a little
back of the interval calculation with you here
imagine I'm trying to build a 32 bid adder
that's how reasonably
allows you to represent reasonably large numbers
well then what I would need
are 96 knot gates 512 ant gates and 192
oregates how did I get to that
well
this thing over here for the one bit has six oregates
16 and gates and three knot gates
okay and so I just multiplied that by 32 each
I have 800 gates to do only
only only addition right
multiplication division all those things can't be done
so is that a lot is 800 gates a lot
well
that 800 gates corresponds to about 1500 transistors
because when you're building circuitry
you're building gates
but really underneath its transistors
right so now look at what I'm doing
I'm popping out the levels of abstraction
I'm pushing through the one bits
I've got the circuitry for the
for the 32 bit adders
that's made up of a bunch of one bit adders
that's made up of a bunch of gates
and that's made up of a bunch of transistors
I need 1500 transistors
to do one single mathematical operation
which is 32 bit addition
now if we were in 1945
I would need roughly a refrigerator size computer
to do that single calculation
that's insane
and that's because transistors were not these
tiny minuscule things we have today
they were big physical things
that occupied a lot of space
so the magic in
today's computers that if I have for 1500 transistors
I can put that on something that is much
much much smaller
than a printed period on a
piece of paper
this is the magic of modern day computers
that these transistors
can now be made incredibly small
and so you can pack more
more transistors onto a circuit board
which means you can pack more gates
which means you can pack more circuitry
which means you can have now in
your jacket pocket
a cell phone
that is the equivalent of a supercomputer from
60 years ago and so this is
what's sort of amazing about this
to know when you do these calculations
is you see the complexity of a modern computer
all we've done is built edition not even a calculator
and look at how much work we've had done
but look at the power of these tiny transistors
all right
so in the next two lectures these are the last two
we're gonna talk a little bit more about circuitry
we're gonna talk about optimization
how do you make these things
because of how big they can get
if you do this sort of very simple design
you may end up with prohibitively large circuitry
and there's some smart things that you can do
and I'm going to give you a couple of examples of that
just to round out the circuit design here
alright see you in a few minutes
in this well
I'm going to ask you to build a
circuit that determines if an
eight bit number
is identically zero
so why would I do this
why this kind of specialize thing
well it turns out that you often design circuitry
depending on what the computer is being asked to do
and I don't think it'll surprise you to learn that you
often will check to see if a number is zero
so imagine you're counting down
imagine if you want to know
should I divide by this thing as it zero or not
and I'm willing to bet
if you go back
and look at all the codes you've written
at some point
you've checked if some variable is equal to zero
and sometimes
it's useful to have
highly specialized circuitry that does just one thing
very specific
that is very common
because you can put that
in the overall
circuit board in a place that's very efficient
and you can
design it in a way that's as efficient as possible
so always having general purpose circuitry
so let's do this one
very specialized circuit and it's just a good exercise
also turning the crank
of working through our four step process
so first things first
what is our input output that's always the case
I have a single eight bit binary number
which means I have eight inputs corresponding to a 0
to a seven the bit positions
and I wanna know if this number is equal to that number
that is all of the numbers are zero
a zero zero a100
and so on and so forth
okay so I could write a one way to do this
as I could say okay let's write a one bit
compare for zero
build that circuit and then wire everything together
because it seems like maybe
well that's been the trend
we went from a one bit compare for equality
to a four bit compare for equality
went from a one bit adder to a four bit adder
and this seems like a lot of inputs
because if I have eight inputs
how many rows am I going to have in my table
two to the power eight to 56
I'm not writing a true table 2 in 56 centuries
and I don't think you should either
but before we
try to design the one bit compare for zero
and then generalize it
let's think through this truth table for a second
so I know that I have to enumerate every
single possible row
for all possible
inputs and I know that there are 256 of those
but what do I also know
that's going to happen in step two
I'm going to go through this output column
and what am I going to do
I'm going to find all the places where there's a one
and I'm going to build a sub expression
using and a knot
and then I'm going to combine
those sub expressions using ores
all right but let's think through that
think through any row here
that is not 0 0 0 0
to that what is the value of I going to be
zero it's not zero
there is one row and one row only
0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 where there's a one
so in fact this isn't nearly as bad as it seems
because every row and it's the first row by the way
on top of that
every row after that will have a zero in the eye
I don't have to worry about those rows
because
I'm not going to build a sub expression for them
so in fact this truth table is incredibly simple
there's only one row that is relevant to us
because all the other rows will come for free
because there is a zero and the eye column
well once I have this
I've got a pretty easy expression
let's write it out
so what is the sub expression for this
well again
we're going to combine
all the inputs with a combination of
and a knot
all right how do I get a one when I have eight zeros
it's not a and not b and not c up to not h
I take the knot of everything
if they're all zero all of those will be one
and if they're all one
well
then the whole express sub expression will be a one
and if any one of these is a one to begin with
when I nodded it flips to a zero
and they have veto power
the whole thing will evaluate to zero
and that's 255 rows below this
all right so this turns out to be pretty easy
the sub expression
which is also
the expression because there's only one of them
is just not a
not and not b and not c up to not h
all right now we can draw the circuit
I've got my eight inputs here
corresponding to each of the bits of my
a bit number I'm going to shove
them into a knot gate
you see them lined up right here
and now I've just got to start ending them
now be careful here and can only take two inputs right
you can't shove all of these things into some big
fat and gate
so you gotta start pairing them off a little bit
and there's you can do it in any different way
you can pair these two these two these two these two
and then combine them
it doesn't matter because as long as
they're all coming into the same and gates
eventually
it doesn't matter the order in which they do them
so let me pair them off two at a time
so a and b go through their knots they go into the end
so at this point I've pair wised and everything
and now I'm gonna do the same thing
I'm gonna pair wise and pair wise and
and then
of course I just need one more at the very end here
and then I'm done
and notice
follow through make sure that this logic works for you
let's say they're all zero except for this one
okay so that g is a one
let's walk through the circuitry
that's a one coming through
it gets nodded
so this is a zero now so into this angle comes to zero
what comes out
I don't even care what h is if this is a zero
zero comes out
all right zero comes out
the whole thing is zero
notice how any one of these flips to one
it propagate through the entire circuitry
and I get a zero out
and the only way I get a one there
is if these are all zero
they all flip to one
and then I propagate only ones through the series of
okay so simple little trick is that
because the sub expressions
we only care about the one in the output column
if you have a really spar set of ones
you in fact don't have to enumerate
the entire truth table
those zeros are eventually going to get kicked out
it's nice to have them there
when you have a small number of inputs
just so you can see everything
but as your inputs get bigger and bigger
you can be fairly strategic on how you build those
truth tables good so that's a simple step
in the last such
I'm going to talk about what it called carnoff maps
and these are now a slightly different design
that allows us to try to reduce the number of gates
why do I want to reduce the number of gates
because that reduces the number of transistors
which means I can pack more and more power
and so there's lots of different optimizations
we can talk for
months about that
I'm going to just show you one very simple idea
to give you some intuition on
how some of this circuitry
optimization works
all right we'll pick it up in a few minutes
all right in this last step
you're going to talk about as I promise
karnoff maps
which are a very simple technique for optimizing
your circuit design
that is by minimizing the number of gates
not to true minimum
but reducing I should say the number of gates
that you are going
to have to use to implement a particular
truth table and expression
so let's imagine this very simple
it doesn't matter what the output here
but imagine I have four in
so how many rows do I have with 4 in 2 to the four
which is 16 and I have one output which is e here
and I've just color coded it slightly different
okay so we could do what we've been doing up until now
we could identify all of the ones here
there's one there there's one there etc etc
build the sub expressions from these four inputs using
and a knot combine them with or draw the circuitry
but you can see this is going to get
to be a fairly large circuit
but let's just go ahead and
pump through that as a good reminder
then we're going to see
how we can do a little bit better
all right so what are we going to do
we're going to go down through the output and
isolate the ones there
there there there there there
okay and we're going to build the sub expression
so let's build the first one
you go back to the input
not ABC not d
there it is right there
let's go to the next one
what's this sub expression
a not b not c not d
good that one of there it is right there
and let's do a couple more
just as for practice I've got what a
not b not CD
all right that's pretty easy
let's do another one
a not b c
not d
and now I think we can probably just
go ahead and do the rest
okay so just convince yourself that those all map back
to those sub expressions
so okay
so we've got a bunch of noddings
we've got a whole bunch of angates
and of course I can combine those with an orgate
and we can keep through that process
okay and you can see that
there's a fair amount of circuitry
at all those
and gates all those little dots
corresponds to a gate
which corresponds to two transistors
I'm going to have ores to combine all of these
those correspond to two transistors
and as I said earlier
it'd be nice if we could try to reduce
the amount of gates and therefore
transistors and therefore
the amount of space on the underlying circuitry
so what I'm going to do is
the way these karnoff maps work
there it is right there
karnoff that's how you spell it
is they reimagine the truth table
and the way we're going to draw this truth table
is instead of having
each entry for the four inputs take a single row
we're going to have them occupy this little
four by four matrix
so notice what I have appear
up top I have the input pair ab
and on the side I have the input pair CD
so this entry corresponds to when a is 0 and b a 0
a is 0 b is one a is one b is one and
a is one b is 0
okay so
and then this of course corresponds to what's c in
d is c is 0
d is 0 down to c is one and d is 0
and notice by the way
that there's no loss of information
this is four by four which is 16
which is how many rows I have
so each cell here corresponds to a row
so it's simply a different visualization
of the standard truth table
and so how do I
populate it well
for any cell here
I know what rowa corresponds to
so for example let's do the cell
this cell is a as zero b a 0
c a 0 d a 0 that's that row right there
this cell is 1 0 0 0
so that must be this one right here
so there is a direct translation every row here
in particular those outputs get shoved into here
now obviously I need a different one of these
for each of the outputs
this is only for one output
all right
so let's go ahead and just start populating it
all right there are 00 00
I know what the output is zero so I put a zero in this
now it's called a two dimensional tooth table
let's do this 1 1 0 0 0
that's this row right there there's a one
so I put a one right there
let's do a few more
so this corresponds to 1 1 1 1
let's see there it is right there
and I put a zero here
by the way notice the ordering here
I've got 0 0 0 1 and then I've got one one and one zero
that ordering matters
you have to do it in this order
and I'm going to explain it a little bit
why this ordering matters okay
but until I do that notice that
this bit right here
the second zero and the first zero are the same
the ['one']millisecond and the first one of the same
the second one and the first one of the same
that's not an accident
the same of course is true here
we're going to take advantage of that
structure in a minute
all right let's do one more
0 1 1 0 that corresponds to let's see 0 1 0 1
that oopsari 0 1 1 0 0 1 1 0 that's a one
so I'm gonna put a one right there
okay good so
I can go there's a direct mapping from this
one dimensional tooth table to this
two dimensional tooth table
and all this information is here
this is exactly what I want
I want the circuitry to be one
for these inputs here here here and here
and at zero everywhere else
okay so how does this help me
all right well let's look at a few things here
let's look at this string of ones right here
okay so remember
again conceptually what do I want
I want to build some expressions that evaluate to one
here here and here
and if I can do that I'm home
that I've implemented this computation
that I've specified in the truth table
look at this expression right here
well let's see
for a one to be here
do I care with the value of crds
no because notice no matter what pairs of value crd are
this thing is a one
right and in fact it's a one when a is one in b a zero
no matter what the value of c and d r
that's interesting
okay so what that means
is if I have this little expression right here
a not b
how did I get that a not b
so when a is one and b is zero
which means that and is one
I want a one on my output
I don't care what c is
completely irrelevant to me
yeah so notice when I just did
a single sub expression with one end and one knot
gave me four rows of my truth table
that's incredible that's incredibly efficient
right and I did it because I've noticed this pattern
and of course
that's because I've put this in this nice little
two dimensional
tooth table is that these four ones don't depend on cnd
and all I care about is then that value right there
so there's a big bang for your buck
I've gotten four ones out
from a single sub expression with one and and one knot
very nice all right so now what do I have to do
I still need remember
all I've got to do is build an
expression that evaluates to one
that occupies all of these cells right here
so once I get those covered
I've got
and then I can start building my circuitry
all right so let's do the
let's look at this one right here
so there's two ones next to each other
and let's see so it's not quite as clean as here
I can't just ignore ab or CD
it still depends on both of them
but what do I know here what doesn't matter
let's put it this way
well there's a one here and here when what is true
well when c is one and d is zero
so that's clear
right where you have to be in this row of the
two dimensional trues table
now do I care what the value of a and br
yes because it's not a one across the whole thing
it almost is because I had a one here
but I don't have a one there
so if I had a one here then I'd have that same win
I'd get them all
yep but what don't I care about well let's see
a is zero here and a is one here
those are the only two possible values so in fact
these two ones right here don't depend on a
and they only depend on b equal to one
so let's see what it is when c is one and d is zero and
b is one then I get those two ones right there nice
it's not quite as much of a big as a bang for
as you got here
but it's certainly saving something
so when b is one
and when c is zero
and b is one
c is zero and d is
sorry d c is one and d is zero so b c
not d I
that little sub expression availage to one
in these two situations
so again one sub expression
with only three variables
by the way because a is irrelevant here
gives me two ones nice
all right so we're almost home
we've just got to cover those two
okay so I could do the same trick
I could draw a little colored box right here
and what would be true
a would have to be one and b would have to be one
and what else is true I don't care about d
because d can flip between zero and one
so I could have written another expression that was a b
and not c and I would have gotten those two right there
but it turns out we can do a little bit better
so let's think about not just those two but these four
okay so
notice that they're overlapping with the previous one
we'll get back to that in a little bit
all right what doesn't matter here
all right but what do I know
I know that in order to get these ones here
c must be zero
right c can't be one
and I also know that a must be a one
so think about that thing
c equals zero carves out rows
a equals one carves out these two columns
the intersection is that little square
so these four ones right here don't depend on b
because b can be one or zero
they don't depend on d
because that could be zero or one
and the only thing I care about is when is a one
and when is c zero
and what's that as sub expression a not c
now notice that this sub expression
let me put them all up here
this little sub expression a and not c
will value to one in these four instances
this little sub expression here
a not b will availate to one
in these for instances there's an overlap
do I care
no what do I care
so let's think about this situation right here
where a is one
b is zero and c is 0
and d is zero
so what's going to happen in our expression here
this will evaluate to one
this will evaluate to zero
and this will evaluate to one
great two of them one I only need one of them
but what do I care I'm going to get one at the output
and it doesn't matter
that these two sub expressions both said yes I'm here
because it's irrelevant to us when we
or as long as one or more of them is one
we're still going to get the same answer
so you're allowed to overlap these things
and what's the benefit of overlapping
why did I overlap is
well the sub expression was easier
I only hit simpler shorter
I only have two variables
instead of three variables
the way I did over here with this one right here
so notice what happened now
by simply drawing this kernoff map
this two dimensional truth table
I was able to take
let's go ahead and look at the comparison
these sub expressions here right
and then of course I have to combine them with ore
and I could reduce them to those three
little tiny sub expressions
and so the amount of circuitry
the amount of gates is greatly reduced
now the karnoffs map are really just one of many
many different techniques for doing optimizations
and in fact reducing
the
number of gates and transitions is only one of many
optimizations you have to do
you also have to think about
where are things positioned in how much power
and lots of complexities in designing circuitry
but what I hope that you got out of this
from the very beginning of
when we started with binary numbers
through boolean logic
through gates through transistors
an eventual circuit design
is an appreciation for the nature of computation
you now know
the building blocks of a modern day computer
and how we can do actual computations
and there's a certain simplicity and beauty to it
and a remarkable complexity to actually get it working
and I hope someday you'll be able to take a computer
architecture course
and learn some more about it
all right that's it for now and that's it
this is the last lecture
we'll see you live in a little bit
and we'll talk some more before the class ends though
talk to you soon