61a lecture 20 q a all right let me ask
john a question while we're waiting for
everybody uh to chime in
i've been coding for a lot of years john
and i have to say
except for like commercial things i
don't think i've ever done object
oriented like when i just code
internally even when we build big things
is that some a crappy programmer or is
that is there some obstacle
uh still like i never build a lot of
classes and do all the things that i
teach what's wrong
well um object-oriented programming
shines in this particular scenario when
a bunch of stuff is changing
yeah and a lot of code that gets written
these days especially data processing
code
doesn't really have like mutation going
on it doesn't have
changing state over time or you're like
tracking a lot of stuff
this happens more often in like software
that's got a
user interaction cycle or something like
that so yeah if you're doing much data
processing
workflows then it just doesn't show up
as much
yeah that's a good point that's that's
an interesting way i hadn't thought
about it that way but i like that
oh in lecture i said stir
is not a function but instead is a class
so if we look at what stir is it says
it's a class
classes and functions are extremely
similar in the sense that
the way you do something with them is
you call them
and so when you call some function like
abs
it could really do anything when you
call a class
it's always going to create a new
instance of that class
so the stir though it looks like a
function
it's really a class and what you're
doing here is you're calling the
stir classes constructor in order to
make a new stream
and you can call this on pretty much
anything and it will always make you a
string
so in that sense stir is a class
it's probably a distinction that doesn't
really matter that much
um honestly yeah it doesn't matter at
all
but it's interesting to see that yeah
our teams and
classes are so similar i mean right
there it's just classes or
functions that always create a
particular instance of this class
the next question was about a mistake in
the polymorphic functions video
from today's lecture where i redefined
stir and wrapper
below the places where i was calling
them and so those definitions had no
effect yeah good question
if you print first and then you
redefine stir and wrapper then the print
won't know about the read definition
which i think is just a mistake in the
video but uh
i checked it and if you rearrange the
code it still does the same thing so
uh it's it's uh the code wasn't doing
quite what i said but it would have done
what i said had i written it right does
that make any sense
so uh yeah so anyway you're right that
if you print before you make changes
then those changes obviously won't be
reflected
okay so this question is about how
addition works
when there's an instance of a
user-defined class involved
and the answer is it's kind of
complicated so
when python sees x plus y
it uh checks to see if x
is a user defined has a user defined
class
and if so if it has an add method
if that's not true then it checks y
and sees where whether y is a user
defined class
that has an r add method what's our ad
well this is the method that gets called
when an instance of this class is on the
right
of the plus and if neither are those are
true
then it tries to use the built-in
edition that it has
which basically only works for the
built-in
classes like ant and float and stir
and um you know if that doesn't apply
then you'll see an error
which says i don't know how to add an
int and a
widget or whatever uh you have there
so this multi-step process is not
terribly important
except for um it indicates just how
complicated it is
to to set up a language so that you can
arbitrarily extend what plus does
and it's complicated because there's
these two different arguments to the
addition
and um you know
you might want to be the case that your
user-defined thing shows up
on either side but then sometimes the
order matters it's not always the case
that every
addition operation is commutative like
for strings
a plus b is different oh come on
a plus b is different than b plus a
and you might want that kind of behavior
in your own version but then you need to
know whether
the object you created is on the left or
the right of plus
the next question was for the kangaroo
class is it okay to use
in to check the contents of the pouch
instead of using a for statement
um no i think using the in is fine um
i the reason i use the for loop in the
while loop is i like to exercise that
for students to make sure that they
understand it
but the in operator is a perfectly fine
thing it's essentially um
this is one of those cases where python
has given you a construct
that does something that you could have
done manually but you could have
absolutely used the end and done it in
one line
instead of two or three lines yeah great
question
so the question is is instance the same
as just finding the type of something
and figuring out whether that's equal to
a class and they're oh so close
but because of inheritance they are
actually different
so let me show you an example if you
have a class a
um that
is the base and you have a class b
which inherits from a and is the
subclass
if i build a b and ask
is this an instance of the b class well
the answer is yes but it's
also an instance of the a class
whereas the type of b is the b
class but it's not the a
class so what is instance does is ask
is b an instance of
this class or any of its subclasses
that's a tricky little thing isn't it
yeah but it can be useful because
basically you're you're future proofing
your code by saying is it an instance of
a kangaroo
if somebody comes up with this special
subclass of like a short kangaroo
your code's still going to run correctly
yeah good question so what's the
difference between
this built-in wrapper function
and this thing well um
you'll see them in different places so
wrapper can show up anywhere
it's a built-in function that's in the
global frame you can
call it on anything and
what it will do is really really simple
it will ask its argument what is your
wrapper method and we'll just call that
so i can get a wrapper of you know
basically any kind of object i create
but when is happening there is that
there isn't a whole bunch of code within
repper that says
here's all the different kinds of
objects in the world and here's what
they do
instead all rapper does is take its
argument
and invoke the method
that means this can be defined in the
class
of whatever this thing is this happens
to be a list
and uh it has a
wrapper method built into it
you can ignore what a slot wrapper is
that's kind of
some random detail of python that we
don't care about but this is just like
some function
that uh that knows how to turn
lists into strings and you know what
does it do
it adds square brackets and commas and
spaces in the right place and stuff like
that
so the difference is that these are
built to be related to each other
these appear in class definitions
so you will have often a wrapper
method which takes in the object that
you're trying to make a string of
and returns a string something like that
and this is a function that's built in
that always knows
when it gets an object and it doesn't
know how to print it out it just
invokes this wrapper method this
underscore underscore wrapper method in
order to do the work
but if you had called this something
else it wouldn't work so the
relationship is between
the repper without underscores being a
built-in function
and the wrapper which is a special
method name with the underscores
that does the work so uh if we make an a
now it will look like a instead of
some kind of like funky thing with
angled brackets
the next question was whether every
class defines ripper
yeah great question so the underscore
underscore wrapper method
is something that the user has to define
in each class
if it's not defined there's some
default behavior and you've seen it many
times
it's this uh thing where
uh it shows you some angled brackets
and it tells you what the class is and
it says the word object
so like this is built in but it's not
very useful
it's just like a placeholder and so it's
almost always the case that when you
create a class
you want to add a rapper method that
shows
uh more interesting information about a
yeah good question so how would you take
a tree
and print all the paths um so let's say
we want to
print a first we have to decide what a
path looks like so a typical thing would
be it's the list of labels
along a path a path is really like a
list of
nodes each one is a tree but um
you know the interesting part of a path
is that it's got a bunch of labels in it
that are numbers or whatever
yeah so if we take in a tea tree and we
want to
print all the paths from the root
to a leaf
some zoom display stuff i don't know how
to do this yet but i know it's going to
be recursive steve
you know the most straightforward way to
do this is in two steps
you get all the paths and then you print
each one out
so let's try it that way what would this
actually look like
if you had a tree
uh
what have i done
made a mess is what i've done i hate
this notation john
okay
i shouldn't get that off my chest that's
all
[Laughter]
okay so we get one two three and we get
one four let's see
um
that seems like a good way to go no what
is all paths
a path comes by
finding a path from uh the root of a
branch
all the way to a leaf and then putting
the current label at the front
that's like a recursive way to think
about a path is that a path has the
first thing
and then it's got the rest of the
elements in the path and the rest of the
elements in the path
are a path in a smaller tree
a tree that starts at a branch so one
way to do this
is to say that for every branch
you want to get all the paths in that
branch
like here's a branch and a path through
that branch would be 2
3 but we want 1 2 3.
so if we go through all the paths
in the
paths in the branch
then what we want to return here is not
just 2 3 like path
path might be 2 3 we want to return 1 to
but there might be multiple of them so
i'm going to write it as a generator
function we can change it
later if you want but what we
uh yield here is one two three
which would have to have the label of t
first and then
uh the rest so this is yielding
one two three which is what we want
i don't know if you heard that but john
had this beautiful recursive definition
in there he said what is a path
it's one if we start at the tree that
he's just
described up top with the path of
everything below
everything right so there it is i mean
that that one
statement is what what wrote your
function for you
so now we have to think about what
happens when you hit a leaf
here there are no branches in a leaf so
this would do nothing but that's not
quite right
when you get to a leaf there is a path
which is just a one length path so
if uh t is a leaf then i think we want
to yield
a list of length one okay
and now that some uh gardeners have
showed up it's gonna be very hard for me
to talk but
i'll try anyway okay so that seems to
pass the test i think that's a good way
to print
all the paths and actually this is
exactly the same structure that we had
in a question that we had to skip
at the end of the last time why is there
sometimes two for loops
the reason there's two for loops is that
in each particular branch there could be
multiple
paths so let's like extend this example
just a little bit
now what should happen is that we should
get one two three one two five
and one four um
when we pass in t is one two three
and we go to the first branch which is
this guy
this actually has two paths through it
two three
or two five 5. for the branch
which looks like this there isn't just
one path through that branch
there's two and that's why we have a
second
nested iteration it's that for each
individual branch there might be two
different paths
and for each one of those we want to
yield a new path
so this is a question about fall 2015
midterm two question three a
and just understanding the question it
is a good
idea to read what's there but then
take a look at the examples the doc
tests
to make sure that you've really
understood what it does and
if like it's doing something that you
don't expect
well then um then
you gotta address the wording of the
question try to figure out what's going
on
and uh you know in an exam if you really
can't understand what a question means
um then you know feel free to ask a
question
because there's no point in working to
solve a problem if you can't figure out
what it's asking okay so
implement complete which takes a tree
instance t
i'll tell you in advance that on friday
we'll talk about tree
with a capital t which is that we'll
build a tree class which is just like
the tree data abstraction
except it's a class um so you might see
some notation in here that's a little
bit different i think all that's really
different
is that you write t dot branches instead
of branches of t
um and same with the label so maybe we
could just ignore that for a little
while but i just wanted to let people
know
that this is something we will cover but
haven't covered yet okay
so which takes a tree instance t and two
positive integers d
and k and returns whether t is dk
complete which is some term that's made
up for this question
a tree is dk complete if every node
at a depth less than d
has exactly k branches and
every node at depth d is a leaf
the depth of a node is the number of
steps from the root
the root node has depth zero built in
all function blah blah it's
not really relevant the the thing to
think about with this
is like what what the heck does this say
and um
looking at examples and thinking about
examples is really important to figuring
out what this means
so let's see what the example says so
a tree that has
a node at depth 0 but no other nodes
is apparently d k complete
for d equal to zero because the depth is
zero
and k equal to five
and it seems like this five is just kind
of irrelevant
what's going on here is that
every node at depth less than d has
exactly five branches but there are no
nodes
less than zero depth zero is the
smallest depth
so all that matters here is is it the
case that
every node at depth d which is zero is a
leaf
and that is true so this has only one
node its depth is zero and it is a leaf
and therefore this happens to meet the
definition
kind of by accident it doesn't have any
nodes at less than zero
so this five becomes irrelevant but
that's why this came out as
true okay um
let's look at a more interesting tree so
here's a tree
that's got three branches and each one
is a leaf
is it the case that this tree
is one three complete
yes because for all the
nodes at depth less than 1 which is just
it has 3 branches and u itself the root
is the only node that has depth zero
and it does in fact have three branches
and
then all the nodes at depth one are
leaves
and that is true tree tree tree um
is it the case that this is depth one
two complete no because the root has
three branches not two
is it depth two three complete no
because
the nodes at depth one which is less
than two like this one
don't have three branches it's just leaf
it doesn't have three branches it has
zero branches so that's why this is
false and this is false and
what about this tree well this is a
funny tree
this is a tree where one is at the root
and then it has three branches which
each look
like you so if we were to write this out
it would be pretty long to write out
it would be a tree with one at the top
and then one in the middle
three times and then each one of these
middle nodes would have three leaves
under it that are all ones so there
would be nine different leaves
and that is a two three complete tree
which means that all the leaves are at
depth two
and everything in between has
three branches how might you approach
this kind of problem
the um
the base case here is that you've hit a
leaf
whether a leaf is dk complete really
depends on what d
is so leaves are okay
if d is zero we saw that in
this first example but they're not okay
otherwise
we saw that in this example if there's a
leaf at depth one
and this is supposed to be depth two has
all the leaves
then you've run into a problem so you
can't just return true here you
have to return whether uh
t is equal to zero that's that means
it's okay to have leaps
and this is actually like a poorly thing
because it says two positive integers d
and k but here we see a
non-positive d so uh i think whoever
wrote this wrote it wrong
maybe it was me this is a non-negative d
and positive k
yeah i think that the instructions are
are not quite right
we're rewriting the problem as we go
some of them
feel free to do this on the exam just
rewrite the problems if you don't like
them
i'm kidding don't do that
sorry about that john
okay i think that's a better description
of the problem because obviously d
appears to be something that isn't
necessarily positive
um so this is saying
if it's the case that we've reached the
depth where
leaves are allowed and we hit a leaf
then we should return true
otherwise we should return false um
there's a clue here about what to do
with this line
b's which is that the result says
all b's and all is a built-in function
that only returns true if all the
elements of b's
are true so this needs to be
a list of trues and falses
right and what gives you trues and
falses is recursive calls to
complete so we need to be calling
complete on something
and um as for as usual i think it's
natural to do this for every b
in t dot branches t dot branches is just
the object-oriented way of saying
branches t
and what recursive call will we make
well for this to be
dk complete it has to be that
for all the branches they are
d minus 1 k complete
um so now we get a list of true and
false values where they all need to be
true in order to get a true result but
something else needs to be true in order
to get a true result which is
that it has to be the case that the
number of branches
of at t is equal to this number
k which is the branching factor that's
supposed to happen
so this is like a very strict structural
description of what a tree looks like is
that it's got like the same number of
branches until you hit the leaves and
all the leaves are at the same depth
and here's how you would check for it so
the question is
why is it the case that
you can have a different behavior
typing oski
wrapper than you can
calling rapper on oski and in general
this is like not important but i figured
if i'm explaining something in python i
might as well explain it correctly and
there's this weird case
in which this can be true but only if
you use the object system in a way that
is not
really designed which is that you put a
function as an
instance attribute then these can be
different
so if you have a class bear
that has nothing in it and you make
yourself
a bear and then what you do
is you build a function that does
something
like return
go bears and you
set that as an instance
attribute of the ascii instance
not part of the class but just part of
oski himself
then you'll get this weird behavior uh
where they printed this but you would
never do this
it's just like you know it's some weird
esoteric fact about python
that you know it's fine if you
uh would never use this but it does
show the behavior which is that what
repper does is it looks in the class it
doesn't look an
instance which is like very strange
almost everything else in python would
first look in the instance
and then the class but this one doesn't
otherwise one thing python could have
done to avoid this weirdness it says you
can't define functions with double
underscores before and after the name
right that's what's basically happening
here you're making something look
like it's a member function using that
default nomenclature but there's no
protection of that
so sometimes when you make something as
flexible as python then
uh then instructors find weird ways to
abuse it and that's i guess what i've
done here but uh yeah so so anyway
what you're supposed to learn is how
wrapper methods like how you define
wrapper methods within a class
uh it happens to be that you can't put
them on the instance or they won't work
good question so why aren't we seeing uh
the stir function instead of the wrapper
function
um the default stir
is to just do whatever repper would do
that's just a fact about python is that
like if there's no stir method
then printing something we'll call the
stirrer but the default stir
is just to call repper and figure out
what that would do and so
for classes that don't have a separate
stir and wrapper method
they do the same thing because stir just
does whatever rapper does
so if you kind of want to get them both
you could define a wrapper method
and then you've kind of implicitly
defined a stir method because
stir just does whatever record does um
so for this reason um if you create
something that's got no stirs or
wrappers anywhere
we get rid of all this stuff
and we just print the
wrapper of oski we're gonna get the same
thing as if we print
oski which is uh
that by default the stir and the wrapper
string are the same
it's only if you make them different
that they would be different
uh so the question is about the order of
ad
and our ads special methods and what
they do
um it's just like a very particular
thing
but if you want to build a new kind of
number
then you have to deal with many cases
in particular you have to deal with the
case where this new kind of number
shows up on the left and where this new
kind of number
shows up on the right because it might
be the case that something different
happens
in whether it's on the left to the right
uh
if python hadn't made plus so flexible
then maybe the order wouldn't matter at
all
but it's so flexible can be used with
strings it can be used with lists where
sometimes order does matter
and so for this reason um there's two
different special methods
one that gets called when x is on the
left and a separate one that gets called
when x is on the right
and they're called add and r add
respectively
yeah so um well maybe we'll just do an
example
and and uh that might fix things so
let's assume other is an end
you know how do you add i think you'd
have to return a new rational
that's got your old numerator in there
plus it's got other times d in there and
your old denominator
and how would you r add well
okay so so this is like the x plus
three case where other is 3.
and how would you r add
okay so now we have a different case
this is the 3 plus x case
where other is 3. so what do we return
there
we return a rational where
the numerator is n plus other times d
and then the same denominator and then
it will work
in either case i think in order to see
what's going on
we at least need a wrapper method which
would return
uh
rational of
and and
d
oh i went off the line it's okay
and now if i have my thing x
which is like uh one half and i write
x plus three i get oh
self rookie mistake
seriously
the number of times i do that john
then we get seven halves and if we write
three plus
x we get seven halves but we wrote the
same code
here and here so um one option
instead of writing this out would be to
just write that r
add equals add we had already written it
why write it again and then we don't
need this
anymore and we get the same behavior
that was what was going on