61 a lecture No.17
announcements
homework three is due on Thursday
you can revise your
hog project to earn
back any lost composition points by Friday
here's a link to a piazza post
about exactly how to do that
and the key part is that you submit
by typing python three
okay dash dash revise from your hog directory
after you've made whatever changes you want
please attend a discussion orientation
before your tutorial
I understand that many people have been
coming to tutorial
without going to a discussion orientation first
tutorials are designed to follow up
on what happens in discussion orientation
so if you don't go to the orientation
you won't really be able to participate in the tutorial
and you'll lose out on that learning experience
if you look at the core schedule
we have a midterm coming up in a few weeks
midterm two is scheduled for Wednesday the 28
which is three weeks from tomorrow
and the core staff has put together a study guide
that gives you some advice about how to prepare
not just the day before or the day of
but in the weeks before an exam
this study guide is mostly
about how to master the material
and notice that an
important component is to actually watch lecture
so you're doing the right thing
now finish this lecture
and then take a look at the study guide
and I hope that it helps you
finally we will be holding advising office
hours on Friday
in addition to the regular office hours
to help you with lab and homework
since there's nothing do on Friday
we'll just hold these on the regular office hour
q
so if you'd like to talk to an experienced staff member
about anything
related to the course or berkeley in general
come drop by on Friday
and they'd be happy to talk to you then
sequential data
can be represented implicitly using an iterator
iterators are common interface
in many programming languages
and they're used in python
as a way
to access the elements of lots of different containers
a container can provide an iterator
which in turn
provides access to its elements in some order
the built in functions iter and next create
an advanced iterators respectively
so itter takes anything itterable
which could be a container
or something you create yourself
and it returns in iterator over the elements
of an iterable value
next is a built in function
that returns the next element in an iterator
let's say I have a container
a list containing three four and five
if I call iter on that list s I get an iterator t
that iterator
knows the contents of the list
and it also has a marker for what's next
so you can think of an iterator as a position
in some sequence
it gives you access to the element of that position
and everything after it
if I call next on t I'd get the No.3
as a consequence of calling next
the marker here is going to advance
which means the next time I call next
I'll get four instead of three
and since I've called next twice I've advanced twice
and now the markers set to five
if I create a second iterator for the same container
that means I have a second marker into the same list
so you is an iterator that hasn't been advanced at all
if I call next on you I'll get the No.3
now t doesn't forget where it was
just because I created you
so if I ask what's next in t I'll get the No.5
and the iterator will advance past the last element
saying that it's at the end of this list
it's still the case that I can ask for elements in you
so if I ask what's the next thing in you it'll say for
so t and you are iterating over the same values
but they're otherwise independent in the position
that they're going to give you next
okay let's build ourselves a list
that's slightly more complicated than when
the one you saw before
this one's a nested list
if I ask for the next value in a list I get an error
that's not what next does
next first expects you to have created an iterator
over the contents of some container
at which point then I can ask for the next value of t
which will give me the sub list one two
so all it does is give me
the element and index zero
of the list that I'm iterating over
and if I ask for the next t again
I'll get a different value
if you ever want all the values in an iterator
you can just list them out
now here you see that
we only get the values that are left
we already used up the list one two and the No.3
so when I build a list
of the remaining contents in an iterator
I just get the numbers four and five
now if I ask for the next element in t at this point
I get an error
a special kind of error called stop iteration
and that's how you tell you at the end
is that python will raise a stop iteration exception
let's talk about dictionary iteration
you can get
multiple views of the contents of a dictionary
which are different objects that are all itterable
an iterable value is any value that could be
passed to itter
the built in function to produce an iterator
and an interator is returned from iter
and can be passed to the built in next function
all iterators are mutable objects
and when you call next on them
they mutate to point to the next element
a dictionary and its keys and its values and its items
are all itterable values
all can be passed into itter
and the resulting iterators can be passed into next
the order of items in a dictionary is the order
in which they were added
this is true of the most recent versions of python
starting at python 3.6
however an older versions of python
items in a dictionary appeared in an arbitrary order
dictionaries were called
unordered collections of key value
pairs as a result
but now they are ordered
although when you write python code
is a good idea to keep in mind
that depending on the
version of python that people use to run your program
ordering of dictionaries may not be reliable
but I'll assume in my examples
that we're using a recent version of python
and therefore
dictionaries will end up ordered
according to how they were constructed
so if I have a dictionary with three keys and three
values one is bound to one two to two three to three
and then I add a 4th value zero is bound to zero
then I would expect
that iterating over the keys would give me
1 2 3 and then zero
because zero was added last
and here's how I iterate over the keys
I say I want an iterator by calling the iter function
over the keys
if you don't say d dot keys but instead just say d
you get the same effect
you iterate over the keys
and this k is an iterator over keys
which means if I ask for the next one I'll get one
then two then three
then zero if instead I wanted to iterate over
the values in a dictionary
I would ask for the values
this object is an iterable object
that provides access to all of the values in the order
that the dictionary was constructed
so the next value is one then two then three then zero
and finally I can ask for items in the dictionary
those are key value pairs represented as tuples
so the first one is one
where we get both the key and the value
in a two element tuple
and then two then three then zero
so there are many
ways to iterate over the contents of a dictionary
and the way that python is designed
there's only one dictionary d
I can access different views of it
by asking for the keys
values or items
and I can get an iterator for any of those
now one interesting thing to note is that if I
have a dictionary
and I've already constructed an iterator over the keys
and I'm in the middle of iterating over those keys
and I change the dictionary
now it's the case that the iterator is invalid
and so I see this error
dictionary changed size during iteration
which says that I cannot use k anymore
because the dictionary has been mutated
while I was using k
so our dictionary now looks like this
if I just change the value for one of the keys
while I'm iterating through the keys
so here's one two and then I change 0 2 5
I can continue to iterate
because I haven't changed
the shape or the structure of the dictionary
I've just changed one of the values for the keys
but if the dictionary changes size
then I can't use any of the iterators I've constructed
instead I need to make new ones
and that's true for keys values or items
four statements iterate over iterable values
that can also iterate over iterators themselves
let's say I have a range from three to six
the contents of that range are the numbers three
four and five
if I iterate over that range
I see all of the elements
and if I do it again
I see all the elements again
because I haven't changed the range
iterators are a little different
so if I get a range iterator from my range
this has a particular position in the
range associated with it
which changes every time I call next
so I can ask
for each element in the rest of the iterator
but it will not print out three because three is past
instead it will just print out four and five
now four statements also
move the marker within the iterator
advancing it all the way to the end of the sequence
so I still have my range
I'm going to build a new range iterator
that starts at the very beginning
and for every element in our eye
I'm going to print out eye
so I've passed a range iterator
to the four statement to be processed
now there's nothing left in the range iterator
if I iterate over it again
I see nothing because I'm already at the end of roi
that's another consequence of using an iterator
in a four statement
so to summarize
if I use an iterator in a four statement
I can still
go through all of the elements until I reach the end
but that will advance the iterator
so that I can't use it again
on the other hand
if I'm working with an iterable object
like the range itself
every time I use that in a forest statement
I'm able to go through the entire contents
from beginning to end
without worrying about anything changing as I do so
a great deal of
processing of sequences and other iterable values
uses built in functions
but take in one iterable value
and give you back an iterator
so many built in python sequence operations return
iterators that compute results lazily
what lazy computation means
is that a result is only computed
when it has been requested
so the interpreter
gets ready to compute whatever is desired
but doesn't actually compute it
unless that value is going to be used
let me show you some examples
there's a function called map
that takes in another function and in iterable
and it applies
that function to each element in the iterable
but instead of applying it immediately
it returns in iterator
in iterator that iterates over the values funk x
for every x in the iterable
there's another built in function filter
which takes a predicate function in an iterable
and it iterates over x and iterable
if it's the case that funk x returns a true value
zip takes two iterables
it iterates over co indexed xy pairs
reversed iterates over x in a sequence in reverse order
all of these return iterators
and those iterators produce these values
each time you call next on them
if you ever want to
view the contents of an iterator in its entirety
you can place the resulting elements
into a new container
by calling list or tuple
or sorted sorted
creates a sorted list containing
all of the elements in the iterable
let's do some demos
so if I create a list bcd
I could upper case all of those elements
by invoking the upper method for x in bcd
I could get a similar effect by calling a map
on a lambda function
that computes the upper case version
of every element in bcd
but what I get is not the list
capital b capital c capital d
but instead a map object which is an iterator
so if I give it the name m
then I can ask for the next upper case letter
which is b and then c
and then d and then we're done
now how those results computed is quite interesting
less to find a function double
which takes an x and prints out
exactly when x got doubled
x is doubled into
two times x
right now two times x
if I map double over the list 3 5 7
I get a map object and you notice nothing was printed
so I'll give this thing the name m
and then I'll ask for the next element in m
and at that very moment it doubles three
to get the No.6
not until I ask for the next element will it double
five to get the No.10
and then finally
if I ask for the next element after that
it computes the No.14
so the point here
is that double is not applied to three and then
five and then seven immediately
but instead applied leisurely
only when we ask for the next element
is the function applied and the result computed
the map object that's returned when I call map
can be passed into another
sequence processing function
so for instance
let's say I take the range from three to seven
I map double over that range
and I call that m
then I create a filter function
that takes in a value y
and returns true as long as y
is greater than or equal to tin
I could filter
using f the map object
and build a new iterator from the result
notice I still haven't doubled anything at all
if I ask for what's the next doubled
element in the range from three to seven
that's at least 10
then it will double three to find that the result is
six which is false according to our filter function
so it doubles four to get eight which is also false
then it doubles five to get ten
and ten is greater than an equal to 10
so that gets returned
so you can see that it did exactly as much work
as it needed to do
in order to return the next element
of the sequence
of doubled values
that are greater than are equal to 10
but it didn't do any more work than that
if I ask for the next element
then it will just double one of them
find out as greater than are equal to 10 and return it
and if I list the contents of tea
while it finds that there's nothing left
because this range only goes 3 4 5 6 6
doubled as 12
and then we're done
so starting from scratch
if I want to filter
all of the elements of the result
of mapping double over the range three to seven
I'll get an iterator over the values ten and twelve
which I could place in a list
and placing them in a list means that it's going to run
this process to exhaustion
until I reach an empty iterator at the end
and that returns the values 10 and 12
and it had to do all of the work in order to get there
it had to double every number 3456
so it's possible
to use these iterators to compute the exhaust of answer
but if you don't ask for the list of values
and you'll only ask for elements one at a time
then they will be computed legally
lazy computation is mostly convenient
because
it allows you to specify how to compute lots of values
but if you don't actually need all those values
then you don't bother computing them
however there are some things to be careful of
for example
if I create a list that's the same forward or backward
and I ask what's the reversed version of that list
what I get is a lust reversed iterator object
so just saying is the reverse of t equal to t
will give me the result false
now if I list out
all of the contents of the reversed iterator
that's equal to t
but you want to avoid applying equality
to a list and an iterator because you'll get false
you'd have to compare a list and a list
here's one last demo
if I have a dictionary
the elements come in any order
but when I iterate over them
I get a consistent order each time
one way to iterate over the items
is to get an iterator
over dw items
and then I'd get b two followed by a one
but another way to get the same result
is to zip together the keys and the values
zip returns in iterator
that gives you each of the items
in the same order as before
a generator is a special kind of iterator
just like a map object is a special kind of iterator
the thing that's special about a generator
is that it's returned from a generator function
a generator function looks like a regular function
here's an example
the difference is that it uses the yield keyword
instead of return
in order to return values
so I know this is a generator function because it has
yields in it somewhere
when I call plus minus on the value three
I get back a generator t
this generator is an iterator
meaning I can iterate through the values
yielded by plus minus
so if I call next on t I get three
but I can call next t again to get -3
so you can see that both of these
yield statements are being executed
t itself is a generator object
and its job is to help iterate through
all of the yielded values
of the function that was called
so a generator function
is a function
that yields values instead of returning them
a normal function returns just once
but a generator function can yield multiple times
a generator is an iterator
created automatically
whenever you call a generator function
so here's the call expression where we called
plus minus and got back a generator
when a generator function is called
it returns a generator
and that generator iterates over
the yields of the function
here's another example
let's say I want to
return iterators that go over even numbers only
I give integer start and end points
but I want to make sure
that I actually
start at the even number
that's greater than are equal to start
so the next even number is start plus
either zero or one
depending on whether start is even or on
while it's the case that this even number
is less an end
I'm going to yield it
and then I'll increase even
by two to get the next even number
so when I call evens
and I go from two up to 10
I get a generator object
that's going to give me two and then four
then six and then eight
and then stop iteration
meaning we're done
and if I list all the evens between one and ten
it still starts at two
goes up through but not including 10
so what's actually happening here
when I create a generator
by calling a generator function
I haven't even begun
executing the body of this function yet
it's not until next is called
that the body begins to be executed
and it keeps executing
until a yield statement is reached
at which point
that number is yielded
as the next element in this iterator t
and in that case
execution pauses at that yield but remembers
all of the environment
of the function execution
so that the next time next is called
it can continue where it left off
so the next thing I would do is add two to even
continue back up into the wild statement
see that even is less than end
and yield the next even number
and what's powerful
about generators is that you can set up
any computation you want
and that computation will be executed lazily
so when somebody asks for the next element
then you continue until you reach the next yield
but if nobody asks
for all of the elements
then you don't have to continue computing everything
you just pause there until the next value is needed
generator functions return generators
but they often process iterators in
the course of their execution
and this happened so often that in python 3.3
released back in 2002
they added a new statement yield from
that just has a generator
yield all the elements in some other iterator
so a yield from statement yields all
values from an iterator
or iterable
for instance let's say I want to define a then b
which is a function that takes in
two iterables or iterators
and returns all the elements in the first
followed by all the elements in the second
one way I could write this is to say for x and a
yield x and then for x and b yield x
but there's a simpler way
I could just write yield from a then yield from b
these are completely equivalent
so you can think of yield from
it's just shorthand
for writing down a four statement
where you go through all the elements in a
and yield them
but it does allow you to avoid giving a name
to each item in this sequence
which just cleans up your coat
here's another example
let's say we want to define a generator function
that counts down from five
well one way I could do it is recursively
if k is greater than zero than I yield k
then I yield all of the values in countdown k minus one
by calling yield from countdown k minus one
so if I'm counting down from k
if kray is greater than zero
I definitely want to yield k first
if I wrote this wrong I just wrote yield countdown
k minus one
the second element in the iterator that I got back
would actually just be another iterator
so counting down from three would start out well
but the next thing I'd get back is a generator object
which is not what I expected
I expected the No.2
so to get the numbers two and one
I'd have to write a four statement
and yield each element in the four statement
then if I count down I get three
and then two and then one
and the shorthand way to do that
is instead of writing a four statement
I just read yield from
everything in countdown
and I got 3 2 1 last off
wouldn't it be cool if it said blast off at the end
well we could change that
we could just say else
yield
blast off
okay so now we can go for every
k in countdown
three
print k
and it gives me the whole countdown sequence
and something exciting at the end
let's finish with a slightly more involved example
I can yield all the prefixes of s
or I'm gonna assume s as a string
but it really could be any iterable
if it's not empty
then I'm gonna yield from the prefixes
of all of s up and two
but not including the last element
and then I'll yield s itself
so the prefixes of both
is a generator object
if I list them out
then I get b bo bot and both
and I get them in this order
because I yield from prefixes before I yield s itself
once I can generate prefixes
I can also generate substrings
if s is not empty
then some of the substrings are just the prefixes
so I'll yield all of those
and then I'll yield from the substrings
of the rest of the string
so substrings
of tops for instance
is a generator
if I list its contents then I see t two top and tops
those are all the prefixes of tops
but then I get all the prefixes of ops oop ops
and then PPS and s
and together those are all of the substrings of tops