61 election No.18
announcements
homework three is due today
you can revise your hog
project to earn back any lost composition points
by tomorrow
submit with python three ok desh desh revise
click on here to get the whole
piazza announcement that describes how to do this
here's a study guide created by the core staff
that gives you some indication of how to get ready
for the next midterm
which is three weeks from yesterday
and we'll have some dropping advising
office hours tomorrow from 1:00pm to two 30 pm
so that's Friday
just join the office hours q
and you'll be able to ask questions about anything
you want and get some advice
today we'll start a new unit in the course
about object oriented programming
this approach to programming
has a lot of new ideas in it
but you've already been exposed to most of them
there's a notion of data abstraction
there's a notion of mutation
you know about those things already
there's some new stuff too
including some new syntax
and some new concepts like inheritance
since there's a lot to learn
students often
struggle a bit with this part of the course
so I recommend dedicating some time
to practice all of the lab problems that you see
work through the homework problems
and allocate a fair amount of time
for the project we will release next week
which is about object oriented programming
in lecture
we're going to try something a little bit different
I'll start you off with professor fried's introduction
to object oriented programming
because I think the way that he describes it is just
great then you'll hear the standard 61 a
introduction to objects from me
but I'm also going to link to a bunch of other
videos by professor fried
that you're welcome to watch if you want
to hear his description
the rest of his
lectures on object jointed programming are great
they do involve a little bit of stuff
that we haven't covered in this course
so there might be a few things about
drawing pictures on the screen
that might look unfamiliar to you
I'll make sure to give you a link
to how to catch up on all that
stuff if you're interested
and so I hope that by having two descriptions
the one that's usually in 61 a
and the version
that professor fried developed for his graduate course
to a sixa helps all of you get a better
understanding
of what's going on in object oriented programming
okay here we go
welcome back we're now ready to
start a bit of a new chapter in the course
which is we're going to be talking
about classes and objects
and in particular object oriented programming
which may be something you've heard about
and we're going to spend the next full three lectures
talking about exactly what that is
so let's just go ahead and dive in
all right let me just define a few simple terms
a class is something that combines and abstracts out
data and functionality
and it's important to understand those two things
data and functionality up until now
we have been talking about really mostly functionality
a little bit on data when we talked about lists
a little bit of
data when we talked
about different types of variable ties
but for the most part
we've been focused on functionality
iterative constructs conditional constructs
function parameters in parameters out recursion
and now we're going to talk about
putting all these pieces together and how we combine
of course data
and functions
and so what a class does
is it combines the storing of information
data and functionality on that data
an object is just an instantiation of a class
and I want to distinguish between these tubes
that's a really important
becoming be using the words
but it's also an important conceptual distinction
and so maybe
the simplest way to think about this distinction
is this way
you can think about a class as a blueprint to a house
can't live in it
but it sort of tells you how to build it
and the object is well the house itself
so I can take this blueprint
and cookie cutter that down the street
and get multiple instantiations of this object
so think about the class is a definition of something
and an object as an instantiation of it
it's an actual thing that we now get to manipulate
and I'll be using these terms
throughout the next few weeks
I just want to make sure that we understand
the distinction between a class which is a definition
and an object
which is a thing that we've actually created
that we can now act on
now as I said
a class combines and abstract data and functions
an object is an instantiation of that class
and I've been
hinting this throughout the whole semester
is we've sort of seen objects and classes already
there's that notation that's been lingering around
I think I probably mentioned
that a string at some point
is sort of like a class
a list is like a class
so here's a really simple example of a class
a string is a built in class
that the data is the string itself
quote unquote ardvark
the functionality is append
I can append something to the end of a string
an integer is a built in class
stores data the actual number
and the addition operator is a function on that data
so now you see what I mean
when I say data and functionality
we store information a string and integer a list
and then we can operate on that
we provide you the programmer
functionality to operate on that data
now I don't think it'll surprise you to learn that
we can define our own classes
it's not just
whatever python gives us and that's all we can do
we can define our own classes
our own data our own functionality
and then build up really nice functionality from that
and that's what we're going to spend
of course the majority of our time doing
is talking about how we define our own classes
all right so
let me start off by saying
I'm going to define a class for you
and it's going to unfold over a series of lectures
and the class is of type ball right there you see that
so this
and I'm going to sort of do a bit of a slight of hand
here I'm not going to show you the details of the
class or the object just yet
I'm going to tell you
that we have this object this class called a ball class
and what it allows you to do
is store some data which is the position
and the speed of the ball
and the functionality is you can move the ball
you can render the ball etc etc
and again
I'm not going to show you the code for a little bit
because I want to again
start sort of conceptually
and then we'll dive
into the details of how all this works
so
the class that we define called bald has a constructor
and this line of code is calling the constructor
to do what to instantiate an object
so there it is
I have a ball class and I want to build a ball
the way I do that is I call this constructor
the constructor is just the name of the class
and then some information
about what I want my object to be
in this case it's the xy position of the ball
and the xy velocity of the ball
and we'll talk some more about what we're going to do
with all those things
and then of course
my ball is now an object of type class ball
so this looks pretty similar to everything
we've seen before
it's a function call
in this case it happens to be a constructor
which I'm going to describe in more detail in the
second to a class of type ball
it's going to return something back
and that now is going to be an object
now this constructor is really
really special and very important
where I spent a little time talking about it
before I actually show you the code
for how to build this class
so what the constructor does No.1 is that
remember this class is just this concept
it's just a blueprint
I don't physically have anything yet
I don't have an actual object
so the first thing it's going to do
is it's going to create in memory a ball object
so it reaches into memory it allocates some memory
that says okay
we're going to store some information in here
some data with along with some functionality
and it does that for you
good not No.1 so actually create the ball
No.2 it's going to initialize the data
based on what you passed it
so now what it says is okay
I can have multiple balls
the same way I can have multiple houses
I'm going to build an object
I'm going to allocate memory for it
and I'm going to store the data that the user wants
x y position
vx vy velocity in the x and the y direction
good initialization
and it returns to you
this is really important
the address of the ball object that was
allocated in memory and initialized for you
now this sounds should sound pretty
familiar to you because this sounds a lot like a list
with a list what do we do
we say score bracket score bracket
slightly different syntax for calling its constructor
a bunch of data in the list common delimited elements
what does python do
it reaches into memory allocate some space
sticks the data in there
allocation and initialization
and what does it hand you back
the address of a list
not the actual list but the address to the list
which you can of course
then reference the contents of the list
so in fact and I think I even hinted at this list
are a built in object
and they do all three of these things
good
so this is sort of the picture you can have in your
head
and we've seen a picture like this when we did lists
so I have a class called ball again
you have no idea how I've done this
and we're going to get there
so just abstract out the details of this for a minute
and you know because I tell you that you can generate
you can build a ball
it has four pieces of information you need to specify
where is it on a drawing
canvas
how fast is it moving in the horizontal and vertical
direction
and so when you call this constructor
it does what it allocates some memory that's this box
it initializes the variables which are
I'm going to tell you are called xy vxby
which we'll see in a few minutes
to the values you passed in 10
15 0 -5
and it hands you back
address to the object
so this again is just some random number
it's just a pointer to where it is
so I have an object in memory I have instantiated an
something of type ball a class of type and now
I have two things at my disposal
I have the data
which I've just initialized
and I have all the
functionality that comes with this class
which I haven't shown you yet but I will
in a minute
now if I define another ball
here's ball two with a different xy position 12 and 23
and a different velocity two and three
then what happens is
well that's a call to the constructor
the constructor allocates memory
it initializes four variables
and it hands you back an address
and now I have two objects
completely separate from each other
right
this is a call to instructor please build a ball object
this is a call to instructor
create another one and I can do this all day long
and each one of these stores its own data
each one has access to functionality to do what we want
to this ball object
good
so
and again
I haven't shown you how to construct a workout
I haven't shown you how to define a class
I haven't shown you anything yet
but I want to sort of
track that out for a minute and get through these
concept and then we're going to dive
into the details of that in the next segment
okay
just let me make a few points before we finish up here
so when I define an object ball one
I can access the various
elements of the data that I initialize
and remember it's xy vxvy
using that little dot notation right there
so ball one of course is the name of the object
and I can reach in to that object
and I can access the data and the functionality
of course using that dot notation
so you remember a while back
we introduced that dot notation
and I sort of wave my hands vigorously
to tell you this is some syntactic thing
having to do with object orienter program
don't worry about it we'll get to it
we're getting to it
this dot notation is part of accessing either data
or functionality associated with an object
so you give the object name
dot and then the data type
and of course
you can see why this is
if I can create multiple objects
it's not x per se
it's this balls x or this balls y or vx or vy
so I have to say which object do you want
and then which data element of that
same thing with a house
if I have five houses that are the same
I can't say go deliver this package to ball or house
I have to say this house this address
and then you go into that particular house
and get what you want out of it
good and
I can also access functions associated with objects
and again I haven't
shown you how to do this yet
but I just want to introduce the notation
so here what I'm doing is I'm initializing a ball
at position five four with velocity three and six
and I can
print the x coordinate by just saying ball one
that's of course the name of the variable x
and when I print this out it will print for me five
because that is the x position here
now remember that classes bundle up
data and functionality things that you can actually do
what functionality well whatever I want
so for a list
I can add things remove things append things
sort things
that's the functionality that's been given to me
for this ball class
well we're gonna see it a little bit
but it's whatever I want to do for the ball class
that's my job as the constructor of this class
that give you certain amounts of functionality
I will tell you that one of the functionality
is a function called update position
it takes as input a time step
and it moves the balls position according to the
velocity
okay so let's just think about this for a second
this is in some pixel coordinates and velocity is what
how many pixels are you moving per 2nd or per frame
so with a time step of 0.1
when I update the position of this ball
its x coordinate moves from position five
to position five plus one tenth of three
because this is three pixels per 2nd
I've moved for half a one tenth of a second
and so I've moved 0.3 pixels
and now it has a new position
okay so notice here that the function
associated with the object ball
is operating on the data associated with the object
ball okay
so again this class bundles up data
information about what you are storing
and then gives you the ability to manipulate that
data through functions
and there again is that not notation
I'm not calling the function update position
that's not a function
that's a function associated with a class of tight ball
I'm calling this ball's update position
and another ball
it has a different update position
why because it has to operate on its own data
so every time you instantiate an object
you get the data and the functionality associated with
that object
okay I know that was a lot
there's a lot of
conceptual things going on here
a lot of syntactical thing
hold on
we're gonna do a couple more segments of this lecture
and I'm gonna start now
to reveal
how you build these classes and objects and show you
where the data is where the functionality is
and hopefully this will become more clear
all right let's pick it up in a few minutes
the rest of this
playlist is the standard lecture that I give
about object oriented programming
starting from the very beginning
so it will be just a little bit redundant
with what professor frie just said
however I think there are enough
differences in how we tend to describe
these things and motivate them
that is worth watching them both
and the rest of this lecture will also cover
all of the mechanics
of how you build
your own classes and methods and all of that
but perhaps you haven't gotten enough
of professor fried's description yet
I totally understand
it's great
so if you look in the description of this video
you'll find links to the rest
of his object oriented programming lecture
it does rely
on a few things that we haven't covered yet
like how to draw on a screen
and how to use a notebook to write python
you can learn about that stuff
just by following
the rest of the links in the description
which walk you through
the very first week
of professor for reed's graduate course 206a
I've also added a link to that course website
in case you want to find
more videos that he's made there
so you're welcome to go explore that stuff now
or you can keep watching this playlist
and hear the standard 61 a
introduction to objects
today we begin
learning about object oriented programming
so we already know that all
values are objects in python
but we're going to start to
understand what that really means
object oriented programming is a method for organizing
modular programs
meaning that you define each piece
without worrying about the other pieces
and then they all work together
so that means we're going to worry about abstraction
barriers and bundling together information
and its related behavior
object oriented programming is also a metaphor
for computation using distributed state
what do I mean by distributed state
well we'll have a bunch of different objects
and each of those will have its own local state
so when we want to know
what's going on in the program
we have to inspect each
object in order to figure that out
each object will also know
how to manage its own local state
based on method calls
so you call a method on an object
and that might change its state
the object knows how to update its state correctly
and those method calls are best thought of
as messages being passed between objects
so that's the metaphor
we have a bunch of different things
objects pass messages amongst each other
and each one is responsible for taking care of its own
internal state
so what's going on with itself
several objects may be instances of a common type
and different types may relate to each other
so we're going to see examples of all this stuff
but that's the basic idea that you want to understand
when you think about object oriented programming
and to support this metaphor
we're gonna have specialized syntax and vocabulary
in order to make this all
make sense so
we saw in last lecture
that we might have different objects
back then they were functions now they'll be objects
that are john's account and stevens account
and let's say we have another object john
I made it tall because you know
and so what happens in this metaphor
is
that if john wants to withdraw money from his account
to give it to steven
then there will be a message
passed from john to the account
the accounts business is to
make sure that it knows how to withdraw money
and update its balance correctly
as one as john's done that
then I might send another message to stephen's account
saying a deposit $10
and then stephen's accounts balance will be updated
now the balance for each account is stored
within the object
and john can ask for it using a message as necessary
and the idea is
that all these different objects might have other
messages coming in
and they might send messages to other objects as well
so john's account might occasionally say
after many withdrawals
john is probably time to apply for a loan
so that's the idea that we want to create
when we write code
in an object oriented programming language like python
fundamentally
objects are organized according to classes
a class serves as a template for all of its instances
and each object is an instance of some class
so we have built in
classes that we've seen along the way
but now we're going to start defining our own classes
so the idea is
that all bank accounts will have a balance
and an account holder
that's what makes a bank account a bank account
so the account class
should make sure that everyone of its instances
has those attributes
what's this current balance
and what's who's the account holder
that'll happen when we create a new instance
and here's what the code is going to look like
we'll say I'm creating an account
I'll pass in the account holder jim
and I'll bind the resulting object
which is an instance of the account class
to the name a
then if I ask
well who is the holder of a
the account holder is gym
I set that
when I call the account class to create the object
and now I can access it later
as an attribute of that account
and what's the balance ball of jim
so far doesn't have anything
so how's it jim gonna have some money in his account
what we want all bank accounts to have
withdraw and deposit behaviors
and all bank accounts should work the same way
which is why they're all instances of the same class
so if I deposit $15
into this bank account which we've named a
as a gym's account
now we'll get the balance back of 15
and if we would draw $10
then the balance goes down to five
what's the balance now it's five
so notice that some of these look like call expressions
and some just access a value
that's part of the object
if I always draw $10 again I will have insuvision funds
so there's two different ways we could realize this
we could put deposit in withdraw methods as
part of every single account
but that's not what we're gonna do
instead we'll make sure that all accounts share
the same withdraw and deposit methods
at our way we can guarantee that they all behave
in the same way
which is what we want
class statements
let you create any type of data you want
the class statement looks like this
you say class give the class a name
and then write a suite of other statements
a class statement creates a new class
which can be the type of some new object
and it binds that class to name
in the first frame of the current environment
within the suite
assignment and deaf statements
create attributes of the class
normally they would create names and frames
but class statements are special
so the suite is executed
immediately when the class statement is executed
so if I define a class called clown
and have an assignment and a def statement within there
then
nose and dance become attributes of the class
with their attribute values
being whatever was assigned or defined
so clown dot nose is big and red and clown dot dance
called returns no thanks
now these are not typical ways in which you use
class statements
but I just wanted to tell you what it
means to write a class statement
and the rest of this lecture
will go through the details of how to build a class
so that it works effectively
when you create a class
it is bound to a name
and those names are usually an upper case
and you'll see the class value printed out in this way
now the whole point of classes is in order to let you
construct objects of that class
so what we want to do is define an account class
that allows us to create bank accounts
and here's an idea
all bank accounts have a balance and an account holder
so the account class should do something to make sure
that these attributes
appear on each one of its instances
so we'd like it to be that if I have an account for jim
and I bind that to the name a
it creates an object
that has both a balance and an account holder
so here we're calling our class as you can see
and that's how we create instances of the class
when a class is called
a new instance of the class is created
it starts out as a blank slate
and it's up to the class to fill it it
the specially named in a two method of the class
is called with the new object as its first argument
bound to the name self
along with any additional arguments provided
in the call expression
here we have jim provided in the call expression
so if we look at the definition of an account class
what we're going to see
is a def statement within it
for this special name called in it
which takes his arguments self
that's going to be balanced
to the account object itself
and anything else we need to know
in order to create this account
now the object which starts out as a blank slate
is passed in and bound to the self name
the other names are bound to whatever else is passed in
in this case we passed in jim
and that's our account holder
then what happens is that the body of this function is
executed
and that allows us to assign
attribute values to the new object that was created
the new instance
so self dot balance equal zero
means that
as part of this account now there's a zero balance
and self dot holder being the account holder
binds holder as an attribute with attribute value gym
and now we have something useful
it's not just a blank slate
it's something
that has a balance and an account holder
which is the idea that we wanted to implement
and this is how we implement it
in it is a special name
and we always use that same special name
it's called a constructor
so you can see the relationship
between data abstraction
and the object oriented programming system in python
and it's special because whenever the class is called
this gets called automatically
with these arguments as described here
so now once I do all that work
if I look up the holder for a I'll get jim
and if I look up the balance I'll get zero
now let's say a word about the identity of objects
every object that is an instance of a user defined
class has a unique identity
it's its own thing
so a fi akite
create an account for jim
and a separate account for jack
then a and b are bound to different accounts
every call to account creates a new account instance
and there is only one account class but many instances
so if I look up the balance of a I'll get zero
if I look up the holder of b I'll get jack
they both have their own balance and their own holder
identity operators is and is not
test if two expressions evaluate to the same object
so a is a is true a is not b
is also true
and binding an object to a new name
using assignment does not create a new object
but instead just gives another name to the same object
this has been true for every
example we've looked at in the course
and it's true for user to find instances as well
if I say c equals a
c and a refer to the same thing
so they always have the same balance of the same holder
because they're the same account
the last piece we need
in order to finish implementing a class is to add
additional methods
methods are what represent the messages
that an object will accept
and they're just functions
they're defined within the class statement
so let's take a look
methods are defined in the suite of the class statement
so we write class account
and then we define the in it method
and then we can define other methods
so here's a deposit method
it takes in an object
of the instance of the class account
and it takes some amount to deposit
and what it does is it changes the balance
to be whatever the balance was
plus the amount that was passed it
now it's important to pay
careful attention to what's going on here
self is a name that's going to refer to an instance
of the account class
that's being deposited into
when we
change an attribute using this assignment statement
what we're doing is we're changing the balance of that
particular account at particular instance
to whatever its balance was
plus the amount as being deposit
so a mount doesn't need it in itself in front of it
because it's passed in
as an argument to this deposit method
then we're going to return the balance
of the account that was passed in which we call itself
and that's what depositing is
what about withdrawing
well
that's slightly more complicated but the same idea
we'll pass him
an instance of the account class called self
and then the amount that we want to withdraw
we'll check and see if that amount is too large
if so the more we turn insufficient funds
otherwise
we'll set the balance to be whatever the balance was
minus the amount
and then we'll return the balance
and then we're done
so now we've implemented the account class
in such a way
that it starts out with a balance and an account holder
all that's set up with the constructor
and then we can deposit amounts into it
and we can withdraw amounts
so these deaf statements create function objects
as always
there's no new rule for executing a deaf statement
but their names aren't bound in a particular frame
instead they're bound as attributes of the class
so the account class now has three attributes in it
deposit and withdraw
okay so now that we've defined our methods
what can we do with them well we can invoke them
so all invoked methods have access to the object
the methods being invoked on
via this self parameter
so self
is a name we give to the object that we can manipulate
look up its balance whatever
and so all these different methods have access
and can manipulate the object state
so there's only one balance for every account
but we can deposit and withdraw from it with
two different methods
okay so here's our count class
I've abbreviated some of it
because it's not important for this example
what is important
is that we define deposit with two arguments self
and then the amount that we want to pass it
and then we use dot notation
in order to invoke this method
and dot notation
is special because it automatically supplies
the first argument to the method
what's it supplying
what's supplying the
object instance that we're invoking the method on
okay so let's look at this
after we have to find the account
we can create an account by calling account
passing in the holder
now tom account has that balance of zero
and the holder is named tom
and I may deposit $100 into tom account
notice that I define deposit with
two formal parameters
but I call it with only one argument
so where's the second argument
well
it's actually that the first argument is tom's account
and the second argument is 100
so when we call this function
we're calling it on tom account which we call self
and 100 which we call them out
and then we just execute the body of the function
as if it were any other function
okay so let's look a little bit deeper into these
dot expressions
objects receive their messages in this metaphor
of object oriented programming
using not notation
so don notation accesses attributes
of the instance or attributes of its class
so balance is an instance attribute
every instance has a different balance
withdraw the method
is a class attribute
all instances share the same withdraw method
okay dot notation looks like this
you give it any expression you want on the left
but you just have to give it a simple name
on the right separated with a dot
the expression can be any valid python expression
it evaluates to some object and then we look up
the named attributes so it has to be a simple name
so what happens with this dot expression
well it evaluates to the value of the attribute
looked up by name in the object
that's the value of the expression
what's looked up by name me what
we're gonna have to go through all the details
and we'll do most of them next lecture
but the basic story is you look in the instance and see
is this name bound there
if not then you look in the class
okay so let's think about tom account that deposit tent
here's an expression we've seen before
what's really going on
is that this is a call expression
with a compound operator
the compound operator is a thought expression
and what it does is it goes and finds
the deposit method
of tom account
which is actually part of the account class
that tom account is an instance of
okay so this dot expression evaluates to a function
and then we call that function on 10
and that's how we deposit $10 in the time account
so let's look at the demo real quick
so over here on the right we'll see
the account class that we've been talking about
it's exactly the same as the examples
but I've added a little bit of documentation
so when you define a class
you usually give it a dock string
and account as a bounds and a holder
and then you can give it some dock
test to show you how to use this account
so we created an account
my account
we deposit 100 we withdraw 90 we have 10 left
withdrawing 90 again gives us insufficient funds
because we have a balance of only 10
and we create all this behavior by having an instructor
that's a posit method
and a withdrawal method
and this really does work
if I load this file
then account is a class
and
john
will make will bind to an account for me
so what is john
john's an account object
so here's the class
if I ask for the type of john it will tell me
the class account which I'm defined here
and john has a balance
not very much there
and john has a holder which is me
and when I deposit
10 into john and I do it again and again and again
then john's back this goes up
and then I can withdraw
all of that out again
okay so it behaves like an account should
you can deposit it withdraw from it
it knows what to do when you overdraw
so we can think of it as an abstraction
for a bank account
and we define this behavior
with the following class statement
so what are attributes anyway
well they're just data that's stored within
either an instance or the class itself
and how do we access them
we can use dot expressions
or there's a built in function that does the same thing
so going back to our account example
I could create an account
by calling the account class
and I can access the balance on that account
with john dot balance
there's also a built in function
called get atter that's get attribute
where you pass in an object
in the name of the attribute that you want to get
and you'll get that balance back
and this works
even if we've deposited
some money
we can also check and see
if an object has a particular attribute
so we have a balance
but we don't have a lengths for instance
so if accessing an attribute
we can use a dot expression
or we can use get adder
and that allows us
to look up an attribute using a streak
so we looked at that example
and we can also check
whether an object has an attribute
get
adder and dot expressions are exactly the same thing
it's just a functional form of a specialized syntax
they look up the name in exactly the same way
and looking up an attribute
may return either
an instance attribute or an attribute of the class
but basically you look on the instance first
if it's there then that's the attribute that you get
otherwise you look in the class
okay so let's talk about methods and functions
well a method is an attribute
that's a function
so python distinguishes between two things
functions which have been
around since the beginning of this course
we know all about those
and bound methods
which coupled together a function
and the object on which the method will be invoked
so what does that mean
well when I have an object and a function
and that object is going to be passed
in as the first argument of that function
a function is a method
then that's called a bound method
so let's take a look
if I look up the attribute deposit on the account class
all it is is a function
and it's something that takes two arguments
it takes the object that I'm depositing into
and then the amount that I want to deposit
if instead I look up deposit on an
instance of the account class
where tom account is an account
then what I see is that this is a method
which means it's taken the deposit function
and bounded together with the time account
which will be passed yet as the first argument
when we actually call the function
okay
so what happens well
if we access the function directly from the class
then we need to pass in two arguments
because remember how it was defined
it took two arguments
one was called self and the other was called amount
so if I take in time account that I pass in 1001
now
there's one thousand and eleven dollars in the account
on the other hand
if I start out with time account
and I look up the attribute deposit
what I get back is a method
a method is different than a function
in the sense that the first arguments already filled it
with tom account
so tom accounts are already the first argument
and all we need to do is supply the second argument
so let's talk about looking up attributes by name
we see a dot expression
in order to evaluate a dot expression
we evaluate the expression to the left of the dot
which yields the object of the dot expression
that's where we're going to look up the name
then name is matched against the instance
attributes of that object
if an attribute with that name exists
its value is returned
if not then name is looked up in the class
which yields a class attribute value
that value is returned unless it's a function
like withdraw or deposit
in which case a bound method is returned
in stiff where what's bound together
well the object of the thought expression
is bound together with that function
to create a bound method
so there are attributes of an instance
and there are attributes of a class
so far all the attributes of the class we've seen
have been methods
but that's not the only option we have
class attributes are anything that
shared across all instances of a class
because they're part of the class
not part of the instance
now what happens to be that when you look up
that attribute by name on an instance
and it's not on the instance
you'll find it in the class
okay so let's extend our example a little bit
here's our account class
in addition
to defining the constructor
we're also going to add a class attribute called
the instructory
now this is something that will be shared among
all accounts
so all accounts have the same interest trait
if I look up interest on an account
I'll find 0.02 as the value
so here I create a new account
tom is the holder
jim is the holder of a second account
and what's the interest rate for tom account in 0.02
and what about for jim same thick
because they both are instances of this class
neither of them has its own interests
but the class has an interest rate
and that's what we're looking up in these two cases
so it's important to note
that interest is not copied in to each instance
instead it's always kept in the class
and that's important
because if it changes in the class
well that change will be reflected
in all of the instances