61a lecture 27 q a
the first question was whether
parentheses always indicate a call
expression and whether adding a single
quote before them
an apostrophe converts that call
expression into a list
it is definitely the case that an
opening parenthesis
causes a call unless
there's something special here in which
case it's called a special form which
kind of behaves like a call
but always has some tweak on its
behavior um
but if you don't have some uh special
form keyword there
then this is the beginning of a call
expression
so what's the story with quotation well
that basically says
don't do this thing just talk about it
that's supposed to be the metaphor um
and so
kind of like how you quote something in
uh
in prose so this
won't make the call instead it will just
output the call itself which happens to
be a list containing the symbol f and
the numbers two of three
so a couple of things so i think let me
make sure we understand the questions
the question is write a function that
takes as input a list and returns the
sum of the even numbers
so as john starts to do his magic let me
just say you're you're absolutely right
that the syntax in scheme
is a little weird um it's okay that will
come
quick the concepts i think you probably
one thing you can do by the way is make
sure you can write it in python
and once you can do that it's really
just a translation problem now and that
syntax will come
it's a little awkward i always find
scheme like all the parentheses make me
a little crazy in scheme over time and
it's hard to sort of keep track of it
and one of the things you'll get good at
is figuring out how to indent and space
your code
so it looks like sort of a python like
program yeah
yeah that's a great point i mean you
mentioned that scheme seems to have a
steep learning curve
and it will not feel natural to you the
first hour that you work with it that is
true and i think that's true of most
programming languages
even if they look kind of familiar
there's always some tricky parts that
take a little practice to get used to so
um the way this course is structured is
that there isn't a whole lot of
lecturing about scheme i mean we're kind
of done with that but we do give you
a series of labs and homeworks and
discussions just so you get like enough
practice that it starts feeling familiar
um and it is true that a lot of what you
know applies but everything's just
slightly different in terms of the
syntax and so you gotta get used to that
okay so uh how would we define
some evens um so we're gonna take in a
list it might have some
even numbers it might have some odd
numbers if i put some odd numbers in
here then it doesn't change the answer
right is the idea and you know i wrote
them in order but they aren't
necessarily in order
so i think it's a good idea to have some
notion of whether something's even
or not in advance and we could like test
that
the scheme convention is actually to
name
procedures with a question mark if they
return
just a true or false value so if you
want to know
whether some number n is even well
um we got to figure out the scheme way
of doing this right so
uh the it's this might actually be built
in
i guess we should check is there even oh
i guess there's even built-in
okay so uh it kind of does what we'd
expect
um this is the symbol for a true value
in scheme there's like a built-in true
and there's a built-in false
um but we could write this too i think
that there's a
operator to do modular arithmetic oh
it's not called mod
what is it called remainder i thought it
was it's called remainder so
uh one way to implement this would say
is the remainder
of whatever we're trying to figure out
uh
and um divided by two
zero that would make it even one that
would make it odd so if i did want to
define this i think i would write it as
is the remainder of dividing n by
two zero and there's a built-in zero
or you could do equal zero that would be
fine too
so and you know the way i work in scheme
is i kind of check stuff as i go along
so now i've made my own even
does it do the right thing it seems to
do the right thing okay so now i have a
piece
now we're going to try to sum the even
numbers within s
we're going to do it recursively
basically how you process all
lists in scheme is that you treat them
like linked lists which you already know
about
and most linked list processing is
either recursive or with a while
statement
but we don't have while statements so i
guess we're stuck with recursion
that means we do something with the
first element unless there is no first
element and then we have to decide what
to do
okay so if it's the case that
s is empty and how do we say that well
the most common way to say it is to say
is
if no s that basically is a way of
saying is
s this special empty list called nil in
scheme
um then what is the sum of all the even
elements well i'd call that zero that's
kind of the
basic sum identity
if you don't have anything to sum
together otherwise
you have to figure out how to make this
sum well here we have to decide
is the first element in s in the sum or
not
if even car
s
car s is schemes version of first
element
and here's how we check whether it's
even
if it is even we want to add it to the
result so i would say
plus car s and then we need to sum the
evens in the rest of s
so there's a recursive call some evens
in the cutter of s
what if s is not even well then we don't
need to really subtract it we just need
to
ignore it and therefore sum all the even
numbers
ends the cutter of s and that will give
me the same thing as the sum
of the evens and all of s because the
first number is odd
now i can see what this does
if i try to sum evens 2 4 6 i get 12
and if i try to sum evens 1 2 3 4 5 6
i also get 12. all right looks pretty
good
yeah good question so the question is
how come there's no lambda in here and
where's the function when you write
define
and what comes immediately after define
is
uh stuff in parentheses a combination
you are defining a procedure which is
same thing as a function just the
scheme speak so
if you define just a symbol
you're not building a procedure
necessarily if you really wanted a
procedure you'd need a lambda
but if you were ever writing a
parenthesis right after
define what you are building is a
procedure
so now i have an f which is a procedure
if i call it on three then i'll add four
to it
and writing this is really just you know
shorthand
for a lambda is one way to think about
it this would do the same thing
well so this is the same thing as in
python right we could write it as an
explicit function or as a nameless
function
right the same way yeah it's just the
syntax is just slightly different
the next question was about a specific
example of
building a list out of an existing list
so we ended up just doing a bunch of
examples related to that
so let's just go through and do some
list examples where we build things out
of
the cons operator and the nil
and some numbers and see what we get and
why
um writing cons
1 to cons 2 to cons
3 nil is a lot like in python
writing link 1 link 2 link
3 or if you wanted to put in link.empty
here you could but that part if you
recall is optional but that's like the
equivalent of nil
this just builds a list
scheme lists are linked lists and so
if it's always the case that you're
considering a number with
another list in that order you're not
going to get any nesting at all
the only time you get nesting is if
whatever expression you put in this
element position
evaluates to a list itself so
you asked about one example what if
instead of a number here
i have an expression that evaluates to a
list
this is like there instead of the number
one and what this builds
is a list that contains four and three
so now we have a list with
as one of its elements a list
this cons is just continuing
the list without building any nesting
into it
so if i put a 1 here and a 2 here and a
nil
then i get a nested structure looks just
like this
except for instead of 1 i have 4 3
because the expression is the same
except for instead of a 1 i have 4 3.
so that's kind of the story there
if i already have a list i can use
that in the place of a number i mean i
can write any expression i want it's
just a question of whether this
evaluates to a number
if it evaluated to 1 i'd be building
this if it built
it evaluated to a list like 4 3 or 1 2
then i would building a list of lists
so this expression gives me a two
element list there's that structure of
it's a list here's the first element now
we continue
here's the second element it just
happens to be that the elements are both
lists
so now let's do the first line in the
chat and notice y is different
right so notice where that s is in the
first line
you're building up this list the first
element is the list for
three and then the last element is well
that's just the list
one two so you're just appending a new
element to
the remaining list yeah no
yeah good question are symbols different
than strings i mean
they're kind of an impoverished version
of strings because you can't put spaces
in them and you can't put new line
characters in them and stuff like that
what's special about them is that they
can show up in code
so like you would never have a name like
an identifier or a variable
in python that had a space in it and
likewise symbols can't have spaces in
them either
so sometimes they're used like strings
we'll do that in this course just so
that we don't have to talk about strings
so much
in scheme the full language there are
strings that are supported
and there's like double quote marks to
delimit them
and they can have spaces and new line
characters and stuff like that
um so you'd probably use that if you
were going to like
you know write some program that really
had a string interface to it
but for simple examples uh symbols are
sufficient
a good question so the question is
what's the difference between unquoting
versus evaluating something um
it's the same to unquote means to take
part of an expression that has been
quasi-quoted and evaluate that part so
in that sense unquoting and evaluating
are the same thing
now evaluation happens automatically by
default
so if i type plus one two
it doesn't result in a list containing a
symbol plus and a one and a two you get
the number three that's kind of how
scheme works is that as you're
processing
scheme code things get evaluated along
the way
so quotation and quasi quotation are a
way of presenting that
if you have some longer thing i want
3 minus 2 gives me 1.
if i quote that whole thing then i end
up with a nested list
it is true that if i had that nested
list and let's say i gave it a name
i could then ask scheme to evaluate it
as if
it were code and it would tell me 3
minus 2 is 1.
quasi quotation gives you a little bit
more control instead of just saying
i want the whole thing quoted or i want
the whole thing evaluated
you can say i want
this part to be evaluated to give me the
number 3
but i want to keep the minus 3 2
structure intact so
you know it's not a new idea to unquote
it's just to evaluate
but uh what's new about it is that
within some larger structure you can
pick which parts get evaluated and which
parts though
oh good question so what's the
relationship between
unquoting and repper in python
i think the the roles are a little bit
different so
repper will give you back a string
that if you were to evaluate it
you would get kind of the value that is
described by that string
and when you unquote something you get
the value
that you get when you evaluate it so i
guess there's kind of one more step in
python right it's like if you've got the
wrapper string of something you would
then have to evaluate that thing in
order to get a value
whereas unquoting kind of does the
evaluation immediately
yeah great question so the question is
in python
can you generate code like by quoting
stuff
um and the answer is yes but it's not
done
very often so um
python code doesn't look like a bunch of
linked lists
it looks like all kinds of stuff you
know it's got colons and
a mixture of parentheses and commas and
all sorts of like square brackets and
various things like that
it is definitely the case that you if
you have an existing
value and then you build a string that
describes some expression about it
like i have a string that says i want to
start with s
and i want to slice it
but how much do i want to slice it well
i kind of want to start
somewhere around
2-1 and i want to
keep slicing to the variant
i can build a python expression this way
through string manipulation and then i
could
evaluate that in python
and it would be as if i had just written
this piece of code and asked python to
evaluate it
so yes python has this functionality as
well
lots of programming languages don't
python
draws a lot from the lisp tradition in
fact and so it has this kind of thing
but
building python expressions is just
basically harder and more awkward
because there's so much variety in the
syntax makes it much easier for humans
to read
makes a little bit harder for machines
to process
the next question was what a call to
print returns
in scheme ah good question so how do we
figure out what this
evaluates to i think we would try to
bind the result of printing one
to some symbol
notice here that the one has already
appeared and what is
s anyway oh it's like it's not there at
all what if we try to print it
well we get this special value called
undefined
that's it's kind of close to python's
none
except for here's the rule this is like
more of a conventional rule than
enforced by the language but here's the
rule is that
you're never supposed to do anything
with the undefined value
whereas in python people use none for
all kinds of stuff they like compare
whether you know something is none etc
that basically never shows up in scheme
code so when you get this undefined
value which happens to exist
the idea is you should never do anything
with it you should never check to see if
it's equal to another undefined you
should never check to see
how many undefineds there are in a list
or something like that you should just
stop so basically like this expression
is legal but it's a no-no you should
never take the value of
print and do something else with a
follow-up question was what
are the properties of this undefined
value is it true or is it false
so is print is undefined a true value
or a false value um
it i guess is a true value in the
interpreter that we use but this is just
an implementation detail it might be
that in someone else's scheme it would
be a false value or it would give you an
error
yeah so i would have thought i thought
that was going to give you an error so
that's something in the underlying
interpreter that's different right so
the idea of undefined is that the scheme
specification for how scheme's supposed
to work
doesn't say anything about it is it true
is it false
when you add it to 12 what happens it's
just something you shouldn't ever do
um in like
certain versions of lisp they check very
carefully to make sure that you never
use undefined so like this would
probably error and this would error
uh in our version it's it's there but um
its behavior is as as it's described
undefined
so you should never really count on its
behavior being true about scheme it just
happens to be true about the interpreter
that we're using
okay so great question the question is
about this example from lab where you
have a procedure
which takes x y and z if it's the case
that x is true
then it uh returns the value of y
otherwise it returns the value of
z and then we have this example that's
like
if two is greater than one which is
definitely true
then we want five otherwise we want
print seven
and since this is true you're expecting
to get five
which we will and the question is how
come it
also prints seven which it does
when if for example i had just written
this
i wouldn't see this heaven so before you
answer john can you do
if one is greater than two and let's see
what happens this may give us a little
bit of an insight into what's happening
sure
if two is less than one we just see the
seven
and that's true in this case as well
okay
um this is behavior that's entirely
similar to python
the story is that before foo is
called you evaluate all of the
sub-expressions
in order to figure out what to call fu
on
and in as a byproduct of evaluating this
one you print out seven
so before the body is even acknowledged
before the scheme interpreter even
really knows what it's doing
it's already figured out that two is
greater than one
that five is a number and it is already
printed seven
which is much like you'd get if you uh
define foo in python
xyz
oh what have i done this is hard
this is really hard folks by the way
this is going to happen to all of you
you are going to start writing define in
python
so if you wrote something like this
and then you called this foo in python
on two is bigger than one
and five and print seven then you'd see
the seven
because what actually got passed in here
is
true and five and none likewise in here
you got true and five and undefined
so to your question shyvana is that
prince7
in the parameter of the function gets
evaluated and what gets passed in
in python is none and in scheme it's
undefined
right which is why you don't see print
seven twice right and when it evaluates
to false because it's undefined and
undefined doesn't do anything
yeah good question so the question is
how do you evaluate some
expression that has been quoted
if i have a unquoted expression it will
get evaluated automatically
if i quote the same thing then it has
not gotten evaluated
at this point really the only way to
evaluate it
is to call the special built-in
eval procedure which takes in some code
represented as a scheme list and tells
you what would happen
if you evaluated it you might think that
this is like a really complicated thing
like a function
that can just evaluate any expression
but in fact
that's already built into the
interpreter anyway that's exactly what
it does is it evaluates expressions so
it's just triggering that ability that
the interpreter already has
to treat whatever value is the result of
of evaluating this part as an expression
now it might be that you wrote something
that's not
legal like if i try to evaluate one two
three it's going to tell me
int is not callable and if i build a
list
one two three let's say i build it like
this not without quotation
and i say oh i want to evaluate that
let's just pretend it's code
well it will pretend it's code this code
and it will give you the same error that
you would have gotten if you had tried
to call one on two and three
so um yeah it's eval
is a way of taking some
piece of data and pretending it's code
and evaluating it
and that will either work out or it
won't depending on what the data is
a follow-up question was whether you can
evaluate using a comma
yeah so i think this question is about
quasi quotation
if you start your quote with this
backtick instead of the apostrophe
then you are allowed to evaluate
some parts of it along the way
so if instead i didn't have this
unquote i would have gotten this nested
structure but with the unquote
it just says well you know don't
evaluate the whole thing but evaluate
this part
and you know i could have done this the
long way i could have said i want to
build a list
where the first element is one the
second element is the result of
evaluating
plus one one and the third element is
three
so it's not like quasi quotation is
giving me any special power
it's just um it's allowing me to
quote something most of the way but then
have some parts be evaluated
and by the way if scheme is making sense
on the quotation part
you should not worry at all like this is
just something like minor detail
which leads to some cool examples but
mostly you should worry about just
quoting
and what that means and or even better
at this stage just make sure you get
like defined and if
making sense and then and then you're
kind of on track
yeah so the question is can you perform
any kind of non-local assignment
in scheme you know we have this uh
example of a
withdrawal
function so here's a withdrawal
procedure which has some balance
oh no i think it was called make
withdraw with the starting balance
and what this did was define a
withdrawal function
which took in some amount that you want
to withdraw
and let's just pretend that there's
always enough money
what this was supposed to do was change
the balance and then return the balance
how do you do that
well there are parts of scheme that we
will not teach you in this course
because you know we i kind of want to
teach you enough
schemes so that you get the sense that
you could learn the rest if you wanted
to
but not so much that it takes the rest
of the semester so
um so we've kind of picked and chosen
and we
chose not to include non-local
assignment but um
it does exist it's called set so if you
really wanted to change balance to be
the result
of subtracting balance by amount you
could do it
and then you could return the balance
and then you could with turn
withdraw and then i think we should be
able to withdraw stuff
so if i define my account
as uh well maybe we'll call it a
as make withdraw and i start with ten
dollars
and then i would draw two dollars then i
have eight left and if i draw
you know you can work your way down so
anyway you do need this uh
other special form that we haven't
talked about called set in order to make
non-local assignments
i remember remembering right john i
remember when i first learned scheme
many many years ago
there was some controversy around set
there's people who think you shouldn't
use it is that am i remembering right
so um you're right
it's the same controversy that we kind
of talked about earlier in the course
of the consequence of mutation
is that you lose this notion of what's
called referential transparency which is
basically like
things are easy to analyze because if
you ever have a block of code
you could just pretend that whole block
is replaced by its value
and you get the same answer and this
notion of substitution where you can
like look at some complicated piece of
code you're like oh well this thing
you know that evaluates to the list one
two three and you don't have to think
about whether it changes the environment
in any way
is really nice for trying to for a human
trying to understand
their own program and so if you never
use set
then you can do this forever you can
just think about
any expression is substitutable by its
value now this is not true if you start
setting things because there's a
side effect so you know
a lot of scheme code can be written with
no side effects at all
the fact that we never do any kind of
assignment anywhere um
except for defining some procedures and
everything is done with recursion
means that it's rare that you reassign
anything ever
and so that the goal there is just to
preserve this notion of referential
transparency so that you can think about
your program more easily yeah
good yeah so the question is do you need
to know all the different notions of
equality
and uh memorize them in advance
or will we kind of uh tell you when you
need to know
and it will be my goal to tell you when
you need to know
in fact i don't always remember there's
like a number equality and there's an
identity check and then there's like uh
some kind of thing where if you ask if
two lists are equal then it will tell
you that they
are uh even if they were built in
different ways
to uh yeah okay so anyway there's a
bunch of different equals
and no i don't think you need to know
the difference between all of them
but if you want to know like this is
like is
this is like nothing that exists in
python
because it only works for numbers this
is this is a lot like the equal sign
yeah in in python i think that
just like uh this will check okay so
yeah this will check whether two things
are like generally equal
just like in python 2 equals 2
is true and also a list containing 2 and
a list containing 2
is true so um yeah this is usually the
one you want
but if you want to check for is it looks
like that and this is some like weird
thing that only works with numbers
but no you don't need to know it yeah
and i'm going to just reiterate what
john's going to say is we're not going
to teach you the full-blown scheme
programming language it's really just
enough to to get you going and then
the rest when when and if you want to
learn it will will come
but you definitely need to know how like
define works and
lambda works and um you know
just a handful of like basic arithmetic
functions
we usually feed those to you if you're
ever like doing a
homework or an exam we'll say like oh by
the way there's a
zero procedure that checks where there's
something zero
but also this manipulation is something
you're meant to know so car and cutter
and cons and list
and null and that kind of thing this by
the way is the best part of scheme is
you get to say car and cutter all the
time that's my favorite part of the