sixty one eight lecture No.11
announcements
thanks for recording yourself taking midterm one
if you have not yet been contacted
about saving your midterm one recording
you can delete it
if you had trouble making
the recording in the first place
we do have your notes about that
and that's okay
there will be no penalty
and we will try to improve the process
for future exams
most people had no problem making a recording
but the ones that did found it very frustrating
and I'm sorry for that
we'll try to figure out how to make it better
homework two is due on Thursday
and next week the cats project is due on Friday
you can get an early submission bonus point
for submitting the project on Thursday
and if you want the checkpoint which is one point
to make sure that you're tracking toward
the solution at an efficient rate
you need to complete the first part of the project by
Tuesday this project includes course topics
including today's lecture
as well as everything earlier in the course
and what is the cats project
well it's something that tests your typing speed
there's a command line interface and a web interface
and your code has to compute the accuracy and the speed
of whatever is typed
so let's try it
what a mess
look I made mistakes
my accuracy was only 87.5%
wouldn't it be nice
if it could correct my mistakes as I type
uh huh will enable auto correct
now as I type if I make a mistake like having
then it's going to try to correct it for me
it doesn't actually look at what you're trying to type
it just looks at
what you've typed so far in order to guess
about what you should have typed instead
up to
that point all you can see
my accuracy
is much better now that I have auto correct on
if I type a real word like wit
then it's not going to correct that
but if I type various
non words
then it will try to guess what word I meant to take
oh and even corrected that one
so that's the cats project
hope you enjoy it
you'll use some recursion
some containers
and some data abstraction to implement that program
data abstraction
a new method of abstraction
here we go
so most values are compound values
in the sense that they combine
different objects together
in order to create some object with multiple parts
such as a date which has a year
a month and a day all combined together into one thing
or a geographic position
would have a latitude and a longitude
an abstract dated type
lets us manipulate compound objects as units
that's a form of abstraction
what it does
is it allows us to isolate two parts of any program
that uses data
we want to separate how data are represented
and how data are manipulated
by doing this
we separate good concerns within our program
among two different areas
and we can change one without affecting the other
so data abstraction is a methodology
by which functions enforce an abstraction bay area
between representation of data and the use of that data
now
all programmers work with compound data at some point
but only great programmers embrace data abstraction
in order to make their programs more modular
and you too will be a great programmer very soon
let's take a look at an example
rational numbers
and we'll see what we mean by data abstraction
so a rational number can be expressed
as numerator divided by a denominator
where both numerator and denominators are integers
and since we can represent integers exactly
this gives us an exact representation of fractions
so a pair of integers lets us tell you exactly what a
fraction we have
such as one divided by three
but as soon as we actually divide one by three
then we'll get back a float
which is not an exact representation
but a finite approximation of it
through a binary expansion
so
we want to separate the numerator and the denominator
not divide one by the other
but instead have a compound data type
so we assume that we can compose
decompose rational numbers as follows
we have a function rational which takes
n and d enumerator and a denominator
which are integers
and returns a compound data type a rational number x
we have another function
numer x
which returns the numerator of a rational number x
and likewise we have a d nom
x function which returns to the denominator
so we have a way of combining together
enumerator and a denominator
and then we have a way of selecting those two parts
this is called a constructor
it builds a new
value which is an instance from an abstract data type
and then these are selectors
which are the functions that get back
those parts of the whole rational number
what we can do then
is
we can start writing other functions that manipulate
rational numbers
such as adding them together or multiplying them
let's take a look
so just to refresh your memory
if we want to multiply three halves and three fists
we get nine tenths
and why is that
well the general formula for multiplying together
two rational numbers
is that the numerator
of the result
is the product of the numerators of the first
in the second
and the denominator is the product of the denominators
adding together
two rational numbers is slightly more complicated
three halfs plus three fist gives you 21 tenths
how do we get that
while in general if we have two rational numbers
then we multiply the numerator of the first
by the denominator of the second
add that through the numerator of the second
time is the denominator of the first
and that's our new numerator
and our new denominator is the product
of the denominators
of the first and 2nd rational number
that we're adding together
so now we have formulas for how to multiply
and add rational numbers
how do we write code that does that
we will write it
in terms of our constructor and selectors
so here's a function which multiplies together
two rational numbers x and y
it returns a new rational number
the numerator
of which is the product of
the numerators of the inputs
and the denominator is the product of the denominators
of the inputs
just like our formula says
we see that we've used the constructor
to create a new rational number
and we've used the selectors to select out the parts
of xmy that we need in order to complete this formula
likewise we can write a function that adds together
two rational numbers
we give names to their numerator and denominator
because we use those multiple times
in our expression
and then we return a rational
which follows the formula on the right
one more function lets us
really work with rational numbers
and that is equal rational which returns true
if x and y are the same number
now we can't just compare their parts
because one half is the same rational number as
two fourths
so in order to resolve whether x and y are equal
we multiply the numerator of the first
by the denominator of the second
and check and see if that's equal to
the numerator of the second
times the denominator of the third
first
hung twister
okay so what you see here
is that we've defined
all of the ways in which we will manipulate
rational numbers
in terms of three functions
and these functions implement an abstract data type
for rational numbers
what that means is
all of our manipulation of the numbers is written in
terms of these functions
we haven't even defined these functions yet
but since we know that these are the tools we use
to access the parts of rational numbers
or create new rational numbers
we can write functions in terms of these
and then implement them later
a pair consists of two values that are joined together
bundled together in such a way that you can treat them
as a unit as a whole
even though there are two parts
now there's lots of different ways to represent a
pair of things
but we're going to use a built in
data type first called the list
so I can write the line of code
pair equals open bracket one coma two close bracket
and what we have here is what's called a list literal
which creates a new list that contains one and two
as two values
and as we have two values in the list
we'll color the pair
and when I display this pair
I see its contents written just like the literal
so a list literal has a comma
separated expression in brackets
once I have a list
which is the value of a list literal
I can access the elements within the list
through what's called unpecking that list
into different values
so by saying x comma y equals pair
I'll bind x to the zero element and y
to the first element
after which
if I look at what x is bound to lc one and what
y is bound to lc two
that's because that's the contents
of the list that I've created
so we now have a way to bundle together
values and split them apart again
this is called unpacking a list
another way to access the elements of a list
is to the element selection operator
which again uses square brackets
so these square brackets are different from this one
although they're certainly related
but this is just square brackets without anything
before it whereas this has some expression before it
so when you have square brackets after an expression
that involves selecting an element from
the value which is to the left of the brackets
so pair is a list value and its zero th element is one
its first element is two
so element selection using the selection operator is
another way to access the elements in a list
there's also a function that does the same thing
as we've seen many times over in python
each operator has some function
most of which are within the module called operator
so the element selection operator is called get item
all one word
it's okay to say it fast because it's all one word
get item pair zero
gives me
the zero element of the pair list and that's what
get item pair one will give me the value two
this is an element selection function
or the get item function
okay we now have a basic introduction to what lists are
and so far we've used them
to create pairs
and why is that useful
well a rational number is a pair of integers
the numerator and the denominator
so here's a definition of the constructor
of the abstract data type for rational numbers
it's a function
that takes in the numerator and denominator
and we need
some way of representing of that pair of things
we'll use a list
so
we construct a rational number that represents n over d
just by returning the list of n come a d
so this constructs a list and the list
we're using as a rational number
now this can contain anything
they don't necessarily just contain integers
but we're using it to represent a rational number
in which both n amp d should be integers
now how do we get the numerator out
assuming that x is what was created
by the rational constructor
while we just access the zero of element
and that the nominator is element that index one
so we're going to select an item from a list here
in order to implement
what we want which is selecting
the denominator of a rational number
so let me show you the first example of why
data abstraction can be useful
recall that we implemented multiplication
among rational numbers
and here's an example three halves times five thirds
what do you get
well you multiply the numerators together to get 15
you multiply the denominators together to get six
and the answer is not 21th but five haves
and why is that
when we had 15 6 but
those were not relatively prime integers
we can reduce the fraction
to lowest terms
by multiplying both the numerator and the denominator
by one third
and that gives us an equivalent fraction five halves
that's simpler
now the reason
we do this is in order to keep the integers small
so that they're easier to look at and understand
what about two fists plus 11th
well we can apply the same procedure we had before
for adding together
rational numbers
and we'll get one half
now why is it one half
it's because through the cross multiplying in addition
we got twenty five over fifty
and so there's the 20 there's the five
we add those together to get twenty five
fifty is five times 10
but then we can reduce that
to lowest terms
by multiplying both the numerator and denominator
by one over twenty five
leaving us with one half
so how would we change our implementation to do that
well here's the idea
addition and multiplication
actually were correct in the first place
what was wrong
was our definition of rational
a rational number should be something that's
always represented in
lowest terms or with two relatively prime integers
so one thing I can do is import a function
that computes the greatest
common devisor
in a previous lecture
I showed you how to write a function that does this
but it also happens to be built into python
and then what I'm going to do is redefine
the rational constructor
to take any numerator in any denominator
and then constructs a rational number that represents
n over d but does it in a way
such that
the numerator and denominator that are accessed later
are always relatively prime
which you can achieve
by computing the greatest common devisor
of both the numerator and the denominator
that's three in this case or 25 in this case
and then returning a pair
that contains
the numerator and denominator
each divided by the greatest comment devisor
so that they're guaranteed to be relatively prime
and we use integer division here because we know
that g evenly divides both n and d
that's the property of a greatest common devisor
is it's the devizer
it evenly divides those numbers
okay so we computed the greatest common devisor
we changed the constructor
we don't have to make any changes to add rational or mo
rational or print or anything like that
because we've been using data abstraction
which means that everything
was defined in terms of this constructor
so changing this constructor
changes the behavior of all the other functions as well
and that's a good thing
abstraction barriers
separate different parts of a program
so that each part only needs to know so much
about the rest of the program
now these separations are
important because
they allow you to make changes
to one part of your program
and have other parts take advantage of those changes
without breaking in any way
or creating in consistencies
so let's talk about the abstraction barriers
in the development of a rational arithmetic system
that we've been working on for this lecture
so there's a part of the program
that uses rational numbers to perform computation
so I actually want to know
what's one half times one third
in those cases
we're actually treating rationals as whole data values
they just represent some number
we don't care how
we just want to know
what it happens when you multiply
these things together
and in order to do that
we use certain functions that are part
of the data abstraction
for rational numbers
add rational mole rational rationals are equal etc
are all things that take in
rational numbers and do things with them
perhaps returning new ones
but using these
functions doesn't mean you need to know much at all
about how rational numbers are represented
in a next layer down
where we look at the implementation
instead of just the use
of these arithmetic operators
we find parts of the program that create rationals
or implement rational operations
and they treat
rationals as a numerator and a denominator
paired together
now they may
not need to know exactly how that pairing happens
but they do need to know that a rational number
has a numerator and a denominator
these two things can be selected
and they need to know that
you create a new rational number
by combining a numerator and a denominator together
and these all happened
using the functions called rational
numer and dina
so I had drew a really thick line right there
to represent an abstraction barrier
that barrier says anything
that's using rational numbers to perform computation
should only do it in terms of these functions
and should not be using functions of a different layer
in this way the programs that we write
make as few assumptions as possible
about exactly what representations were using
and instead obey the abstraction that has been set out
by the programmer
so what if we go one layer down from that
well there are parts of the program
that implement selectors and constructors for rationals
and those implementations of rational numer and dinam
treat rational numbers as two element lists
so they do
understand their whole data values
that they're consisting of numerators and denominators
and then we have a further detail
that the numerator and denominator
are glued together using a list
so for this we use list literals and element selection
and again there's an abstraction barrier
if we're in the business of
creating rationals or implementing rational operations
we shouldn't need to know
that we're using lists under the hood
and we shouldn't cross this abstraction barrier
and use a list literal or element selection directly
instead
if we write our programs in terms of just rational
numer and dinom
then changes to those functions later
we'll be propagated throughout our program
and we could for instance
start expressing every fraction in lowest terms
now is that it
well actually
there are many layers of abstraction in a program
and there is stuff that's even
lower detail than what we've seen so far
so this are somehow implemented in the python language
we don't really need to know exactly
how that implementation works
all we need to know is that this can be created
with list literals
and taken apart using element selection
and so any place
where we are implementing selectors and constructors
for rationals
shouldn't worry about the implementation of lists
it should just know that list can be created
and selected from
so each big line is an abstraction barrier
and you should know that when you're writing
one part of a large program
that it should use the level abstraction
appropriate to what you're trying to do
and the higher you stay up
without crossing of these boundaries
the easier it will be to change your program
in the future
so let's look at an example
of violating abstraction barriers
so I've said add rational one two and one four
so a half plus a four should give me three force
and under the code we've written
this will work just fine
I have a definition of dividing a rational
which returns a list
of whatever is the zero
element of x times the first element of y
and then we have the first element of x
and the zero element of y
again in our current implementation this will work
no errors will be raised
and yet we've done something terribly wrong
we violated abstraction barriers
so for instance here
we've assumed in our use of ad rational
that a rational is represented as a list of
two integers
which means if we went and changed
the rational constructor
it wouldn't be used in this block of coat
because I didn't actually call rational here
so I did not use constructors
is that so bad
well it's pretty bad
but it gets really bad when you see that it happened
twice in a row
okay now I'm getting angry
that's unacceptable that you would
just violate abstraction
barriers like that
I hope we're done
oh oh down here we're dividing rational numbers
which should
treat rationals as numerators and denominators
but not necessarily assume that their lists
so instead of using the
numer selector function
instead I've used
the element selection that works for lists
thereby assuming that x is a list
instead of saying oh
it's something that has a numerator in a denominator
but I don't know exactly what it is
so
I've gone down to too low of the level
and oh look
I did that four times
and then I returned a rational number
but again
I did not use the constructor called rational to do it
this is not okay
this you know
if I saw somebody's computer with this code on it
I think I would honestly just light it on fire
and just watch it burn
because
code that violates obstruction barriers should burn
the purpose of maintaining abstraction barriers
is so that you can change your data representation
without having to rewrite your entire program
let's poke a little bit deeper
into this idea of data representation
what does data
what does it mean
for something to represent a rational number
well we need to guarantee
that the constructor and selector functions
work together
to specify the right behavior
you don't have a representation of a rational number
unless it behaves like a rational number
a behavior condition would read something like
if we construct rational number x
from numerator n and denominator d
then it should be the case that numer x divided by
nom x equals n divided by d
here we relate the constructor called on nnnd
to the selectors and an operation between them
data abstraction uses selectors and
constructors to define behavior
that's the whole idea of data abstraction
if the behavior conditions are met
then the representation is valid
so the key underlying idea
related to data abstraction is that you can recognize
what sort of data something is
by its behavior
not necessarily
by how you constructed it or how you implemented
the constructor and selectors
so let's look back at our example
we have add mull
on an equality measurement
and a way of printing rational numbers
all of this doesn't assume anything
about the representation itself
only that the constructor and selectors exist
the constructor and selectors
below this abstraction barrier
are implementing rational numbers in terms of lists
so it's the case that I can say x and y
are the rational number one two
and the rational No.3 eighths
I should say one half and three eights
so what happens when I print
the result of multiplying together x and y
I got three over sixteen
it should be the case that I can
change my representation
and all of this will still work
so here we go
instead of using a list to couple together n and d
into one thing
we're going to use a function
we're going to find a function called select
which takes in
some name
if that name is n
then it's going to return the numerator
otherwise if the name is d
it will return
the denominator
and what else
well we're not going to worry about those other cases
we'll just return the select function
from the rational function
now it must be the case that the constructor
and the selectors
are complements of each other
that when you construct something
with the rational constructor
you can then select its numerator
using the numer function
so if x is the result of calling rational
then it's a select function
which I can call on n to get the numerator
and likewise I'd call x on d to get the denominator
let's try our example again
I set x and y to be one half and three eighths
I then printed the result of multiplying
x and y together
and I got three sixteenths
did we really change anything
well certainly we did because x is now a function
so that's a change in representation
that led to another
valid representation of rational numbers
that works
just as well with our old code as what we had before
but uses an entirely different mechanism
to keep track of the numerator and the denominator
and notice that we did this with just functions
we didn't actually need that built in list
data type at all
so what exactly happened when we implemented
rational numbers as functions
when we defined the constructor and selectors
and it was this function
the select function
that represented the rational number
it was returned by the constructor
which was a higher order function
and the selector
just called the function that resulted
from calling rational
in order to get the numerator back
by defining a function within another function
we were able to refer to the n and the d
in the enclosing scope
and so this select function that we returned
did have carrying with it
the numerator and denominator
that we wanted to access later
as part of its parent frame
so let's say a simpler example
we set x equal to rational three eighths
and then we ask for the numerator of x
which should be three
the environment diagram looks like this
rational numeran d nam are defined
and then we call rational on three and eight
which creates a select function whose parent
is the f one frame
where n and d are bound
that's returned and bound to x
x equals rational three eights
once we have x we can ask for its numerator
which creates a new frame in which
x is bound to the select function
the body of numer
says that we're supposed to call x on n
so that's exactly what happens in this
3rd frame f three
where name is bound to n
the body of select is executed
name is n and so it returns it
looking here we see that the name n is not defined
but if we look in the parent f one
n is bound to three and so that's what's returned
I've already extolled the virtues of sequences
but there are other
things fundamental to computation as well
and one of them is called a dictionary
and a dictionary allows you to associate values with
keys
so to create a dictionary you use curly braces
and what you do is you associate with some key
in this case I
a value in this case one
and by separating by commas I can associate
multiple different
values with different keys
so right here
I've described part of the roman numeral system
which is an association between
capital letters and numbers
now I evaluated this expression
it created a dictionary for me
notice something wild happened
this one looks different from this one
and there's a reason for that
dictionaries don't have an order inherently
they establish a relationship between x and x
and v and 5
but they don't establish any fixed relationship between
v and x
and so
pythons free to shuffle them around however it chooses
okay so let's call this numerals
and numerals is this association
and if I select an element
what I'm going to pass in instead of an index is a key
at which point
I can get the value associated with that key
now I cannot go the other way around
10 is not a key it's a value
okay
so now we know the basic functionality of dictionaries
you create them with a dictionary literal
which separates by commas
key value pairs that are separated by colons
and then using element selection you can select a key
and it will give you back to value
there are a few more things you can do
you can look at all the keys
and these are the dictionary keys xv and I
and you can look at all the values
you can also look at all the items
and those are the key value pairs
now if you had this list right here
of items
you could actually build a dictionary out of it
just by calling the dict constructor
at which point you could look up
x in there and it would give you tit
now you can ask python if a particular key is in a
dictionary
so x is in there
and x ray is not
if you want to get out the value for a key
but you're not sure it's there
and you want to supply a default instead
you can use the get method
so if I get x
with a default of zero
it will give me 10 because x has a value
but if I get x ray
it will give me zero the default
two more things that I'll show you
there's an expression called a dictionary comprehension
which is like a list comprehension
I won't go through the details of its execution
procedure
but I will show you how it works
so let's say I want to associate x with
x squared for some x in a range
let's say the range up to 10
I've just created a dictionary
where the keys are the elements in range 10
and the values are that number square
so if I call this squares
and I look up the square of seven
I should get 49
now there are some restrictions on dictionaries
you can't have the same key twice
so if you do
it will just throw out one of your elements
and that's part of the design of what dictionaries are
you get one value per key
now instead of having the same key twice
it's fine if I have
a sequence of multiple values for a given key
because this is really just one value
it's a sequence
it contains other values with it
however
I'm not allowed to use lists or dictionaries as keys
so I can't write the list containing one
is associated with two
and I'll get this error unhashable type
I wish I could tell you exactly what that means
but I'm not allowed
because I have to leave some topics
for future classes
like 61 b
so just accept that you can't put list's keys
you cannot put other dictionaries's keys
and that's just a constraint of the language
so dictionaries associate values with keys
they're unordered
so don't rely on the order that you put things in
because it will not be maintained
keys cannot be list or dictionaries
or any mutable type in the language
we'll talk about what that means soon
two keys cannot be equal
because you can only have a key once
this first restriction is tied
to how dictionaries are implemented
and the second one is part of the
design of what a dictionary is supposed to do
like I said
if you want to associate multiple values with a key
put them all on a sequence