sixty one eight lecture No.32
announcements
lab 12 is do Tuesday
but please do it Monday
because you have other things do Tuesday
a checkpoint for the scheme project
we will have
lab parties from three to four and seven to eight
on Monday
which means Monday is the best day to finish the lab
homework eight is do Thursday
we've shortened it relative to its normal length
because there's a lot going on this week
scheme project is do next Tuesday
but you could finish it this week
and then you'd have all next week off
checkpoint one is due Tuesday
checkpoint two is due Friday
when you've gotten through checkpoint two
you've finished most of the project
and if you finish the whole thing by Monday
of next week
you'll get an early submission bonus point
we have extra staff
in office hours this week and next Monday
so hopefully you won't have to wait too long
if you get stuck
but the best way to make
sure that you get helped in a timely manner
is to make progress every day
instead of leaving everything to the last minute
this is one of the busiest weeks in the whole semester
but once you get through it
you'll have a nice thanksgiving break
there's one more thing we're releasing today
which is completely optional
the scheme recursive art contest
the scheme recruits of art contest is one of my
favorite parts of the course
it's your chance to use your scheme interpreter
to draw something cool
that can be related to 61 a or not
but should involve recursion of some kind
you'll use the same drawing
primitive procedures that we use
to draw sir pinsky's triangle
and people have come up with some really wonderful
things in the past
for example
here was a winner in two thousand and twelve
in two thousand thirteen
someone figured out how to draw in three d
and since then sometimes three day drawings have won
but sometimes they haven't
here was the winner in 2015
and in 2018
some entries are elaborate
some are less so
and one of the best outcomes of the contest
is not the winner
but the gallery of all the entries
the way we determine the winner
is to take your entry and everybody else's
and put them in a web page and let the students vote
so if you're in this course
and you don't want to create art
you can still critique art
by voting for your favorite entries
to the scheme recursive art contest
and no piece of art is complete without a description
so when you make your entry
you're also allowed to submit a haiku describing it
and that will be published
along with the entry and its title
in the scheme gallery that we create
after the entry submission deadline
which is the Monday after thanksgiving
November 30
so if you're looking for something to do
feel free to create some art
if you don't that's okay too
you'll get to look at your peers art
which often is quite cool
this is completely optional
there is a poultry amount of extra credit given
to the winners
but don't do it for the extra credit
do it for the sake of art
okay and back to our regularly scheduled programming
sequel today we learn about joining tables together
which is an important fundamental operation in sequel
and it's the reason
that you might want to use a database
to represent your data
instead of just a long list for example
so far we've been projecting just one table
but we can do much more powerful operations
by joining tables together
now if you ask someone what a join is among two tables
they may tell you which kind of join
there are so many
and in fact
database people have been thinking about this problem
so long
that they have invented many different kinds of joints
and some ways of joining two tables together
I have multiple names
so it's complicated
but we're just going to focus on one fundamental type
two tables a and b are joined
using a comma
two
yield all combinations of a ro from a and a ro from b
this is the fundamental idea of what it means
to join two tables together
is to list all the pairs of rose
so back to dogs
when lead a second table
in order to do anything interesting
let's create a table called dogs
that has a name for each dog
and what kind of fur it has
abraham has long fur
barack has short fur
which will indicate using dots instead of dashes
clinton has long fur delano has long fur
eisenhower has short fur
filmore has curly fur
grover has short fur and herbert also has curly fur
now this table called dogs
just declares a relationship between each dog
and its fur
what about all that information
of whose parent was whose
well that's in a separate table
so the full data set describes this tree structure
which gives the parent of each dog and the fur
but since they're in two separate tables
we need to join that information together
let's say I want to select the parents
of curly furred dogs
f and h are the curly ones
their parents are eisenhower and delano
the following select statement will pull those two out
select the parent from parents joined with dogs
where the child equals name and the fur equals curly
that's the join
what's going on in the wear claws
while fur equals curly is straightforward
it's matching
combinations of a row from a and a row from b
that have fur as curly
which we'll give them this
this film or curly row and this herbert curly row
child equals name
is a relationship
between the row that we've chosen
from parents and the row we've chosen from dogs
so this says that the name
that's given in the dogs table
needs to be the same as the child in the parents table
now how do we know
which of these names came from which table
right now will just assume that they're unambiguous
that every column name is different
across different tables
will deal with ambiguity in a minute
1st let's just play around with what we have
so I've now put
the sequel statements for defining dogs and parents
into a file called dogs sequel
I can start sequel light
and using the in it flag
tell it
to execute all the statements in dogs doubt sequel
so it's loaded those resources
which means I can select
star from dogs and get all the different options
now if I select all of the columns
from parents comma dogs
that's a join over these two tables
and we'll see many results
these results are all the pairs of rows
so there was an abraham barack row
and an abraham long row
here they are
there's also an abraham clinton row
paired with a delano long row
now you might think
these have nothing to do with each other
all it is is exhaustively computing all pairs of rows
it's up to the wear claws to define
some relationship between them
so let's start using a wear claws
select from parents comma dogs
where
let's relate the times when
the dog's name is the same as the child
so we write just child equals name
in order to get those cases
okay we still have four columns
two columns from the parents two columns from the dogs
but it's always the case that the child
and the name
column have the same value
so abraham as barack's parent and barack has short fur
della know is herbert's parent
and herbert has curly fur
if we add to our wear
by saying and for equals curly
we'll restrict ourselves to only
the two rows that were interested in
among the join of parents and dogs
now we have to decide how to project these rows
to get only what we want
and what we said we wanted was not all of the rows
but instead just the parents of the curly dogs
which are eisenhower and delano
then we're done
now we'll have to deal with the interesting case when
two different tables have the same column name
and we want to be able to pick out
one column in one particular table
for that we have aliases and dot expressions
we can even join a table with itself
two tables may share a column name in general
and certainly a
tables shares the same column names with itself
dot expressions and aliases help disambiguate
so here's the structure of our select statement
select columns from table where condition
order by some order
table is a comma separated list of table names
and also tell you that they have optional aliases
so if I want to select all the pairs of siblings
like barack and clinton here are siblings
because they have the same parent abraham
I would write the following select statement
select
a dot child as first b dot child as 2nd
from parents as a parent says b
where a dot parent is the same as b dot parent
and a dot child is less than b dot child
here we're not only joining parents with parents
but we're also giving an alias to this parents as a
and this parents as b
now what does this mean
to join a table with itself and give aliases
what's going on here
is we're looking at all pairs of rows in parents
and that's important
because if we want to pick out
barack and clinton together
we're given only a row with abraham barack
and another row with abraham clinton
so if we want to couple these together somehow
we need to consider
both of those rows at the same time
now the as a and as b
are the aliases were giving to these tables
in order to refer to them separately
the last piece of the puzzle is dot expressions
where you say
which table you're getting this row from
and then dot and then the column name in that table
so a is an alias for the
first parents table which has a child
and what we're doing here
is creating a new column in the output called first
where its contents is the child from a
and the second column
its contents is the child from b
we join together
parents with parents in order to get all
pairs of parents
and the wareclaws says
that in the first parents row
I want the parent be equal
to the parent in the second parents row
and that makes sure that we only get together
a joined row that has abraham as the parent both times
what about this part
a dot child is less than b dot child
well if the children were equal
then you wouldn't have siblings
you just have barack twice
so we want them to be unequal
if we just said unequal then we'd get repeats
I would say well
barak is the sibling of clinton
and clinton is the sibling of barak
but by putting an ordering here
we'll only get result rose
where the alphabetically earlier sibling comes first
and the one later in the alphabet comes 2nd
so here's the result table
barak and clinton are siblings
abraham and delano are siblings
abraham and grover are siblings
and delano and grover are siblings as well
any time you join a table with itself
you're going to need to use aliases
and dot expressions in order to specify
which of the rows you're talking about
in the joined row
those sub rows within there
are either from the parents a
or the parents b
and you want to know which
child column or which parent column
you want to compare
you can even join multiple tables together
and when you join together multiple tables
you get all
possible combinations
of a row from each table that you're joining
so let's get another table
in the mix
a grandparents table
here's what it says
select a's parent
and b's child
where a and b
are both rows from different parents tables
joined together
there joined with the restriction that the parent in b
is the child in a
now that defines a grand parent
and we'll call the columns in the resulting table
the grand dog and the grand pup
how does this work
well from parents will get eisenhower fillmore
and from the other parents will get filmmore abraham
we'll find that filmore equals filmore
and therefore
that eisenhower is the grand dog
and abraham is the grand pup
now this is just a join on two tables
but let's say we want to select all grandparents
that have the same fur
as their grandchildren
take a minute to think about how you would do that
and in particular
which tables do you need to join together
in order to get that result
and the answer should be that filmore
is the grandparent of herbert
and eisenhower is the grandparent of grover
here's a select statement that will do the work
select the grand dog the grandparent
from three different tables joined together
the grand's parents table
the dogs table and the dogs table again
now why do we need so many tables
well we need to talk about the fur
of the grand dog and the fur of the grand pup
to make sure they're the same
since we have dogs twice we need to alias them
I have alias to them as c and d
the grand dog is c dot name
meaning we're pulling out the row from c
that matches the grand dog
the grand pup is d dot name
meaning we're pulling out the row from d
a separate table
where it matches the grand pup
and then we make sure that they have the same fur
so let's try it out
well you'd said we were going to create a table
grandparents as
what you get when you select
a dot parent and b dot child
from the join of parents as a
and parents as b
where it's the case
that the child of the grandfather
is the same as the parent of the grandchild
let's see how we're doing so far
if I want to select
the grand pups
from the grandparents table
where
it's the case that the grand dog is eisenhower
we should get all of eisenhower's grandchildren
which are all of film wars children
abraham delano and grover
so far so good
next we wanted to join three tables together
which involves selecting the grand dog from
the first table is the grandparents table
the second is the dogs
and the third is more dogs
and the reason why we joined all three together
is so that we could express
that the fur was the same
four
a dog named grand dog
and another dog
named the grand pup
loading resources will execute this select statement
and tell us that eisenhower and filmore
are the only two dogs
that are grandparents of a grand pup
with the same fur
numerical expressions in sequel
are very similar to numerical expressions in python
expressions can contain
function calls to built in functions
they can also use arithmetic operators
such as plus and minus and times
now these can occur in any expression
within a select statement
there's a wear expression
there's an order by expression
and within the columns description
which is a comma separated list
there are expressions there as well
and in all of these expressions you can
add subtract multiply etc
you can take the absolute value or round number
or negate it you can compare different values together
one thing to note
is that there are two different
ways of expressing not equals and sequel
one looks like that one looks like that
equality is expressed with a single equals
and why not
there's no notion of assignment in what we're doing
so the single equals isn't used for anything else
just to get warmed up for the day
let's do some examples
so let's say I have a table of cities
with their latitude
longitude and name
berkeley Cambridge Minneapolis san diego Miami
and the north pole isn't really a city
but we'll go with it anyway
if I want I can say select
name from cities
where the latitude is greater than or equal to 43
now 43 is pretty northern
northern
than that you start getting to pretty cold places
so if we wanted to give a name
for this select statement
I would probably call it cold
so if I start see quill light
initializing with this file
I have loaded those resources
and I can select name from cold
and find that Minneapolis and the north
pole are both cold
but that's not every place does cold
Chicago is also cold
so I can use a union
in order to get Minneapolis north pole and Chicago
all in one table
now what about arithmetic
well
let's say I want to compute the north south distance
between cities
northern south really matters
because that affects climate
more than eastern west
well I'd say something like create
cable distances as
selecting the names of two cities
let's call this first
and this 2nd and then what we want to select
is some expression that computes
the number of nautical miles
north that you have to go
to get the second city from the first city
there are 60 nautical miles in a degree of latitude
and we have the latitude degrees right here
so I could say 60 times the difference between
b dot latitude
and a latitude
and we'll call that the distance
now we have our column descriptions
but we still have to say
what we're selecting from
we referred to a and b so far
those are different versions of the city's table
will be true you'll have to join with itself
in order to compute the latitude difference among
two different cities
cities as a joined with cities as b
so now let's say I'm in Minneapolis
and I think I want to get somewhere far away from here
I would say select the second
from
distances
where
1st is Minneapolis
and we want to order the results by the distance
so a negative distance will come first
and that means going south as far as possible
people from Minneapolis really like to go to Miami
and san diego
not so much the north pole
so here is an expression that does some sort of
manipulation of numerical values
and that's very typical in a sequel expression
there are also combinations involving string values
string expressions
so string values can be combined to form longer strings
through the concatenation operator
which looks like two vertical bars
so if I want to put together hello comma
and space world
to get hello world
I just write it like that
and this is a very common thing to do
so I've given it the green light
there's also ways to do basic string manipulation
that are built into sequel
they're different from python
and honestly
the language doesn't have the best support
for string manipulation
so let's say you have a table already called freeze
which has hello world in it as a column s
people do write expressions like these
the substring of ass that goes
from position four and has length two
contaminated with the substring of s
that starts at the place in s where you find the first
space plus one and has a length of one
selecting that from the phrase table
gives you one row back
which gets this lndo for the first half and the w
for the second half
if you want to learn more
about these string manipulation functions
of course I recommend that you do so on your own
but I won't go to over the details
because I don't think they should be used as
much as they are
strings can even be used to represent structured values
but doing so is rarely a good idea
so for example
you could think
each row is actually going to represent a linked list
in a table called lists
or I'll have one column for the car
or the first element in the linked list
and in this case is just a string one
and then the cooter column
will have
comma separated elements for the rest of the list
so in this way I'm using a string
but putting in some delimiting character
to try to remind myself
where one element ends and the next one begins
and that's what I mean by using a string to represent
a structured value
is supposed to represent a list with three things in it
and then people would do things like
oh let's get the cotter
by
looking in the kutter
finding the first comma
and then getting the first element there
and that would return me the two from this 2 3 4
so it's certainly possible
to do structured manipulation like this
but typically it's not a good idea
there are certainly better ways
to manipulate data structures
than by trying to put them all inside of a string
in a table in a database
but anyway
let's take a look at combining strings together
I could create a table called nouns
which we'll have dog in it
dog is a noun
how about a cat
and why not a bird
okay now that we have some nouns
we can select a whole sentence
by getting the subject
phrase concatenated with chaste
and concatenated with the object phrase
where are we getting these subjects and objects
well those are just nouns
we'll need to join two nouns together
in order to build up different sentences
you don't want dogs just chasing dogs
we'd like dogs to be chasing cats
maybe we'll
put in a requirement that the subject phrase
is different from the object phrase
let's see what we get
the bird chase the cat
the bird chase the dog
the cat chase the bird the cat chase the dog
the dog chase the bird and the dog chase the cat
but can we build more sentences well sure
we can create a table called annes
which is just
a dog and a cat
we'll get this by selecting from the nouns
as first and nouns a second
and I liked this idea of saying
where we don't want the first phrase to be the same
as the second phrase
now I can make this even more interesting
by selecting not from nouns but from the ends
we can give a name to this column
and then we can run it
to see that the dog of the bird chased the cat
and the dog
the dog and the bird chased the dog and the cat