61 a lecture No.12
announcements
the cats project is due next Friday
but you need to finish phase one by next Tuesday
in order to get the checkpoint
that's there to make sure you're making
progress so that you finish
on time
it's a good idea to finish phase one even sooner than
Tuesday and you can just submit
whatever you have that includes a
completed phase one in order to get credit
you'll get a bonus point for submitting the whole
project by next Thursday
and what are the phases anyway
well in phase one
you measure typing speed and select things to type
in phase ii
you build the autocorrect system that I talked about
in the last announcement video
and in phase iii you build multiplayer
if you want to try out multiplayer before you build it
you can go to our implementation at cats csixtona org
it finds other opponents
by finding other people who are also
trying to play a multiplayer game
and then starting up a multiplayer game
here we go
oh this person's fast
oh
lost by almost 5 seconds
so if you want you could try that out
but more importantly you have to build it
by the way
if you haven't hovered your mouse over this gift yet
I recommend doing so
we have an exam prep session Friday at 200 pm
extra q amp a coming up
recording so far are all stored here
and the last announcement
is that the hog strategy contest is over
and I wanted to say congratulations
actually to everybody
who participated in the hog strategy contest
we had a massive number over 150 entries
which I think is just awesome
the thing that
makes me most happy
is just seeing lots of participation
but since there were rules
we do need to announce a winner
and with first place winning 146 times
there was a five way tie
I don't think this has ever happened before
how could it be that there's a five way tire for first
well actually the submissions were different
but the rule
state that a submission scores a match point each time
it has an expected win rate
strictly above 50 point 0001 %
and these five entries were also
close in their wind rates
that none of them beat another one by this
very small margin
but they were not all the same
the five entries bobby tables anonymous poet
the golden ratio wet app program and blockchain
one or lost against each other
in a very interesting pattern
bobby tables had a win rate above 50%
when playing against the golden ratio
a golden ratio had a win rate above 50% when playing
against the anonymous poet
but the anonymous poet had a win rate above 50% when
playing against
bobby tables
blockchain and anonymous poet
had a win rate of exactly 50% against each other
I think they were effectively the same strategy
whereas all the other ones were different
bobby tables among the top five
won more than half the time against two opponents
and lost more than half the time against two opponents
it was actually only wet app program
that one more than half the time
against more opponents
than it lost but it still
had a lower than fifty percent one rate against
bobby tables
in any case these were the rules
and so none of these entries
scored a match point against any of the other entries
leading to a five way first place ti
congratulations to everybody who is part
of one of those
winning entries
here's the list of folks in reverse alphabetical order
awesome job you all get extra credit points
and if you want to see more
about what happened in the hug contest
you can go to the leaderboard here
so those are all the announcements
now we'll talk about today's content which is trees
trees are one of my favorite topics in this course
when we bring together
what we've learned about containers and data
with what we've learned about recursion
in order to built recursive data
and this is one of the main reasons that we learned
about recursive functions in this course
is to process tree structured data
and today you'll mostly see
trees filled with numbers or strings
but tree structure data appears in
lots of other programs as well
when you're representing a website or an org chart
or a system of government
or anything else that has a hierarchical structure
then you're going to need tree structured data
bucks and pointer notation is a way to represent
lists within our environment diagrams
so the reason why we need a notation is that
sequential data can actually become quite complicated
and that's because of the closure property
a method for combining data values satisfies
this closure property
if it's the case that the result of combination
can itself be combined using the same method
if I can put items within a list
I should be able to take that list
and put it into a list
closure is powerful because it permits us to create
hierarchical structures
hierarchical structures are made up of parts
which themselves are made up of parts
and so on and that is an extremely useful way
to represent all sorts of things in the world
so the important point
here is that list can contain other lists as elements
in addition to anything else
and that means
that we need a way to keep track of
what's inside of what
that's where we use box and pointer notation
lists are represented in environment diagrams
as a row of index labeled adjacent boxes
one per element
each box either contains a permanent value
or points to a compound value
so if I just say pair equals the list one two
I'll write that in my environment diagram
by binding the name pair
to a list that contains one and two
these small numbers in the corner
are just indices of the list
and so since the list has two elements
we see two adjacent boxes
now for a more complex example
nested list is bound to a list that contains a list
a list and another list
and this 3rd list contains lists itself
and within it are all sorts of things even a function
so let's walk through everything that's on the screen
nested list is a three element list
and so we see it bound to three adjacent rectangles
now each element of nested list is actually
another list
and so that's why we see pointers to compound values
lists are compound values
functions or compound values
anything that has multiple parts
is going to be represented using an arrow
to some depiction of that thing
okay so here we see that the elemented index zero
is just a list containing one and two
the element that index one is the empty list
here we see the empty list
and the element that index 3
is its self a list that contains two other lists
and so that's why we see this hierarchical structure
where
this is made up of parts which are made up of parts
the primitive values three
false and none can be written directly into the box
so can for the function
we write as we've always written functions before
and we use a small arrow to say that it's contained
as this element at index one
of the list that's within this list
that's within this list
slicing is an operation that you can perform
on sequences such as lists and ranges
let's say I have a sequence already 3 5 7 9 11
and what I'd like to get out
is just the five and the seven
so these are elements at index one and two
well I could
get myself the indices one and two
and then I could use that in a list comprehension
I want odds I
for I in range 1 2 3
and remember
range one to three gives me one and two but not three
okay
so that's one way to select out the five and the seven
a sub list of this list
slicing is a notation for doing this more compactly
it does the same thing but without you typing so much
you just write odds
and then in square brackets you say
I want to go from one to three
so it has the same rules as ranges
the indices include the lower bound
but exclude the upper bound
now there's some additional flexibility
just like if you leave out
one of the boundaries in a range
if you leave out the beginning number
it's going to start
from the very beginning of the list
so odds up to three gives me indice zero one and two
I can also leave out the end
and it will go all the way to the end
so if I want to start at index one
then I'll skip the three at index zero
and get all of five
seven nine and eleven
and you can even skip the beginning and the end
and you get back
all of the elements in the original list
so these square brackets for the colon inside
are called a slicing operator
slicing always creates new values
so here are some examples I have digits which is a list
and then I slice it three different times
the environment diagram that I get
includes four different lists
notice the digits is unchanged by the slicing
but when I sliced the one out
saying that I want to go
from the beginning all the way up
but not including index one
I got a new list of the value one in it
asking for the middle gave me a
third list with eight and two
and asking for everything from index two to the end
gave me a 4th list with two and eight
processing container values
often involves
iterating over all of the values contained
in the list or dictionary that you're interested in
but there are some functions built in
that help us do this more efficiently
in particular
there are several functions that perform
sequence aggregation
so these are functions that
take iterable arguments and aggregate them
into a single value
I'm just going to show you the actual
documentation in python three
and help you understand how it works
so there is a built in function called some
which takes an adorable argument such as a list
now this notation
doesn't actually
mean you write square brackets when you call it
instead this is something that's used in python docks
to say that the second argument is optional
so you can call some with just one argument
a list and it will sum the values
or you can call it with two arguments
a list of values and then some start value
and it will go through
all of the values in the iterable
and add them to the start
okay so here it says
return the sum of an iterable of numbers
not strings plus the value of parameter start
which defaults to zero
when the iterable is empty returns start
some 2 3 4
is nine
it doesn't work with strings
now what's this starting value about
well if I started with five
then it would add five and two and three and four
now why is that useful
well let's say you're adding together
values that aren't just numbers
you have to provide a value of that
type in order to get started
so remember that I can add two and three the list
to four the list and I get a longer list
well in the same way I can some
a list containing two and three
as well as four
as long as it's the case
that I start with a list in the first place
if I hadn't started with a list
I'd try to add this list to the No.0
and that's not possible
so that's what would have happened if I had
summed without
that starting value
but since I provided an empty list to begin with
and then I added in two and three
and then I added in four I ended up with a list 2 3 4
max takes two forms
you can pass it and iterable such as a list
as well as an optional key function
and it returns the maximum value
or you can pass it multiple different arguments
such as a bunch of numbers
along with a key function
and then it will take the max of the arguments
so it says with a single argument
return its largest item
that is an element of the list of the two pass in
with two or more arguments return the largest argument
so the max of a range going up to five is four
or I could have said max 1 2 3 4
with a zero at the beginning
and that would have done the same thing
now what's going on with this key function
well the documentation didn't tell me
but what happens is that it applies
a function to every element that you're considering
and actually
computes the maximum based on the return values
of calling those functions
so you can ask things like
what's the max value in the range
from zero through nine
if what I care about
is some algebraic expression like 7 x minus four
times x minus two
now that's some parabolo
where the maximum's right at three
if I designate this as my key function
then it's going to tell me the maximum value in this
range as an output of calling this function is three
so if I take this function and I apply it to the No.3
then I get eight
what if I applied it to two I get something less
if I applied it to four
or five or six or seven I'd get something less as well
so that's why it's giving me the return value of three
here's a third one called all
all takes an iterable and returns true
if you get a true value
when calling bull on every element in the iterable
if the iterable is empty return true
what's this bull function
well bull tells me whether a value is true or false
so five is a true value
true of course is a true value as well
even -1 is a true value
but zero is that not a true value it's a false value
likewise hello is a true value
and an empty string is a false value
we learned about these
when we talked about boolean contexts
back when we introduced conditional statements
so what about all
well let's say I have a range five
and I want to ask is it the case
that x is less than five
for x in range five
I'd get true true true true true
the goal of all is to aggregate those together
and tell me whether they're all true or not
I don't have to pass it a list of poolian values
I could pass it the list of numbers zero one
two three and four
and it would tell me that since zero is false
these are not all true values
so those are
three built in functions that operate on sequences
there's also min and there's any
which are complements to max and all
trees are an important data abstraction
for representing hierarchical relationships
we've drawn pictures of trees before
and discussed how in computer science
they grow upside out
now we'll talk about the common vocabulary
used to describe trees
there are in fact
two different metaphors used regularly
the first is the recursive description of trees
where a tree is like a wooden tree like an apple tree
in this description
a tree has a root label and a list of branches
there's the root label
there's a branch
there are only two branches to this tree
and the other branches here to the right
by the way each branch is a tree
that means the branch has a root label as well
a tree with zero branches is called a leaf
so there's a leaf with no branches
it does have a root label of its own
now once you've constructed a tree recursively
you might want to describe certain
locations within the tree
and so we say in the relative description
about family trees
that each location in a tree is called a node
so here are all the nodes I've circled them
and this is the root or the root node at the top
each node has a label that can be any value
so the data stored within the tree
are stored at the labels
now the reason I call this a family tree relative
description
is that one node can be the parent or child of another
so we can say that this node containing two
is the child of that root node containing three
and you can also describe other familial relationships
such as ancestors and descendants and siblings
by the way people often refer to the label
values themselves by their locations
so something like
each parent is the sum of its children
which is true of a fibonacci tree
now that we can talk about trees
we can talk about implementing the tree abstraction
a tree has a root label in a list of branches
and the constructor is going to take close to values
each branch must be a tree
so
if I want to construct a representation for this small
tree I would write the following code
it's a tree where the root label is three
and the branches are a tree with one
and a tree with a 2 1 1
in this case
I'm using the constructor as I've described it
so that I can change representations however I wish
now you might say
aren't I violating an abstraction barrier
because I'm using a list
no it's part of the abstraction
that a tree has a list of branches
so it's totally fine that I'm using a list here
because that's part of the abstraction
it's not part of the representation
now let's come up with a representation
I can come up with anything I want
and that will determine
what actually gets printed out by python
when I evaluate this constructor expression
here's what we'll get
it's just some lists within lists with the
label values emitted within them
the way we construct this is to define
a constructor tree
which takes the label in a list of branches
by default the list of branches
by default the list of branches is empty
so by default I'll get a leaf
which is why I'm able to call just tree on one
in order to construct this leaf node here
I put the label into a list
branches is already a list and so I sum them together
the label of a tree is a selector
that returns the elemented index zero
in the list representation of the tree
and the branches are the rest of the list
elements as a list
now in order to make sure that
while I'm using the tree constructor
I don't build something that's not a tree
I'm going to add some checks
the first check here says for branching branches
assert that the branch is a tree
as part of the abstraction
and my code is going to make sure that I obey that
abstraction as I construct the tree
I'm also going to call
list on branches instead of just saying
label in a list plus branches
in order to make sure
that if I pass in some other kind of sequence
it gets converted to a list
before adding to another list
so these two lines are really just there to verify
that the tree definition is being respected
within the body of whatever program I write
how do we know if a branch is a tree
well for anything to be a tree
it has to be a list
it has to have at least one element for the label
so if that's not true will return falls
and it has to be the case that all the branches are
trees
so in fact is tree is a tree recruited function itself
that goes through every branch in the branches of the
tree if it's not a
tree that branch
then the whole thing can't possibly be a tree
if these two techs pass then it must be a tree
because it has a label
and it has branches that are trees
finally
I'll add one more function to my tree abstraction
which is a check to see
if a tree is in fact just a leaf
which checks that the branches are empty
if I call branches on tree and get back on empty list
that's a false value
so not branches tree will be a true value
just as long as this tree has no branches
now that we have the code for our data abstraction
we can use it
we can create a tree that's just a leaf
is it a leaf oh yes it is
if I want to create a tree with branches
then I specify those branches in a list
because every tree should have a list of branches
which by default is empty
now if I just put a single value in here
I'm going to get an error
that say branches must be trees
it must be the case that when I construct this
everything I put in the branches list is itself a tree
if I want a tree with branches to be one of my branches
then I give branches to that tree
and in this case we'll just put a leaf
so I finished the tree rooted at five
I want another branch which is a single leaf
rooted by six
now I've listed all the branches for the tree
and there's the tree
notice that when I
evaluated this constructor expression
there were no errors
because I've built a well formed tree
now it happens to be
that it has this complicated nested representation
but that's not how I will access it
and said I'll just ask what's the label of t
it's one
what's the branches of t
while a bunch of trees
if I want to get the
branch of index zero then I just write that
that's a tree
and I can get the root label of that branch
just by asking for the label
of the index zero branch
by treating branches as a list
I'm not violating any abstraction barrier
because I said in my abstraction
that a tree has a list of branches
functions that take trees as input
or return trees as output
are often tree recursive themselves
let's look at some examples
in practice one does not often
create trees using the tree constructor
and a set of explicit labels
but instead generates the tree programmatically
for example if I want to create a function
that builds a fibonacci tree
then I would write it in the following way
if n is less than equal to one
that means the fib tree for that n is just a leaf
I create the leaf using my tree constructor
otherwise
I need to build the two branches of a fibonacci tree
the left branch and the right branch
are both going to be constructed
with recursive calls to fib tree
finally I want to return a tree
that means coloring the tree constructor
on some label value
and the branches the branches are placed into a list
and what about the label value
while here I apply the fibonacci recurrence
I get the label of the left tree
and add it to the label of the right tree
the base case of fibtree one or fibtree zero
is just a leaf
fibtree 2 has structure within it
it's the label
and has two branches which are both leaves
fib tree four
is the fibonacci tree
that we've been looking at in examples so far
so its label
is three and then it has how many leaves 1 2 3 4 5
different leaves
often times we'll write functions that take in
trees and do interesting things with them
here's a not so interesting thing
as a simple example
if I want to count the leaves in a tree t
I'm going to write a tree recursive function
processing a leaf of a tree
is off to the base case of a tree processing function
here if t is only a leaf and I count the leaves
there's one leaf
the recursive case typically makes a recursive call
on each branch
then aggregates the results
in this case what we're going to do
is take each branch in the branches of the tree
and count the leaves in each branch
the leaves in the total tree
are just all the leaves in the branches summed up
there's our first tree processing function
let's walk through it one more time
the t comes in
I don't know if it's a large tree or a small tree
if in the simplest case it's just a leaf
then I know it to do I just say there's one leaf
otherwise
I sum up all
of the results of making
recursive calls on each of the branches
count leaves
b for b in the branches of the tree
so what's particular about the count leaves function
is what it returns in the base case
and how it aggregates its recursive calls
and of course don't forget to return that result
we saw before that fib tree four
has five leaves
and let's make sure that our count leaves function
returns five
it does
now by the way fib trees get pretty large
fib tree 10 which has fibonacci No.10 at the top
has lots of leaves
how many leaves
let's count
89 leaves
an interesting fact is that 89 is fibonacci No.11
here's a discussion question
implement leaves
which returns a list of the leaf labels of a tree
so how does it work it takes in some tree
and you call leaves on it
and it gives you all the values of the leaves
so notice that the root label three is not in here
only the leaf labels
in order to implement this function
we're going to use effect about some
which is that if you some a list of lists
you get a list
containing the
elements of all of the lists in the input
let me show you some examples
if you sum the lists one two three and four
you get one list containing one two three and four
in order to call some
on a list of lists
and have it aggregate all of the values in those lists
you have to provide a starting value
of an empty list
if I sum a list with one I get a list with one
if I sum a list
that has two elements
and the first element is a list within a list
then
what I'm going to get is still a list within a list
in the output
notice the difference
between this structure and that structure
one was a value in the output
in this case a list containing one is a value here
so it's not enough just to sum the whole tree
and get all the labels within it
because
some doesn't remove all of the nested structure
it just gets rid of one level
okay here is the implementation of the tree processing
function that takes in some tree
and returns a list of the leaf labels
if it's a leaf
then we get the label
and put it in a list
otherwise we sum up something
here are eight alternatives
I recommend that you pause and think about it
I'm going to show you the answer in 321
our goal is to
get a list of leaf labels for each branch
and then put them all
into one long list of all the leaf labels
we get that by summing a recursive call
to the leaves of b
for every b in the branches of the tree
so this is almost identical to count leaves
except for we have a different base case
and a different use of some
meaning a different way of aggregating
the return values of the recursive calls
a function that creates a tree from another tree is
typically also recursive
so for example if I have a tree
maybe it's a fibonacci tree
maybe it's something different
and what I'd like to do is return a new tree that has
exactly the same structure
but the leaf labels have been incremented
then I'll write a tree recursive function
to build the new tree
if I'm building a tree that's only a leaf
I get the label
I add one to it
and then I need to return a tree
because that's what increment leaves does
so a quick check is that I do have the right range here
I'm returning trees just like I should
in this case we return a leaf because we got a leaf in
if I have been given a tree that is not a leaf
then I need to
increment the leaves in all the branches of that tree
and then build a new tree with those new branches
notice that I keep the label the same
and that's because this function doesn't do anything
with the labels
of the nodes that aren't leaves
here's another tree processing function increment t
which returns a tree like t
but with all labels incremented
I'll show you a trick
you don't always
need to have a separate base case for the leaves
if every tree is treated the same way
this is a one liner that says
return a tree where I've incremented the label
and I've incremented
all of the labels in all of the branches
this is tree recursive
how do we ever reach a base case
while when there are no branches such as in a leaf
this is an empty list and we're done
we don't make any recursive calls when we reach a leaf
we didn't need to use an if statement to say that
because that's built into list comprehensions
that if this list is empty
then the whole comprehension is empty
and doesn't require any work to construct
here's an example of one more tree processing function
I'll write a function that prints out a tree
it will first print the label of that tree
and then for every branch it will call print tree
on the branch
I don't return anything
instead
this function exists in order to display a tree value
so that we don't have to look at
nested lists all the time
if I call print tree on fib tree
four
I can see all the values
but I can't see this structure
let's write a better print tree
that uses indentation in order to show the structure
if I wanted to indent by
five pairs of spaces and then write
the No.5 after that
I would build
the string using multiplication and addition
and if I print that out then I get five indented
by default
I don't want the root label to be indented at all
but I want the possibility of indentation to happen
later where I'm going to take those two spaces
multiply them by the indentation level
and then add a string representation of the label of t
the way that
indentation occurs is that I'm going to indent
all the branches
and since this is defined in terms of indent
if I get a branch of a branch
it will be indented twice
so now when I print tree fib tree four
I can clearly see the structure
even for a larger tree
I can clearly see that there's fib tree four
there's fib tree four again as one of the branches
here's the other branch of fib tree five
the indentation level of a label
corresponds to its depth in the tree
let's work through one more example
about summing all the labels along a path
from the route to the leaf of a tree
and then printing out that sum
some recursive functions build up their result
by manipulating the return value of a recursive call
where other recursive functions
build up their result by passing information
into the recursive call as an argument
and both of these strategies are useful when
processing trees
so let's look at an example
of both ways of doing things
before working with trees
let's go back to our old friend factorial
one way to write it is if an equal zero
we return one
otherwise we return end times
the result of calling fact on n minus one
and if we run this example on say four
then we'll get four times three
times two times one is 24
and this is an example
of taking the return value of a recursive call
and manipulating it in this case for multiplying in it
but there's another way
instead I could define fact times
which takes in both n and k
and instead of returning
just end times end minus one times end minus two
this returns k times end times end minus one
times end minus two times end minus three
all the way down to one
and we'll do it as follows
if n is zero will return k
because n factorial is just one
otherwise we're going to return the result of calling
effect times on n minus one
and k times n
and I think what's interesting about this example
is that we're not manipulating the return value
of this recursive called effect times at all
instead we're just returning it
which means that the result of the recursive call
better be the result of the current call
in extending this reasoning
it means the result of the base case
needs to be
the same result as the original recursive call
and that turns out to be true in this case
so if we're trying to compute k times and factorial
here's the expression
it turns out that's identical
to k times n times and minus one factorial
here's the k times n
and here's the and minus one factorial
so here the result is being built up
and by the time you hit the base case
you're done with all of the multiply
whereas in this version
you haven't done any multiplying at all
when you hit the base case
that all happens after you return
and in fact
if we wanted to define fact in terms of fact times
that wouldn't be too hard
we just returned the result
of calling fact times on nn one
fact four is still 24
okay now let's work on an example with trees
so I have a file with all of the
tree constructor and selector functions in it already
called tree dot pi
so if I want to be able to use all those
I can write an import statement that imports them all
and now I could build a tree
a number tree
might look like
three's at the root
and then we have a branch that's a leaf with four
and we have another branch that's not a leaf
with five and six
and let's have another tree
one with letters in it instead
we'll put h at the root
which has a branch rooted at a
and this will have two leaves
the s leaf and the t leaf
and then we'll also have
an e
which is its own leaf under the h route
so haste is a tree
that has the
underlying representation of a bunch of lists within
lists within lists
but I can get its label and that will be h
and I can get its branches
all right let's say we want to write a function
that takes in a tree
finds all the leaves and for each leaf
prints out the sum of all the labels
from the route to that leaf
much like the fact times function
I'm going to add a second argument
the sum so far
so that I can build up this sum as I go
and then when I get to the leaf I just print it out
so whether this is a leaf or not
there's going to be a label
and we should add that to so far
but then
we'll figure out if we're at a leaf or not
if we are then we print out the sum so far
which includes the leaf label and everything above it
otherwise we go through all the branches
t is a tree so I can call branches on it
I get a list of trees so each b is a tree
and print sums is a function that I can call on trees
so if I call print sums on numbers starting with zero
I'll see seven
and the seven came from
the three of the route
followed by the four
which is directly below the route and is a leaf
the other thing that should be printed out is
the sum along the path from three
to five
oh but five is not a leaf so we don't print yet to six
three plus five plus six is 14
which is the 14 we got down here
and what happens when we call print sums on the haste
tree instead is that I think we should start with
an empty string so that we can add more strings to it
at which point we print out has
that came from HAS and we reached a leaf
or hat h
a
t we reached a leaf or heat
which is this leaf below this route
and the structure of this function
is that we're
building up the sum as we go
always passing a new value into so far
I could have written so far plus labelty here
instead of this assignment statement
and that would have been fine too
or we could just update so far
and then use the new value either to print
or to pass in to all of the recursive calls