61 a lecture No.20 announcements
the announcements are the same as they were on Monday
you've got lab due today
homework due Thursday
the ants project is out
it's due next Friday
but there's a checkpoint next Tuesday
and an early submission
bonus point for submitting by Thursday
there's also an extra credit problem on the project
if you want the extra credit from that problem
and you want the extra credit from submitting early
then you do have to finish the extra credit problem
by next Thursday
this is a bit shorter than usual
but it's still quite long
so leave yourself plenty of time
get started early and make progress every day
we'll have an advising panel
with members of the staff from 11 to 12
on Thursday where you can ask the core
staff questions about anything you want
and listen to other students
questions and the staff's responses
this won't be the whole staff
just a selection of folks
that are interested in helping guide you
and your berkeley experience
advising office hours are on fridays
if you want one out one help about any of these
topics that aren't related to the course
there's an anonymous survey that we'd love you to take
about how the course is going so far
it's very short
it's not required
but I'd like you to be completed by next Monday
just so we can have a sense of how things are going
and as a reminder
midterm two is on Wednesday the 28th at 7:00pm
it has a similar format and style to midterm one
and will cover content up to an including fridays
lecture
so this lecture is going to be covered on the midterm
in particular
there's a video right at the beginning
about string representations
and that's the most important part of this lecture
in terms of understanding
the mechanics of python and how they work
and this also shows up in various ways on exams
because if you can't print something out
then it's hard to know what's going on
string representations
and the object oriented programming metaphor
we say that an object
should behave like the kind of data
it is meant to represent
and one aspect of that
is that an object should know how to
present itself to the world
as a string
or to produce a string representation of itself
and strings are important
their descriptions
not only in natural languages
that the humans used to communicate with each other
but also in programming languages
you can put an expression in a string
so in python
this distinction is built right into the language
all objects produce two string representations
one is called the stir string
and it's designed to be legible to humans
the repper string by contrast
is designed to be legible to the python interpreter
that is it's supposed to be an expression
an expression in the python language
now
a lot of times the stir and repper string are the same
because python was
designed to be a language that people could read
and so
a lot of the expressions have exactly the same form
as a person my right down
when they try to communicate the same idea
you read the No.1 in either case
but sometimes these different
let's look at an example
1st will consider the repper string for an object
there's a built in function called repper
it returns a python expression as a string
that evaluates to an equal object
if I call help on repper
this is what I see built into the language
repper can be called on any object it produces a string
and it's supposed to return
the canonical string representation of the object
for most object types the documents tation says
calling eval on the repper of the object
gives you
some object that's equivalent to the original
the result of calling repper on a value
is exactly what you see in an interactive session
it's what python prince out
right below the expression you evaluated
so if I evaluate this expression
which represents 12 times tend to the 12th power
the canonical string representation is one and then two
and then twelve zeros and then a decimal point
and then a zero
and that's what gets displayed
exactly the same thing gets displayed if you call print
on the result of calling repper
on 12 times 10 to the 12th
now some objects do not have a simple
python readable string
there's no way to write down an expression
that very easily captures everything
that some object is
or
an expression for how to create something that's equal
to the original object
and this is typically true of compound things
such as functions or classes
the min function that's built in
just can't be written a single expression
so instead what you see when you call repper on min
is this proxy
which uses angled brackets to indicate
that this is not in fact
a python expression at all
it's just some standard
a human readable description
because generating a python expression
just didn't work out
the stir string of an object can be different
human interpretal strings are useful as well
and so we'd like to have
our programs be able to generate them
because
often times a program wants to communicate something
with a user
so here's an example
there's a fractions module
part of the standard library
and it has a fraction class
a fraction is built from a numerator and a denominator
the ripper of a fraction
is just a call to the
class itself exactly how you'd construct
the fraction in the first place
that's not how human's right fractions
human's right fractions like that
so stir is a built in function that takes any object
gives you back a string
or this string is some human interpretable
representation of the original object
the result of calling stir
on the value of an expression
is what python prints out
when you actually call the print function
so if I print half I'll see one divided by two
now notice this has quotes around it because this is a
string
or as
this is just what happens when you print the string
the contents of the string
all right let's try it up
from fractions
import fraction gives me access to this class
which I combined
an instance of to the name half
now half is a fraction
the repper string of half is just that
if I print half
I see one divided by two
the stir string of half is one divided by two
now if I evaluate the repper string of half
I get the fraction
it's a different object but it's this quibbling right
if I evaluate the stir string of half in this case
it turns out that is a valid python expression
but that's just kind of coincidence
what you get back is not a fraction
it's a flop
one divided by two is really just there
to be interpretable by humans
we can learn a little bit more about
the repper and stir functions
just by trying them out on strings
so here's a string
hello world
what happens when I evaluate s
I see that string
that's what happens when I print out the repper of s
same thing
now what happens if I print out s
the quotes go away
which is exactly what I see when I get the stir of s
because the stir of s is just s
now what happens if I just call repper of s
I see quotes within quotes
what's going on there
well what repper is giving me is a string
or if I evaluated it I'd cut back the original string
and what if I call the repper
of the repper of the repper of s
I'd get a mess
what's going on there
well this is not just quotes within quotes
but quotes within quotes within quotes within quotes
and python has to use backslashes in order to indicate
what quotes really industrying and what don't
the details of that are not important
what is important
is that if I evaluate
the result of evaluating the result of evaluating
the repper of the repper of the repper of s
I get back s
now what if I just evaluated s in the first place
I'd get an error
hello comma world is not a valid python expression
when I have quotes around it it is
so if I evaluate the repper of s everything's fine
but I can't evaluate s or the stir of s
because what I have here is not valid python
polymorphic functions
a polymorphic function is a function that applies
to many different
types of data
and stir and repper are great examples
because you can really
pass any kind of object you want
tis this built in stir and repper functions
and they're always supposed to do the right thing
how's that possible
well the fundamental idea
is that repper just asks its argument to display itself
and in python
this is done using a special method name
now it's a special name
because it corresponds to a built in function
but this general idea
that you can have a function that just
asks the argument what to do
certainly applies beyond the python language
okay so repper in particular
just invokes a zero argument method
called underscore underscore
repper underscore underscore
on its argument
in order to get the repper string that it returns
so I can call repper on half
which was the fraction one two
or I could invoke its method
invoking the method
gets looked up in the class
so it's really the fraction class
that knows how to generate the repper string
for a fraction
it's not the repper function
and likewise stir invokes a zero argument method
that is correspondingly called underscore underscore
stir underscore underscore
another special method name
and so I could invoke this method directly if I wanted
and that would generate a stir string for a fraction
so there's a really important idea here
you could write a function
like stir a ripper
that actually doesn't have much logic at all
it just defers to the
argument that comes in to decide what to do
by invoking a method on it with the particular name
so let's talk about how
repper inster are actually implemented
it turns out that it's slightly more
complicated than what I described
instead of just invoking the repper method
on its argument
an instance attribute called repper is ignored
only a class attribute called repper
is invoked by the repper function that's built in
how would I implement that
so which of the following function definitions
corresponds to a function repper
that takes in some argument
looks up the class attribute
called underscore underscore repper
and invokes it
here are five options
only one does what I described
think about it for a minute
I'll tell you the answer in 321
this one
manages to skip instance attributes or ignore them
by looking up the type of the argument
that gets you the class
and therefore
asking for the repper attribute of the class
is guaranteed to give you a class attribute
now it's a class attribute that's a function
and that function is not a bound method
because it's looked up on the class
so you have to explicitly pass in x
in order to have this class attribute invoked
on the particular argument x that were interested in
we'll look at an example in a moment
stir is also complicated
even more complicated than repper
an instance attribute called stir is ignored
if there's no stir attribute at all on the class
then calling stir just returns whatever repper returns
so by default they're the same
it's only if you explicitly make them different
that they differ
how would we implement that
well let's try
by the way stir is a class not a function
so when you're calling stir
you're really calling a constructor
for the built in string type called stir
so to explore all these different
nuances of string generation
let's create a class called bear
this is a bear
and it's going to have a repper method
which just returns the string bear
now I'm going to try
to invoke this in various different ways
I'm going to create a bear called oski
I'm gonna print oski
I'm gonna print the stir string for oski
I'm gonna print the repper string for oski
I'm gonna print what I get when I invoke on oski
the stir method
and I'm gonna print invoking the repper method on oski
so at the moment all of them
print out bear
there are five different print statements here
they're all the same
what happens if I define a stir method as well
well since there is a stir now
it will be called whenever we use the stir string
which is here here and here
so in this case we're going to return a bear
and we can observe the different behavior
than what we had before
printing oski gives me the stir string
as well as explicitly asking for stir
using the stir built in function
or looking up stir the special method name
now in order to get even more variety
we need to introduce and in it
which will set instance attributes
let's have an interest instance attribute called repper
which is a function
that takes no arguments
because here we see we call it with no arguments
and it's going to return oski
and self dot stir
will return
this bear
executing my five print statements
we see that
printing oski and printing the stir string for oski
are always the same
there's no real way to make them different
the repper string ignores this instance attribute
just uses the method
which is a class attribute that's also a function
and so we see bear is returned
likewise the stir string
skips the instance
attribute and goes straight to the class
however attribute look up in the conventional way
gives us these functions which when we call them
return oski and this bear
so we see
there are four different things that we can get
based on how we print
as a final step to prove our understanding
let's see if we can write a repro function ourself
so this is going to replace the built in repro function
and what we'll do here is just return the type of x
invoke the rubber method on that
and pass in x like I said before
and what about stir x
now we certainly need to get the type of x
because we're going to ignore instance attributes
if it's the case
that this type has an attribute called stir
with underscores around it
then we will use that t dot stir
and pass in the original instance as its argument
otherwise
we can just return the result of calling repper on x
here we'll run the same program
and it should behave the same way
if we've successfully implemented repper and stir
just as they behave in the built in methods
and here we see exactly the same output
because we've implemented the same logic
that reprinster apply
so now you know what they do
we're using an important idea here
it's called an interface
so when I talked about object oriented
programming in the first place
I said that the central to this metaphor
was that objects would pass messages to each other
and that's how they would interact
now the mechanics in the language is that they just
look up attributes or methods
and that's how they communicate
so that's the idea of passing messages
passing messages is the metaphor
looking up attributes is what we actually do
in order to pass messages around
now the attribute lookup rules are
designed in a special way
they allow
different data types to respond to the same message
just by having the same attribute name
and a shared message
an attribute name that exists on many different classes
and elicits the same behavior
from those different classes
is a powerful method of abstraction
that's what we'll call an interface
an interface is a set of shared messages
and some specification that tells you
what they're supposed to do
what they meet
so as an example
classes that implement repper and stir methods
and have those methods return python interpretable
and human readable strings respectively
interfaces don't have to be built into the language
although this one is
if you ever just define
that
there are a bunch of classes that all have the same
method and all those methods do similar things
then you've created an interface
so let's see if we can build a class
that exhibits this interface
we already saw that there was a built in fraction class
let's build something similar
I'll call it a ratio so we can tell them a park
the way you create a ratio
is just to pass in a numerator and a denominator
if we want instances of the ratio class
to be able to display themselves
we need to define our repper method
it will return a string
the string ratio
followed by parentheses
here we have two different gaps within our string
that we fill in
using the format method on strings
self numer fills into the first
or a zero index gap and self need on the 2nd
now if we want a human readable string as well
following the example of fraction
we just write zero divided by one
or again
zero is the numerator
and one is the denominator
now we can create a ratio half
print out half and we'll get the human readable version
just display half directly and we'll get
the python expression
special method names are a topic
particular to the python language
certain names in python are special
because they have built in behavior of some sort
and they always look the same
they always start an end with two underscores
so when you see a name with two underscores around it
that's just an indication
that it has some particular behavior
it interacts with the built in
object system in some way
for instance the first one we saw was in it
this
method is special because it's invoked automatically
whenever an object is constructed
other than that it's just a regular method
repper was discussed in the previous videos
it's the method that gets invoked in order to produce
a string that represents an object
and it's the one that's used in an interactive
python session
to display the value
what about add
well that's a new one
this is a two argument method
that's invoked to add one object to another
there's a one argument method called bull
and another called float
this one
is invoked to convert an object to true or false
telling you it's boolean value
and float tries to convert an object to a real number
so for example
if I set zero one and two to zero one and two
and then I add one and two
I'll get three
if I'll call bull which is a built in function
on zero I'll get false and on one I'll get true
and this bull function
gives you exactly the behavior that you'll get
if you place these objects in a boolean context
such as a conditional statement
now it's possible to rewrite
this entire sequence of statements
I could say zero one and two or zero one and two
and then add one and two together
using the special method name
or convert zero and one to boolean values
using that special method name
so there's a correspondence
between built in pieces of syntax
and built in functions
and these special method names
that actually do the work
it's another example
of using an interface in order to allow
user defined objects
to interact with the built in systems within python
so python is very extensible
you can create a new class and be able to add
instances of that class together using the plus sign
just by overriding the special method name add
so what
happens when you have two instances of user defined
classes added together
well what happens
is that you invoke either ad
or there's another method called r ad
I'll tell you about that in a moment
and that actually performs the addition
again we're just asking the objects
how do you add yourselves together
so if we want to extend our ratio class
so that we can add ratios
this is certainly possible
I could add a third and a six to get a half
either using the plus site
or by using
the method that actually performs the addition
both of these expressions are equivalent in python
now people almost always use this one
because it's much easier to read
the purpose of this is just to allow ourselves
to use the method definition syntax
in order to override what happens
when you use a plus sign
between two objects
you can also use r ad
the difference between r ad and ad
is that this here
is the argument on the right side of the plus sign
and this is the argument on the left
now for numbers addition is commutative
so it's irrelevant what order they come in
these two functions are equivalent
but you could imagine some cases
in which you'd like to invent addition
that's not commuted
and so it is possible using rf
I'm not going to go through every special name and
how it corresponds to some built in feature of python
but that has been done before you
both in the python docks and in this
online textbook call dive into python three
but let's see if we can add addition to our ratio class
we define an ad method
that takes self another
and what it does
is just computes
the numerator and denominator of the result
so the numerator of two added ratios
is the numerator of the first
times the denominator of the second
plus the denominator of the first
times the numerator of the second
the denominator is the product of the denominators
if we want to reduce
this ratio to two relatively prime integers
then we have to compute the greatest common devisor of
n and d
then we can return the ratio
of n divided by g and d divided by g
and what's the greatest common devisor
we did talk about this earlier in the course
one way to compute it is to say
well and does not equal d
rebind n and d
to be in no particular order
the min of n and d
and the absolute value of n minus d
so now we can take the gcd of 12 and eight and get four
we can also add together the ratios one third and one
six
now maybe we're not done
what happens if I add together the ratio one third and
one I should get four thirds
but I'm assuming that the thing that I'm adding this to
is in fact another ratio is opposed to an integer
one thing I could do
is inspect the type of other in order to figure out
what action to take
so I could say if it's the case
that other is an instance of the inch class
then instead I have a numerator
that's the self dot numerator
times while the other denominators just one
and then I add in self dots d nom
times the other which is the numerator
of the other
here I'm just treating other as a numerator of other
and the denominator of one
d is the denominator of self
otherwise if it's the case that other
is an instance of the ratio class
then I use the formula that I had before
I can still take the gcd
and I think I'm back in business
I can add the ratios together
or I can add one to the ratio
now can I add a ratio
3rd to one in this order
not yet because I don't have right side edition to find
but I can just say
that right side edition is the same as edition
for this class
at which point I can add ratios
I can add integers to ratios in either direction
and I've fulfilled
the interface
for adding addition to a user defined class
in the python language
now what happens if we add a floating point value
0.345
well then this result will not be an integer
so it doesn't seem likely
should be building a ratio at all
at that point
there's another option
instead we could convert
our existing ratio into a floating point value as well
by that I mean I just attack
if other is an instance of float
and if so I return not to ratio at all
but instead
what I get when I convert
self into a float and add it to other
now what does it mean to convert self into a flute
well I'll have to define that
I define that using this special method name
or in this case I'll just return what you get
when you divide the numerator by the denominator
so I've extended by system yet further
where now I can add 0.2
to the ratio one third
and I'll get some reasonable result
I've actually used two important ideas here
in one example
this is called type dispatching
where you inspect the type of an argument
to decide what to do
and here this is called type coercion
which is when you take an object of one type
convert it into another type
in order to be able to combine it
with some other value
these are two strategies that people use
in order to have different classes interact
you know add is a two argument method
and now we have a version of add
that operates on two values of different types
so let's do the last drill
I would like you to create a class called kangaroo
and it has of course it has a constructor
and the constructor initializes an instance variable
called a pouch contents
to be an empty list
so now the data associated with the
kangaroo is going to be a list
and initially adjust an empty list
that's it now you're going to create a function
called put in pouch
and then you're going to create a print function
so put in pouch takes a string as input
and adds it to the kangaroos pouch
which of course is the list
okay
if the object if that string is not already in there
so if the string is already in there
then print object already in
pouch and don't do anything
so if I add something into the pouch
like a bowling ball
and then I try to add a bowling ball again
you shouldn't put two bowling balls in
only one at a time
but if it's not then you should add it to the pouch
and it doesn't matter where in the list it is
the print function
should print the kangaroos pouch contains
and then print out
everything that is in the list
good again as always write a little driver
so create a pouch
print its contents add something print its contents
add something in
make sure it got added
print its contents try to add something twice
make sure you get the message saying
this is already in here
alright take some time again full blown class
constructor put in pouch and a print function
and the data associated with this particular object
is going to be a list
that we will be adding to using the
put in pouch
and when you come back I'm going to show you
my solution
okay here's my solution again
I'm going to separate out the class from the driver
so let's do the class first
I have class kangaroo
I have my constructor
my putin pouch and my print function
so the constructor is trivial
in fact it doesn't take any input it's just south
why well I said the initialization is an empty string
so south
pouch contents equals open brackets quos bracket done
nothing to do
constructor takes no input
fine perfectly fine
put in pouch it takes a single parameter's input x
and what you have to do now is add it to the pouch
if it's not already in the pouch
now you got to do a little bit of work
so I've got to go through
the pouch and check to see if that element is in there
all right let's go ahead and do that
for I in range the length of south
underscore contents
so south is the object
and I'm going to grab the pouch contents
which is the list
and I will take on every
index from zero to the length of the list minus one
and I'm simply going to ask that if south
pouch contents sub I is equal to x
that's what I'm trying to insert into the list
then print already in pouch and what do I do now
I'm done go home
return
return out of the function there is nothing to do here
right there's nothing to add to the list
you don't have to check any more elements
you found it and you're done
so for every element the list
check to see if the object exists
if it exists print a message and boot out
and if I get to this point in the code
after the whole for loop is executed
what do I know
object's not in the list
right obviously not
otherwise I would have hit this statement
I would have printed this and I would have returned
so at this point
I can simply append the object to the list
so let's follow the south
what is that
address of the object pouch contents what is that
the list associated with this object
and that is a list
so I can call the append function
with the element that I want
so look at the three levels of in direction object
data associate with the object
member function of that list
right there good
let's look at the print statement
this is pretty easy
if the length of self
pouch contents that is the list of zero
then just say the kangaroos pouch is empty
there's nothing in there otherwise
say that the kangaroos pouch contains
and then I'm going to tape the list
and just convert it into a string
which you can do of course
or you could have put that into a for loop
in printed them out
and then that will print the contents of the
list of the pouch which of course is just a list here
all right let's go ahead and look at the driver now
so I'm going to create a kangaroo object
call that capital k
and I'm going to go ahead and print it
let's just make sure that the first thing works
and it'll say the kangaroo's pouch is empty
good that tells me that the
constructor work and I have an empty list
let's add something to the pouch
k dot put in pouch a ball there's a string
and then print k
the kangaroos pouch contains
and then it shows me a single object
let's put something else in there
make sure I can get multiple things in there
good so that now it has
tells me that when I put the hammer in
I print k I get a ball in the hammer
and one more test let's make sure that it can deal with
multiple objects trying to be put in
so if I try to put a ball in
it will say already in pouch
and I'm going to just print that
and make sure I didn't
screw anything up
so you have to be careful here
maybe I got the message right but I still added it
so when I printed it should only say ball hammer
and really probably what I should do here
because this is testing
the first object in the pouch is an object
I probably should have also tested hammer to make sure
somehow make sure I'm iterating through that whole list
so you probably want to
drive this a little bit more with a few more
test cases to make sure you can find an object
regardless of where it is in the list
and but again just you know basic functionality testing
make sure your functions do what you think they do
because one of the hard things with
well ever really any code
but particularly these member functions is
you got to drive them you got to run them
and you got to test all of them
even if you don't know that you know when
or how they're going to be used
so that testing code will do we'll see more and more of
in the coming weeks
to make sure we know how to verify
that our code is doing what we think
all right that's it for now
and when we come back we're going to have
you know
a little bit more talk about objects and classes
and start refining some of our thinking
about these things
so we'll see you in a little bit