61 a lecture No.30
announcements
midterm two regrade requests are du Monday
homework seven is due Thursday
and we're about to release the scheme project
this scheme project is where you write
a scheme interpreter in python
then you write some scheme code to run
on your very own interpreter
the goal of this project
is for you to learn how interpreters work
how is it that
programs turn into behavior by the computer
well here's the simplest sketch there is
of how you could
build an interpreter for a programming language
and it's the longest project in this course
so we'll have not one but two checkpoints
you have to finish the first few problems by
next Tuesday
and then finish the whole interpreter by next Friday
the rest of the project is just to write some scheme
code to make sure your interpreter really is working
and that's due Tuesday the 24th
but you'll get an
early submission bonus point
for completing it by Monday
the 23rd
unlike previous projects
there will be two versions that you can choose from
the normal version and the challenge version
through the normal version
the normal version is structured much
like previous projects
it's broken up into individual questions
and a lot of the framework or structure of the program
is given to you
in the challenge version
it's up to you to figure out
how to organize your program
the only test will run
is to make sure that at the end of the day
you've built a functioning scheme interpreter
but you don't have to break it down
into the various functions that we came up with
you can do it any way you want
you don't get any
extra points for doing the challenge version
it's just harder
but if that's what you're looking for at
this point in the course
a chance to organize your own program
instead of having us do it for you
well then try it out
you can always
switch back to the normal version if you want
so I recommend
that if you're going to do the challenge version
you do it early enough
that you can always switch back to the normal version
or you could take inspiration from the normal version
and look at how we structure the program there
so it's completely up to you which version you do
but I would expect almost all
students to do the normal version
this project is plenty large and challenging
even without the
extra challenge of having to organize
the program yourself
and don't worry
you'll get plenty of practice
organizing large programs in 61 b
if you take that course
so it's not like
you have to do it here to get the experience
since this project is so large
today's lecture
will just describe how to do the project
it won't tell you the exact code to type
but it will give you a description of
what the different parts of the program are
how they've fit together
so that you can keep oriented
when you're working through the project
it's not really educational
to work through this project
just by trying to pass the test cases
it's better to
understand how each piece that you build
fits into the whole interpreter
and that's what this lecture is about
Wednesday we don't have lecture at all
because it's veterans day
so we'll have no lecture
no lecture q amp a
no staff office hours
no discussion no tutorials no orientation nothing
just take the day off
there is a discussion worksheet for this week
which will be covered in today's
orientations the lab orientations
but there won't be any tutorial questions on it
it's a little shorter then
just give you some guidance
about quotation and evaluation
that I think will be helpful
we've also revised the lecture topic schedule
we were going to have some optional lectures
this Friday next Monday
but we looked at the rest of the semester
and realized that
we wanted to make sure you had
lab and discussion and tutorial time
for all of the required topics in the course
so we've shuffled things a little bit
and on Friday we will have
our first lecture in a new unit in the course
about declarative programming
where you're going to learn
yet another programming language
called sequel or sql
so let's briefly review the schedule
here we are today no lecture Wednesday
declarative programming will start Friday
in a normal semester this would be four lectures
but we've made the fourth one optional
but lab and discussion next week
we'll cover this content
and then we'll release a homework on it
this homework isn't actually due
until after thanksgiving
but since there's a lab next week
you do need to start getting oriented with this new
lecture material
at least a little bit
and if you master it as it comes out
then you could take a break during thanksgiving week
which I think would be great
this will be the last
piece of new content in the course
for the semester
next Wednesday
after that we'll cover some optional topics
help make sure you're ready for the final exam
and conclude
in project four you're going to build an interpreter
for the scheme language
and this lecture is all about the structure
of that interpreter
so how all of the important pieces fit together
in order to achieve the result that we want
which is a program
that's able to understand other programs
so here's the structure of an interpreter
it shares a lot with the calculator
example that we look at
on Monday
there is an eval
and an apply function
an eval
evaluates primitive expressions
it also evaluates combined expressions
but when it finds one of those
then it calls apply to actually apply
some procedure to some arguments
so these are both recursive
here's how the base cases of evil
are for primitive values such as numbers
it just returns that number
and for recursive calls that it makes
well when it gets a combination
which is an operator in some operands
it has to evaluate
that operator and evaluate those operands
in order to get the pieces that you're going to apply
so recall that you apply
the procedure
that's the value of the operator expression
to the arguments
that are all the values of the operators
so how do you get those values
while you just call a eval
and you get that
and then it makes a call to apply
now so far this doesn't look like a recursive call
but we'll find that it is
so we apply some procedure to its arguments
and that's all that we had to write for calculator
but I've left some gaps
because we're going to add a few more pieces to a valve
what about apply
well in the calculator example
everything was a base case
it just applied built in primitive procedures
plus minus times and divide
but we'd like to extend apply to be able to apply
procedures that we define to
so here are the extensions that we'll talk about today
one is that there's a new base case for evo
where it will look up a value bound to a symbol
so we can define what symbols mean
and look up what those mean in an environment
another one is that we're going to evaluate
sub expressions of special forms
special forms are things like if expressions
that aren't the same as call expressions
because they have a different semantics
a different evaluation procedure
but they have sub expressions
and those need to be evaluated
so you make recursive calls to eval
and then finally we'll talk about how
in order to apply a user defined procedure
we just evaluate its body
so that's calling eval on the body
where eval is up here
so eval calls apply in order to apply procedures
apply calls eval
in order to evaluate the body of those procedures
and thus we have two mutually recursive functions
and it's also the case that eval plus eval
directly in several different instances
and both of these have bass geeses
so some new aspects that we'll see today
are that eval is going to require an environment
in order to handle its
new base case of looking up a symbol
so the environment remembers what names mean
and how does that environment get constructed well
part of what apply
does is it creates a new environment
each time a user defined procedure
is a plot this is just the same as python
every time we call a function
we're creating a new environment
here every time we apply a procedure
or creating a new environment
and that environment will be passed to eval
so that when we look up a name
we get the right value for it
let's talk about special farms
so in the evaluation of a scheme expression
we need to know what sort of expression it is
calculator just divided ski expressions engine numbers
and call expressions
but in scheme there are some other alternatives as well
so the schema vowel function
dispatches on the expression for
meaning that
it has
just a bunch of different options of what it does
depending on what
sort of expression it gets
symbols are bound to values in the current environment
self evaluating expressions are return
those are things like numbers and the empty list
everything else is going to be a scheme list
called a combination
so we call it a combination
just to say that it's a well formed scheme list
that's part of some scheme source code
and some examples are
the if expression the lambda expression
the define expression
and just a regular old call expression
so if you see a combination that starts with if
then you know it's an if expression
so special forms in general
are identified by the first list element
if flanda and define
and if it's not one of these that we know about already
that does lamb that undefine
then we know it's a call expression
and so we just evaluate the operator
which might be a built in name or a name we've defined
that gives us some procedure to apply to the arguments
which are the values of these operand
sub expressions
okay so
now we
can do something that we couldn't do in calculator
we can define
a new procedure and call it
so here's one called demo
takes an s iff s is null
then it returns the list three
otherwise
it builds a new pair with cons
that's first element is the first element of s
and the rest
is whatever we get back
from a recursive call to demo on the rest of the list
and we might call that on for instance one two
now what does this do
think about it for a minute
this function demo
puts a three at the end of the list that's passed it
well actually it constructs an entirely new list
with all the elements of the original s one and two
as well as the element three
because the base case gives us back three
and then we just start conzing on
each element at a time
in order to build up a full list that ends in three
and starts with whatever elements were in the list
that was passed in
and does dissolve recursively
so it says we're supposed to do a demo
let's do a demo
what you see on the right
is your project for main file called scheme dot pi
and what does it do
well it has eval
and apply functions
and scheme eval evaluates a scheme expression
which could be one of a number of types
we could have just a number
or we could have a combination
so let's see what happens when we trace this
and then we start up our scheme interpreter
out the No.2
involves a call to the schema valve function
with two is the expression
it's evaluated in the global frame
and the result is two
if instead I negate two
then I'm evaluating this whole thing
I'm putting this in angled brackets to say that this is
not a python expression but a scheme expression
so -2 is evaluated by looking up the thing that negates
the No.2 is evaluated
and then we're
applying negative to two in order to get -2
and we can do this larger example as well
so we'll define
demo of s to b
a procedure where first your check can see if s is not
if it is then just return the list that contains three
otherwise
let's make this window bear
we will return what we get by
building a pair out of the first element of s
and then calling demo on the rest of s
close the cutter close the demo
close the cons close the if
close the the
fine and we're done
notice that schema
val hasn't actually
evaluated the body of this procedure yet
all it's done is create the demo procedure
so now let's see what happens when I call demo
on the list one two
a lot of work happens
let's try to trace through what it is
so at the very beginning
I call demo on list one two
which means I'm evaluating this expression
which is a call expression
we figure out what demo means
demo's a function that has the body
that we wrote down before
and we figure out what list one two means
after a bit of work
we find out that it's the list one two
so now we're going to do the work of applying
this
procedure to this argument
so that involves evaluating the body of the procedure
in a new environment
where s the formal parameter
of our procedure
is bound to the argument one two
and this frame is followed by the global frame
in the environment for this call to schema vel
okay so some work ensues
and we're not gonna trace through every bit
but it involves looking up every name
null is the null procedure
one s is bound to one two so we look that up etc etc
work is done
each time we make a recursive call
were making a recursive call to the same procedure
but with a different environment
so notice here s was bound to one two
but in a later recursive call s was bound to two
and in a further later recursive call
s is bound to the empty list which is the base case
we detect the base case here and we return
this base condition of just the list containing three
okay so we've returned to that
we now build a larger list
which puts the No.2 on the front
remember this is the case where s is bound to two
so the first element of s is two
and we put that on three to get two three
and then we have a
still later case
the original recursive call had s bound to one two
which constructs the list 1 2 3
and eventually we get the result that we want
next we'll talk about logical forms
so logical special forms are things that
involve conditions
and they only evaluate some sub expressions
so and if expression is one of these
insects its evaluation procedure
is that you evaluate the predicate
and then you choose one
either the consequent or the alternative
and in or
have an evaluation procedure
where they evaluate from left to right
each of the sub expressions
until you know whether the entire
expression is true or false
and there's also one called the khan expression
which you can read about in your project
and it involves not only
if an else closes but also a bunch of lf closes
so it's much more like
the conditional statement that's in python
and for all of these
it may be the case that some sub expressions are never
evaluated
so here's what you do
if you're going to evaluate an if expression
you evaluate the predicate
and then you decide
which of the sub expressions you want to evaluate next
the consequent or alternative
and then it's
as simple as evaluating that sub expression
in the place of the whole expression
in order to get the result that you want
so in your python program
that is actually the interpreter
there's something called do if form
and that's a python function
that gets called every time
your interpreter encounters an if expression
and all it does is it evaluates the predicate
and chooses a sub expression to be evaluated next
we already have a function
that evaluates a sub expression
and so we just use that schema val
in order to do the rest of the work
so the total effort of
evaluating and if expression is broken up
into two pieces
the thing I'd like to show you in a demonstration
is that if you evaluate an if expression
say if this is true
then one otherwise two
it evaluates the entire expression
by evaluating the predicate
and then evaluating the consequence not the alternative
so notice that two is never evaluated here
so even if it's the case
that I put something that errors
as the alternative
I won't get an error overall
because I'll never evaluate one divider by zero
and on the other hand
if the predicate were false
then I get a division by zero error
and why did I get that
well because I attempted to actually evaluate
one divided by zero
because that was the alternative of this if expression
let's talk about quotation
so the quote special form
evaluates to the quoted expression
that expression is not evaluated
so if I quote an expression
that is a quote special form
and for example quoting plus one two
evaluates two
the scheme list
which contains the symbol plus followed by the No.1
followed by the No.2
it does not evaluate two three
because it's quoted
that's the whole point of quote
is that we can turn anything we want
any expression into data just by quoting it
the expression itself is the value of the
quote expression
and putting a single
quote in front of an expression is just a short hand
for the quote special form
which involves more parentheses
so we're actually saving parentheses when we use this
that is quote one two is equivalent to quote one two
and this equivalency goes both ways
so when
we see this
this is a special piece of syntactic information
which we'd like to actually get rid of by the time our
scheme evaluator has to deal
with the case of evaluating a quote expression
so what actually happens in your project
is that the scheme read parser
converts this short hand
into a regular old combination
that starts with the word quote
so what am I talking about well
there's a file called scheme reader
and what scheme reader does is it just reads
expressions it doesn't actually do any sort of summing
and we look at this before
this is called the syntactic analyzer
and it's also running lexical analyzer as well
and it can do fancy things
like take something
that's broken up on multiple lines and has
decimal points in it
and turn it into a nested expression
understanding that 2.3 is a whole number
and that the
third element of this list is in fact a list itself
now with quotation
I can write quote one two
or I can write quote one two
and it's up to scheme reader
to convert them both into an equivalent form
since one is just a short hand for the other
so when
the scheme evaluator actually deals with quotation
it never sees this
it only sees that
the most important special form of all
is the lambda expression
lambda expressions work like this
they evaluate to user defined procedures
so you have a whole expression that starts with lambda
and when you evaluate it
you get a new procedure that you didn't have before
it has formal parameters and a body
so for instance
if I write lambda x is x times it is times xx
this defines a procedure that squares things
now how do we encode this
well in python
we're actually going to introduce a class
called the lambda procedure class
which has a formal parameter list
a body and an environment
so this is a scheme list of symbols
that tells us
what are the names of the arguments that we pass in
a scheme expression
which tells us what to evaluate when we
call or apply this lambda procedure
and then a frame
that tells us what's the first frame in the environment
in which this lambda procedure was originally the fight
let's talk a little bit about frames and environments
a frame represents an
environment by having a parent frame
so a hole
a frame is always the first frame in some environment
it has a parent frame and it has a parent frame
and eventually you get to the global frame
and then you have your whole environment
frames are python instances with two important methods
lookup and define
in project four
frames don't actually hold any return values
they just hold the name value bindings
well that are used for lookup
so let's do this example in code
we're going to have a global frame
with y bound to three and z bound to five
and then another frame f one
with x bound to two and z bound to four
okay so I'm gonna start up scheme
and then I'm gonna quit out of it right away
now I'm at python
remember python
and in python
we've loaded up
all of the different
functions and classes that we've defined
for our scheme interpreter
so we have a frame
we have a function called scheme val etc
okay so let's make g a frame that has no parent
so g is the global frame
and then let's make f one
a frame that has g is apparent
so f one is a frame
which currently has no bindings within it
and starts an environment
that's followed by the global frame
now I believe right said I was gonna bind y to three
and z
to five
so now if I look up why
if I look up why I'll get three and if I look up z
I'll get five
okay
so now we're going to actually define
x to be two in the f one frame
and define c to be four in the f one frame
so what does f one look like now
well it has x bun the two z found to four
and it's followed by the global frame
so if I look up
x I'll get two
if I look up z I'll get four
which is interesting because z is also divided b five
and the global frame
but remember we look in the local frame
before we look in the global frame
just like in python
and so here we are
we can look up z but we can also look up y
even though it's not in the local frame
we can find it in the global frame
so we look here first there's no y so we find it there
in order to support abstraction in our
programming language
we need to be able to find symbols to values
and we do that with the defined expression
so let's talk a little bit about how
the mechanics of that work
in the interpreter that you're going to build
so define binds a simple to a value
in the first frame of the current environment
and we just saw that frames are objects
that behave like dictionaries
but they can chain because they have parents
and so when you look something up
you might find it in the parent frame
the defined
expression just gives a name and an expression
we evaluate the expression
then bind the name to its value in the current frame
so if I define x to be plus one two
notice that we evaluate plus one two so we get three
and x is then bound to the No.3
it's forgotten the expression that created three
it really just knows that it's the value three
procedure definition is shorthand
for define with a lambda expression
so
when I say I'm going to define a new procedure
which has a name and some formal parameters and a body
all I'm really saying is I'm going to define
a new name that evaluates to
a procedure with some form of parameters and a body
so these two expressions are
completely equivalent in ski
and that means they should be handled in the same way
in the interpreter that we built
so when a defined expression like this is encountered
it gets converted into something that looks like this
and then we apply our regular procedure
for evaluating alamda expression
and then binding that procedure value to innate
okay so
applying user to find procedures is something we can do
we saw a demo of it in the very first
video of this lecture
to apply a user to find procedure
we create a new frame
in which formal parameters are bound
to argument values
whose parent is the environment of the procedure
and end here
is an attribute of the procedure object
that remembers
the environment in which the procedure
was originally defined
okay then we
evaluate the body of the procedure
in the environment that
starts with this new frame
so let's return
to the demonstration that we started with
at the very beginning of this lecture
this demo procedure returns a new list
taking in an old list and giving us back
something with the same elements
but also the No.3 at the end
so let's look at the environments that are created
when I define this thing
and I've bound the name demo
to some lamb to procedure instance
which has its parent as the global frame
then when I call it
that involves creating a list one two
which we can represent as nested pairs
creating a new frame in which
formal parameters are bound to the argument value
the formal parameter s is bound to the argument value
which is this list
a news parent
is g also the parent of the lambda procedure
that was just applied
okay now if we look through the body of these things
we're evaluating the body and we realize s is not null
so we have to call demo on the cutter of s
which means we introduce yet another frame
where s is now bound
to the cutter of s which is the rest of s
everything except for the first element
making another recursive call we find that
we're now binding s to whatever is the cutter of
this s which is just the empty list called nip
and when we evaluate the body of this procedure
with us bount the nill list
then we just return three
this run returns two three
this one returns 1 2 3
but in this environment
we're not keeping track of return values
that happens elsewhere in the program
now this idea that you can evaluate and apply
recursively is really old
so here's the original definitions of apply and eval
in the documentation for a lisp 1.5
which was the predecessor to ski
so this is very old
but it has much of the structure that you see today
though in a different syntax
it kept track of things like car and cutter and cons
those were built in
there was a check of something was atomic
that's just a number
there was also a built in notion of equality
other than that
they were just built in notions of quotation
and conditionals
and everything else you had to build from there
except for our famous lambda
so
as you can see e val dispatches on the type of thing
and calls apply
an apply calls a val
cool