61a lecture 16 q a
well while we're waiting for a question
let me ask you john what
do you do you ever use the non-local
construct
um it's pretty unusual to use it
is that mutable values
and non-local assignment are quite
interchangeable
yeah and
python was originally designed without
it which is kind of interesting
yeah and then um there was kind of a
push from the community
that gives feedback to python that they
should support this because
it is a kind of natural thing to do in
specific circumstances
where um you're trying
for example not to use mutable values
but you still want to
have like certain functions have access
to some value that's in a
in a parent frame so um
it also kind of comes up in the context
of this course as we talk about higher
order functions enough people wonder how
come i can't
kind of change things in the enclosing
environment that i can read from well it
turns out you can
yeah but the consequence is very similar
to the consequence that you get with
mutable values which is that
uh now functions might change how they
behave and
this is kind of the simplest possible
way to do it but you know you could also
do it with a list or something like that
yeah yeah i i'm not crazy about the
construct it's
it's it does it's there's something
about it makes me uncomfortable
anyway um i i didn't realize that it
wasn't part of the original python but
it does fee it does have that feeling of
something that was added in later yeah
the um
the the particular way in which python
allows for non-local assignment which is
that you have this non-local statement
is weird and that is clearly a symptom
of them adding it late
it was it was it was an afterthought you
can see the construct okay
okay so the question was about uh when a
list refers to itself
like what's going on there and um there
was a particular example
from lecture last time
that i think it looked something like
this
that looks right something like that
well let's talk about this example so a
very curious thing happens here
where when you try to display this you
get something that's not just full of
one twos and threes and lists but also
this
elided portion uh this is an ellipsis
basically to say this is just the whole
thing
all over again so if you look at what's
actually in here
the len of t is 2 t 0 is 1
and t 1 is just t again
and um there's lots of ways to get a
list to contain itself
but they all do involve some kind of
mutation
like assignment or sorry like a slice
assignment which we have here
or using append or extend or something
like that
um and uh what we've done here in
particular
is we've said replace elements from one
to three so that would be element one
and element two
with the contents of this list and the
contents of this list is actually just
one element that element happens to be
t and so uh you get this structure
and this i i find not the most
easy thing to read so i prefer looking
at this as an environment diagram
so you can kind of see what's going on
and if we do the same thing there we'll
see that one of the elements of t
is in fact t
so while john's doing this notice
there's there's two things going on
there there's how the list is being
stored
and then how it's represented when you
try to print it and those are distinct
things
that's right so this is the storage is
this t
is a name for a list with two elements
whose
elemented index one is that same list
and then how on earth would you print
this out well um
python does it this way yeah so the the
the representation of the list is finite
but the
printing of it is infinite because you
have to keep referring to yourself you
keep chasing your tail essentially
a follow-up question was could you refer
to the zeroth element of the first
element of t
good let's try that you could so once
you got t1 that's just another name for
t
and so its element at index zero is just
the number one
and in fact its element that index one
is just
t again and that's t and that's t and
that's t
and that's the one at the beginning of t
so i could have an arbitrarily long
referring expression but really all
we're doing is just deciding how many
times we want to re-refer
to the same thing the question is about
how you compare different node labels
in a tree that don't have kind of a
direct
relationship like comparing the parent
to a child
pretty straightforward because whenever
you have a tree you can refer to the
parent label as just label
and the child label as the label of a
branch
but what happens when you want to
compare things that are kind of farther
apart
and that does involve
recursion usually and some mechanism
for getting the information in one part
of the tree
available as you're processing another
part of a tree
so um i guess uh
there's two kinds of questions there's
questions that involve
just like some fact about all the labels
like what's the second largest label in
the whole tree
and in those you kind of want to process
but as you go you need to keep track of
what's going on so i think you'd have to
keep track of both the biggest and the
second biggest thing you've seen so far
and whenever you see something that's
bigger than one of those then you need
to kind of update that
so that's one kind of problem and
another kind of problem might be
for two nodes at the same depth but not
necessarily direct siblings um
which one's the biggest or something
like that
like yeah what's the largest difference
between
two nodes that are at the same depth
and this um it similarly involves just
processing the whole tree
but at the same time keeping track of
an additional piece of information which
is what depth you're at
but let me offer another thought here is
processing data in a tree
is just a slightly more complicated than
processing data in a list
so in a list you have neighboring
elements right there are indexes
different by one
in a tree you have the parent-child
relationship but if i want to know for
example that john was just saying you
know what's the smallest element in the
list
i've got to traverse the whole list if i
want to know what the smallest element
in the tree is i have to traverse the
whole tree and there's a couple
different ways of doing that
you can go all the way down and then
start making your way back
and then the only other example i could
think of too was that same notion of
maybe you want to come because there's
there's another sort of dimension if you
will to a tree it's just not the
ordering there's sort of the depth
ordering that's that's the only other
thing i can think about
in which case as you're traversing a
tree you have to keep track of that
information
and then sort of analyze things at the
back end
okay let's take a look so the question
was about
this um quiz four from the exam prep
section
question one a quant firm has enlisted
your help in maximizing their trade
profits
you know ahead of time how much profit
you will make by executing each trade
these values are stored in a tree
however if you decide to trade a stock
represented by some node s you are not
allowed to execute trades
that have an edge directly connected to
s
for example if you choose the parent you
can't choose the child i think that's
what's going on
um return the maximum profit you can
make based on these constraints
and then there's a skeleton
which involves saying oh the profit of
the tree involves calling a helper on a
tree and something that we're going to
track
that something might be whether we are
allowed to do anything on this level or
not
or it might be something else i guess
we'll see
so i guess unfortunately it appears that
this question
is using a representation of trees that
we have not taught you
yeah and that we do not plan to teach
you in this semester
so i would say that the template here is
problematic and we should ignore it
instead try to solve the problem using
the tree representation that you do know
because we don't have any like none
trees and we don't have any lefts and
rights and things like that
uh but we could still solve this problem
with the tree representation that you do
have
and uh how would we do that so
profit of a tree let's get ourselves an
example um return the max
profit and uh here's an example tree oh
it's big one isn't it
two at the top we've got a
three my goodness
it's going to take a while isn't it
maybe it was a mistake to do an example
maybe we'll do a small example
and uh then we can make it larger if we
really feel like it
okay so in this particular tree if i
took the two then i wouldn't be allowed
to take the three and the four
uh but if i take the
three and the four that's allowed
because they're not directly connected i
guess we need to make it
just slightly more interesting and we'll
put a
5 down here so if we take the 4 we can't
take the 5 but we could take the 3 and
the 5 or the 2 and the 5 or the 3 and
the 4
and the best would be to take the 3 and
the 5 which would give us 8.
how might we do this well i agree we
need to kind of keep track of some
information as we go basically to decide
am i allowed to use
the values in this part of the tree or
not and
there's a constraint which i think says
uh once you've used a label
you can't use any of the labels of its
children
so um if i were to come up with a helper
uh i think it would take entry and say
whether or not we had used the
parent and at the beginning there kind
of is no parent so we don't need to do
that
um
uh used parent
okay so if we use the parent
then we're not really allowed to use any
of the
current labels the best we could do is
return the
sum of the results of using
the branches okay john in the chat steve
is saying that you can't use his
children or
parent well that's right
um
i i think that
if you impose a constraint that like
if i don't use the parent i'm allowed to
use the children and i do that
everywhere
yeah then i've kind of covered the
constraint in all ways like basically uh
as long as i make sure that whenever i
use a parent i don't use a children
a child then i've also made sure that
like whenever i use a child i don't use
the parent
because it's kind of symmetrical that
way
um well i got long didn't it
um but if i don't use the parent then i
kind of have to decide
like am i gonna use this current label
or not so i think i have
uh i could use it
which would mean that
uh i have the label for t
as part of my result
um so i've used the current label
uh all right let's do this way
we'll add to the total or everything
that we find in the branches
or i could start with a total of zero
meaning i don't use the current label
but that means i'm allowed to use the
children then i think what i want to do
is well maybe the total is the wrong
word
well okay total plus equals the sum
of everything i use below where i'm
deciding whether i use the label or not
this time
something like that the
hardest part of programming during these
things is that zoom has put like all
kinds of stuff on the screen
that i'm trying to avoid
clearly this did not work making up a
problem and trying to solve it together
seems to have caused an issue
um i think what the chat may be
somebody in the chat said you have to
compare the two totals
and i think that's right yeah okay so
this is what i was supposed to do
um there's kind of a version
where we
okay so this is like a total one and
there's a total zero
there's a terrible way to write it
but we'll do it this way anyway then
we'll clean it up later
do you need two different used labels
now
uh oh no you don't oh okay so i think
you should okay
so that works okay so let's write it
this like a normal person would write it
which is basically like uh
keep making it longer
so this is the use label total
and then the skip label total
which involves i'll write this out
explicitly
not using the current label but
in this case you don't get to use the
children and in this case
you do sorry john what's label zero
yeah we're getting close
um now you have to fix your max
max now
yeah we're getting there
okay so passes for our one example and i
guess you have to trust us that it
passes for the rest of them
um
this expression here
and this expression are the same
so there is another way you could write
this which is to kind of assign this to
a name and use it twice and that would
probably be a reasonable thing to do
but in both cases i guess we are
illustrating exactly the general
principle we were talking about before
which is that sometimes as you traverse
a tree
you have to keep track of information
about the rest of the tree
that you can't see right now so at the
very beginning you can see the whole
tree
but later on as you're making recursive
calls you can only see
the current node and what's below it if
you need information about what's above
it
like whether you included the parent and
the total
then you need to keep track of that
information by passing it
as an argument and this
recursive call is telling the
function that's going to process this
branch some information about what's
going on
above that branch
that's a good comment uh the chat says
we always see people who know the
solution solve the problem seeing the
way
someone approaches a problem for the
first time is really helpful i think
that's true by the way
it's always easy to solve the problem
when you know the answer um it's good to
see this sort of iterative approach and
the mistakes that we make
okay well let's see uh yeah great
question so
why is it the case that when you're
performing local assignment
and also trying to read a non-local
variable you get the error
in the wrong place so uh let's
illustrate this with an example and see
why it seems like it's the wrong place
you get an error here where
everything we know about python so far
says that there should be no error here
you want to print x plus one so you
figure out what print is it's in the
global frame no problem you figure out
what
x is you you don't find it here so you
look here and you find an x and so
this should print four um
all programming languages have some
quirks
uh this is a particularly nasty one that
exists in python
it exists i think because um
you know the
there are two central concerns in
programming language well there's many
concerns in programming languages but
two of them are it should be easy for
the user to express the
program that they want and uh that
program should run
reasonably fast there's this particular
optimization
i think python does which is that it has
a constraint that says
all the names within a function that are
the same
so like all the x's within this body of
g
have to refer to the same frame that's
just like a restriction that exists in
the language
that means you can't have two x's in the
same body
where one refers to the global frame and
one refers to the local frame or
something like that
and they do this so that like basically
when you're figuring out what your
program means and you're going to
execute it it's easy to figure out like
where in memory something lives i think
i think it's sort of an optimization but
why isn't important i think as a
programmer you just need to know that
this is a constraint
so there's no way to write a program
that kind of accesses this
x and then changes an x in here and
this line would in fact change an x in
here as opposed to anywhere else this is
local assignment
so why is it that you get the error here
instead of here well
in some sense you could say like
python's broken
and that's a perfectly reasonable
reaction um
there is an error so whether it shows up
here or here
i don't know if it's that big of a deal
like there's a problem with this code
and python is telling you there's a
problem with this code
and so you got to go fix it i would have
if i were designing the language i would
prefer for the error to like come up
somewhere else or to say something other
than this because this is particularly
misleading
the error really is that you're trying
to use an x
from the f1 frame and then assign to an
x
in an f2 frame and that isn't allowed
x needs to refer to one particular
variable in a particular frame whenever
it's uh
used multiple times in the definition of
the same function
so one way to think about it is um
the problem is not so much line four
it's really the combination of line
three and four
it's that you're using the variable in
different ways so if i had taken out
line three
line four would have been fine so that's
a one way to convince yourself that
you know it's the combination of the two
lines so you may as well do it in the
first one
but it also means that python knows
what's happening
downstream right it's not it's not blind
to the code it is about to evaluate
yeah yeah this is the particularly
spooky part i think for students who see
this
is like well you mean python knows the
future of what the rest of the code
looks like
and in fact it does so there's multiple
stages to interpreting a program
and one of them is just to read the code
and make sure that all the parentheses
line up and all the brackets line up
and actually that happens for your
entire python file
before anything gets executed is that it
kind of does a syntax check
now that syntax check in python tends to
be a little bit more involved because
it's trying to set up the program to run
quickly
so it doesn't just make sure the
parentheses are matched
it also figures out that for every name
which frame is it going to refer to
and so it has kind of looked ahead at
your code to figure out
is this a local x or is this a non-local
x
like where in the environment is this x
going to be
and it saw this line and determined it
was going to be local
and then when it tried to execute this
it didn't find that x defined yet
and so that's why you got this
particular error but that's just like a
detail of how the interpreter works
not so much about the language but like
about how the language
mechanics actually run which i guess now
you know
but uh the mistake of
having x try to refer to two places at
once is
something that like everyone should know
because that's a
constraint about the language and by the
way i agree that the error message here
is awful
right they should be able to give us a
better error message than that yeah
the next question was about summer 2020
midterm two question seven
all right i guess i'll have to read the
question here we go
the village operation takes a function
apple that maps an integer to a tree
where every
label is an integer
a tree t whose labels are all integers
and applies apple to every label in t
to recombine this tree of trees into a
single tree simply copy all of its
branches
to each of the leaves of the new tree
well i definitely need an example for
that
oh i don't know about these exams i
didn't write okay so
uh if you have a tree
uh if you have a function that
builds a tree of x x
plus one and x plus two and a tree
that looks like that
oh i see so i think what's happening is
i see all these branches showed up here
and they showed up here
okay that sounds reasonable
fascinating so take a look understanding
this write down that it creates
two trees one with the result of x plus
one to every label and one to the result
of x plus two at every label and then
creates a parent
no it uh finds the root label
10 yeah
passes it into this function to create
10 11 12.
yeah and then for every branch of the
old
tree ah
does the same thing except it does it
multiple times it does it here
and i guess i can't highlight this i see
right so over here and it doesn't there
gotcha okay okay
so
we get a helper function called graft
which says graph the given branches
onto each leaf of the given tree
and then we're going to call
graft on some tree
and some branches and your question was
how come these aren't
part of graft or how come they're
indented the way that they are
this structure says define a new
function
called graft which in principle has
access
to the apple function and the t which we
might need
um and then
after you're done defining this function
build some new things a tree
and some branches and then call graft on
those two things
let me just start with one obvious thing
because i didn't notice this until you
scrolled up john
is that that that graph function is
embedded in a larger function
so the three lines that you're seeing
there base tbs in return are the body
of the parent function it's just that
the comments are so long you can't see
the header
all right let's see if we can make some
progress because why not uh
so we need to build we need to call
apple on the label
of the tree we need to
[Music]
um kind of recursively do this i think
uh we either do it now or we do it later
it's not clear to me how this is set up
uh
john can you make that a little bit
bigger oh sure thanks
no better so
i guess we need to know what we're going
to graft on
and that will be the result of
calling village
a branch of
tree using apple apple's the first
argument
for every b in branches of t
okay now we do the grafting and what
does that
grafting look like well
if t is a leaf
then
to graft these things on
what a strange structure we have here
so are we making a tree
do you have to return a tree with t in
the node and bs as the
children is that right
i guess what we could do is we could uh
graft
these branches on all to onto all the
branches of the tree
i was thinking that was going to be our
base case i wasn't expecting a recursive
call there
yeah i'm just trying to fit the template
yeah
okay so now we've got a leaf
uh
oh i see so they're trying to set us up
to
do this here i think yeah
that makes more sense
seems like this template has multiple
possible solutions but we'll uh
do it this way okay so to if we reach a
leaf
then we create a tree with a bunch of
branches otherwise
we do this recursively and create a
tree with these new branches
it looks better
that works at least for their one
example
let me describe how we got here
and then you know they only gave us one
example so it might be wrong but it
seemed like it basically worked
it felt like in order to build this
monstrosity from this original part
we needed to go through and call this
apple function on
10 and 20 and 30 and anything else that
was in the original t
so you get this like typical pattern for
that like how do you call a function on
every
label within a tree you call it on
the current label
and you call it on
everything in each of the branches and
fortunately we have a function that does
that that like recursively
calls apple on everything in each branch
so this structure gives us a sense that
we're going to be
calling the apple function on every
uh label in the original t
and what's unusual about this function
is how you put together the results
because
instead of like just getting a number
back you get a whole tree back
there's no like good way to place all
these trees so whoever invented this
question decided that we were going to
duplicate parts of it all over the place
and then graft them in and that's how we
came up with this
okay so so this basically says go until
you hated leaf
and then put all the branches on that
leaf and otherwise
uh go search the tree until you find
leaves
so this is a fine way to do it
yeah good question so the question is
um how do you like since we
the output tree is a different structure
than the input tree how is it that we
have
kept track of the original tree well
enough to build the output tree
without kind of getting the two confused
with each other and
without changing the original tree
so one thing about changing is that we
are just building new stuff
all the time we're not editing the
contents of the original tree
we know that because we don't see any
append extend
element assignment slice assignment
anything like that
all we're doing is going through the
original tree and building
new trees along the way um
now how is it that we're building these
new trees
and still kind of keeping track of where
we were
in the original tree and
that's a great question we're kind of
relying on recursion to do that for us
so when we make a recursive call to
village
we're making it on branches of the
original tree
so all those calls to village that will
happen along the way
because of the recursion are going to be
processing
parts of the original tree and there's
no risk that they will
instead be processing something else
because we only call
village on parts of the original tree
which then calls village on parts of
that original branch
etc and the building of the
new tree with the new structure only
really happens
in the return value to village which
does have this like unusual structure
with a lot of repetition in it
but but but that all gets constructed
after you've kind of gone through and
made sure you
call village on each note
okay so great question the question is
what's the difference between adding two
lists using plus
versus using append when you use
plus you create a new list so if i have
a
and i have b and i write a plus b
a hasn't changed and b hasn't changed
and in fact i could write something like
c equals a plus b
and now c a is that b is that and c is
that
so we have three different lists whereas
originally we had two
and to be clear if we change a now c
doesn't change
right it is really a new list oh that is
right
if i yeah get rid of the contents
of a now a is empty
but b is still there and c is still
there
okay so that's how plus works is it
always just creates a new list
uh what about append
if i have two names for the same list
and i append
to a a has changed we see that change
reflected in b
because a is b these are just two
different names for the same list
so append changes this list but the
other query thing about append is that
it doesn't return anything
so if i said something like c equals
eight out of pen for
what's a it's now got one two three four
in it b does two and what's c
well c is actually no the return value
of a call to append
is not why does that make sense well
append does something to a
but it doesn't really create anything
new which is why it doesn't have a
return value or the return value is none
so instead of adding where we made a new
list
we're just changing an old list
i guess the last thing i'll say on this
issue is that
if we wanted to put these things
together
you might imagine something like uh
a and b and c where a is c
or if i said something like a equals a
plus b now i'm making a new list and
assigning it to a
so a is one two three four and b is
three four and c
is still a name for that original list
one two which used to be called a but
now a
has been used for something else okay
i'm gonna go for another
one minute and say my least favorite
thing about pipeline
and that's a lot because there's a lot
of problems with python but one of them
is that it has a plus equals operator
that kind of does not what i'd expect
so watch this
if i set a to 1 2 and b equal to 3
4 and c equal to a
everything's the same because i haven't
done anything different
if i replace this line
with a plus equals b
instead of a equals b now a is one two
three four b
is three four and c is different
meaning this doesn't actually mean the
same thing as this
i made some effort to get these to line
up nicely but somehow i failed
maybe the font size is different or
something
but you should just be aware that if you
have a list on the left side of a plus
equals
then something weird happens that's a
lot like extend and so i almost never
use this construction
because i don't trust it i feel like it
should do the same thing as that
but it doesn't so now that you've
learned about this has been like a theme
of this
uh quest q a session is that python has
all these weird quirks
and you know that's true other languages
also have weird quirks
you may not have learned about all of
them so you might think things are
rosier
on the other side usually they're not
there is
a notable exception a language that
basically has very few quirks
and that is called lisp and we will
learn about that later in this
semester and it is quite internally