61a lecture 33 q a
yeah so we've come to the end of
required
content there wasn't a whole lot in
today's lecture it's an important
concept to figure out how to
interleave aggregation with all the
other stuff you've learned joining and
filtering and all that
um and i think it does show up a lot in
like practical sql
that you do a fair amount of grouping
and either summing or maxing
i think that's a big part of sort of
data analytics is just being able to
query the database like
what what i'm looking for this and what
about this and what about this and that
kind of just being able to poke at your
data
and understand the landscape is i think
probably one of the most important or
widely used um applications yeah
and it definitely takes practice it's
just like you know you learn what a
while statement is and an assignment
statement is that doesn't mean you know
how to do
everything that you can do with those
right uh
and and so now you know kind of all the
primitive parts of a
standard select query which is
kind of the main way that you access
things in a database
and you just have to practice a little
bit to learn how to
get exactly what you want out of any
given data set
yeah every time i write a sql command it
takes me like five iterations to get all
the
little pieces exactly right
right yeah people write these kind of
interactively right that's kind of how
it's set up so
maybe you only run on a sample of the
data if you have a huge data set but you
often do kind of look at the result and
say like oh does that actually make
sense or did something go wrong
yeah exactly the first question was
about whether
when you aggregate and you also select
an
individual rose value
like for example you take the max legs
and you also want the name of the animal
that has that many legs
how do you know which one you're going
to get in a tie
i don't know the exact answer this maybe
john does but i think it depends on the
underlying implementation
um which sql implementation you're using
yeah that's right i mean sql doesn't
give you any kind of standard for what
happens
when you aggregate and yet you also
select some
element that's not aggregated
sqlite's pretty reliable with
macs in that it will give you some max
but
i don't think it gives you any
guarantees about which one
and if you write a longer query you can
get a lot of control
right so you could write a longer query
that says first i want to compute the
max
and then i want to find all the rows
that have that max and then i want to
pick the order for them
and so if you're kind of willing to
write something more elaborate then you
can
know exactly what you're going to get so
in general you should
not rely too much on this shortcut of
you know you can select a
non-aggregated value along with an
aggregated value
because uh you might not know exactly
what you get and it's sort of better to
to write something longer and get
control yeah and you definitely
shouldn't assume
just because you see a particular sort
of side effect behavior
don't assume that that will always work
first of all the language will evolve
and change
there'll be different sql
implementations and so you know if it's
not defined
i actually think it's a bad thing that
people let you get away with this yeah
um right and
um and uh
yeah there's certainly a good argument
that we shouldn't have even taught you
the fact that this works because
because maybe you'll rely on it and it
won't work in some other
implementation of sql but um
yeah the the one thing that we don't
really cover in this course but is
covered in more advanced courses is that
sometimes you have a query that has
another query embedded in it so like how
would you get the max and then use that
max to do something else
um you know this actually does show up
in some real
world uh sql programs that you kind of
have
nested queries inside of queries inside
of queries and they get really huge
you'll see some of that if you take for
example data 100
but you know we had to we had to pick a
boundary here
and so that's kind of where we stopped
yeah good question so kind of when you
use lists and when do you use cons
in some recursive procedure like zipping
or something like that
um it's always good to remember what
they do
so list builds a new list where you have
the elements and you're putting
them into a list and cons builds a new
list where you have most of the list the
rest of the list
and one new element and you're building
a new list out of an existing list
by adding one thing to the front i think
one way to check your work
is that if you ever have some
procedure
where you know somewhere in the middle
of it
you have a recursive case that looks
like
list you should know that since this
takes two arguments in your code it's
always going to build a list of length
two
so if you're ever trying to build a list
that's arbitrarily long
like it depends on the input then list
isn't going to do the trick
list is really only there to build lists
of a particular fixed length
you can build a list of length three
like that but you would never have
this piece of code building a list that
might vary
in its length this will always build
something that has
three elements so in anything we're
building up a long list
from kind of smaller versions
cons is more common or append
append is kind of your third option and
append
takes two lists but they can be
arbitrarily long and it builds a new
list
that's got all the elements of this and
all the elements of that so
so a pen sometimes shows up in recursive
cases
um cons i think is more often because
often times what you do in your
recursive case is you add one more
element to whatever you've already built
and then list shows up there less often
i guess it's always possible
that exactly what you want is a
two-element list every time
but if you don't know how long the list
is that you're building then you need
cons or append
yeah i mean so so what does cons do
right so the question is
uh can we replicate lists with cons cons
adds one element at a time
so if you want to create a list with
three elements you enumerate the three
elements
if you want to use cons you cons an
element to the empty list you con's
another element to that yukon's a third
element to that so just
it's just a little more tedious right
you're just you have to do this
embedding
consing as opposed to list abc so you
can you can do whatever you want it's
just
sort of where the convenience is i think
john said it right which is
if you're adding one element to a list
the cons and the appending is probably
the right way to go
if you're constructing the list from
scratch or from multiple elements
probably use list although you could use
cons you could use a pen it's just a
little more tedious
okay so we're taking a look at a problem
from
cs mentors worksheet this is a
mentor section 13. here we are on page
four
and we're doing the first scheme
question which is called the skip list
which takes in a potentially nested list
and a single argument filter function
that returns a boolean when called
and goes through each element in order
it returns a new list that contains all
elements that return
true when passed into the filter
function
the returned list is not nested
so if we have a function that finds all
the even numbers
and we go through a nested list that's
got one and then a list within it that
has three
we end up with nothing okay
if we go through this nested list which
has one two three four five six seven
eight
nine and look for all the odd numbers
then we find one three five seven and
nine
but we kind of we have to search through
the structure of the input but we don't
have to recreate it in the output
we take in this list and this filter
function
there's some helper which has
one two three different arguments
kind of the list we have left to process
i think
the list we've built so far and some
notion of
next uh i'm not sure exactly how these
are all going to fit together but let's
um
skim through and see if we can figure it
out
so when we reach an empty
list that we're processing we need to
check and see if something else is null
and then do something
pair is a primitive that tells you
whether what you're looking at
is a list or not
we don't actually use this anymore but
there's something called list which will
tell you that's not a list
and that is
and pair will actually give you the same
result
so what's the difference between a pair
and a list is something that we don't
talk about
anymore in the course there is a
difference in scheme but it's not worth
your trouble so assume this checks to
see if this is something that's a list
or not
okay something might be a list or not
and um
if so we do one thing if it's the case
that calling filter function on the
first element of a list
gives you a true value
then i think you want to keep that
otherwise filter function returned a
false value
we want to discard that john i'm still
trying to figure out what next is for
it's not is it obvious to you yeah
here's what i think is going on
is that let's say you
want to keep the one and then you see
this list
what the heck are you gonna do you're
going to make a recursive call
on this list in order to find the 3 and
the 5.
yeah but then after that you're going to
have to process all this stuff
so while you're processing this sub-list
you need to remember what's next
is i think what's happening here
um i see so list so
far in that example would be one list
would be
the list two three four five and next
would be six to nine
yeah i wasn't so sure what list
so far is yet
uh we don't want to build this backwards
oh this is a fun one meaning it's pretty
challenging so
what are they doing with all these names
i guess uh
it remains to be seen whether i would
have written it this way but
um i think that
we can start putting sound stuff in
so if the car of the list that you're
trying to process
is itself a list then you're gonna have
to call
helper on
that piece
now what do you build you build uh
in this example you'd build a list
containing three and five
and the list you have so far
well let's assume it is whatever we have
so far
because we didn't add anything to it yet
and uh
what's next well eventually we have to
process the cutter
of the list that we started with
that's one way to go
if it's the case that we want to put car
list into the result well
we actually could then process the rest
of the list
building up a longer list so far
that's one way to do it and we process
the coder of the list
otherwise we ignore
the car of the list and just keep the
list so far
that we already have
so what happens when we get to the end
of a list
there's either a next that we have to
process or not
if next is null then we really hit the
like
very end at which point the
list that we've built means that we're
done
if there's still a next then we still
have some work to do
we want to call the helper
on next the stuff that we haven't
processed yet
the list so far that we have
stays the same we've already added stuff
to it
and
let's see what happens with the next of
the next
i think it we're done with the next or
my confidence is not high here yeah me
either
so um
how would we get started well we'd want
to process the whole list
we would have built nothing so far and
after we process the whole list there's
nothing left to do
so let's think about what might happen
here
we pass in this whole thing as list and
next is nil and list so far is nil
we see that the first element
is odd and so
we construct a new list which
appends nil to a list containing the
number one so now we're building a list
containing just one
as our list so far we're going to
process
a list that's everything here without
the one at the beginning
and
this is wrong
and whatever's next should be whatever's
next
which currently is nil so there's
nothing like more to do
after we finish processing this entire
list
okay now we get to this tricky case
where
this is the list that comes in its
car is itself a list
so we call helper
on you
with our list so far being the one that
we've already seen
and the cutter of the list being next
that looks good um
what happens when we call
helper on this well we ignore the two
that's fine except for this should be
next
um we see the 3 4
let's assume that it works and puts a 3
in a list so far
and then calls on
five with the right next value okay
so
maybe i went too fast when we call
you the next is
this five
now but computers would be really good
at this
yeah let's pretend this isn't nested for
a second and see if it works at least
with one level of nesting so
if this were just two three four five
then we'd go through and we'd be adding
the three and we'd be adding the five
and then we'd get to the empty list here
and we'd see oh but null is not next
so i need to call helper
on 6789 using
the 135 i have so far and nothing after
that
okay so one level of nesting i'm pretty
convinced that we've handled
what about two levels of nesting so when
there's two levels of nesting
we get the three and the four and we get
to this nil
no um
the next from this call would just be
like this list five
so so that's where we've gone wrong
yes as we've kind of forgotten about
like
when we hit this case the second time
we uh forgot about
the 6789 that we needed so the next here
can't just be the cutter of the list it
has to be
more stuff than that yeah it has to be
that
after we finish with the 3 4 we have to
keep processing
a list that starts with 5 and then has
six
seven eight nine after
gross no that think means that we need
to handle the
list and everything that's after it yeah
that's ugly
i think what was confusing here this is
where i got jammed up too was the
double more than one nesting
um is yeah it's hard to keep track of it
i think this looks more right but i'm
not entirely sure again
yeah but actually you could write this
procedure
without a helper and it wouldn't be so
messy
yeah that's the part that sort of bugged
me is i i
found the the helper function made it
worse
yeah it really did so if instead we had
defined
skip list of s
as just oh and there's some filter right
if s is no you're done
if s is a list then you have to append
whatever you get from calling skip list
on the car s
using that same filter function
onto whatever you get by calling skip
list
on the cutter of s using that same
filter function
if uh
oh sorry my on syntaxes struggling here
switched over to sql uh if i call f
on the car of s and i get a true value
then i should just cons
the car s onto whatever i get
by calling skip list
on the cutter of s using that filter
function
yeah and this is it right and otherwise
yeah i
forget the caravas yeah
okay so if we take one of these
crazy examples
paste it in here see what we get
we got a disaster
[Laughter]
i did this wrong ah yeah
okay and then it works sorry so
you know this base case is i mean these
like cases are the same
but it's much easier to build a list
by um
kind of putting things on the front and
processing the rest in this case i think
than it is to do it this way which you
know you should understand how to do
things this way this is building up a
list
kind of like you would in python
appending stuff to the end
and remembering what you have left to
process
but remembering what you have less to
process would be easier for the
interpreter to do for you
than to be something that you handle
yourself here we're handling it
ourselves by kind of like building up
this list of things that we still have
to process
and here it's just kind of like up to
the recursive leap of faith to figure
out what's left the process
so if i were actually writing this
procedure i would write it this way
turns out my way is also more efficient
but we don't talk about efficiency too
much in this class
um though i think that something like
this would work
uh since i didn't type it in i cannot
guarantee that it is right but
it looks kind of right to me but i have
looked at this problem before but not in
a long time so it's going to take us a
while
um all right my guess is that this will
round out
our session for the day because it takes
a little bit of time but we should be
able to do it
um so here we are in fall 2017. question
number six
um the
question takes the whole page to
describe
and then the code takes a whole page to
write
it is about scheme that processes scheme
like a program that writes programs
which is a common kind of question that
shows up
because you know that's really what's
new about scheme
relative to python otherwise most of the
stuff is the same so one reason we teach
scheme is just to give you practice with
all the stuff that you already know how
to write recursion and stuff like that
but another is to show you that you
could build programs
that write programs so let's take a look
for this problem consider
a very small subset of scheme containing
only if
and true and false great
such expressions can be simplified
according to the following
transformation rules here p
e 1 and e 2 are scheme expressions
in the subset meaning it's just like ifs
and trues and falses
p prime e 1 prime and e 2 prime are
their simplified versions
here's the ways in which you can
simplify if you have
if p e1 e2
and it turns out that p is just true
then you don't need an if expression
anymore you could just
write e1 or a simplified version of e1
that's why the prime is there
if this is false and you know it's false
then you don't need the if expression
anymore you could just have e2
well a simplified version of and here's
another interesting one
if you're choosing between two options
that are equal
then you don't need the if expression
anymore you could just choose the first
one because they're
equal okay otherwise the if expression
has to have a simplified version of the
predicate the
consequent and the alternative or i
guess they're called the predicate then
pardon else part here which is fine
um so you basically like take this apart
simplify each of these and then put it
back together with an if in front
any expression e simplifies to true if e
is known to be true
or to false if f is known to be false
oh sorry if it is known to be false okay
and then here is an interesting part
if the in the expression if pe1
e2 p prime is known to be
true while simplifying e1 and is known
to be false while simplifying e2
initially only true is known to be true
and only false is known to be false
okay let's look at some examples to try
to understand what that last one was
here's an example if you write
if a then if a b
c the only way you'd be evaluating this
is if a were true which means you know
that a is true
which means you know that this will come
out as b the only way you'd be
evaluating this
is if you know the day is false which
means that a will come out as false
which means you know that this is e so
this nested if a
if a structure can be simplified to just
if a
b otherwise e basically like no matter
what a
is this long expression will be equal to
this short expression
i did not write this problem by the way
this was written by a teaching assistant
very clever but also very very involved
okay so
uh i think that the rest of these
examples don't really tell you anything
new but maybe i'll pause for a second
and see if people have questions about
what is going on before i try to dive
into the code
a student has to clarify what this
question is even asking
you're just you're basically saying look
i'm giving you this conditional
and there are certain rules that will
allow you to simplify it
if the predicate is true you just have
to evaluate the then clause if the
predicate is false you evaluate else
clause and then
where things get more complicated is
that logic that we just went through
where in the then clause you know
that a certain things are true right so
your job is basically take this long
expression and simplify it
following the rules enumerated above
some of them are pretty straightforward
right so you can imagine that the rule
that if p
is true then you simply return the then
clause
right i think where things will get more
complicated is
the sort of percolating the
value of the predicate into the then in
the else box
a great problem but not for an exam
okay so i think we know what we're after
we're going to have to write code
that detects these various conditions
and builds the right thing as the result
it's going to be recursive because of
this case
and if expression that looks like pe1e2
has to be a simplified version of p a
simplified version of e1 and a
simplified version of e2
but that recursion is not only going to
have a different expression to simplify
but it's also going to have different
stuff that's known to be true in order
to handle this case
of no matter what a is it's going to be
the same here as it is here
and therefore we know it's true here and
can get the b out instead of the whole
if abc structure
to simplify an expression is to simp
with a context an expression with two
um helpers or sorry with two other
arguments which in this case are what's
known to be true and what's known to be
false
and simp is the thing that we're trying
to
implement and it told us that in the
beginning the only things that are known
to be true
are true and false so i think we just
write that in here
i didn't write just true and false but
cons t nil
and cons f nil because i'm assuming that
known t
and known f are going to be like a whole
list of known true values that that will
like build up over time
in the beginning it's just true in that
example we looked at it would be true
and
a and so i've put this into a list what
does it mean to simplify
an expression in a context where this is
the things we know are true and this is
the things that we know are false
well oh a simplified expression is
if this thing is a pair
then we assume it's an if expression
because that's the only
combination that were allowed in this
subset
at which point we call simp if
which what's nth uh
i guess uh maybe that pulls off the
end our the first argument the second
art like that that parameter
yeah it just gives you one of the
elements in a list yeah
so it just clears through the list
giving you
the nth car yeah yeah it must have been
it must have been defined somewhere but
whatever
uh oh here it is for convenience assume
and exists
and returns the k th element of the list
okay so
we're back this says call simp
if on whatever is the first thing the
second thing the third thing and the
existing known true and known false
values
um otherwise it's
not an if so it's just an expression
john can you show i can't see what's
below this a little bit can i just see
what's coming
what's coming is if you have an if
expression here's all the stuff
you should do yeah okay
let's get this right and then we'll
figure out what we have
so if we have a pred a then part and
else part
part that's known true a part that's
known false then we simplify the pred by
calling
him context on the predicate using
what we already know to be true and
false
to simplify the then part
we have to call simp context
on the then part
but in this case we know that
the predicate is a true value
[Music]
so this is the part where because you're
in the then statement you know that the
predicate must be true so you have to
add it to the knowledge of what is known
true for that part
exactly right and same thing obviously
if you're going to do the
yeah and the same is true
when you process the else part then you
assume
that the predicate is false
if it's the case that that pred is true
then you do
sim then
if it's the case that
pred is
false then you do
simples if it's the case
that the simp then
expression is identical to the simp
else expression meaning after you've
done all the simplifying they're both
true
or they're both false or they're both a
then you don't need to choose between
them anymore you just return one of them
that was one of the rules
otherwise it's put together an if
expression
recons the word if
oh i guess we know that there's going to
be always four parts to an f expression
there's the if
there's the predicate
there's the then part and there's the
else part
this simplified expression might still
be an if or it might not be an if
if it's not an if what is it it's true
but there's another case when it's true
which is that it's one of the
expressions in the known t
list
uh i actually forgot in scheme how you
figure out whether something is
contained in a list
i was just trying to remember that john
is is there uh is there like a member
function
tricky
uh contains maybe i don't know if that's
built in
i tried them remember is member
an expression
i got nothing uh all right let's assume
we have it then
that's the thing we have it and if we
don't have it then um
we can figure out a way to hack around
it i guess but
i i think the logic that we want is
if the known true list
contains this simplified expression
then we just want to return true
and if the known false list contains a
simplified expression then we want to
return
false otherwise we just want to return
the simplified
expression now
if contains didn't exist what would we
do
ah mem uh i think might be
it looks like member or memq does that
look familiar
doesn't look good no you know what never
mind john it doesn't matter
and i don't think it gives us any
guidance oh it does
it says used in so even though n doesn't
work it says use in so you have to read
the instructions which i didn't do
okay so
and this says in takes two arguments and
the element's supposed to come first i
think
maybe i should read carefully if e
is equal to a member of the list
so this should have gone the other way
man it pays to read the directions
that's like the one thing you should
learn from this example okay so
um for like a goddamn page long john
[Laughter]
so what did we learn if we had uh
this long description of all the things
we need to handle
and we had this long block of code it
was basically a game of figuring out how
to handle each part of that long
description
in a recursive process that will handle
a whole
nested expression i i found it easier to
work on the bottom part
because that was just sort of following
the directions what the various rules
were and then the top are sort of
putting all the pieces together
it is almost always the case that if
there's some like
helper function and you're not quite
sure what it does
you should kind of focus on that
oftentimes it can be solved
in isolation and then by the time you're
done with this you kind of know what
you're getting back
so at this point we know we're either
getting true or false or a
or b or maybe some big if expression but
now we know what we have here and i
always find it's helpful to think about
particular examples we didn't do a whole
lot of that
um this time around but it was kind of
in the back of my mind as i was working
and so you could think of like oh what
is this thing it might be
a or b or true or false or it could be a